<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Security on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Security on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 23:07:58 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining “Participatory Ecosystem” — Grow the Pie, Not Slice It!</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2016/04/defining-participatory-ecosystem-grow-the-pie-not-slice-it.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 23:07:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2016/04/defining-participatory-ecosystem-grow-the-pie-not-slice-it.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c82f02ac970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Little Men Circle&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c82f02ac970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c82f02ac970b-320wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Little Men Circle&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;As part of being a&amp;#0160;member of the sustainable MBA community at &lt;a href=&#34;http://pinchot.edu/&#34;&gt;Pinchot University&lt;/a&gt;, I have been trying to articulate what I like about the kinds of collaboration that are possible even inside a competitive industry. In our MBA program, we don&amp;#39;t just teach about competitive strategy&amp;#0160;(using classic&amp;#39;s like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/On-Competition-Michael-E-Porter/dp/0875847951&#34;&gt;Porter&amp;#39;s book&lt;/a&gt;), but we also teach about the nature of&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coopetition&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia link to Coopetition&#34;&gt;coopetition&lt;/a&gt;. These practices&amp;#0160;are more&amp;#0160;likely to lead to sustainable businesses (not only sustainable=green, but sustainable=enduring).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been a participant during several periods of technology history where coopetition has been practiced, most recently during the early days of the Twitter ecosystem. I can distinctly remember two companies&amp;#0160;offering competitive Twitter clients sharing best practices at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iosdevcamp.org&#34;&gt;iOSDevCamp&lt;/a&gt; hackathon I hosted. Unfortunately these practices ended when Twitter pulled the rug out from independent developers by controlling the API keys under the guise of &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20131017201719/https://dev.twitter.com/blog/delivering-consistent-twitter-experience&#34;&gt;Delivering a Consistent Twitter Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#0160;(post now only visible on Internet Archive)&lt;/em&gt;. There are some that argue that Twitter may have ultimately &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.novaspivack.com/technology/where-twitter-went-wrong-and-how-to-right-it&#34;&gt;killed its ecosystem&lt;/a&gt; in pursuit of short-term profits over a long-term community of innovators. We have seen this take over elsewhere as described in&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pando.com/2012/11/03/how-ecosystems-became-the-new-walled-gardens/&#34;&gt;How Ecosystems Became the New Walled Gardens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes a great participatory ecosystem? My recent work in trying to understand Elinor Ostrom&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/11/a-revised-ostroms-design-principles-for-collective-governance-of-the-commons-.html&#34;&gt;design principles for the collective governance of the commons&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and some other thoughts have led me to this definition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Participatory Ecosystem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A participatory ecosystem is a business ecosystem with relatively low barriers to economic participation, artistic and professional expression, and civic engagement by all stakeholders, including producers and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has strong support for creating, sharing and increasing the production of goods and services of value to the ecosystem. A participatory ecosystem will have system processes where established stakeholders are incentivized to share knowledge, access to markets, and capital to new stakeholders in the ecosystem, and to turn consumers into producers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders with leadership positions in a participatory ecosystem may change over time, but the function of an ecosystem leader is valued by the community because it enables members to move toward shared visions, grow the market, to align their investments, and to find mutually supportive roles in the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A participatory system is resilient, and has system processes, such as decentralization, to prevent bad actors. Every stakeholder in a participatory ecosystem believes that their goods and services matter, and feel some degree of social connection and community with one another (at least they care what other people think about what they produce.) Not every stakeholder must produce, but all must believe that they are free to produce when ready and what they contribute will be appropriately valued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not completely an original idea&amp;#0160;— it is of&amp;#0160;a mashup of Henry Jenkins’ &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Participatory_culture&#34;&gt;“participatory culture”&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;definition&amp;#0160;with&amp;#0160;James Moore’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_ecosystem&#34;&gt;“business ecosystem”&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;ideas. I&amp;#39;ve added a few&amp;#0160;things I&amp;#39;ve observed about&amp;#0160;working participatory ecosystems, and have also&amp;#0160;run this definition&amp;#0160;by a number of my colleagues in a variety of industries for small tweaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recently I&amp;#39;ve been using it in talks about the blockchain ecosystem. I have &lt;a href=&#34;https://blockstream.com/2016/04/05/blockstream-christopher-allen-linux-foundation-w3c-ietf/&#34;&gt;recently joined&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blockstream.com&#34;&gt;Blockstream&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;where I am leading a number of&amp;#0160;strategic initiatives, including the company’s participation in cross-industry collaborations, as well as future technical efforts with international standards organizations such as W3C, IETF, and Oasis. In these efforts I have been sharing this definition more broadly, and it seems to be resonating with the community, in particular as the blockchain community cares deeply about decentralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve posted this definition to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.participatoryecosystem.com/&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;hoping that others can fork it and submit pull requests to make it better — just like how&amp;#0160;open source world works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#0160;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Revised “Ostrom’s Design Principles for Collective Governance of the Commons”</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/11/a-revised-ostroms-design-principles-for-collective-governance-of-the-commons-.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 15:23:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/11/a-revised-ostroms-design-principles-for-collective-governance-of-the-commons-.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c76aaed3970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Resource Sharing&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c76aaed3970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c76aaed3970b-250wi&#34; style=&#34;width: 250px; margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Resource Sharing&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The traditional economic definition of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commons&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“the commons”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are those resources that are held in common and not privately owned. This is closely related to economic concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_good&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;public goods&lt;/a&gt;, which are goods that are both &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Excludability&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;non-excludable&lt;/a&gt; (in that individuals cannot be effectively excluded from use) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rivalry_(economics)&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;non-rivalrous&lt;/a&gt; (where use by one individual does not reduce availability to others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own personal definition for the commons is broader — any regenerative, self-organizing complex system that can be drawn upon for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artbrock.com/presentations/new-economy-new-wealth&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;deep wealth&lt;/a&gt;. These can include traditional commons, such as lumber, fish, etc., but can also include other regenerative systems such as communities, markets, intellectual property, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elinor_Ostrom&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Elinor Ostrom&lt;/a&gt; received the Nobel Prize in Economics for her “analysis of economic governance, especially the commons”. In that, she listed 8 principles for effectively managing against the tragedy of the commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;#39;ve found her original words — as well as many adaptions I&amp;#39;ve seen since — to be not very accessible. Also, since the original release of the list of 8 principles there also has been some research resulting in updates and clarifications to her original list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to generalize her principles for broader use given my broader definition of the commons, and apply them to everything from how to manage an online community to how a business should function with competitors. I went to the original version, more contemporary research, as well as a number of modern adaptions to define a new set of design principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/10-design-principles-for-governing-the-commons.html&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;first draft&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;divided up her 8 principles into 10. I then ran this&amp;#0160;list by a number of experts in this field, and here is my second draft based on their feedback. This draft in fact breaks up her principles into 12 different ones, but I have retained her old numbering system as there are large number of works that refer to the original 8. In addition, there appears to be some differences in thoughts on number 8, so I&amp;#39;ve included two variations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ostrom’s Design Principles for Collective Governance of the Commons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to Avoid the Tragedy of the Commons within Self-Organizing Systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1A. DEFINE AUTHORIZED USE:&lt;/strong&gt; The community of those who have the right to use the common resource is clearly defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1B. DEFINE COMMONS BOUNDARIES:&lt;/strong&gt; The boundaries of the commons are clearly defined so as to separate the usage rules from the larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2A. MAKE COSTS PROPORTIONAL:&lt;/strong&gt; Costs for using and maintaining the commons are proportional to the benefits that those users receive from the commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2B. PAY ALL COSTS:&lt;/strong&gt; People that use the commons keep costs inside the local system as much as possible. They do not externalize costs either to neighbors or future generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3A. DECIDE INCLUSIVELY:&lt;/strong&gt; Everyone who benefits from or is affected by the use of the commons makes choices about it. This includes decision-making on resource allocation and on rules and responsibilities for use of the commons. Members of the community operate with respect and mutual regard for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3B. ADAPT LOCALLY:&lt;/strong&gt; Members of the community adapt the rules and culture for the commons to local needs, resource qualities and environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4A. SHARE KNOWLEDGE:&lt;/strong&gt; All members are actively engaged in observing and sharing knowledge about the conditions of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4B. MONITOR EFFECTIVELY:&lt;/strong&gt; Monitors who are members of (or supported by and accountable to) the community view and report on the use and maintenance of the commons by community members and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. HOLD ACCOUNTABLE:&lt;/strong&gt; Violators of the rules or culture of the commons face graduated sanctions, proportional to the seriousness of the transgression. These are applied by members of the community or by others who are accountable to community for applying such consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. PROMPTLY RESOLVE CONFLICTS:&lt;/strong&gt; The community offers inexpensive, fast and easy access to mediation for effective conflict resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. GOVERN LOCALLY:&lt;/strong&gt; Community self-determination is recognized and supported by higher-level authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. CONNECT TO RELATED SYSTEMS:&lt;/strong&gt; Any side effects or other repercussions by one community to another in managing their commons, should be addressed in the context of larger, nested communities that have a legitimate role in those consequences. These externalities should be resolved by the community at the most immediate or local level (aka subsidiarity) that can operate from effective human relationships, rather than by a faceless authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALT 8. COORDINATE WITH RELATED SYSTEMS&lt;/strong&gt;: For groups that are part of larger social systems, there must be appropriate coordination among relevant groups. Every sphere of activity has an optimal scale. Large scale governance requires finding the optimal scale for each sphere of activity and appropriately coordinating the activities, a concept called polycentric governance. A related concept is subsidiarity, which assigns governance tasks by default to the lowest jurisdiction, unless this is explicitly determined to be ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2015/11/a-revised-ostroms-design-principles-for-collective-governance-of-the-commons-.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Spectrum of Consent</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/09/a-spectrum-of-consent.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 09:28:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/09/a-spectrum-of-consent.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1551c0e970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Consensus-flowchart&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1551c0e970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1551c0e970c-320wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Consensus-flowchart&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I have made understanding of consent and consensus, in both their human and technological forms, a major part of my career. I have explored them through my work in cryptographic technologies, but also in human terms at the&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://groupworksdeck.org/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Group Pattern Language Project&#34;&gt;Group Pattern Language Project&lt;/a&gt;, by co-authoring with Shannon Appecline forthcoming book on the design of collaborative games, and another book in progress on the patterns of cooperative play. My business management style is also more collaborative and inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic is so important to me that I named the company I founded in 1988 (that eventually led the effort to establish TLS 1.0 as an internet standard) was named &amp;quot;Consensus Development&amp;quot; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/19980709005818/http://www.consensus.com/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus&amp;#0160;I&amp;#39;ve been fascinated this week to watch a major online community try to define for itself what “consent” and “consensus” in their community will mean.&amp;#0160;This community in question is the Bitcoin cryptocurrency community, which is faced with a minority of the community attempting to “hard fork”. This weekend they &lt;a href=&#34;https://scalingbitcoin.org/montreal2015/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;meet in Montreal &lt;/a&gt;to attempt to discover another way to return to some form of unanimity and broad consent of their stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is of the hardest problems in human interactions. Consent comes from the Latin, meaning “feel together”, which this community now believes they lack. But&amp;#0160;it is particularly poignant that this particular community is facing these questions. Bitcoin is technologically based on a formal protocol that uses a mathematical and cryptographic method for consensus called the “blockchain”. Every 10 minutes, thousands of nodes and hundreds of miners arrive at a consensus on all the bitcoin transactions during that time. Bitcoin, and the larger Blockchain community are the worlds experts on cryptographic forms of consensus. But the human consensus problem is still hard for them too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 1.5em;&#34;&gt;A Spectrum of Consent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my recent efforts into understanding this topic, and some recent dives into my &amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Systems for Collective Choice (start of series)&#34;&gt;Systems For Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;#0160;the topic of the &lt;em&gt;A Spectrum Of Consent&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#0160;has repeatedly come up. There appear to be a range of levels of consent required for various deliberative processes and voting systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had these incomplete notes on the Spectrum of Consent around for a couple of years, which I&amp;#39;ve only shared privately. However, given my discussions this week at the&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coindesk.com/events/consensus-2015/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Consensus 2015&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;conference and elsewhere, it was time to share. I welcome comments and suggestions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, many groups view consensus processes as a requirement, however, many others see consensus processes as unworkable and a serious problem to be avoided. These efforts to define &lt;em&gt;A Spectrum Of Consent&lt;/em&gt; are somewhat to help me understand this dichotomy. I personally believe that certain deliberative processes and voting systems are good for some things, some for others. But I find I&amp;#39;m rare in that opinion — most people lean strongly in way one or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is clearly some conflation and orthogonality in my list below of types of representation (who decides), deliberation (how you approach a decision), and choice selection method (voting system), but I think this is a good start at defining a spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uniform Consensus (or Absolute Agreement)&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where all parties are required support and agree to a decision, without anyone voting to neither agree or disagree (aka abstaining).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unanimous Consent (or Unanimity)&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where all parties support and agree to a decision, however, some parties may abstain by raising no objections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consensus Decision Making&lt;/strong&gt; — A deliberative process of reaching unanimous consent (everyone agrees or abstains) with a number of procedural rules or cultural norms that limit blocking. Most forms of Consensus Decision Making all members have equal voice in the deliberation and equal vote. Most ask a closing question question such as &amp;quot;Are there any remaining unresolved concerns?&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Are there any paramount objections?&amp;quot;. Some believe that in Consensus Decision Making that there is never a “vote”. (Another &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.community4me.com/consensus.html&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;definition of consensus&lt;/a&gt;) (PDF on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://seedsforchange.org.uk/consensus.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Consensus PDF&#34;&gt;Consensus Process&lt;/a&gt;) and (&lt;a href=&#34;https://rhizomenetwork.wordpress.com/2011/05/30/when-not-to-use-consensus/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;When to not use Consensus&#34;&gt;when to not use consensus&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sense of Meeting&lt;/strong&gt; — A deliberative deliberative process practice as originally created by the Quakers. It is related to consensus which seeks “unity in the discernment of a decision” It is not necessary for every member to fully agree with a decision, but rather for members “to discern that as a body they are called in a particular direction.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consensus Minus One&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where a party may block only if they can find at least one other uninvolved party to agree to join together to block. Otherwise the decision passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consensus Seeking&lt;/strong&gt; — A deliberation process that attempt to reach unanimous consent, but can fall back to a majority vote when required. Essentially Consensus Decision Making in deliberative process — listening to those with objections, but the ability to go to a vote stops the &amp;quot;tyranny of the minority&amp;quot; that sometimes happens with consensus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mediated Consensus&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#0160;— Related to Consensus Seeking. An immediate decision can be made by consensus, but if that fails the blockers and proponents have to meet separately with or without a mediator, and if they still don&amp;#39;t agree then its brought back to the next meeting for a vote.&amp;#0160;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Consensus&amp;#0160;(still seeking right name of this one)&lt;/strong&gt; — There are some rules for how decision making is distributed into smaller, inter-related groups, each who have authority over a domain. Consensus is required within each group but not of the whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consequential Consensus (still seeking right name of this one)&lt;/strong&gt; — Only those affected by the outcome of the decision can participate and vote in the decision, which requires consensus of all those affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Representative Consensus (still seeking right name of this one)&lt;/strong&gt; — Each party who participates in the deliberation votes represents the interests of others by some rules. Consensus is required only among the representatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appreciative Inquiry Based Deliberation (another one needing naming)&lt;/strong&gt; — A deliberative process that focuses on moving forward on moving forward on things that there is agreement on that are &amp;quot;the best of what is, in order to imagine what could be, followed by collective design of a desired future state that is compelling and thus, does not require the use of incentives, coercion or persuasion for planned change to occur.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blocking or Vetoing Representation&lt;/strong&gt;— Voting systems where one or more members may have the right to block the deliberative process before a vote, or veto after a vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absolute Super Majority&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where support for a proposal to pass much be larger than a simple majority based on the entire membership rather than only on those present and voting, typically 2/3rds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Super Majority or Qualified Majority&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where support for a proposal to pass must be greater than a simple majority of those present and voting, typically 2/3rds of those voting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absolute Majority&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where support for a proposal to pass much be 50% + 1 vote, based on the entire membership rather than on those present and voting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple Majority&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where support for a proposal to pass must be 50% + 1 vote of those present and voting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules of Order or&amp;#0160;Parliamentary&amp;#0160;Procedure&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#0160;— A deliberative process such as&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%27s_Rules_of_Order&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Robert&amp;#39;s Rules of Order&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliamentary_procedure&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;other rules&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;used by legislative bodies such as a senate or parliaments,&amp;#0160;but &amp;#0160;often used by corporations for decision making such as a board of directors meeting.&amp;#0160;&amp;#0160;At their heart is the rule of the majority with respect for the minority. Its object is to allow deliberation&amp;#0160;upon questions of interest to the group and to arrive at the sense or the will of the organization as a whole upon these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plurality or Relative Majority&lt;/strong&gt; — A voting system where when there are multiple options, the largest number of votes wins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right to Fork&lt;/strong&gt; — Unique to open source communities, consensus can be reached by having the stakeholders lacking consensus to split off to form their own consensus, and since the assets are largely intellectual the can compete equally for the attention of the community and markets they serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citizen Assembly (sometimes called &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sortition&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;sortition&#34;&gt;sortition&lt;/a&gt;, public sector representation, jury or allotment)&lt;/strong&gt; — A deliberative process where a representative random sample of eligible voters is selected to make binding decisions for the group. The voting system used may be consensus or some form of majority. Ancient Athenian democracy actually form of this of this in the Boule and Jury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Authority&lt;/strong&gt; — There are some rules for how decision making is distributed into smaller, inter-related groups, each who have authority over a domain. How each group makes decisions is decided by that group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Executive Authority&lt;/strong&gt; — Rules for how a party is elected to represent a group, who then has authority to make decisions for that group, typically for a limited period of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dictatorship&lt;/strong&gt; — Executive authority exercised to ensure a monopoly of authority by its elected representative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;em&gt;(image credit:&amp;#0160;grant horwood, aka frymaster &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5-2.0-1.0&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;CC BY-SA 2.5-2.0-1.0&amp;#0160;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2015/09/a-spectrum-of-consent.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Design Principles for Governing the Commons</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/03/10-design-principles-for-governing-the-commons.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 20:55:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/03/10-design-principles-for-governing-the-commons.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c76aaed3970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Resource Sharing&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c76aaed3970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c76aaed3970b-250wi&#34; style=&#34;width: 250px; margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Resource Sharing&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elinor_Ostrom&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia Page on Elinor Ostrom&#34;&gt;Elinor Ostrom&lt;/a&gt; received the Nobel Prize in Economics for her &lt;em&gt;“analysis of economic governance, especially &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commons&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia Page on The Commons&#34;&gt;the commons&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then I&amp;#39;ve seen a number of different versions of her list of the 8 principles for effectively managing against &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia Page for The Tragedy of the Commons&#34;&gt;the tragedy of the commons&lt;/a&gt;. However, I&amp;#39;ve found&amp;#0160;her original words — as well as many adaptions I&amp;#39;ve seen since — to be not very accessible. Also, since the original release of the list of 8 principles there has been some research resulting in updates and clarifications to her original list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last weekend, at two very different events — one on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.futureofworking.org&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Future of Working Summit&#34;&gt;future of working&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and the other on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://crypto.sabir.cc/?page_id=237&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;future of the block chain&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;(used by technologies like bitcoin) — I wanted to share these principles. However, I was unable to effectively articulate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So&amp;#0160;I decided to take an afternoon to re-read the original, as well as more contemporary adaptions, to see if I could summarize this into a list of effective design principles. I also wanted to generalize them for broader use as I often apply them to everything from how to manage an online community to how a business should function with competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up with 10 principles, each beginning with a verb-oriented commandment, followed by the design principle itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DEFINE BOUNDARIES:&lt;/strong&gt; There are clearly defined boundaries around the common resources of a system from the larger environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DEFINE LEGITIMATE USERS:&lt;/strong&gt; There is a clearly defined community of legitimate users of those resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADAPT LOCALLY:&lt;/strong&gt; Rules for use of resources are adapted to local needs and conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DECIDE INCLUSIVELY:&lt;/strong&gt; Those using resources are included in decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MONITOR EFFECTIVELY:&lt;/strong&gt; There exists effective monitoring of the system by accountable monitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SHARE KNOWLEDGE:&lt;/strong&gt; All parties share knowledge of local conditions of the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HOLD ACCOUNTABLE:&lt;/strong&gt; Have graduated sanctions for those who violate community rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OFFER MEDIATION:&lt;/strong&gt; Offer cheap and easy access to confict resolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GOVERN LOCALLY:&lt;/strong&gt; Community self-determination is recognized by higher-level authorities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DON&amp;#39;T EXTERNALIZE COSTS:&lt;/strong&gt; Resource systems embedded in other resource systems are organized in and accountable to multiple layers of nested communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I welcome your thoughts on ways to improve on this summarized list. In particular, in #10 I&amp;#39;d like to find a better way to express its complexity (the original is even more obtuse).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I love it Chris.  Our conversation this morning was about playing the role of the &#34;translator.&#34;  You work fast.
Quick notes:
#7 has a typo (sanction).
Could number 10 be rephrased as Internalize Externalities? (that may be even more abstract)
And at what level is ten really about feedback loops&gt; -- particularly since resources actual &#34;cost&#34; can be hard to even estimate, particularly when those resources are the result of thousands of years of natural processes (ex: oil, or fertile soil).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://matthewschutte.com&#34;&gt;Matthew Schutte&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2015-03-25T02:24:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2015-03-25T02:24:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thank you. Linked here;
http://solidarity.coop/wiki/Governance_Principles
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/ccsolidarity&#34;&gt;Ccsolidarity&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2015-03-25T19:49:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2015-03-25T19:49:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Christopher, let me suggest the following revisions to items 3, 5, and 10, based on:
Cox, M., G. Arnold, and S. Villamayor Tomás. 2010. A review of design principles for community-based natural resource management. Ecology and Society 15(4): 38. [online] URL: http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol15/iss4/art38/
3.  ESTABLISH LOCALLY　APPROPRIATE RULES　FOR　USING AND MAINTAINING RESOURCES: Rules for use and maintenance of resources are adapted to local needs and conditions, and provide benefits to users that are correlated to their level of inputs.
5.  EFFECTIVELY MONITOR RESOURCES AND USERS: There exists effective monitoring of the system by monitors who are accountable to the users.
10. TIE-IN TO RELATED SYSTEMS: The resource system is appropriately connected to parent/fraternal/subordinate resource groups and to governmental systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/tokyotom&#34;&gt;TokyoTom&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2015-03-28T03:08:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2015-03-28T03:08:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Excellent version. I think a critical adaptation is the active voice, as you&#39;ve done in the bold verbs.
#10 expresses a dynamic relationship with #9, yes? Thus, &#34;govern locally&#34; (or &#34;organize locally&#34;) is in relation to &#34;don&#39;t externalize costs.&#34; That is, within holarchies or (spatially, temporally, institutionally) nested set of commons or jurisdictions, both other levels and other holarchies are recognized and respected. Perhaps the positive flip on &#34;don&#39;t externalize costs&#34; would be &#34;seek to externalize benefits&#34;? In other words, seek to transmit one&#39;s learnings from such local organization up the holarchy and across to other holarchies. Like Ostrom did, and one seeks to do, by developing design principles!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.solvingforpattern.org/&#34;&gt;Howard Silverman&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2015-04-11T11:34:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2015-04-11T11:34:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2015/03/10-design-principles-for-governing-the-commons.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>