<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Software on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/social-software/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Software on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 23:07:58 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/social-software/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining “Participatory Ecosystem” — Grow the Pie, Not Slice It!</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2016/04/defining-participatory-ecosystem-grow-the-pie-not-slice-it.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 23:07:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2016/04/defining-participatory-ecosystem-grow-the-pie-not-slice-it.html</guid>
      <description>As part of being a&amp;#0160;member of the sustainable MBA community at Pinchot University, I have been trying to articulate what I like about the kinds of collaboration that are possible even inside a competitive industry. In our MBA program, we don&amp;#39;t just teach about competitive strategy&amp;#0160;(using classic&amp;#39;s like Porter&amp;#39;s book), but we also teach about the nature of&amp;#0160;coopetition. These practices&amp;#0160;are more&amp;#0160;likely to lead to sustainable businesses (not only sustainable=green, but sustainable=enduring).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Revised “Ostrom’s Design Principles for Collective Governance of the Commons”</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/11/a-revised-ostroms-design-principles-for-collective-governance-of-the-commons-.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 15:23:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/11/a-revised-ostroms-design-principles-for-collective-governance-of-the-commons-.html</guid>
      <description>The traditional economic definition of “the commons” are those resources that are held in common and not privately owned. This is closely related to economic concept of public goods, which are goods that are both non-excludable (in that individuals cannot be effectively excluded from use) and non-rivalrous (where use by one individual does not reduce availability to others).
My own personal definition for the commons is broader — any regenerative, self-organizing complex system that can be drawn upon for deep wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Spectrum of Consent</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/09/a-spectrum-of-consent.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 09:28:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/09/a-spectrum-of-consent.html</guid>
      <description>I have made understanding of consent and consensus, in both their human and technological forms, a major part of my career. I have explored them through my work in cryptographic technologies, but also in human terms at the&amp;#0160;Group Pattern Language Project, by co-authoring with Shannon Appecline forthcoming book on the design of collaborative games, and another book in progress on the patterns of cooperative play. My business management style is also more collaborative and inclusive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Four Kinds of Privacy</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/04/the-four-kinds-of-privacy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 22:30:30 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/04/the-four-kinds-of-privacy.html</guid>
      <description>(This article has been cross-posted in Medium)

Privacy is hitting the headlines more than ever. As computer users are asked to change their passwords again and again in the wake of exploits like Heartbleed and Shellshock, they&amp;#39;re becoming aware of the vulnerability of their online data — a susceptibility that was recently verified by scores of celebrities who had their most intimate photographs stolen.
Any of us could have our privacy violated at any time… but what does that mean exactly?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Design Principles for Governing the Commons</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/10-design-principles-for-governing-the-commons.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 20:55:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/10-design-principles-for-governing-the-commons.html</guid>
      <description>In 2009, Elinor Ostrom received the Nobel Prize in Economics for her “analysis of economic governance, especially the commons”.
Since then I&amp;#39;ve seen a number of different versions of her list of the 8 principles for effectively managing against the tragedy of the commons. However, I&amp;#39;ve found&amp;#0160;her original words — as well as many adaptions I&amp;#39;ve seen since — to be not very accessible. Also, since the original release of the list of 8 principles there has been some research resulting in updates and clarifications to her original list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mini Resume Card for Conference Season</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 23:55:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html</guid>
      <description>Between the business of the March/April conference season and leaving Blackphone, I&#39;ve run out of business cards. Rather than rush to print a bunch of new ones, I&#39;m created this mini-resume for digital sharing and a two-sided Avery business card version that I am printing on my laser printer and sharing.
Not as pretty as my old Life With Alacrity cards, but effective in getting across the diversity of my professional experience and interests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kathy Sierra of Serious Pony on Trolls</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/10/kathy-sierra-of-serious-pony-on-trolls.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 11:47:43 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/10/kathy-sierra-of-serious-pony-on-trolls.html</guid>
      <description>Post by Christopher Allen. original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Context Shared Languages</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/06/deep-context-shared-languages.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 20:58:04 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/06/deep-context-shared-languages.html</guid>
      <description>If you consider yourself a futurist or an agent of change, you should read this article from The Atlantic &amp;quot;Shaka, When the Walls Fall&amp;quot;. Yes, it uses a Star Trek episode as an allegory, it is a bit confusing and has a lot of complexity and depth, but it is a good introduction to a topic I care about — Deep Context Shared Languages.
I consider one of my missions in life to be to &amp;quot;create tools that allow people to communicate about complexity&amp;quot;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Look Up” Your Strong Ties, Connect to Your Weak Ties</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/05/look-up-your-strong-ties-connect-to-your-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 12:02:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/05/look-up-your-strong-ties-connect-to-your-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>Post by Christopher Allen. original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“The Really Big Questions” Podcast Asks “Why Do We Share?”</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/04/the-really-big-questions-podcast-asks-why-do-we-share.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 10:39:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/04/the-really-big-questions-podcast-asks-why-do-we-share.html</guid>
      <description>Post by Christopher Allen. original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the Sharing Economy Changing Our Culture of Trust?</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/04/is-the-sharing-economy-changing-our-culture-of-trust.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 12:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/04/is-the-sharing-economy-changing-our-culture-of-trust.html</guid>
      <description>Post by Christopher Allen. original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To be persuasive, you need to understand “Identity Protective Cognition”</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/04/to-be-persuasive-you-need-to-understand-identity-protective-cognition.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 13:35:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/04/to-be-persuasive-you-need-to-understand-identity-protective-cognition.html</guid>
      <description>Post by Christopher Allen. Comments Actually, the implication of the study is that argument, as the term is conventionally understood, is a myth and that persuasion is functionally impossible. Also that nobody knows anything, nor can they. S.M. Stirling 2014-06-04T16:18:36-07:00   original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second Gov &amp; The Consensus Project</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/03/second-gov-the-consensus-project.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/03/second-gov-the-consensus-project.html</guid>
      <description>Post by Christopher Allen. original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dyads &amp; Triads — The Smallest Teams</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:16:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html</guid>
      <description>(by Christopher Allen with Elyn Andersson and Shannon Appelcline)
Two years ago, the Bainbridge Graduate Institute (www.BGI.edu) faculty gathered to radically reinvent their sustainable business curriculum for the next decade. Our goal was not only to update course content, but also to significantly update how the material was taught. We wished to make our teaching process (our pedagogy) more interactive and also more effective for students graduating into a 21st-century work environment, where people increasingly work in teams-both online and offline.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to the Social Web (Reading List #SW4SX)</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2012/10/introduction-to-the-social-web-reading-list-sw4sx.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2012 17:21:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2012/10/introduction-to-the-social-web-reading-list-sw4sx.html</guid>
      <description>These are the initial required readings for the first two weeks of my Using the Social Web for Social Change class (hashtag #SW4SX) that I teach in the MBA in Sustainable Systems&amp;#0160;program at Bainbridge Graduate Institute.
The goal of this portion of the class is to&amp;#0160;cover an introduction and overview of the landscape of the Social Web, establish among the students the beginning of a shared language about the medium, and introduce a process toward a collaborative culture that we will use for the rest of the course.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing your Social Graph with Google&#43; [Google Plus]</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</guid>
      <description>With Google+ almost two weeks into its test phase, conversation about this new social network service seems to be going in circles.
Literally.
That’s because Circles is the Google+ feature that users are generating the most buzz about. It’s Google’s answer to the problem of organizing your social graph online.
If you’re not familiar with a social graph it’s a map of everyone you know and how they are related to you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facilitating Small Gatherings Using “The Braid”</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/09/facilitating-small-gatherings-using-the-braid.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2009 16:19:40 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/09/facilitating-small-gatherings-using-the-braid.html</guid>
      <description>I was musing as I was preparing for next week&amp;#39;s Intensive at BGI that I have 21 students in my class, an uncomfortable size. That&amp;#39;s because it lies between a smaller size where good conversations naturally occur, and a larger size where you can take full advantage of different activities that work well for larger groups.
I talk about this a bit in my Group Threshold and Dunbar Number posts, where I call the group threshold size of between 10 and 24 people the&amp;#0160;“Judas Number” nadir, or low point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creative Commons Posts “Defining Noncommercial” Report</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/09/creative-commons-posts-defining-noncommercial-report.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2009 13:55:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/09/creative-commons-posts-defining-noncommercial-report.html</guid>
      <description>Last year I participated in a survey followed up by a focus group on the topic of Noncommercial Use, in particular around the context that about 2/3rds of the Creative Commons licenses extant use the NC attribute, such as in&amp;#0160;CC-BY-NC.
Defining &amp;quot;Noncommercial&amp;quot;: &amp;#0160;A Study of how the Online Population Understands &amp;quot;Noncommercial&amp;quot; Use
http://wiki.creativecommons.org/Defining_Noncommercial
 
The topic is somewhat of a sticky one, as there are many competing interests. There are content creators who wish to profit from their work, there are other content creators who don&amp;#39;t want anyone to profit (even themselves), and of course there are content creators who want everything to be free provided you share free content back.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community by the Numbers, Part III: Power Laws</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/03/power-laws.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 01:46:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/03/power-laws.html</guid>
      <description>In my first article&amp;#0160;in this series I talked about community numbers: how the sizes of groups ultimately affect their success (or failure). However what I discussed only offers up the most rudimentary explanation of the dynamics, and that is because typically not all of the members of a group are equally involved.
In order to better define who constitutes the tightly-knit &amp;quot;participant community&amp;quot; upon which the group thresholds act, we have to study power laws which let us measure the intensity of individuals&amp;#39; involvement in a group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2008 12:44:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I talked about the limits on sizes of tightly-knit communities. These group limits are closely related to a number of interesting personal limits, and are often confused with them.
Unlike the group limits, personal limits actually measure something different: the number of connections that an individual can hold. They&#39;re yet another thing that you must consider when thinking about communities of people.
Personal Limits The Support Circle: This is the number of individuals that you seek advice, support, or help from in times of severe emotional or financial stress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community by the Numbers, Part One: Group Thresholds</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2008 13:53:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html</guid>
      <description>We often think of communities as organic creatures, which come into existence and grow on their own. However, the truth is they are fragile blossoms. Although many communities surely germinate and bloom on their own, purposefully creating communities can take a tremendous amount of hard work, and one factor their success ultimately depends upon is their numbers.
If a community is too small you&#39;ll often have insufficient critical mass to sustain it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Blog for Ephemera</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/07/new-blog-for-ep.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2008 13:22:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/07/new-blog-for-ep.html</guid>
      <description>This blog has been quiet lately as I&#39;ve been doing a lot of work in the last year on the iPhone. I&#39;ve been speaking at conferences like eComm 2008 (presentation, video from panel), writing an book on the iPhone with my co-author Shannon Appelcline called iPhone in Action: Introduction to Web and SDK Development (first two chapters free), and I am one of the organizers for the upcoming iPhoneDevCamp 2, a MacHack style conference on August 1st-3rd, and I am working on some social software apps for the iPhone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Ready for the iPhone</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/06/getting_ready_f.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2007 20:06:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/06/getting_ready_f.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been excited about the web capabilities of the upcoming iPhone for some time. As a reluctant laptop user (&amp;quot;oh, my aching shoulders&amp;quot;), there is real appeal to me in a better portable web browser. I have tried most of the PDA and cellphone browsers to date, and none offer more then a poor cousin to the web that we experience on the desktop.
Instead, the iPhone offers a desktop-class browser.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Experimenting with Ratings</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 22:38:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[This is the fourth in a series of articles on collective choice, co-written by my collegue Shannon Appelcline. It will be jointly posted in Shannon&#39;s Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities online games column at Skotos.]
Last year in Collective Choice: Rating Systems we took a careful look at eBay and other websites that collect ratings, and used those systems as examples to highlight a number of theories about how to make rating systems more useful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking about SynchroEdit at WikiWednesday</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/12/speaking_about_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2006 14:34:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/12/speaking_about_.html</guid>
      <description>I will be speaking tonight at WikiWednesday on the topic of Same Time, Different Place Editing, and will be demonstrating SynchroEdit integration with MediaWiki and EditThisPagePHP.  If you are interested, see you tonight (Wednesday) at 6-8pm, at Socialtext. original layout</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ratings: Who Do You Trust?</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2006 16:28:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html</guid>
      <description>My colleague, Shannon Appelcline, has been working on a game rating system for RPGnet. This has resulted in real-world application of the principles for designing rating systems which we&#39;ve previously discussed in our Collective Choice articles. Shannon&#39;s newest article, Ratings, Who Do You Trust? offers a look at weighting ratings based on reliability.
On the RPGnet Gaming Index we&#39;ve put this all together to form a tree of weighted ratings that answer the question, who do you trust?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Number Presentation at MeshForum 2006</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2006 11:52:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html</guid>
      <description>Last May I did an abbreviated version of my Dunbar Number talk at MeshForum 2006. A MP3 podcast of that talk is now available at IT Conversations&amp;nbsp; or can be downloaded here (10mb).
If you&#39;d like to follow along, here is a pdf copy of my presentation sides (10mb).
Biggest addition to what I&#39;ve written about before is some discussion about different kinds of social software and what what size groups they seem to be appropriate for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Number Presentation at MeshForum 2006</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2006 11:52:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html</guid>
      <description>Last May I did an abbreviated version of my Dunbar Number talk at MeshForum 2006. A MP3 podcast of that talk is now available at IT Conversations&amp;nbsp; or can be downloaded here (10mb).
If you&#39;d like to follow along, here is a pdf copy of my presentation sides (10mb).
Biggest addition to what I&#39;ve written about before is some discussion about different kinds of social software and what what size groups they seem to be appropriate for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using 5-Star Rating Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 08:49:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</guid>
      <description>In Collective Choice: Rating Systems I discuss ratings scales of various sorts, from eBay&#39;s 3-point scale to RPGnet&#39;s double 5-point scale, and BoardGame Geek&#39;s 10-point scale.

Of the various ratings scales, 5-point scales are probably the most common on the Internet. You can find them not just in my own RPGnet, but also on Amazon, Netflix, and iTunes, as well as many other sites and services. Unfortunately 5-point rating scales also face many challenges in their use, and different studies suggest different flaws with this particular methodology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using 5-Star Rating Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 08:49:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</guid>
      <description>In Collective Choice: Rating Systems I discuss ratings scales of various sorts, from eBay&#39;s 3-point scale to RPGnet&#39;s double 5-point scale, and BoardGame Geek&#39;s 10-point scale.

Of the various ratings scales, 5-point scales are probably the most common on the Internet. You can find them not just in my own RPGnet, but also on Amazon, Netflix, and iTunes, as well as many other sites and services. Unfortunately 5-point rating scales also face many challenges in their use, and different studies suggest different flaws with this particular methodology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BayChi Talk Next Tuesday</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/07/baychi_talk_nex.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2006 13:58:20 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/07/baychi_talk_nex.html</guid>
      <description>I will be speaking next Tuesday (July 11th) at the monthly meeting of BayCHI, the San Francisco Bay Area Chapter of ACM SIGCHI (Computer Human Interface Special Interest Group), along with Michael H. Goldhaber.
The synopsis of my topic is:
The Dunbar Number, Unstructured Trust, and Why Groups Don&#39;t Scale
We are relying increasingly on internet-mediated social software tools for our day-to-day interaction with other people. To design this type of software, we must better understand the psychology and social dynamics of individuals in groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flames: Emotional Amplification of Text</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/02/flames_emotiona.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2006 13:07:32 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/02/flames_emotiona.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been a moderator/host/forum leader for various bulletin boards and other online communities since the early 1980s; first on CompuServe, later on GEnie and AOL, and then professionally in the early days of Consensus Development. One of the behaviors that happens in online communities and that I rarely see elsewhere is flaming -- where one member writes an extremely inappropriate, typically passionately worded attack on another. Flaming behavior can hurt an online community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flames: Emotional Amplification of Text</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/02/flames_emotiona.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2006 13:07:32 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/02/flames_emotiona.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been a moderator/host/forum leader for various bulletin boards and other online communities since the early 1980s; first on CompuServe, later on GEnie and AOL, and then professionally in the early days of Consensus Development. One of the behaviors that happens in online communities and that I rarely see elsewhere is flaming -- where one member writes an extremely inappropriate, typically passionately worded attack on another. Flaming behavior can hurt an online community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being an Angel</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/on_being_an_ang.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2006 18:17:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/on_being_an_ang.html</guid>
      <description>In the last month or so I&#39;ve received a number of links to Life With Alacrity as a venture capital blog, and to myself as a venture capitalist.
 However, I don&#39;t consider myself a venture capitalist. Instead, I am what is known as an &amp;quot;angel investor&amp;quot;.
This week has also seen a new topic enter the blog zeitgeist: the topic of reforming or reinventing venture capital. This topic was initially raised by Dave Winer, followed by Robert Scoble, Doc Searls, Jeff Nolan, Michael Arrington, Thatedeguy and many more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2006 23:37:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[This is the third in a series of articles on collective choice, co-written by my collegue Shannon Appelcline. It will be jointly posted in Shannon&#39;s Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities online games column at Skotos.]
In our first article on collective choice we outlined a number of different types of choice systems, among them voting, polling, rating, and ranking. Since then we&#39;ve been spending some time expanding upon the systems, with the goal being to create both a lexicon of and a dialogue about systems for collective choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Rating Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2005 17:58:34 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[This is the second of a series of articles on collective choice, co-written by my collegue Shannon Appelcline. It will be jointly posted in Shannon&#39;s Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities online games column at Skotos.]
In our previous article we talked about the many systems available for collective choice. There are selection systems, which are primarily centered on voting and deliberation, opinion systems, which represent how voting could occur, and finally comparison systems, which rank or rate different people or things in a simple, comparative manner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems for Collective Choice</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2005 16:03:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[Shannon Appelcline is a friend and colleague of mine at Skotos, an online game company. Over the last few years we&#39;ve had many discussions about how decisions are made, and how our society collectively makes choices. The origin of these discussions have varied from &amp;quot;what makes this board game work?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how can we give our players more control of our online games?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how do we make decisions in our company?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Number &amp; Group Cohesion</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2005 16:16:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html</guid>
      <description>There is some more excellent research this week by Nick Yee and Nicolas Ducheneaut in the PlayOn blog. Again, their research provides good insight into social group dynamics as they appear in online games.
I last mentioned their research on guild sizes in my blog post Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft where I compare the distribution of guild sizes in Ultima Online vs PlayOn&amp;#39;s results from World of Warcraft. However, both distribution tables suffer from a variety of biases due to the nature of the different game designs, many of which are discussed in the commments in the post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Number &amp; Group Cohesion</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2005 16:16:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html</guid>
      <description>There is some more excellent research this week by Nick Yee and Nicolas Ducheneaut in the PlayOn blog. Again, their research provides good insight into social group dynamics as they appear in online games.
I last mentioned their research on guild sizes in my blog post Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft where I compare the distribution of guild sizes in Ultima Online vs PlayOn&amp;#39;s results from World of Warcraft. However, both distribution tables suffer from a variety of biases due to the nature of the different game designs, many of which are discussed in the commments in the post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SynchroEdit: Simultaneous Editing for the Web</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2005 16:04:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html</guid>
      <description>For the last several months I&#39;ve been working on a new open source project that I&#39;ve been calling SynchroEdit. SynchroEdit is a browser-based simultaneous multiuser editor, useful for &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration.
The basic concept is that it allows multiple users to WYSIWYG edit a single web-based document, all at exactly the same time. SynchroEdit continuously synchronizes all changes so that users always see the same version. They can also see each others&#39; changes as they type, see where each user is currently editing, and see each others&#39; changes by color.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar &amp; World of Warcraft</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2005 16:01:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html</guid>
      <description>In my initial blog entry on the Dunbar Number I presented some statistics on group sizes based on the online game Ultimata Online. In it you could clearly see the power-law (pareto) curve, with diminishing returns at around 150, with most groups being 60 in size:


More recently, Nick Yee and other researchers at the PlayOn Blog have been researching the behaviors of players in the popular World of Warcraft online game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2005 16:35:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</guid>
      <description>In yesterday&#39;s All Things Considered, NPR commentator Jake Halpern questions why you feel like you have a relationship with the characters in your favorite TV shows. His answer: &amp;quot;That&#39;s because you do.&amp;quot; This idea is interesting not just to help us understand how we relate to imaginary characters, but also to correlate with our own understanding of Dunbar Number relationship limits and how they might relate to this concept.
In his commentary, Bostonian Jake Halpern considers two academic ideas, &amp;quot;belongingness theory&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;para-social relationships&amp;quot;, and how they affect the relationships we develop with television characters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2005 16:35:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</guid>
      <description>In yesterday&#39;s All Things Considered, NPR commentator Jake Halpern questions why you feel like you have a relationship with the characters in your favorite TV shows. His answer: &amp;quot;That&#39;s because you do.&amp;quot; This idea is interesting not just to help us understand how we relate to imaginary characters, but also to correlate with our own understanding of Dunbar Number relationship limits and how they might relate to this concept.
In his commentary, Bostonian Jake Halpern considers two academic ideas, &amp;quot;belongingness theory&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;para-social relationships&amp;quot;, and how they affect the relationships we develop with television characters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extrapolative Hostility in the Online Medium</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/extrapolative_h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2005 14:13:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/extrapolative_h.html</guid>
      <description>ExtrapolateTo infer an unknown from something that is known; conjecture.&amp;ndash; The Random House College Dictionary Mick LaSalle, an acerbic movie reviewer for the San Francisco Chronicle, writes a regular column &amp;quot;Ask Mick LaSalle&amp;quot; in the Sunday paper, where he sometimes allows others to vent their displeasure at his movie reviews. In this week&amp;rsquo;s column he says something that I find very accurate to my experience with the online medium:
As for why people get hostile when they hear a differing opinion, I go back to Spinoza&amp;rsquo;s definition of love and hatred.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extrapolative Hostility in the Online Medium</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/extrapolative_h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2005 14:13:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/extrapolative_h.html</guid>
      <description>ExtrapolateTo infer an unknown from something that is known; conjecture.&amp;ndash; The Random House College Dictionary Mick LaSalle, an acerbic movie reviewer for the San Francisco Chronicle, writes a regular column &amp;quot;Ask Mick LaSalle&amp;quot; in the Sunday paper, where he sometimes allows others to vent their displeasure at his movie reviews. In this week&amp;rsquo;s column he says something that I find very accurate to my experience with the online medium:
As for why people get hostile when they hear a differing opinion, I go back to Spinoza&amp;rsquo;s definition of love and hatred.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Sidebar: Recent Bookmarks</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/04/if_you_read_my_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2005 11:40:41 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/04/if_you_read_my_.html</guid>
      <description>If you read my blog through an aggregator, you may not have noticed my new sidebar &amp;quot;Recent Bookmarks&amp;quot;. It is a list of web pages that I&#39;ve found interesting enough to annotate using the del.icio.us service. It is useful if you want to have an insight into what future blog entries I&#39;m working on, as links will often show up there before my actual blog posting is out.
You alternatively can view my last 10 del.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Topics</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/04/future_topics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2005 01:08:16 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/04/future_topics.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been working on an ambitious list of topics that I&#39;d like to cover over the next year. I offer them to you here so you can have some idea the areas that I am thinking about.
Office Architecture for Innovation -- Over the years I&#39;ve built or converted three offices to my specifications. From this I have learned a number of things about about how to create a productive environment innovation-oriented businesses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:38:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</guid>
      <description>In my post about the Dunbar Number I offered some evidence on the levels of satisfaction of various group sizes based on some empirical data from online games. There I was able to show that even though the Dunbar Number might predict a mean group size of 150 for humans, that in fact for non-survival oriented groups the mean was significantly less, probably between 60 to 90.
 I also offered a second hypothesis, that there is a dip in satisfaction level of groups at around the size of 15.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:38:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</guid>
      <description>In my post about the Dunbar Number I offered some evidence on the levels of satisfaction of various group sizes based on some empirical data from online games. There I was able to show that even though the Dunbar Number might predict a mean group size of 150 for humans, that in fact for non-survival oriented groups the mean was significantly less, probably between 60 to 90.
 I also offered a second hypothesis, that there is a dip in satisfaction level of groups at around the size of 15.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Content, Social Software &amp; Online Games</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/user_content_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2005 15:17:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/user_content_so.html</guid>
      <description>Shannon Appelcline, my colleague at Skotos (an online game company that I founded in 1999), has been writing for several years a sometimes weekly, sometimes bi-weekly column on the topic of game design called Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities (rss feed for all Skotos Articles including TT&amp;amp;T).
His latest column Social Software &amp;amp; Gaming: User Content discusses issues of user content and user facilitation that apply both online game communities and social software:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Content, Social Software &amp; Online Games</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/user_content_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2005 15:17:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/user_content_so.html</guid>
      <description>Shannon Appelcline, my colleague at Skotos (an online game company that I founded in 1999), has been writing for several years a sometimes weekly, sometimes bi-weekly column on the topic of game design called Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities (rss feed for all Skotos Articles including TT&amp;amp;T).
His latest column Social Software &amp;amp; Gaming: User Content discusses issues of user content and user facilitation that apply both online game communities and social software:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voluntary Health Associations &amp; Social Software</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 11:20:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m a keynote speaker for the FVHA (Future of Voluntary Health Associations) Conference in Atlanta today. My job is to give to this community a gentle introduction and overview of concepts and products related to Social Software and Social Networking. (My slides are here - 6.6MB .pdf)
 In my research about this community, I find that they have some unique and interesting problems.
The attendees of this conference are a collection of VPs and national directors from major Voluntary Health Associations such as American Cancer Society, American Heart Association, American Diabetes Association, March of Dimes, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voluntary Health Associations &amp; Social Software</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 11:20:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m a keynote speaker for the FVHA (Future of Voluntary Health Associations) Conference in Atlanta today. My job is to give to this community a gentle introduction and overview of concepts and products related to Social Software and Social Networking. (My slides are here - 6.6MB .pdf)
 In my research about this community, I find that they have some unique and interesting problems.
The attendees of this conference are a collection of VPs and national directors from major Voluntary Health Associations such as American Cancer Society, American Heart Association, American Diabetes Association, March of Dimes, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2005 15:05:50 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</guid>
      <description>As someone who now has over 171 professional &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot; in my LinkedIn Profile, 198 &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut, many more non-intersecting friends and acquaintances on&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Tribe.Net, LiveJournal, and other social networking services, as well as a plethora of correspondents that I only interact with via email, I am trying reconcile a mismatch between my connections and my own Dunbar Number.
How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2005 15:05:50 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</guid>
      <description>As someone who now has over 171 professional &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot; in my LinkedIn Profile, 198 &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut, many more non-intersecting friends and acquaintances on&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Tribe.Net, LiveJournal, and other social networking services, as well as a plethora of correspondents that I only interact with via email, I am trying reconcile a mismatch between my connections and my own Dunbar Number.
How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracing the Evolution of Social Software</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/tracing_the_evo.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2004 23:40:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/tracing_the_evo.html</guid>
      <description>The term &#39;social software&#39;, which is now used to define software that supports group interaction, has only become relatively popular within the last two or more years. However, the core ideas of social software itself enjoy a much longer history, running back to Vannevar Bush&#39;s ideas about &#39;memex&#39; in 1945, and traveling through terms such as Augmentation, Groupware, and CSCW in the 1960s, 70s, 80s, and 90s.
By examining the many terms used to describe today&#39;s &#39;social software&#39; we can also explore the origins of social software itself, and see how there exists a very real life cycle concerning the use of technical terminology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracing the Evolution of Social Software</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/tracing_the_evo.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2004 23:40:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/tracing_the_evo.html</guid>
      <description>The term &#39;social software&#39;, which is now used to define software that supports group interaction, has only become relatively popular within the last two or more years. However, the core ideas of social software itself enjoy a much longer history, running back to Vannevar Bush&#39;s ideas about &#39;memex&#39; in 1945, and traveling through terms such as Augmentation, Groupware, and CSCW in the 1960s, 70s, 80s, and 90s.
By examining the many terms used to describe today&#39;s &#39;social software&#39; we can also explore the origins of social software itself, and see how there exists a very real life cycle concerning the use of technical terminology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JotSpot: Application Wiki</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/jotspot_applica.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2004 00:39:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/jotspot_applica.html</guid>
      <description>Joe Kraus, one of the co-founders of Excite, and new blogger has long been rumored to be working on a new wiki tool. Today at the Web 2.0 conference Joe finally unveiled JotSpot, a new type of wiki that they have named an &#34;Application Wiki&#34;. JotSpot appears to be not only an advanced wiki, but it also moves the predominantly text-based wiki toward being able to handle structured data and web application development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TiddlyWiki</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/09/tiddlywiki.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2004 20:28:46 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/09/tiddlywiki.html</guid>
      <description>I keep an eye out for new ideas in Wiki technology (see my post from February Looking at Wiki), and I recently became fascinated by TiddlyWiki. It is sort of a one-page client-only Wiki written completely in Javascript and HTML. Like my EditThisPagePHP, it appears to be an elegant experiment to look into the future of this medium of user-editable content.
The key feature of TiddlyWiki is that instead of WikiName links leading to new pages, it displays a new set of microcontent at the top of the current page, pushing your previous content toward the bottom of the page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2004 16:56:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html</guid>
      <description>A number of my posts have been about integrating different domains of knowledge in order to better understand how human behavior should be incorporated in the design of social software. I found The Dunbar Number in sociology, and both Four Kinds of Privacy and Progressive Trust come from my work in the cryptography field. The topic of this post comes from the field of architecture.
In order to provide for Progressive Trust, you need to establish what is known as an &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2004 16:56:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html</guid>
      <description>A number of my posts have been about integrating different domains of knowledge in order to better understand how human behavior should be incorporated in the design of social software. I found The Dunbar Number in sociology, and both Four Kinds of Privacy and Progressive Trust come from my work in the cryptography field. The topic of this post comes from the field of architecture.
In order to provide for Progressive Trust, you need to establish what is known as an &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progressive Trust</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2004 23:42:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html</guid>
      <description>I believe that as we evolve social software to better serve our needs and the needs of the groups that we are involved in, we need to figure out how to apply an understanding of how human groups behave and work.
One useful concept I use I call &#34;Progressive Trust&#34;. The basic idea is to model how trust works in the real world, between real people, rather then solely relying on mathematical or cryptographic trust.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progressive Trust</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2004 23:42:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html</guid>
      <description>I believe that as we evolve social software to better serve our needs and the needs of the groups that we are involved in, we need to figure out how to apply an understanding of how human groups behave and work.
One useful concept I use I call &#34;Progressive Trust&#34;. The basic idea is to model how trust works in the real world, between real people, rather then solely relying on mathematical or cryptographic trust.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Yet Sophisticated Group Page Editing</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2004 14:58:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html</guid>
      <description>I have been leading the design of a new Open Source collaboration tool called EditThisPagePHP, which started six months ago and now is in beta.
My goal with EditThisPagePHP attempt to come close to Dave Winer&#39;s visionary statement back in May of 1999:
When I&#39;m writing for the web, and I&#39;m browsing my own site, every bit of text that I create has a button that says Edit This Page when I view it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Yet Sophisticated Group Page Editing</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2004 14:58:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html</guid>
      <description>I have been leading the design of a new Open Source collaboration tool called EditThisPagePHP, which started six months ago and now is in beta.
My goal with EditThisPagePHP attempt to come close to Dave Winer&#39;s visionary statement back in May of 1999:
When I&#39;m writing for the web, and I&#39;m browsing my own site, every bit of text that I create has a button that says Edit This Page when I view it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Kinds of Privacy</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2004 02:00:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been thinking about the nature of privacy a lot lately.
I&#39;ve long been associated with issues of preserving privacy. I helped with anti-Clipper Chip activism in the early 90s and supported various efforts to free cryptography such as PGP and other tools built with RSAREF from export control. However, my efforts in these areas wasn&#39;t really focused on privacy -- instead my focus was on issues of trust.
I&#39;ve always tried to be precise here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Kinds of Privacy</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2004 02:00:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been thinking about the nature of privacy a lot lately.
I&#39;ve long been associated with issues of preserving privacy. I helped with anti-Clipper Chip activism in the early 90s and supported various efforts to free cryptography such as PGP and other tools built with RSAREF from export control. However, my efforts in these areas wasn&#39;t really focused on privacy -- instead my focus was on issues of trust.
I&#39;ve always tried to be precise here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annoyed by Zero Degrees</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2004 00:27:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html</guid>
      <description>As I&#39;m studying social network software right now, I consider it my job to try many of the hundred some odd social networks out there right now.
I just joined Zero Degrees, and like many others, it asked me to upload my address book. I&#39;ve done this before and usually it just finds those who already have joined these networks and links us together. Typically I delete my address book at this point, and don&#39;t bother to invite contacts that are not already members of that particular network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annoyed by Zero Degrees</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2004 00:27:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html</guid>
      <description>As I&#39;m studying social network software right now, I consider it my job to try many of the hundred some odd social networks out there right now.
I just joined Zero Degrees, and like many others, it asked me to upload my address book. I&#39;ve done this before and usually it just finds those who already have joined these networks and links us together. Typically I delete my address book at this point, and don&#39;t bother to invite contacts that are not already members of that particular network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great Social Networking Posts</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/great_social_ne.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2004 08:05:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/great_social_ne.html</guid>
      <description>While I&#39;ve been out attending the SXSW Music, Movie and Interactive Conference there has been a flurry of high-quality postings about Social Networking.
Unlike many of my fellow bloggers, I find it difficult to post meaningful blogs while I&#39;m on the road. It has been my policy in my own blog postings to also be &#34;high-signal, low-noise&#34;, so normally I don&#39;t just post links without solid additional commentary, however, I&#39;m making an exception this time because of the quality and depth of these entries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great Social Networking Posts</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/great_social_ne.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2004 08:05:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/great_social_ne.html</guid>
      <description>While I&#39;ve been out attending the SXSW Music, Movie and Interactive Conference there has been a flurry of high-quality postings about Social Networking.
Unlike many of my fellow bloggers, I find it difficult to post meaningful blogs while I&#39;m on the road. It has been my policy in my own blog postings to also be &#34;high-signal, low-noise&#34;, so normally I don&#39;t just post links without solid additional commentary, however, I&#39;m making an exception this time because of the quality and depth of these entries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 14:17:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</guid>
      <description>Lately I&#39;ve been noticing the spread of a meme regarding &amp;quot;Dunbar&#39;s Number&amp;quot; of 150 that I believe is misunderstanding of his ideas.
The Science of Dunbar&#39;s Number Dunbar is an anthropologist at the University College of London, who wrote a paper on Co-Evolution Of Neocortex Size, Group Size And Language In Humans where he hypothesizes:
... there is a cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable relationships, that this limit is a direct function of relative neocortex size, and that this in turn limits group size .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 14:17:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</guid>
      <description>Lately I&#39;ve been noticing the spread of a meme regarding &amp;quot;Dunbar&#39;s Number&amp;quot; of 150 that I believe is misunderstanding of his ideas.
The Science of Dunbar&#39;s Number Dunbar is an anthropologist at the University College of London, who wrote a paper on Co-Evolution Of Neocortex Size, Group Size And Language In Humans where he hypothesizes:
... there is a cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable relationships, that this limit is a direct function of relative neocortex size, and that this in turn limits group size .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Security &amp; Cryptography: The Bad Business of Fear</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/security_crypto.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2004 14:12:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/security_crypto.html</guid>
      <description>As I head out next week to the RSA Conference I realized that it has been 13 years since I attended the first one. I remember fondly the potential and power of cryptography technology in 1991 -- public keys, digital certificates, new possibilities for privacy, digital cash, etc.
After 8 more years I left the compujter security industry on March 15, 1999. The computer security industry also seemed to be filled with as much potential as it did back in 1991.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hand-Crafting My FOAF</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2004 16:25:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html</guid>
      <description>While at eTech, I attended a number of &#34;social software&#34; sessions. One thing I heard was a persistent call from folk like Marc Canter for all the vendors to support something called FOAF. FOAF is a standard for &#34;Friend of a Friend&#34; files, and is an attempt to make machine readable information about people, groups, companies, and other online resources. In particular, it is focused on representing the information that you might typically put on your personal home page in a form such that meta-data tools can interpret it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hand-Crafting My FOAF</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2004 16:25:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html</guid>
      <description>While at eTech, I attended a number of &#34;social software&#34; sessions. One thing I heard was a persistent call from folk like Marc Canter for all the vendors to support something called FOAF. FOAF is a standard for &#34;Friend of a Friend&#34; files, and is an attempt to make machine readable information about people, groups, companies, and other online resources. In particular, it is focused on representing the information that you might typically put on your personal home page in a form such that meta-data tools can interpret it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sexism, Social Software &amp; the Blogospher</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/sexism_social_s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2004 14:37:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/sexism_social_s.html</guid>
      <description>A fascinating series of blog entries shows the promise and peril of social software and Blogs as a medium in a male-dominated technocracy:
In misbehaving.net: &#34;sexist jokes and Orkut invites&#34;, Dana Boyd writes:When i received this note, i simultaneously recognized the intended joke and felt the shudder of being so blatantly seen as an object.At Radio Free Blogistan: &#34;This social software stuff is tricky&#34; Christian Crumlish apologizes:In my mind, I was cracking on the phenomenon of me being linked to so many other men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Advice to Social Networking Services</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2004 11:39:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</guid>
      <description>I have now had CEOs of three different social networks send me emails asking me to compare Orkut to their service. I&#39;ve not had a chance to dig deeply into good answers for each specific one, but I did have some general advice that I wanted to offer given my recent experiences with Orkut.com, and my evaluation and followup on various social networking services in December.
Privacy First, be extremely careful about privacy issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Advice to Social Networking Services</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2004 11:39:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</guid>
      <description>I have now had CEOs of three different social networks send me emails asking me to compare Orkut to their service. I&#39;ve not had a chance to dig deeply into good answers for each specific one, but I did have some general advice that I wanted to offer given my recent experiences with Orkut.com, and my evaluation and followup on various social networking services in December.
Privacy First, be extremely careful about privacy issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking at Wiki</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/looking_at_wiki.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2004 05:57:48 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/looking_at_wiki.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve not just been spending time looking at social networking services, I&#39;ve also been digging deeper into wiki. I&#39;ve still got more to go, but some of these will be of interest to you if you are considering implementing a wiki for your community, or if you are a wiki developer.
Zwiki is based on Zope, and thus has a very interesting feature set. One of the more popular features is the topic mappings that it creates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking at Wiki</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/looking_at_wiki.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2004 05:57:48 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/looking_at_wiki.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve not just been spending time looking at social networking services, I&#39;ve also been digging deeper into wiki. I&#39;ve still got more to go, but some of these will be of interest to you if you are considering implementing a wiki for your community, or if you are a wiki developer.
Zwiki is based on Zope, and thus has a very interesting feature set. One of the more popular features is the topic mappings that it creates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 17:12:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</guid>
      <description>Another Orkut user and I have confirmed a privacy hole in Orkut whenever you send a message to someone via Orkut.
For instance, whenever I send a message to anyone in the system that is forwarded by email, in the message headers it will read:
 From: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;member@orkut.com&amp;gt; Reply-To: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;christophera@alacritymanagement.com; When someone reads the message in their email software, the &#34;From:&#34; line will be my name but the fake email of &amp;lt;member@orkut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 17:12:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</guid>
      <description>Another Orkut user and I have confirmed a privacy hole in Orkut whenever you send a message to someone via Orkut.
For instance, whenever I send a message to anyone in the system that is forwarded by email, in the message headers it will read:
 From: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;member@orkut.com&amp;gt; Reply-To: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;christophera@alacritymanagement.com; When someone reads the message in their email software, the &#34;From:&#34; line will be my name but the fake email of &amp;lt;member@orkut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insecurity at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2004 13:58:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</guid>
      <description>Like many others, I&#39;ve been paying attention to Orkut in the last couple of weeks. I&#39;ve answered more requests to be &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut then I have of any of the other half-dozen Social Networking Services I&#39;ve tried, and I&#39;ve looking at other people&#39;s friends to see if I know anyone. I&#39;ve yet to ask someone to join Orkut that wasn&#39;t already a member, and I&#39;ve been careful to not have anyone as a &amp;quot;friend&amp;quot; that I didn&#39;t know reasonably well and I thought knew me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insecurity at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2004 13:58:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</guid>
      <description>Like many others, I&#39;ve been paying attention to Orkut in the last couple of weeks. I&#39;ve answered more requests to be &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut then I have of any of the other half-dozen Social Networking Services I&#39;ve tried, and I&#39;ve looking at other people&#39;s friends to see if I know anyone. I&#39;ve yet to ask someone to join Orkut that wasn&#39;t already a member, and I&#39;ve been careful to not have anyone as a &amp;quot;friend&amp;quot; that I didn&#39;t know reasonably well and I thought knew me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too Many Social Network Services</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/too_many_social.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2004 19:20:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/too_many_social.html</guid>
      <description>In the last few weeks I&#39;ve gotten more invitations to friends via Orkut then I have from all the other social networks I&#39;ve tried out. I currently have 61 friends there (and they are all people I know reasonably well), whereas in several months I have only 50 connections in LinkedIn. Oddly, the number of friends I have in each of these is less the older they are. In Ryze I have 36, and in Tribe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working on Wiki Design Patterns</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/working_on_wiki.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2003 16:40:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/working_on_wiki.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been working today on understand the Design Pattern Language behind the Wiki concept. I&#39;ve been making some postings at the Meatball Wiki site on this topic. These are the new topics that I have finished today.
Category of Wiki Design Patterns
Pattern: Cheap and Easy Collaboration
Pattern: Simple Text Formatting
Pattern: Character Formatting Rules
Pattern: Paragraph Formatting Rules
Wiki Design Patterns Meta Commentary
I&#39;ve also been doing a survey of the features of various versions of Wiki that have evolved over the years, and have started posting some of them at the bottom of the pattern documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joi on Identity and Size of Networks</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/joi_on_identity.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2003 17:52:48 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/joi_on_identity.html</guid>
      <description>Joi Ito&#39;s Web: Blogger&#39;s block, collapsing facets and the number 150 offers some insights on two different topics:
The first is on the nature of identity when we write in our blogs:&#34;The depth of my identity is becoming shallow because the context has collapsed.&#34;I have a lot of sympathy with this but from a slightly different perspective -- I have so many different &#39;identities&#39; of who and what I am and what I&#39;m interested in that it makes it hard for a stranger to be able to understand me if I try to cover it in one blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socialization in Online Games</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/socialization_i.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2003 04:32:03 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/socialization_i.html</guid>
      <description>Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &#34;Trials, Triumphs &amp; Trivialities&#34; column in the Skotos Articles section recently featured a trilogy of articles about stretching the bounds of socialization in online games:
Social Gaming Interactions, Part One: A History of Form
The first article outlines the problem by looking out how social interaction has traditionally been handled in online games, and by considering how limiting these interactions typically have been. It also outlines how to expand traditional social interactions by describing three main categories of social interaction: competition, cooperation, and freeform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Followup to “Evaluating Social Network Services”</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/followup_to_eva.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2003 00:19:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/followup_to_eva.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve received a number of replies and pointers after posting my Evaluating Social Network Services here last Tuesday. Here are a few:
Invite Issues
Esther Dyson writes in her blog about invite issues for her favorite social networking service in Some Comments on LinkedIn:I am getting a lot of invitations from people I don&#39;t know. It would be great to have a button that says &#34;See inviter&#39;s profile&#34; that links directly from the confirm-or decline-invitation page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enterprise Social Networking</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/enterprise_soci.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2003 15:24:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/enterprise_soci.html</guid>
      <description>InfoWorld has an article by Ephraim Schwartz called &#34;Social Networking Targets the Enterprise&#34; that says that corporations are looking to use social networking service features in their CRM (customer relationship management) software. They mention a couple of companies that will be offering this, Contact Network, Interface Software, Spoke Software, and ZeroDegrees.For example, the ZeroDegrees dashboard would allow a person in furniture sales to be alerted when a large company leases more space or places ads for employees, thus indicating expansion and the need to furnish new office space, said Jas Dhillon, CEO of ZeroDegrees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chinese Social Network</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/chinese_social_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2003 12:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/chinese_social_.html</guid>
      <description>The Social Software Weblog discusses DragonVenture Invests in Social Networking Platform in China:&#34;If you think Friendster was slow with four million members imagine if a tens of millions, or hundreds of millions, of the two billion people in China join eFriendsnet.com! Why hasn&#39;t Friendster or Tribe.net launched international sites?!&#34;This reminds of a quote I heard this last weekend from Tom Melcher, former CNET exec, and who has recently left There to live and work in China:There are now more people in China on the Internet then there are members of the Chinese Communist Party.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Social Network Services</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2003 15:11:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html</guid>
      <description>After a week where I met a number of bloggers and social network / social software people, I decided to try to update my various networks at Ryze, Tribe.Net, LinkedIn, and Friendster.
These are my observations of these social network services after a few weeks of work.
Overview of Social Network Services ChristopherA @ Ryze This was the first social network service that I signed up that seemed to already have some of my friends on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Skotos and Social Software</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/skotos_and_soci.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2003 15:53:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/skotos_and_soci.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been interested for several years in the ability of &#34;player-generated content&#34; to create niche or small multiplayer online games, at a company I&#39;ve invested in called Skotos . At this point its oldest game Castle Marrach is completely run by the players, and 7 more games are being developed by their customers. The company is at break-even, but is not yet a &#39;commercial success&#39;. There are some learnings from the world of massively multiplayer online games that apply to other kinds of social networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>eVentor -- an eBay for Events</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/eventor_an_ebay.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2003 15:45:48 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/eventor_an_ebay.html</guid>
      <description>I have been working the last couple of weeks on a business plan idea for a company tenatively called eVentor: eVentor is a unique event marketplace that brings together event producers and attendees to dynamically create, staff, and people events of all types--from concerts and performances to reunions and seminars. It does so by using the power of smart contracts to arrive at joint consensus and by acting as a single clearing house for the entire process of event creation, from earliest negotiations to final registration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conserving Social Capital</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/conserving_soci.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2003 01:17:16 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/conserving_soci.html</guid>
      <description>A followup to my post yesterday Social Software -- Problems &amp; the Definition of &#34;Friends&#34;, I saw in Scott Lofteness&#39; blog a reference to David Hornick&#39;s VentureBlog: Conserving Social Capital:As social networking software grows more prevalent and an increasing number of people attempt to draw upon our social capital to make introductions, entertain business propositions, pass along resumes, etc., I believe we will all grow more guarded with our time and our relationships.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Software -- Problems &amp; the Definition of “Friends”</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/social_software.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2003 12:35:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/social_software.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been playing around with a number of so-called Social Software/Social Networking sites for about six months.
I&#39;m currently on Ryze with supposedly 13 &#39;Friends&#39; and 414 in &#39;Network&#39;, and Tribe.net with 20 &#39;Friends&#39; and 17,677 in my &#39;Network&#39;. I&#39;ve registered for a few others, but wasn&#39;t able to get them going much beyond registering. However, I have not registered for Friendster yet, as it was originally a dating site but I understand now that it is more then that.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>