<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Networks on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/social-networks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Networks on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 11:20:01 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/social-networks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Voluntary Health Associations &amp; Social Software</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 11:20:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a keynote speaker for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nvhainnovations.org/2005/index.htm&#34;&gt;FVHA (Future of Voluntary Health Associations) Conference&lt;/a&gt;
in Atlanta today. My job is to give to this community a gentle
introduction and overview of concepts and products related to Social
Software and Social Networking. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://web.lifewithalacrity.com/christophera/FVHA_Social_Software_Keynote_Presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;My slides are here - 6.6MB .pdf&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my research about this community, I find that they have some unique and interesting problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/acsrelay.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Acsrelay&#34; alt=&#34;Acsrelay&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;
The attendees of this conference are a collection of VPs and national
directors from major Voluntary Health Associations such as American
Cancer Society, American Heart Association, American Diabetes Association, March of
Dimes, etc. In turn, these Voluntary Health Associations organize
communities in order to raise funds for, and inform the public about
the medical implications for the different health problems that each are
concerned with. These associations have an organized volunteer base of
over five million people and raise in excess of two billion dollars
annually. They all have dedicated and diverse volunteer communities
which include practicing MDs, scientific researchers, health educators,
business executives, and working and nonworking mothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think it is the quantity of people served, the diversity of their
communities, and in particular, the need to dive deep into information
that makes these Voluntary Health Associations interesting. A women diagnosed
with breast cancer will need to make educated decisions about her own
health care in order to give informed consent. Yet she may not have the
education experience or background to understand the care decisions she
must make. She may not even have a current era computer. There are
few other online communities that need their members to understand so
deeply such difficult problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thus the desire of these associations to look deeper in to Social
Software. Of course, their key interest is in better understanding,
motivating, and expanding their volunteer networks. They are already
experts in the business of organizing traditional communities, but now
they have to deal with the changing nature of communities as their
members are now using the internet as the primary source of
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ideally Social Software can help increase their sense of touch with
their volunteers, it can empower volunteers to collaborate and work
harder and in new ways, it can increase information sharing and
innovation, and it can help drive fund-raising numbers higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the
openness of social software comes with a price. For instance, many of
these associations are afraid of enabling even simple unmoderated
discussion lists, in fear that bad or inappropriate information would be shared. There are also legitimate concerns about the quality, audience level, and attributation for even correct information. In the Q&amp;amp;A after my presentation I tried to explain how, when looking at individual blogs, or individual events of info vandalism, it is not really relevant if the communities and processes behind the Social Software are able to correct or filter those events. This is a difficult point to get across, as it requires people to learn to trust a system where the squeaky wheels and trolls are the loudest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/acslogowhite.gif&#34; title=&#34;Acslogowhite&#34; alt=&#34;Acslogowhite&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;
One particular interesting thing about this conference is that
it is one of the first between multiple associations. I know from some
other non-profits that I&#39;m working with that they often feel in
competition for funds and resources from other non-profits, so I
applaud the American Cancer Society for sponsoring this cross-pollination effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
You did a great job. This will help us serve the mission of voluntary health.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Mike Mitchell&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-03T10:21:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-03T10:21:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think this blog is very nice one and I appreciate the purpose for which it has been made. Yes Mike, it will definetly help us, continuing the mission of voluntrary health.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.safemeds.com&#34;&gt;Matthew&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-08-17T07:00:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-08-17T07:00:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is something very beneficial for humanity. Helping people voluntrary is not an easy job but  FVHA (Future of Voluntary Health Associations) is doing it easily and people are helping this association.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.safehealthdirect.com&#34;&gt;Stacy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-10-13T07:20:15-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-10-13T07:20:15-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/02/voluntary_healt.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2005 15:05:50 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ryzeblogtribefriends.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=579,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;181&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Ryzeblogtribefriends&#34; title=&#34;Ryzeblogtribefriends&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/ryzeblogtribefriends.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who now has over 171 professional &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot; in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;LinkedIn Profile&lt;/a&gt;, 198 &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=2789681602836776519&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt;, many more non-intersecting friends and acquaintances on&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cluster.tribe.net/tribe/servlet/template/pub,pcard,PeopleCard.vm?personid=ce34093a-3c72-4954-b52f-3d6bc51884af&#34;&gt;Tribe.Net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/users/christophera_/&#34;&gt;LiveJournal&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://socialsoftware.weblogsinc.com/sns-meta-list/&#34;&gt;other social networking services&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a plethora of correspondents that I only interact with via email, I am trying reconcile a mismatch between my connections and my own &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venture Capitalist &lt;a href=&#34;http://sapventures.typepad.com/main/2004/02/quality_or_quan.html&#34;&gt;Jeff Nolan&lt;/a&gt; relates similar concerns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
&amp;quot;It strikes me that the social networking theory holds that the more volume you have, the bigger your network will become by introducing degrees of separation roughly along the lines of Metcalfe&#39;s Law. I disagree, human networks do not grow in value by multiplying, but rather by reduction. For me, it&#39;s the quality of relationships that enhances my professional and personal life, not the sheer numbers.&amp;quot;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately social networking services -- be it LinkedIn, Tribe.Net, Orkut, or LiveJournal -- are making the problem worse, not solving it. Any engineer or information theorist can tell you that a system that only has amplifiers will be out of balance, and that you need attenuators in the system as well. Our current breed of social networking services have focused on amplifying our contacts not only because it serves us, but because it serves them. The more contacts that you make, the more people they potentially have in their service. However, in the long run this is unsustainable -- a social networking service also has to be useful -- merely amplifying your contacts isn&#39;t enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the problem becomes not just one unique to me, where my friends network is overextended, but rather one that&#39;s endemic to the current generation of social networking services. In order to solve it we need to look at the traditional cultural answers to the problem, compare them to technical solutions, both current and to-be-invented, and then see how a new generation of social networking services can be designed that molds the two ideas together into a more cohesive whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offer here the beginning of that discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Cultural Strategies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of overextended social networks are not new with the Internet generation. Many professions require maintaining a large base of relationships and have done so for hundreds of years, among them: politicians, salespeople, public company CEOs, and even professions that you might not think of requiring these skills such as family doctors. The Dunbar Number of 150 may be a kind of species-wide average limit, it is not an individual limit -- thus my guess is that people with an innate talent for maintaining more relationships are attracted to these professions. But even with innate talent those who follow these professions can be overwhelmed, and each have found different cultural strategies for managing larger numbers of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Spending More Time:&lt;/strong&gt; Some people just spend a lot more time keeping up with their connections. Politicians and salespeople are classic examples of professions that require significant schmoozing time in order to keep trusted connections together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does someone like a member of the US House of Representatives manage their relationships? In no way can they even come close to having a relationship with all the 645,952 people they represent. They would, however, at least have to keep up at some level with the other 435 House members, their own staff, key members of the staff of other House members, as well as key politicians and contacts back home. From what I&#39;ve read, successful politicians spend most of their days just meeting with people, and have staff dedicated to &amp;quot;tickling&amp;quot; -- keeping track of constituents, schedules, issues, etc. and reminding the politician before each meeting of the essentials they need to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of this strategy is twofold -- the time spent managing relationships can&#39;t be spent elsewhere, and the quantity of relationships lowers the quality of those relationships. For instance, my experience with most politicians and many salesperson is that I will be forgotten as soon as I leave the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Changing the Standard:&lt;/strong&gt; There are different cultural standards in each profession as to what is an acceptable relationship. Thus some people chooose a profession that manages relationships in different ways. Doctors are a good example of socializers who fit into this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your family doctor has a similar problem to that of politicians -- too many people to keep track of. Yet a good family practitioner can see you and look beyond just today&#39;s symptoms. Thus because of an ongoing relationship with you he can be a better doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way the doctor does this is through cultural and professional limits. Because of the authority, status and title granted to doctors, patients tend to defer to them. There is not an expectation that the relationship is equal. This allows the doctor to have a &#39;shallower&#39; relationship with the patient that is still acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, even this level of serial, shallow socialization can be excessive for many people. A Radiologist acquaintance of mine told me the reason why she ended up in her specialty was that she just couldn&#39;t handle the ongoing patient relationships required by other specialities -- instead, she now looks at one set of images at a time, performs a diagnosis, and doesn&#39;t have to retain any relationship to move on to the next patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also problems with changing your socialization standards. Unless it is culturally understood, or your standard is reciprocated by others, it can make you appear shallow and not trustworthy. I&#39;ve seen this when someone moves from one profession to another, say a salesperson to a manager -- styles of relationships that were acceptable among salesperson and between salespeople and customers are not quite as acceptable as those between managers and their staff. Another example is when someone moves from the East Coast to the West Coast, where the usefulness of casual alumni connections is significantly less valued, but those casual connections are unable to understand the change in standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Prioritization:&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps a more common cultural strategy for managing excessive relationships is prioritization. I could prioritize my relationships and focus only on the 100+ or so that might be the most useful to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two problems with prioritizing. First, analyses of social networks show that it is often the weak and most unrelated links that can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/context/1333462/0&#34;&gt;the most important&lt;/a&gt;. Thus any attempt to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triage&#34;&gt;triage&lt;/a&gt; may cut off some of these weak ties because I thought that the links might not be &amp;quot;useful&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, how do you tell someone &amp;quot;I&#39;m sorry, but I&#39;m overly Dunbarred, so I have removed you from my list.&amp;quot; Rejection is painful (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csudh.edu/dearhabermas/mripain01.htm&#34;&gt;MRI brain studies&lt;/a&gt; have actually shown), so I risk offending people forever by excluding them today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Technological Solutions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great hopes of social networking services is to improve the ways that we interact with other people, particularly those that we know at a distance -- the &amp;quot;weak links&amp;quot;. Right now, these services are part of the problem because they offer out-of-balance social systems. However, they can also be part of the solution; science-fiction writers and social software designers alike are starting to look at these issues and offer new solutions that would not have been possible before the advent of widespread software communication systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technological Solution - Augmentation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/geodesica.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Geodesica&#34; alt=&#34;Geodesica&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;I recently read in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0441012698/qid=1107286515/sr=8-1/ref=skotos_20/102-0974708-1794504?v=glance&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;n=507846&#34;&gt;Geodesica: Ascent&lt;/a&gt;, a new science fiction novel by Sean Williams and Shane Dix, a futurist example of augmentation as a method of maintaining extended social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0441012698/qid=1107286515/sr=8-1/ref=skotos_20/102-0974708-1794504?v=glance&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;n=507846&#34;&gt;Geodesica: Ascent&lt;/a&gt; the protagonist, &amp;quot;Melilah&amp;quot; is a politician in the distant future. She has her own problems with the Dunbar Number, and solves it with her own personalized social networking service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two things she had learned from her political career were that society depended on interpersonal relationship networks, and that everything could turn on a simple misidentification. In her fifties she had set about ensuring that her memory remained in good working order in order to avoid the latter. Anthropologists had known since the twentieth century that people were born with a ceiling on their social groups. Once Melilah exceeded the Dunbar and Hill number of 150, and rapidly acquiring still more associates, it became progressively harder to keep track of everyone she had to know. As she passed her hundredth birthday, it became only worse. Some of her contemporaries option for cortical grafts and other memory prosthetics. She, motivated by a gut-level -- some would say irrational -- desire to keep her body as free of technology as possible, opted for other means.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She had found that using a name once every two months was enough to keep her memory fresh. Any longer than that between reminders, and the associations faded, rendering recall unreliable. So she programmed a complete list of her occasional acquaintances and enemies into a database and programmed it to cycle through them ever sixty days, shuffling the order each time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A hundred years on, she was still in the habit of skimming fifty or so names a day, just to keep on the ball. By flicking through the images, voice files, place names, and more obtuse clues, she felt confident of recognizing any of the several thousand people more or less likely to interact with her at any point in the near future. The list had grown and shrunk down over the years, and many people had dropped off it entirely because of death or distance. Sometimes she added names to the list only to be surprised that they had been on it once before, decades ago, and she had forgotten them completely. That only reinforced the need for the list and the effort to keep it fresh in her mind.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure that the Dunbar Number problem is solely one of &amp;quot;recognition&amp;quot;, as illustrated by Williams and Dix. However, I think this is a great example of seeing how a traditional cultural solution to network overextension (namely, &amp;quot;Spending More Time&amp;quot;) can be better applied by Social Software. In this example Melilah&#39;s software automates the &amp;quot;ticklers&amp;quot; that politicians use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/spokekeepintouchsettings.gif&#34; title=&#34;Spokekeepintouchsettings&#34; alt=&#34;Spokekeepintouchsettings&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;Already at least one social networking service has adopted a somewhat similar idea.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://center.spoke.com/person/personalProfileTab.spoke?id=[serverID=center,ID=4877427]&#34;&gt;Spoke&lt;/a&gt; has a &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; setting. The Spoke client software will watch your Outlook mailbox and addressbook to see how often you contact various people, and if you don&#39;t email them or modify your address book entry for them periodically, will remind you that you should contact them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve never used Spoke&#39;s &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; feature -- largely for privacy reasons (I was &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html&#34;&gt;stung by a Zero Degrees&lt;/a&gt; Outlook extension), but also because Spoke seemed to be oriented toward salespeople and thus emphasized growing the network. My problem is not growing my network, but managing the network I already have more effectively. But I may have to take another look at Spoke. So, it doesn&#39;t quite offer the same solution that Melilah used in the far-future, but it&#39;s still a start upon that path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions and Questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not certain that Spoke&#39;s &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; feature, or Melilah&#39;s social recognition reminder service are the full solution to the &amp;quot;Dunbar Triage&amp;quot; problem. However, they do at least offer a few examples of people looking at the problems, and how social software can help solve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;ve outlined here there are at least three traditional methods&amp;nbsp; that we&#39;ve used to manage Dunbar Triage prior to advent of social networking services: spending more time, changing standards, and prioritization. The technological solutions that I&#39;ve offered up as an example concentrates upon the first of those cultural solutions, but it is by no means a conclusive statement on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could next-generation social networking services improve upon the ideas of changing standards or prioritization? Could simple categorization help improve expectations for attention levels that various associates receive from you? Are there ways that social networking services, acting as an intermediary, could better manage disappointment-inducing events, such as a decision to spend less attention on an associate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More so, could social software offer solutions that aren&#39;t even being considered right now? For example, many Cyberpunk novels have suggested the ideas of avatars that can collect information for you on the &#39;net while your attention is elsewhere. Could these avatars likewise maintain more distant social networks for you, without your full attention? Would that function even be desirable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some solutions are not technological -- what new skills and changes to practices, etiquette and ethics are required for our ever expanding network of relationships? Or as &lt;a href=&#34;http://alevin.com/weblog/&#34;&gt;Adina&lt;/a&gt; asks: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Who will offer us a 21st century, internet-augmented take on Dale Carnegie and Emily Post?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any problem in the developing technical world, the first step is to define the problem and to consider possible solutions. Here&#39;s the start: social networks can become too large, and many social networking services are causing the problem rather than solving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s your solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000219.html&#34; alt=&#34;gapingvoid blog, by hugh&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/zzzmkghilkj38.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Too Many Friends, by hugh, from gapingvoid blog&#34; alt=&#34;Too Many Friends, by hugh, from gapingvoid blog&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;(comic illustration from the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000219.html&#34;&gt;gapingvoid&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000823.html&#34;&gt;hugh&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think the politicians and sales people use another strategy - they pretend that they keep up with the connections, but in fact they don&#39;t.
That&#39;s why they have the people to keep them informed about people they are going to meet. They don&#39;t remember the people but they use techniques to impress them that they do. And that is why we don&#39;t like them.
YASNS let us all switch into the politician networking mode.
For some time I have beed thinking that Huminity which bases the networking on IM buddy lists is a step in the direction of making SNS more balanced, since it bases the networking on the most scarce Internet resource - user attention.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://zby.aster.net.pl&#34;&gt;Zbigniew Lukasiak&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T03:21:13-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T03:21:13-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Nice post. A few random thoughts:
This seems analogous to what happens when people move from rural communities with relatively sparse social options to the city.
Another prioritization scheme is to emphasize face to face relationships, or to distinguish between real-time and non-realtime relationships. These are not always appropriate filters, but because getting f2f or talking realtime requires a special effort, I&#39;ve found these approaches can help me gauge whether a relationship is maintainable.
The older system of etiquette, which separated personal from professional relationships, is another approach, though when I hear the words &#34;I don&#39;t do business with friends,&#34; it means someone neither a friend nor a business associate.
Perhaps there are some other frames for looking at this, e.g. time management or attention management, or as another instance of the Tyranny of Choice.  Approaching the problem as one of more choice in who we pick to be our friends and associates, or as one of more demand on us from others also colors our choice of solutions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.archival.tv&#34;&gt;Jeff Ubois&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T12:03:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T12:03:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;One way of putting the brakes on endlessly expanding contact lists is to have the SNS site charge per contact. If you really need more than 100 contacts then you&#39;d pay for them, but if not then when you&#39;ve got another 1 person you want to add to your list you&#39;d consider dropping one off your current list. It might work better with per-contact charges, so you&#39;re not forced into making a decision when you hit the package borders (101, 201, etc)
Not only does it counter the pack-rat mentality, but it also provides a business model.
Another idea I had was if the SNS would provide me with a continuous feed of updates and changes in the profiles of my contacts - I occasionally notice that some contact of mine has changed jobs, but more likely I wouldn&#39;t notice. The list of contacts just sit there, passive. This feedback would provide two forces: (1) the memory refreshing effect, and (2) the opportunity to drop those contacts that are moving into areas I don&#39;t care for.
A third idea: I&#39;d like it if the SNS I use (LinkedIn) allowed me to attach some notes or tags to each contact in my list ... I have a few there where I have to think really hard just how I happen to know them. Right now it seems that every SNS I look at lets me make connections, but every connection is bland and generic. The system is relying on me remembering why I know that person, when instead it could remember it for me.
When it comes time to triage, I&#39;d really like it if the SNS would provide a simple network map for me. Show me my immediate contacts, any connections they have amongst themselves, and my second circle contacts (anonymised if necessary). This way at least I can see that Person X is a gatekeeper to a whole different community from all my other contacts, and so should reconsider dropping them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://IAwiki.net/&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T18:44:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T18:44:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid has the right idea... but his number of 100 is still too high.
His last paragraph is golden.  When I first joined RYZE  in 2002 [ no longer an active member] I mapped out my 1 and 2 step network there.  In the diagram linked below I am the green node, my immediate neighbors are in blue and my two step contacts are in grey.
The network map reveals why Eric&#39;s 100 number is too high...
http://www.orgnet.com/RYZE2a.gif
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orgnet.com&#34;&gt;Valdis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T10:02:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T10:02:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This, and the earlier article on Dunbar numbers are interesting reading.  I&#39;m not sure whether the Dunbar number applies in all cases.
In some discussion on SNs recently, I theorised that if we analysed Social Networks that there would be people who maintained relationships in Groups, i.e meshes where everyone knows everyone.  Bridging between groups occurs because of multiple membership, i.e. person X knows all the parents in their kids soccer club, AND all the people at the office.  Dunbars number, and the theories around it, seem to apply here, i.e. to the social-grooming required in GROUPS.
There would also be people who maintain relationships, between a lot of people who mostly do NOT know each other. We used to call these people Networkers, and typically they are the people you call when you want to know who to talk to about some topic where you have no personal connections.  I&#39;m not sure whether the Dunbar number applies to those people&#39;s connections, probably the power-law applies better, i.e. they can maintain progressively more distant connections with progressively more people.
Anecdotal, if you randomly pick people in for example Orkut then you&#39;ll see the same names turn up as intermediates in many cases. This is not necessarily because those people have large numbers of Orkut friends, but because their Orkut friends are dispersed over a range of sub-groups.
I don&#39;t think that any of the SN tools do a good job of managing these kinds of relationships yet, in particular the lack of interworking between them causes problems as different Groups tend to belong to different SN systems, so the bridges are often not evident. Also the relative strength of a connection doesn&#39;t seem to drive the ranking of possible connections, i.e. I&#39;m just as likely to be presented with a potential introduction through a person with a weak connection to the target, than through someone with a strong connection.
- Mitra
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.mitra.biz/blog&#34;&gt;Mitra&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T15:40:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T15:40:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;On tactic that comes to mind is the automated equivalent of an 18th/19th century butler, who mediated social interaction at a time when the intrusive, in-person visit was one of only two ways to make social contact.
The butler has broad and nuanced knowledged of the circumstances in which the Lady is to be acknowledged to be IN.
Today&#39;s online presence indicators are flat; they tell everyone the same message; that one is working, or eating ice cream in front of the television.
A butler would understand whether one is working or not, and would put through different connections at different hours.
A butler would understand the understand the nuances of one&#39;s social circle, and admit some people automatically, allowing others to wait, and requiring still others to leave a message.
We also need the 18th/19th century interface to the Butler, the calling card, which conveys by its printed message and accompanying whether the caller is a longlost relative whom the butler may not remember; a recommendation from a reputable source; a specific message about the urgency of the visit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/weblog&#34;&gt;Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-06T08:42:20-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-06T08:42:20-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think that the key to defeating the Dunbar number is to a) establish a real relationship to begin with and b) massage that relationship at least once per year.
I find that if I&#39;ve built a meaningful relationship with someone, based on some shared experiences, simply getting in touch with someone once a year on their birthday is enough to keep the relationship alive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://chrisyeh.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Chris Yeh&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T06:25:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T06:25:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You&#39;ve got to distinguish between &#34;friends&#34; and everything else - the relationships that range across acquaintance, association, colleague and just plain &#34;potentially useful.&#34; Why treat them all with the same UI? Why not invite your true friends to share a more intimate online relationship and keep the rest in the &#34;relationship parking lot&#34; of an Orkut? Yeah, I know that friends are often useful, too, but they deserve better than to share the same utilitarian role as that guy you met at SXSW last year.
I&#39;ll invite my real friends into my Grouper hangout, but I&#39;m not a Congressional Rep, so I don&#39;t need to be responsible to hundreds of familiar names. I&#39;ve got plenty of other things to do with my time, which I believe is the case with most of us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.socialchemy.com&#34;&gt;Cliff Figallo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T15:53:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T15:53:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi, Crhis. Three years&#39; ago Adrian Scott asked this question too, and it led to his founding Ryze...
from: http://www.edge.org/q2002/q_scott.html
Edge.org&#39;s Question Page of 2002 - by Adrian Scott.
******
&#34;How do we scale up the number of quality human relationships one person can sustain by many orders of magnitude? In an increasingly connected world, how does one person interact with a hundred thousand, a million or even a billion people?&#34;
Our one fixed resource is time â€” human attention. As we become increasingly networked in the technological sense, we also become more networked in the social sense.
As our social networks scale up, we move more and more of our interactions to the technological sphere. We can have many more telephone interactions than we can have hand-written letter interactions. When we move from telephone to e mail, the number of interactions between people goes up even more dramatically.
Then we pair our e-mail interactions with a personal Web site, and we start moving our personalities into the technology net, as a way of automating and scaling up the number of relationships even further.
We end up with personal CRM systems to handle our increased interaction load, and then add interfaces from our technology net to our human forms. These interfaces will develop from current-day Palm Pilots and Blackberry&#39;s to heads-up display style interfaces in glasses and eventually retinal and neuronal interfaces.
&#34;Hi Jerry, Ahh.., we met back in 1989, May 14th at 7pm, and since then we&#39;ve exchanged 187 e-mails and 39 phone calls. I hope your cousin&#39;s daughter Gina had a wonderful graduation yesterday.&#34;
The whole range of interactions becomes organized. Introductions from one person to another, and rating systems become automated.
Currently many people run into barriers as their personal networks approach the range of thousands of people. Soon they will move to the tens of thousands, to the millions and beyond.
With these trends, the friction costs of personal introductions go down, and consequently the value of quality measurement and gatekeeping go up dramatically. As the depth of knowledge in a relationship increases, the threshold point at which you &#39;really know someone&#39; increases also. It&#39;s an arms race of intimacy.
Adrian Scott is founder of Ryze, a business networking community. He is a founding investor in Napster, got his Ph.D. in nonlinear optimization at age 20, and has sung with Placido Domingo and performed with the NYC Ballet.
*****
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://dijest.com/dontblog/&#34;&gt;Phil Wolff&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T20:12:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T20:12:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
An Avatar? Maybe that&#39;s what I&#39;m doing. I look at life as a whole. Coincidences (for lack of a non-cliched word) are road signs helping us determine a direction of movement (not necessarily in the physical realm).
I&#39;m working on a software module which links coincidental interaction within Nature and published human consciousness. Currently I&#39;m modeling Climate Change.
For my software to ultimately work within a social network, a persons daily life of data would be connected via an identifier - and freely available. Too, an aspect of human momentum would need to change dramatically - we would trust that life is a whole and not something to be mastered, assimilated, conquered. We would need to move to a much less mechanical decentralized world. And our user base would need to be decreased.
Which coincidentally, Climate Change is forcing upon us. And it&#39;s ramping up.
Google, with all the tools I need (email, blog, webpages, and soon a social network site) seemed like a potential opportunity. They never responded to my email :)
My profile is lost within LinkedIn...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;michael white&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-20T10:05:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-20T10:05:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Learning by Subtraction
The human brain has on half the number of synapses at age six as it had at age two. It learns by subtraction. So do computer based neural nets.
This principle could well be applied to organizations to increase the size of the Dunbar number that could work effectively without drowning in bureaucracy.
Consider three ways to bring order in a human organization. The chain of command, community spirit and marketplace choice.
The chain of command tends to keep demanding ever more connections. You must get permission from all these people before taking action. The free intraprise systems we set up (See The Intelligent Organization by Gifford &amp; Elizabeth Pinchot and link at the end of this post) allow people to connect and disconnect at the end of each contract at will. Teams contract with line officers and each other to get the work done, much like a virtual organization except that key competencies and trade secrets remain in the organization.
Relationships that create value are maintained; those that consume value are terminated by either party. This provides a powerful advantage over the innane connections that are often maintained in highly time consuming ways in a bureaucracy.
The force of community also has a self-organizing quality that allows people to volunteer for what has juice and walk away from relationships that consume purpose and meaning. Community is a necessary balance to free enterprise or free intraprise. Both should be used in place of the chain of command in many of the situations where the chain of command is used today.
http://www.pinchot.com/MainPages/BooksArticles/InnovationIntraprenuring/FreeIntraprise.html
http://www.pinchot.com/MainPages/BooksArticles/OtherArticles/GiftEconomy.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.bgiedu.org&#34;&gt;Gifford Pinchot&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-23T22:43:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-23T22:43:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Adina: Getting in touch once a year may keep a relationship alive, but only just. This begs the question, what do you want from your relationships? What do you value them for? What is the point in keeping a relationship on drip-feed attention when putting so little in precludes the possibility of growth, of enrichment, of greater intimacy, of learning something, of sharing the experience of life in some way.
Perhaps what we&#39;ll see, with or without the help of clever internet applications, is a polarisation: a small circle of close friends, a very wide circle of friendly acquaintances (whether social, professional, shared interest, discussion group, blog reader, etc, by origin), and an almost infinite range of potential one-off contacts. Along the lines Chris Reh is suggesting, I think.
I&#39;m not sure I need to know which of my friendly acquaintances are in touch with one another. Better just to get on and live, and concentrate on putting something into those relationships, the better to get something out of them.
Or have I missed the point?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://thiswayplease.com/extra.html&#34;&gt;Fred&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-30T21:48:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-30T21:48:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Fred, is there someone in your household who sends birthday cards and holiday cards? These are traditional tools for staying minimally in touch. They don&#39;t maintain intimacy, but they do keep an open door, so that it&#39;s easier to keep the benefits of weak ties, and regain contact when the time is right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/weblog&#34;&gt;Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-09T13:26:17-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-09T13:26:17-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I just had a minor realization: when we speak of &#34;dropping&#34; someone from our personal network, are we really doing that? The fact is, they are very probably connected to other people we do know, and so what we are really doing is *delegating* the intimate relationship to someone we also know. Being able to see a map of my local network would help a lot in deciding whether to cut someone loose or not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://IAwiki.net/&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-07-30T01:53:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-07-30T01:53:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 14:17:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately I&#39;ve been noticing the spread of a meme regarding &amp;quot;Dunbar&#39;s Number&amp;quot; of 150 that I believe is misunderstanding of his ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Science of Dunbar&#39;s Number&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar is an anthropologist at the University College of London, who wrote a paper on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbsonline.org/documents/a/00/00/05/65/bbs00000565-00/bbs.dunbar.html&#34;&gt;Co-Evolution Of Neocortex Size, Group Size And Language In Humans&lt;/a&gt; where he hypothesizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;... there is a cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable relationships, that this limit is a direct function of relative neocortex size, and that this in turn limits group size ... the limit imposed by neocortical processing capacity is simply on the number of individuals with whom a stable inter-personal relationship can be maintained.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar supports this hypothesis through studies by a number of field anthropologists. These studies measure the group size of a variety of different primates; Dunbar then correlate those group sizes to the brain sizes of the primates to produce a mathematical formula for how the two correspond. Using his formula, which is based on 36 primates, he predicts that 147.8 is the &amp;quot;mean group size&amp;quot; for humans, which matches census data on various village and tribe sizes in many cultures. The following chart shows the distribution produced by Dunbar&#39;s analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.bcg.com/images/this_is_bcg/strategy_institute/brain_size_02.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcg.com/strategy_institute_gallery/gorilla3.asp&#34;&gt;Boston Consulting Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This number of 150 has become &amp;quot;Dunbar&#39;s Number&amp;quot; and has been popularized by various very popular business books such as Malcolm Gladwell&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0316346624/ref=skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;The Tipping Point: How Little Things Can Make a Big Difference&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0111705/categories/collaboration/2003/12/21.html#a358&#34;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt;), Duncan J. Watts&#39; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0393041425/ref=pd_skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;Six Degrees: The Science of a Connected Age&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/joss/content/reviews/Podolny/&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0691005419/ref=skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;Small Worlds: The Dynamics of Networks between Order and Randomness&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ams.org/notices/200008/rev-chow.pdf&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;), and Mark Buchanan&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0393041530/ref=skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;Nexus: Small Worlds and the Groundbreaking Science of Networks&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americanscientist.org/template/BookReviewTypeDetail/assetid/16209;jsessionid=baadd3W3trYipI&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;), the ideas from which are the foundation of the various Social Network Services that I&#39;ve discussed elsewhere in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Revisiting Dunbar&#39;s Number&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, Dunbar&#39;s number has been taken as a mean size for online networks and groups, as shown in &lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0114726/2003/02/12.html#a284&#34;&gt;Ross Mayfield&#39;s Weblog&lt;/a&gt;, where he states:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;1&#34;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Distribution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Political Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;~1000s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Blogs as mass media&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Power-law (scale-free)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Social Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;~150&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Blogging Classic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Bell-curve (random)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Creative Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;~12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Blogs as dinner conversation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Dense (equal)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Dunbar&#39;s work itself suggests that a community size of 150 will not be a mean for a community unless it is highly incentivized to remain together. We can see hints of this in Dunbar&#39;s description of the number and what it means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The group size predicted for modern humans by equation (1) would require as much as 42% of the total time budget to be devoted to social grooming.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
My suggestion, then, is that language evolved as a &amp;quot;cheap&amp;quot; form of social grooming, so enabling the ancestral humans to maintain the cohesion of the unusually large groups demanded by the particular conditions they faced at the time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar&#39;s theory is that this 42% number would be true for humans if humans had not invented language, a &amp;quot;cheap&amp;quot; form of social grooming. However, it does show that for a group to sustain itself at the size of 150, significantly more effort must be spent on the core socialization which is necessary to keep the group functioning. Some organizations will have sufficient incentive to maintain this high level of required socialization. In fact the traditional villages and historical military troop sizes that Dunbar analyzed are probably the best examples of such an incentive, since they were built upon the raw need for survival. However, this is a tremendous amount of effort for a group if it&#39;s trying not just to maintain cohesion, but also to get something done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Dunbar specifically restricts himself to physically close groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;... we might expect the upper limit on group size to depend on the degree of social dispersal. In dispersed societies, individuals will meet less often and will thus be less familiar with each, so group sizes should be smaller in consequence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My anecdotal evidence generally seems to support the idea that group sizes will usually plateau at a number lower than 150 participants. This comes from 20 years of doing facilitation both on and offline, running several software companies, and running various forums at America Online. In particular, many online communities provide good evidence for Dunbar&#39;s Number actually being an upper limit (either due to reduced efficiency or due to increased dispersion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;onlinecommunities&#34;&gt;Dunbar &amp;amp; Online Communities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ultima Online&lt;/em&gt; provides one of the best examples of what sizes an online community will support because it&#39;s well documented and the overall game size is large enough to generate many smaller communities. If you look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.legendmud.org/raph/&#34;&gt;Raph Koster&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; statistics for the size of groups in &lt;em&gt;Ultima Online&lt;/em&gt;, you will see a definite point of diminishing returns at around 150; however, you will also see that most groups are around 60 large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/UOGuildPowerLaw.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;UO Guild Power Law&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/UOGuildHistogram.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;UO Guild Histogram&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jessica Mulligan, executive producer at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.turbinegames.com/&#34;&gt;Turbine Games&lt;/a&gt;, confirmed these numbers to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The numbers match up with my (currently) mostly anecdotal evidence for &lt;a href=&#34;http://ac.turbingames.com&#34;&gt;Asheron&#39;s Call&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; We have allegiances in the hundreds and even thousands of members, but most of those members are inactive, non-participatory in the group on a regular basis or are mule accounts for farming XP.&amp;nbsp; It is rare to have more than 40 or so active participants in an Allegiance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve seen similar limits myself in some of the small online games that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.com&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt; produces. For instance, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/marrach&#34;&gt;Castle Marrach&lt;/a&gt;, which is a social-dominant game (i.e. like a MUSH), the game grew quickly until we reached approximately 150-200 active users. However, whenever it grew beyond that number, it always seemed that politics and dissatisfaction would bubble up such that people would drop out, leaving us back close to 150 or 160. (That we would ever exceed 150 is a bit of a surprise, but I think it&#39;s due to any number of factors, including a variable 24-hour user base, wherein on a given day we might only see a little more then half of our community members, below Dunbar&#39;s Number, and only get up to close to 200 or so over a full week.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have had some games at Skotos that do manage to overcome Dunbarrian social limits, prime among them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/eternal-city&#34;&gt;The Eternal City&lt;/a&gt; which regularly exceeds the Marrach community by more then double. However, TEC is a much more achievement-oriented game, meaning that people spend much of their time interacting with the environment -- fighting monsters and training skills as it happens -- rather than directly interacting with other players all the time. Thus social limits become less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other online communities that I&#39;ve had experience with have been more traditional, and thus more closely met my expectations for Dunbar&#39;s Number acting as a limit rather than a mean. When I managed the Mac Developer&#39;s Forum community on AOL, a forum would start to break down when it reached about 80 active contributors, requiring a forum split before continued growth could occur. Wikis provide another good example; the WikiPedia, one of the largest active Wikis online, appears to have hovered at approximately 150-175 &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Administrators&#34;&gt;active administrators&lt;/a&gt; for over a year, in spite of a huge growth in usage during the same period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These numbers just keep coming up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all leads me to hypothesize that the optimal size for active group members for creative and technical groups -- as opposed to exclusively survival-oriented groups, such as villages -- hovers somewhere between 25-80, but is best around 45-50. Anything more than this and the group has to spend too much time &amp;quot;grooming&amp;quot; to keep group cohesion, rather then focusing on why the people want to spend the effort on that group in the first place -- say to deliver a software product, learn a technology, promote a meme, or have fun playing a game. Anything less than this and you risk losing critical mass because you don&#39;t have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doceo.co.uk/background/requisite_variety.htm&#34;&gt;requisite variety&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thus Dana Boyd gets it right when she uses the word MAXIMUM in her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/02/11/my_etech_talk_revenge_of_the_user.html&#34;&gt;eTech Talk&lt;/a&gt;, not average or mean:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Dunbar] found that the MAXIMUM number of people that a person could keep up with socially at any given time, gossip maintenance, was 150. This doesn&#39;t mean that people don&#39;t have 150 people in their social network, but that they only keep tabs on 150 people max at any given point.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Expanding Dunbar&#39;s Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To open up the discussion a bit, I&#39;d also hypothesize that Dunbar&#39;s Number is just one datapoint in an overall equation describing what group sizes work and what don&#39;t. Working our way up from the smallest group sizes, I think we can find many break points, both above and below Dunbar&#39;s Number of 150.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience the smallest viable group size seems to be somewhere in the range of 5 to 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking smaller, we see that a group of 2 can be tremendously creative (ask any parent), but often has insufficient resources and thus requires deep commitment by both parties. Notably, often the difficulty of a 2-person business partnership is compared to that of a marriage. A group of 3 is often unstable, with one person feeling left out, or else one person controlling the others by being the &amp;quot;split&amp;quot; vote. A group of 4 often devolves into two pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion it is at 5 that the feeling of &amp;quot;team&amp;quot; really starts. At 5 to 8 people, you can have a meeting where everyone can speak out about what the entire group is doing, and everyone feels highly empowered. However, at 9 to 12 people this begins to break down -- not enough &amp;quot;attention&amp;quot; is given to everyone and meetings risk becoming either too noisy, too boring, too long, or some combination thereof. Although I&#39;ve been unable to find the source, I&#39;ve heard of some references to a study from the 1950s that says that the optimum size for a committee is 7. Likewise, it&#39;s fairly easy for us to see and agree that a dinner party starts to break down somewhere above 7 or 8 people, as do also tabletop games of both the strategic (I prefer 5) and role-playing varieties (I prefer 7). These size limits can be overcome, but require increased amounts of &amp;quot;grooming&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chasm that starts somewhere between 9 to 12 people can be especially daunting for a small business. As you grow past 12 or so employees, you must start specializing and having departments and direct reports; however, you are not quite large enough for this to be efficient, and thus much employee time that you put toward management tasks is wasted. Only as you approach and pass 25 people does having simple departments and managers begin to work again, as it starts to really make sense for department heads to spend significant time just communicating and coordinating (and as individual departments become large enough to once again allow for the dynamic exchange of ideas that had previously occurred in the original 5-9 member seed group).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve already noted the next chasm when you go beyond 80 people, which I think is the point that Dunbar&#39;s Number actually marks for a non-survival oriented group. Even at this lower point, the noise level created by required socialization becomes an issue, and filtering becomes essential. As you approach 150 this begins to be unmanageable. Once a company grows past 200 you are really starting to need middle-management, but often you can&#39;t afford it yet. Only when you get up past that, maybe at 350-500 people, does middle-management start really working, primarily because you&#39;ve once again segmented your original departments, possibly again reducing them to Dunbar-sized groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following chart shows anecdotal satisfaction ratings for these lower group sizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/GroupSatisfaction.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Group Satisfaction&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is probably predicted by Dunbar&#39;s model, if you add in the non-survival and dispursed community modifiers that I discuss here. Essentially, as we increase group sizes beyond 80, to 150, 200, or even 350-500, we typically do so by breaking larger groups down into smaller ones, and continually reducing community sizes down to the point where they can be understood and managed by people -- and so efficiency reasserts itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since this post was originally posted, I have added a number of other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-19: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Excellent analysis!!!
We must remember that people in a group are connected by direct AND indirect ties.  We can keep tabs on many via indirect ties.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orgnet.com&#34;&gt;Valdis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T14:55:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T14:55:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris, this is a very impressive and useful piece of thinking - quite a contribution.
The formulation &#39;7 plus or minus 2&#39;, which I have often heard (and used) over the years as an ideal team size is well-supported by your thinking. It&#39;s worth noting that team-size in thriving real-world team games (basketball, baseball, US football) hover in this area.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.tommandel.com&#34;&gt;Tom&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T15:19:21-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T15:19:21-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris,
Pretty amazing stuff. I&#39;d like to add another break-point. It is anecdotal (but amazingly consistent based on my experience.)
I was part of a company that grew very quickly both organically and through acquisition. In every single office, things worked as you stated from 5-8(or 9), broke down until about 25 and then stabilized. However, the next breaking point was consistently between 50 &amp; 60.
It became my theory after witnessing this again and again that at around 40 people, the *PHYSICAL SPACE&#34; requirements become so large, that you can&#39;t easily shout across them. This may sound silly, but what that physical separation creates is a dynamic where decisions are made on &#34;one side&#34; without the &#34;other side&#34; being involved.
Up to this point most everyone feels included in the whole because news travels so fast, and is often within earshot. Once we passed 40, the only news that travels fast is bad news and &#34;secrets.&#34; ;-)
After much trial and error in trying to scale up offices with &#34;teams areas&#34; of multi-disciplinary folks, we ended up creating physical pods which accomodated 25-35 people. This allowed enough people to manage and have economies of scale, but small enough for quick communications.
The 80 breaking point is certainly when the next breakdown began in those offices that grew that big, but it wasn&#39;t until we got closer to 100 that the crap really hit the fan.
Hope this adds to the discussion and again... wow on the piece.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.inventionasylu.com&#34;&gt;Kyle Shannon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T16:12:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T16:12:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Nice job. FYI, we have intentionally segmented the forums on SWG and other games in order to reduce the admin load--this also entailed getting rid of the â€œgeneralâ€ forum, because it served as an attractor for too many people. Smaller communities of interest prove to be far more manageable from a policing point of view because of peer pressure and tighter social strictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.legendmud.org/raph/&#34;&gt;Raph&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T16:20:22-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T16:20:22-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Interesting stuff.  But, what is a &#34;group&#34;?  If it means &#39;the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable relationships&#39;, the what is &#34;stable&#34; and what is a &#34;relationship&#34;?  What is the context of relatedness?  Is the point of orientation a conversation? a product?  a service?  an battle? a political action committee?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Rob Kost&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T17:47:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T17:47:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Well put, its important people understand the scaling limits at 12 and 150.  I never ventured a guess at optimal group size, as its heavily context dependent. Instead I would suggest that our challenge as creators of social software is to enhance social capital so productive teams can be dynamic while extending their limits with cohesion.
On 12 &amp; 150 with Wikipedia: http://ross.typepad.com/blog/2004/01/phantom_authori.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ross.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Ross Mayfield&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T19:59:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T19:59:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Great article &amp; comment thread, Christopher -- thanks for posting that. Was there something in particular that prompted you to write this? Love to hear the backstory if there is one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://socialarchitect.typepad.com&#34;&gt;AJ Kim&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T20:46:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T20:46:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Great stuff, Christopher!
I like to include the following in explanations of the 147.8 number, because the range is pretty large (100 to 231):
&#34;Because the equation is log-transformed and we are extrapolating well beyond the range of neocortex ratios on which it is based, the 95% confidence limits around this prediction (from formulae given by Rayner 1985) are moderately wide (100.2-231.1).&#34;
From Dunbar&#39;s 1993 Behavioral and Brain Sciences article.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://peterkaminski.com/&#34;&gt;Peter Kaminski&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T23:19:39-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T23:19:39-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Interesting. I just finished an analysis of the e-learning industry here in New Brunswick, Canada. of the 40+ companies surveyed, almost all of them were less than 8 or more than 50 employees. Nobody in the middle, as it seems that&#39;s an uncomfortable place to be.
Also, I remember reading about W.L Gore Assoc, who insisted that all of their plants have less 150 people. More than that and they would create another plant, even if it was next door. Something about group cohesiveness.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.jarche.com&#34;&gt;Harold Jarche&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-11T08:15:17-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-11T08:15:17-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
The references to Ultima Online parallel my experiences with the game. Most guilds that I socialized with or had battles with showed the most solidarity with only 5 to 8 players present in the same area. With too many players, things would get &#39;silly&#39; as players would become bored. Also, too many players in a guild would cause fragmentation since players could never be on at the same times or preferred to play in a different part of the world. When I played, the largest guild around was HKU (Hong Kong Union) with 230+ members. It was a common occurrence to spot two HKU members fighting in anger. I have no idea how the guildmaster of HKU managed to get any actual game play in. :)
Excellent article Chris!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Wes Connell&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-11T09:48:00-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-11T09:48:00-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Just wanted to add my agreement. The larger the general communities get, the weaker the signal in any discussion. I think barriers to globally-broadcast participation can alleviate that to some extent. For instance, we charge some in-game currency (gold) to post on the in-game
general forums. We&#39;re even considering charging gold to file a complaint against another player, as the validity (signal) of people&#39;s complaints
(communication) against others has also declined as the population as gotten larger.
--matt
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ironrealms.com&#34;&gt;Matt Mihaly&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-13T11:40:08-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-13T11:40:08-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris, Must be tough keeping up with all the compliments :-). Let me add mine but also point back to Raph&#39;s comment earlier. The most amorphous piece here is the defintion of a group. I would also suggest that as opposed to non-human primates, humans have the ability to segment their neocortical capacities discretely between various groups and for various function - they can change roles completely. Thus we have multiple networks layered on top of each other - some w/ 2 members, some with 1000 and we swap our focus among them depending on our task, goal, etc.
I think that Dunbar&#39;s number is a strong predictor of a single group&#39;s optimal size but not so much of an individual&#39;s capacity to maintain multiple social contexts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blogoehlert.typepad.com/eclippings/&#34;&gt;mark oehlert&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T06:29:47-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T06:29:47-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Although I haven&#39;t read Dunbar&#39;s work directly, the material I have read suggests that individuals are keeping track of &#34;who did what to whom&#34;, suggesting that group complexity grows as n^2. When n=40, we&#39;re well within our limits, and we can handle many groups of such size (and we all have multiple social groups). My theory is that when n=150 or greater, we&#39;re pushing the boundary, and our ability to handle multiple social groups is diminished.
Marvin Harris, noted anthropologist, says in his book &#34;Our Kind&#34; (isbn:0060919906) that you can find no cases of larger groups forming except when there is both direct military power and no place to else to go. Let me reemphasize this: In no case in history can we find groups that voluntarily formed that were significantly larger than Dunbar&#39;s number. Larger groups formed only when agricultural communities created food, that food was controlled by a chief who had armed guards/police, and it was impossible to splinter off into a new tribe because there was no other life-sustainining land to go to.
-- Will
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.liquididea.com&#34;&gt;Will Hertling&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T18:42:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T18:42:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Anthopological research shows that primate groups thirve at about the size of 30 members. Human tribes in traditional tribal communities around the world demonstrate that same ideal number.
Here&#39;s a thought: If you we could manage group relationship the way of some sports leagues, we would maintain A, B, C... Groups.  We would work with each of these groups differently and communicate in different ways.  Individuals could move up and down as their relevance to our current activity changes.
You know come to think of it... I think I already do group people like that! The A&#39;s are the ones I meet with in person at least once in a while. The B&#39;s are the ones I call at least somewhat frequently and the C&#39;s are the ones I email with.
I guess there&#39;s a group that could be an A+ which are people who have directly lead me to business or are current customers. That would be a very short list, but the most protected and fruitfull.
In that paradigm, these tools are helping me turn C&#39;s into B&#39;s and A&#39;s, and helping me grow my C farm. The more C&#39;s I have which can be turned into B&#39;s and A&#39;s, the better my networking results!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Shally&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T18:43:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T18:43:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Dunbar would agree with your main point: &#34;... the suggestion [in his paper] is simply that there is an upper limit on the size of groups that can be maintained by direct personal contact. This limit reflects demands made on the ancestral human populations at some point in their past history. Once neocortex size has evolved, other factors may of course dictate the need for smaller groups. Precisely this effect seems to occur in gibbons and orang utans: in both cases, neocortex size predicts groups substantially larger than those observed for these species, but ecological factors apparently dictate smaller groups.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Rick Thomas&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T19:08:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T19:08:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;ve never seen this stuff before but it jibes really well with a hypothesis I had made, based on personal observation of group dynamics in my local pagan community, particularly the coven(s) with which I have worshipped the last seven years.  The points at which the dynamics change seem to hover around powers of two:  one person, two people, three or four people, five to eight, etc.   While thirteen is a traditional &#34;target&#34; the groups I&#39;ve circled with have ranged in membership from three to thirty.
In my observation, when a group fell below five active members for more than a few weeks it either sought out new students, merged with another small group, or dissolved completely.  Groups ranging from five to ten members tended to be most stable, with all members actively participating under the &#34;leadership core&#34; of two to four persons.  Groups of nine to fifteen people tended to split into &#34;active&#34; and &#34;less-active&#34; members with the active component having five to nine participants.  This commonly led to less active members either dropping out entirely (reducing overall group size) or complaning mightily about being left out.   The one group which grew above fifteen participants, reaching thirty at its maximum, was extremely unstable as the leadership core struggled to coordinate three sub-groups, each of whom complained mightily about lacking the leaders&#39; attention and feeling left out...
It seems that the 16-32 person group is the one that really needs a leader, though leadership develops at the 9-15 level. Would be interested in seeing if someone has applied this direction of thought (Dunbar&#39;s number, etc) to decision-making processes in groups.  A group that can&#39;t make a decision can&#39;t (as a whole) do much of anything else, either.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Thena&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-16T20:29:35-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-16T20:29:35-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;SÃ©bastien Paquet had a comment in his blog http://radio.weblogs.com/0110772/ I thought was interesting: &#34;Note that if this graph is accurate, jury duty (size=12) must be pretty nerve-wracking!)&#34;
I hadn&#39;t even thought of jury duty as an example, and I just recently was foreman of one.
With only one example my experience is purely anecdotal, but I think the value of 12 in a jury is that that the group isn&#39;t cohesive, and has a tendency to break into two groups, i.e. guilty and innocent. Then it is up to those two groups to persuade each other one way or another.
Also, a smaller jury pool might allow for someone&#39;s personality to win over some else&#39;s judgement. Not that this don&#39;t happen anyhow, just that with 12 people you are more likely to find someone with a like opinion and you&#39;ll be able to stand with them against the strong personality.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-19T09:42:31-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-19T09:42:31-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The applicability of Christopher&#39;s work to analyzing terrorist networks.
http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2004/03/what_is_the_opt.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas&#34;&gt;John Robb&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-27T11:40:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-27T11:40:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Dunbar&#39;s original work was concerned with social groupings that were effectively the whole of an individual&#39;s &#34;stable relationships&#34;.  Ignoring for a moment his insight as to the utility of language in lowering the cost of social grooming, would this not suggest that an individual&#39;s stable relationship total should be aggregated over all groups - so that if you&#39;re in a role-playing guild of, say 70, have a close-knit extended family of, oh, 40, you&#39;re not going be be able to sustain a business (or blog) network of more than about 40.  Now, adding language back in should allow these numbers to grow, but I guess the point is that the limit is individual-based, rather than group-based.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Bob Bechtel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-01T06:38:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-01T06:38:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Someone asked me via email &#34;Is there a format for assessment which you have found useful which you share with others?&#34;
I&#39;ve been thinking about assessment, but I&#39;m not sure about how to approach it.
One argument is to look at it from an individual perspective. Their approach says that each individual has a max 150 meaningful relationships, so if they have 50 professional relationships, 50 personal relationships, they only have room for relationships with a group of 50 additional people. Thus for you to join another group of 10 you need to triage your existing relationships and drop 10 relationships.
The problem with this approach is that although there is probably some truth to it, it doesn&#39;t lend itself to understanding how assess how group works. Does in a new group of 10 each person all only have &#34;room&#34; for 10 more people in each of their networks -- that is doubtful. So there must be separate group dynamics involved with group sizes other then just the Dunbar number.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-01T10:06:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-01T10:06:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I have a question about that last graph -- the Group Satisfaction one. What is its source? Is it just a visual representation of the anecdotal experience that precedes it? Because if so, it should really be labeled as such. Otherwise it carries the same validity weight as the other graphs, which represented empirical data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.johntynes.com/&#34;&gt;John Tynes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-13T09:56:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-13T09:56:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You are correct, it of the anecdotal experience. I&#39;ll change the text right above it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-13T10:34:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-13T10:34:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Dunbar says that human group size, &#34;...would require as much as 42% of the total time budget to be devoted to social grooming.,&#34; and you suggest, &#34;Some organizations will have sufficient incentive to maintain this high level of required socialization,&#34; as long as they&#39;re &#34;...built upon the raw need for survival.&#34;
It is interesting in that regard that two groups of professionals who habitually deal with the &#34;raw need for survival,&#34; soldiers and sailors, are often characterized by their love of conversation, &#34;war stories,&#34; &#34;yarning,&#34; and the like, a social-grooming pastime that may approach the percentage of waking hours that Dunbar mentions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;johne&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T12:15:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T12:15:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi Christopher!
My groupmates and me are writing a paper about groupsize and leadership. We read your article and we found it very useful for background theory about group size. Can you please tell us if this article has been published somewhere and in which magazine?
Thank you!
Best regards,
Anke Koszczol
University of Tilburg
Social studies
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.uvt.nl&#34;&gt;University of Tilburg&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-28T04:05:35-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-28T04:05:35-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Belbin did studies on working groups in the 80s and discovered that there were 8 roles in play and each had its part to play in the group objectives.  The best groups were 4 to 8 sized, and the optimal was 4, where each person fulfilled 2 roles.  (Of course this was latter statistically unlikely.)
Unfortunately, there is very little info on Belbin on the net, as the work is sold as a sort of corporate training aid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://iang.org/papers/&#34;&gt;Iang&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-17T15:27:05-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-17T15:27:05-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Several comments:
- Running live-action role-playing adventures, I have found that the ideal size of an adventuring group is around eight to ten players &amp;mdash; this allows for one or two players to hang back and recuperate while the others interact, as it can otherwise be fairly draining to be in character for hours or days at a time, and the interactions get a bit sparse with fewer than six participants.
- There is a religious community in Canada that lives together and practices low tech farming.  Their farms are not necessarily adjacent to one another, and each farm has up to about 100 members.  Whenever a farm begins to approach this limit, it starts the process of splitting in two.  This involves working together to acquire a new piece of land, build the new buildings, and prepare everything needed in the new location.  The group splits into two, and each chooses a leader.  On the night before the move, everyone packs &amp;mdash; in both groups.  The inhabitants of the new place are not determined until the day of departure.  On the morning of the move, the two leaders flip a coin to decide which will go and which will stay.  This has the function of investing everyone in the new buildings.  In order to replicate this growth strategy, of course, one would have to make sure everyone felt their survival depended on the community, and that they would be willing and able to relocate that investment from time to time.  Not so hard online.  Rather more difficult in the real world.
- Someone is going to start claiming that Dunbar&#39;s analysis doesn&#39;t hold, due to evidence from the recently discovered &#34;hobbits&#34; of Flores Island &amp;mdash; comparative complexity of mental capacity in a much smaller brain-case.  I offer a pre-emptive counter-argument, in the form of an amendment to Dunbar&#39;s anaylsis.  The graph of brain size vs group size might equally well represent brain complexity vs group size.  Someone should re-analyze the data on the basis of complexity of the neocortex (or even of the whole brain), rather than its size, in order to back this up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.wandreilagh.org&#34;&gt;Gavin Weld White&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-07T16:08:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-07T16:08:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Don&#39;t you think that with the advent of computer technologies, the dunbar number has lost its relavance? I mean with all these modern gadgets like computers and Cable Television, people have lost the will and the art to communicate with others. About 10 Years back, there was enough time after work for members of a family to get together after a hard day&#39;s work to discuss about their current day and have relavent communication. But now there is no time for any communication at all in this fast paced world. And if at all  there is time, it is spent in front of the Idiot box (TV) or the more intelligent idiot box (computer) surfing the web.
So much for communication!!
--
http://linuxhelp.blogspot.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://linuxhelp.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Ravi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-15T03:27:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-15T03:27:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I guess Judas got cranky being in a group of 13... :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://euroblogalan.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Alan R&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-05-04T11:18:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-05-04T11:18:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Bless you for this. I have been searching for so long. Now, I need to find fourteen years to study everything you have written so that my questions start to find answers. Thanks sincerely for freely sharing you knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://AmyStephen.us&#34;&gt;Amy Stephen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-10-13T07:34:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-10-13T07:34:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I believe the significance of the range of 5 - 9 may come from &#34;The Magical Number Seven, Plus or Minus Two: Some Limits on Our Capacity for Processing Information&#34; (1956) by George A. Miller, cognitive psychologist. Another thought: with language comes the ability to think to oneself, thereby increasing the number of people in one&#39;s tribe by at least one or two (more for Sybil) ...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Michael Crowe&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-04-03T09:32:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-04-03T09:32:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I was absolutely mesmerized by this blog post, I have to read the others as well!
Anyway, so it&#39;s no coincidence the movie is called &#34;12 Angry Men&#34; ( http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0050083/ )? :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://flickr.com/people/cjsveningsson&#34;&gt;Carl-Johan Sveningsson&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-04-04T10:03:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-04-04T10:03:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Ok, this is ridiculous.  Some assertions here must be answered.  People can maintain more than 150 relationships.  The idea that people can only keep up with 150 people is clearly outside the assertions of Dunbar&#39;s work.  Dunbar only says that the maximum sustainable size of a single group is somewhere between 100 and 230 with a 95% confidence.  (With the mathematical tendency toward 148.something)  This is for a single group with all members fully invested in the group.  The real limit in the human mind is the ability to keep track of the relationships between all 150ish people.  If the maximum size of a single undivided social network with no outside relationships is 150, his research therefore suggests that the average number of relationships a person can keep track of is 11,175 inter-relationships (1 interrelationship between every possible group of 2 people).  It is wrong-headed to say that the limit on a single network of 150 means that someone couldn&#39;t have a network of 50 people in their family network, 70 people in their work network, and another 70 people in their friends network.  If these networks are fully separate, then there are only 6,055 total inter-relationships, which lends credence to later research by H. Russell Bernard and Peter Killworth showing the average modern American maintains a social network of mean 290 members (median 231 members).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Echelon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-09-30T12:54:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-09-30T12:54:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for this writeup on Dunbar&#39;s number, and your scholarship into it.  I followed a Twitter message from Luis Suarez to this blog posting.
When Malcolm Gladwell was lecturing on &#34;The Tipping Point&#34; at the Rotman School at the University of Toronto, I asked him specifically about the number 150 (in particular, on the Goretex example cited in the book).  He didn&#39;t explain that the number 150 was associated with Dunbar, but instead referred to Thomas J. Allen at MIT.  I had found a copy of the 1997 book &#34;Managing the Flow of Technology&#34; in an old booksale, which wasn&#39;t very satisfying.  I now note that Allen has a 2006 book on &#34;The Organization and Architecture of Innovation&#34; which would be contemporaneous with &#34;The Tipping Point&#34;.
Now that you&#39;ve provided with the direct source of the citation, you&#39;ve opened up the academic bottleneck for me.  I appreciate your writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://coevolving.com&#34;&gt;David Ing&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-02-12T08:39:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-02-12T08:39:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It is interesting in that regard that two groups of professionals who habitually deal with the &#34;raw need for survival,&#34; soldiers and sailors, are often characterized by their love of conversation, &#34;war stories,&#34; &#34;yarning,&#34; and the like, a social-grooming pastime that may approach the percentage of waking hours that Dunbar mentions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.paragraf.su/&#34;&gt;Ð¢Ð¸Ð¿Ð¾Ð³Ñ€Ð°Ñ„Ð¸Ñ&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-12-26T15:36:20-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-12-26T15:36:20-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
What a nice collection of reflections on the Dunbar Number.
I would like to add a different formula that I created when studying human groups for my PhD.
A = R + (Sq.Rt)M
where A = attendance at meetings
M = number of formal roles (eg. chair, secretary, coach, etc)
M = total number in group membership
and of course SqRt is Square Root (won&#39;t use the symbol in case the ascii doesn&#39;t work for anyone)
I have found it a pretty good predictor of meeting size all my (post-PhD) life.
It is usually more pessimistic that the anticipations of group members that organize the meetings.  Sometimes I explain that the best way to increase the attendance is to introduce more (real) roles..... sometimes not, as you are not always thanked for suggestions.
I have always felt a fondness for the formula as it is one of the very few non-statistical uses of number in Social Psychology, and it seems a good predictor.
For this reason I throw it into the discussion.
The original publication was in my PhD
1977    Human Social Groups: A cybernetic account of  stability and instability PhD Thesis. Brunel University.
and later in book form (now sadly out of print... but I still have some copies if anyone wants one)
1984    Groups  John Wiley. Chichester and New York
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Mike Robinson&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2010-02-24T12:55:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2010-02-24T12:55:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>