<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/use/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/use/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Creative Commons Posts “Defining Noncommercial” Report</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/09/creative-commons-posts-defining-noncommercial-report.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2009 13:55:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/09/creative-commons-posts-defining-noncommercial-report.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5c52eae970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Creative-commons-non-commercial&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5c52eae970c &#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5c52eae970c-120pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Creative-commons-non-commercial&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Last year I participated in a survey followed up by a focus group on the topic of Noncommercial Use, in particular around the context that about 2/3rds of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org&#34;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; licenses extant use the NC attribute, such as in&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/us/&#34;&gt;CC-BY-NC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining &amp;quot;Noncommercial&amp;quot;: &amp;#0160;A Study of how the Online Population Understands &amp;quot;Noncommercial&amp;quot; Use&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.creativecommons.org/Defining_Noncommercial&#34; style=&#34;color: #2a5db0; &#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://wiki.&lt;wbr /&gt;creativecommons.org/Defining_&lt;wbr /&gt;Noncommercial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topic is somewhat of a sticky one, as there are many competing interests. There are content creators who wish to profit from their work, there are other content creators who don&amp;#39;t want anyone to profit (even themselves), and of course there are content creators who want everything to be free provided you share free content back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also is not agreement on what noncommerical means. There are some clearly commercial uses, but there are also various type advertising and sponsorship and use by non-profit or education institutions where money changes hands (such as a card at a museum gift shop). Finally, there is use in news or criticism where users feel that they are not restricted due to the rules of fair-use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure that there is anything definitely &amp;quot;new&amp;quot; in this report, but there is some consensus and some interesting facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The vast majority (73%) of creators define “commercial use” as a&amp;#0160;use where money is made, 76% of content users agreed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;33% of content users thought that individual use was&amp;#0160;noncommercial use, whereas only 19% of the content creators&amp;#0160;believed so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content creators rate uses by individuals as being less&amp;#0160;commercial (89%) – unless the user is a professional who earns&amp;#0160;money (35%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13% of content users thought that fun, enjoyment, entertainment&amp;#0160;and artistic use was noncommercial use, whereas only 3% of&amp;#0160;content creators believed so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;52% of the content creators don&amp;#39;t believe that content users&amp;#0160;understand the noncommercial provision, and 43% believe that&amp;#0160;content users don&amp;#39;t respect the term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50% of the content creators have been contacted about licensing&amp;#0160;their noncommercial content, 24% of the content creators have&amp;#0160;attempted to contact another creator about appropriate use of a&amp;#0160;CC license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a lack of agreement on a lot of edge cases of&amp;#0160;noncommercial use. For instance, some feel cost-recovery is&amp;#0160;acceptable noncommercial use, money exchanged hands for a&amp;#0160;charitable use would be noncommercial, or use by a for-profit&amp;#0160;company where no money changed hands would still be noncommercial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is some interesting analysis of what people might be&amp;#0160;willing to change their mind about. For instance, before focus&amp;#0160;group participation only 8% thought that use for charitable&amp;#0160;purposes for social good would be noncommercial, but after the&amp;#0160;focus group 17% did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all an excellent report, with lots of good data in it for further investigation. If you are involved in user-generated content, offer users creative-commons licenses, or are a consumer or provider of commercial content online, I recommend you take the time to understand these issues more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal take on this report is that the noncommercial provisions of the CC license need more clarification and there needs to be more user education. In addition I feel that Creative Commons also needs to look at the commercial use side of the problem. I appreciate the recent efforts toward a &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.creativecommons.org/CCPlus&#34;&gt;CC Plus&lt;/a&gt; metadata, but it isn&amp;#39;t enough.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;image&#34; href=&#34;http://wiki.creativecommons.org/File:Cc-by-nc-3.0-88x31.png&#34; title=&#34;Image:Cc-by-nc-3.0-88x31.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image:Cc-by-nc-3.0-88x31.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;31&#34; src=&#34;http://wiki.creativecommons.org/images/4/49/Cc-by-nc-3.0-88x31.png&#34; width=&#34;88&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 280%&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;image&#34; href=&#34;http://wiki.creativecommons.org/File:Commercial-license-button.png&#34; title=&#34;Image:Commercial-license-button.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image:Commercial-license-button.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;31&#34; src=&#34;http://wiki.creativecommons.org/images/9/91/Commercial-license-button.png&#34; width=&#34;88&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
For instance Creative Commons should take a principled stand on what exactly &amp;quot;fair use&amp;quot; is; make it easier for those who offer NC licenses to also offer a standard commercial license for common uses; and possibly creating a standard for what &amp;quot;fair rights&amp;quot; are in commercial license (i.e. fair to both the content creator and the content user).&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also problems in the area of attribution, as all Creative Commons licenses except Public Domain have the BY provision. These get particularly difficult when you have a remix of content from many creators. There&amp;#39;s also difficulty in the fact that it&amp;#39;s not stated what places attribution must be listed in. For instance, can you do a movie or a podcast with remixed content, but have the attribution credits be a link? Or must they be credits in the media itself?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All are interesting problems that I hope Creative Commons will address in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2009/09/creative-commons-posts-defining-noncommercial-report.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>