<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>User Interface on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/user-interface/</link>
    <description>Recent content in User Interface on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 23:55:42 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/user-interface/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Mini Resume Card for Conference Season</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 23:55:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Between the business of the March/April conference season and leaving Blackphone, I&#39;ve run out of business cards. Rather than rush to print a bunch of new ones, I&#39;m created this mini-resume for digital sharing and a two-sided Avery business card version that I am printing on my laser printer and sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not as pretty as my old Life With Alacrity cards, but effective in getting across the diversity of my professional experience and interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; style=&#34;display: inline; border-style: solid; border-width: 2px; border-color: black;&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d0f2961e970c-pi&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d0f2961e970c image-full img-responsive&#34; title=&#34;Christopher Allen Micro Resume&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d0f2961e970c-800wi&#34; alt=&#34;Christopher Allen Micro Resume&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who teaches Personal Branding in my courses at BGI@Pinchot.edu, I always find it hard to practice as I preach to ask for advice and suggestions. In this case I&#39;m trying to tame my three-headed Cerebus of a profession with Privacy/Crypto/Developer Community, an Innovative Business Educator/Instructional Designer head, and my Collaborative Tools, Processes, Games and Play head. All come tied together in my body as ultimately being about collaboration, but it is hard to explain some of the correspondences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing your Social Graph with Google&#43; [Google Plus]</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563798/&#34; title=&#34;Trust Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Trust Circle&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3230/3055563798_5355b9b99c_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With Google+ almost two weeks into its test phase, conversation about this new social network service seems to be going in circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because Circles is the Google+ feature that users are generating the most buzz about. It’s Google’s answer to the problem of organizing your social graph online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_graph&#34;&gt;social graph&lt;/a&gt; it’s a map of everyone you know and how they are related to you. Social graphs are tricky; as you try to define them you’ll inevitably run into some complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete Pachal, news director of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387808,00.asp&#34;&gt;@PCMag&lt;/a&gt; comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;“People want things easy, and Google Circles isn’t easy. It puts the burden on users to take the time to think about each and every contact and put them in a specific bucket. To use the feature effectively, users will certainly have to create new Circles, and that requires even more thought. After using Google+ for a few minutes last night, I was often unsure which Circles to put certain people in and, more to the point, which to leave them out of. And what if you create a new Circle that should include some of the people in other Circles you already have?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circles are lists that you’ve created by grouping people together and giving them a name. They’re important in Google+ because when you post you must explicitly say which “Circles” you wish to share with. Posting to a limited list of people is a big change from existing social networks such as Facebook, where posts are sent to all mutual friends by default, or Twitter, where posts are public. This change forces you to think more deeply about your social graph and who should see each item you post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BwvygI2xKGM&#34; width=&#34;560&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yourinitialsetofcircles&#34;&gt;Your Initial Set of Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google+ will present you with 4 suggested set of Circles: Friends, Family, Acquaintances, and Following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d image-full&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-800wi&#34; title=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Google+ also defines five special Circles: Two are only for reading: &amp;quot;Stream&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; and &amp;quot;Incoming&amp;quot; which is are posts that are shared to you by people not in your Circles. Then are three special Circles managed by Google only for posting: &amp;quot;Your Circles&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; “Extended” which is everyone in your Circles plus the people in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; Circles; and “Public” which is &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few find this default set to be sufficient. As a result, most Google+ users are soon creating new Circles, moving people around, renaming Circles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sound reasons for people finding the default Circles limiting. Sociological research shows that everyone has a number of concentric personal circles (see my blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt; for more details). These circles are sometimes called “ego-centric” social graphs as the individual is located in the center. This sort of graph is the model I used when I began reorganizing my own Google+ Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out using Support (for my Support Circle), Close (for my Sympathy Circle), Trusted (for my Trust Circle), and Colleagues (for my Emotional Circle), but that didn’t work for very long. I’ve since been experimenting with a number of different ways to organize my Circles. I wanted an initial set that would offer useful early advice for using Google+ but would still be applicable for when expanded to hundreds of people. (I now have over 600 people in my Circles.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One insight I’ve had is to avoid the word ‘friends’, which has been corrupted to almost meaninglessness in recent years. So instead I use terminology like Peers for my trust circle and Kith for the combination of my support and sympathy circles. (Kith may be familiar to you from the phrase “kith and kin”. The root of kith means “to know”, thus it’s those people that you know very well and that know you very well.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that sub-Circles exist within Circles. Using a ‘general ledger’ system of naming Circles with numbers—which I’ll demonstrate in a moment—helps me keep these Circles and sub-Circles in order and allows me to easily add new Circles when I need to. Hopefully Google+ will in the future introduce features that allow us to order Circles as we please, but until then this numbering system works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Google+ has also shown me that some Circles are for reading and other Circles are for posting. I’ll talk a little more about this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has only been a week, but by combining these insights to organize my Circles I’ve improved my ease of use and become better able to manage my time while using Google+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my recommended initial list of Circles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 ME&lt;/strong&gt; - a simple Circle with just yourself in it, for saving posts, for drafts, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.0 KIN&lt;/strong&gt; - your family &amp;amp; extended family&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt; 2.0 KITH&lt;/strong&gt; - your best friends, your confidants (i.e. those with whom one shares a secret or private matter, trusting them not to repeat it to others)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.0 PEERS&lt;/strong&gt; - your trusted colleagues, those who you work closely with, your collaborators&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.0 LOCAL&lt;/strong&gt; - your neighbors, parents of your children&amp;#39;s friends, people you&amp;#39;d invite to a party&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.0&lt;/strong&gt; {various groups &amp;amp; interests}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;/strong&gt; - people you know, but that you don&amp;#39;t know well or that don’t know you well&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;/strong&gt; - people who follow you on Google+, who you may or may not know&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;/strong&gt; - people whose posts you read, but who don&amp;#39;t necessarily read your posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 9.0 SPECIAL&lt;/strong&gt; - useful for special lists &amp;amp; exceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expandingcircles&#34;&gt;Expanding Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people will find my default set of ~10 Circles to be very useful, and need only add a few more. However, the design of this set is to allow for much greater expansion should you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like those “personal circles” that I wrote about previously, most of the Circles above are ego-centric: they’re fundamentally centered on your own personal social graph. This isn’t the only potential type of Circle, however. Socio-centric Circles aren’t centered on you, though they still have some sort of membership boundaries, while info-centric Circles are based on topics instead of being based on relationships. These socio-centric and info-centric Circles will support many relationships better than ego-centric Circles do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone seems to write a lot about a particular topic, I put him or her into an appropriate info-centric Circle. My own info-centric Circles thus include people who post about topics like iOS Development, the Social Web, Sustainability/Green, and Entrepreneuring. If a number of people are all part of a group or all come from a certain geographical area then I put them together in a socio-centric circle. After creating the Circles, I put the ones that were geographic into 4.0 of my ledger, then placed the others in 5.0. (I tried separating out groups and interests, and found that didn’t work, so now I keep them together.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now have over 600 people in my Google Plus+ social graph. All together my Circles now look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 Read Later&lt;br /&gt; 0.1 Drafts&lt;br /&gt; 0.2 Book Project&lt;br /&gt; 0.3 iPad Project&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 1.0 ALL KIN&lt;br /&gt; 1.1 Immediate Family&lt;br /&gt; 1.2 Extended Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 2.0 ALL KITH&lt;br /&gt; 2.1 Close Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.2 Old But Distant Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.3 Distant Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 3.0 ALL PEERS&lt;br /&gt; 3.2 Collaborators&lt;br /&gt; 3.3 Current Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt; 3.4 Former Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 4.0 ALL LOCAL&lt;br /&gt; 4.1 Local Kith, Kin &amp;amp; Peers&lt;br /&gt; 4.2 Local Berkeley&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Seattle&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Portland&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 5.0 ALL GROUPS &amp;amp; INTERESTS&lt;br /&gt; 5.1 Entrepreneurs&lt;br /&gt; 5.2 Apple &amp;amp; iOS&lt;br /&gt; 5.3 - iOSDevCamp&lt;br /&gt; 5.4 Green &amp;amp; Sustainability&lt;br /&gt; 5.5 - BGIedu&lt;br /&gt; 5.6 Social Web&lt;br /&gt; 5.7 - Jerry’s Kids&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;br /&gt; 6.1 Familiar Strangers&lt;br /&gt; 6.2 Friendly Strangers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;br /&gt; 7.1 Core Audience&lt;br /&gt; 7.2 Commented or Shared My Posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;br /&gt; 8.2 Pundits&lt;br /&gt; 8.3 Celebrities&lt;br /&gt; 8.4 Noisy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 9.0 ALL&lt;br /&gt; 9.1 Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy&lt;br /&gt; 9.2 Read Daily&lt;br /&gt; 9.3 Read Weekly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future blog post I’ll share my ongoing experience with using this approach to Circles, but this example shows how easy it is to separate and add Circles as your interests change and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;managingyourcircles&#34;&gt;Managing Your Circles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, enjoy social networks in large part because we get to interact with people. Managing your Circles is thus about more than just understanding your social graph. It also allows you to manage your time effectively when you read and share with other people on Google+. Here is my approach for how to manage the time you spend reading, sharing, and managing your social graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforreading&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Reading&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it useful to think about Circles that are explicitly for reading as different from Circles intended for sharing. I have a few of these read-only Circles. Thus, my “Pundits” Circle contains people that share a lot and for whom I don’t always want to read everything. My “Read Daily” Circle is conversely for people for whom I want to read everything they post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also found Circles helpful for close collaborators. It’s easy in Google+ to have a conversation with someone directly by simply typing their name as +&amp;lt;name&amp;gt; into the share field of posts. However, I find these direct posts get lost over time. To resolve this problem, create a Circle dedicated to just the two of you: a dyad. I have a number of people that I’m collaborating with closely and I use these small Circles to both keep track of our mutual posts and to see what they are thinking about at the moment. Examples of this kind of two-person Circle include my “Book Project” and “iPad Project”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofreadingcircles&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Reading Circles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day I look first at my “ALL KIN”, “ALL KITH” and and “ALL PEER” Circles to see what is going on with my support, sympathy and trust cliques. Then I’ll read my “Read Daily” Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading these daily basics (which I try to keep to a limited number), I’ll typically pick an interest, a geography, or a group, depending on what I’m doing that day. (My personal time-management style is to only follow one interest per day, e.g. if I am working on my iPad app then I’m not reading Social Web posts.) If I’m preparing a blog post and want to see what my audience is thinking I might review “Core Audience”, or “FOLLOWS ME”. If I’m traveling I might read one of my non-local Circles such as “Seattle”. If I’m doing ‘weak-signal research’ I might start with “ALL INTERESTS”, but if I’m particularly tolerant of noise I might read “Familiar Strangers”, “FOLLOWS ME”, “Everyone but Pundits &amp;amp; Strangers”, “Pundits”, or even “ALL”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;postingtocircles&#34;&gt;Posting to Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the important reasons for creating Circles in the first place is so that you can share with groups of people. I’ve developed some strategies for this as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforposting:&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Posting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it useful to create a Circle that only contains yourself. I have two of these — “Read Later”, and “Drafts”. If I’m reading and I see something interesting but don’t have time for it immediately, I’ll share it with my “Read Later” Circle so that I can quickly go back to it. Similarly, if I need to do some more research before writing and sharing, I’ll share my immediate thoughts in “Drafts”. As new features are added to Google+ these Circles will hopefully become obsolete, but they are useful for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofprivateposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Private Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sharing, you want to ask yourself if this is ‘private’ post, a ‘quasi-public’ post or a ‘public’ post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My private posts tend to go “KIN”, “KITH”, a dyad project, or one of the sub-Circles of PEER depending on their context. Some posts that are of only geographic interest (say a party, or local event) will be shared privately to the appropriate local Circle. If you are using my ledger system of using numbers in Circle names, these are the lower numbers—5.0 and below are Circles where I’m more sensitive about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once shared, these more personal posts will be labeled as “Limited” instead of using the “Public” label that allows anyone to see them. If a recipient tries to share a “Limited” post, a box will pop up reminding the person: “This post was originally shared with a limited audience – remember to be thoughtful about who you share it with”. Unlike Facebook or Twitter, one purpose of Circles on Google+ is to determine who gets what information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it may be easy to create Circles to segregate those with whom you wish to share private information, the recipients of your posts have no such limitations and could share outward beyond your intent (though they will be warned if they try to, as noted above). To enable further privacy you can disable resharing of these personal posts made to your Circles. To do so, share your post to a non-public Circle, then you select the arrow in the upper-right-hand corner where you can edit, delete or disable the post, and click on the final option, “Disable Reshare”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another privacy issue: by clicking the grey “Limited” label, a message’s recipient can see all others you shared the post with. This could potentially result in privacy problems, as the reader could discover who is in one of your Circles. There are ways of eliminating this by going into your Privacy account settings, which I will cover in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofquasi-publicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Quasi-Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call posts “quasi-public” when they’re of narrow interest to a specific group or a topic that isn’t really relevant to other members of my audience. I find these quasi-public posts happen the most for my more esoteric interests—for instance, when I’m sharing a complex iPhone development article that is really only interesting to a narrow group of my contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Google Reader, I typically wouldn’t share these articles at all because there were so many of my contacts that wouldn’t be interested in them and it would only be noise to them. Ditto with Twitter. I found that sometimes people would stop following me after a conference I attended because I posted regularly and the conference was not of interest to them. This could be quite frustrating at times. Though these posts were not private by any means, I only wanted to share them with a specific group, such as an iPhone group. Now with Circles, I can share this information easily with my “Apple &amp;amp; iOS” Circle. I find that this feature is what makes Google+’s Circles so potentially powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I might offer much of this more esoteric information as “quasi-public” posts to a specific group or interest, I’ll probably offer the best of them to the “Public”. Sometimes that is what it means to be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maven&#34;&gt;Maven&lt;/a&gt;—you share across social network boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofpublicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing a post to your “Your Circles” is effectively public, as is sharing to “Extended Circles”. Ask yourself if there is really some reason why you don’t want to make a post totally “Public” so that it is searchable by those who are not members of Google+. If there is some reason, consider sharing to your “ALL” Circle or some other more limited circle instead, as you’ll have more control and can turn off resharing or commenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;managingyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;Managing Your Social Graph&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining your Circles can take away from the time you can spend on reading and sharing. I’ve come up with the following strategy to limit the time I spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, I have some basic rules for which Circles to place people in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone is following me, I add them to “FOLLOWS ME” and an appropriate other Circle. If I vaguely recognize a follower’s name or face, I put them in “Familiar Strangers”. If I don’t recognize them at all but they look interesting, I add them to “Friendly Strangers”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone has +1’ed, commented, or mentioned me in a post, I add them to “Core Audience” and the appropriate sub-Circle. I will also make sure that the other Circles they are in are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I discover while I’m reading that someone is too noisy for the Circle I selected, I’ll move them to a more appropriate Circle—or place them in the “Noisy” Circle or even block them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Your Social Graph&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition I review a few of my Circles every day. I do so by going to “Manage Circles”, then selecting “People in your Circles” and sorting by last name. I choose that letter of the alphabet that corresponds to the day of the month and hover my mouse over each name. (For example, I look at names starting with “L” on July 12th, as “L” is the 12th letter.) Google+ highlights the Circles that each person is in. If they’re in the wrong Circle, I move them. I might even click on some people and review their profile so that I can see who they are—or (if I already know them) see what they are up to lately, update my address book, and maybe send them a brief email. At the end of the month (on the 27th through the 31st) I review my overall Circles lists. This way, over the course of each month I briefly review my entire social network, without spending too much time on it. (I try to spend 10 minutes or so a day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Periodically (right now weekly, but hopefully eventually monthly) I do some larger scale management of my Circles. Learning how to do this the first time is a pain, but once you know how it only takes a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to “Manage Circles” and select “People Who Have Added You”. I sort that list by “Not Yet in Circles”, “Select All” and add the people revealed to “FOLLOWS ME”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then do the same with all of my Circles to update my “ALL” Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I copy my “ALL” circle to “Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy” and remove any Pundits, Celebrities or Noisy people from that Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When managing your Circles, remember the motto “Perfection is the Enemy of the Good”. You are the only one that sees who is in which Circle, and you can place people in multiple Circles. So your Circles don’t have to be perfect, just good enough. If you share a lot of private posts, concentrate on making sure that those more personal Circles are more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these approaches, you should find Circle management quick, and you won’t get mired down in Circle management for hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish I had this organization when I started on Google+ two weeks ago. By using some of these techniques from the beginning I would have made my life a lot easier. Over the next month I now have to go back and re-organize people and re-Circle them. I hope sharing these tips will make your use of Google+ simpler from the start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I expect that Google will be adding new features to make Google+ easier. For instance I’m hoping for #hashtags (the ability to tag posts into topic categories), favorites (the ability to tag posts into a persistent archive, hopefully with an option tag), ordering Circles, concentric Circles, and better integration with Google Reader. (I share my favorite blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/reader/shared/ChristopherA&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; at &amp;#0160;and my best of best articles and posts in &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ChristopherA/favorites&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Twitter Favorites&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;or &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/christophera&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Delicious&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any new online feature, people are finding out new things and coming up with new ideas every day. So what are &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; methods for organizing your Circles and social graph?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to follow me on Google+, I’m at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/about&#34;&gt;+Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#39;d like to comment using Google+, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/posts/2eYjBB2CpNm&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;public comment thread&lt;/a&gt; about this post.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you would like to subscribe to my Google+ posts in Google Reader, use my &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;feed://plusfeed.appspot.com/113059510043663667610&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlusFeed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts from my blog related to this post:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some recent high signal-to-noise blog posts on Google+ and/or managing your Circles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107631581023945167601/about&#34;&gt;+Matt Stratton&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattstratton.com/tech-tips/how-i-set-up-my-circles-in-google-plus&#34;&gt;How I Set Up My Circles in Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113551191017950459231/about&#34;&gt;+Anson Alex&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ansonalex.com/tutorials/managing-circles-in-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Guide to Working with Circles in Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/101746196094367799224/about&#34;&gt;+Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/?p=2616&#34;&gt;The promise of Google+ for organizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104681313125038107957/about&#34;&gt;+Sterling Ledet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.weteachthecoolstuff.com/2011/07/09/a-thought-on-circles-privacy-vs-relevance/&#34;&gt;A Thought on Google+ Circles – Privacy vs. Relevance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/118432652629200965858/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Dave Pollard&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtosavetheworld.ca/2011/07/11/google-plus-on-communities-circles-friendship-and-love/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google+: On Communities, Circles, Friendship and Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethkanter.org/np-google/&#34;&gt;Are You Going To Adopt Google+ for Professional Learning/Networking? Why or Why Not?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104181568670836761473/about&#34;&gt;+Damon Morda&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brandedclever.com/five-steps-to-configuring-privacy-on-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Five Steps to Configuring Privacy on Google Plus (+)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some quality recent public Google+ posts regarding Google+ or managing your Circles (be sure to look over the comments):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/about/&#34;&gt;+Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/posts/ghn6Bu6tsmM&#34;&gt;My tips for newer users of Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/1SdhSBqwAmA&#34;&gt;Where circles can go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/D9bRJCmjJRV&#34;&gt;Sharing Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/XHvCRURHidx&#34;&gt;Is Google plus public or private?It’s neither, and both!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/posts/DV8QxNzTxaF&#34;&gt;Insightful Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/about&#34;&gt;+Craig Kanalley&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/posts/52dmpNDbWtp&#34;&gt;Tips &amp;amp; Thoughts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/about/&#34;&gt;+Paul Goode&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/posts/W9CaNrwku3x&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Sketch on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on related to this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;personal circles&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the of personal limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;familiar strangers&lt;/a&gt; - those people you recognize by face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustration by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;, Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/102320045646237908121/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Elyn Andersson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;for their assistance with this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I really like the idea of using circles for social time management. One big problem I have with networks is that I feel committed (obligated?) to a certain, indistinct, level of communication - particularly with those people that social media has now kept me in &#39;contact&#39; with, and whom in the old days I would have lost touch with. The end result is always a big time defecit and multiple layers of guilt. The idea of being able to apply some kind of equitable rationing/priority to circles may be a bit geeky... but it&#39;s preferable to non-specific angst  ;0)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/grimbold&#34;&gt;Grimbold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I like your ideas; I&#39;ve also been trying to play about with the circles &amp; work out something that works for me.
How, however, do you manage to add people to them, when you have quite so many (looking at the second list with the 1.3 etc) - I can only see 1.5 rows of circles! (OK, I know you can add someone by right clicking &amp; going for the add to circle, but that&#39;s fiddly if you&#39;re block adding them!)
I&#39;ve also got in the (equivalent of the) me circle my &#39;other&#39; G+ account, that I&#39;ve been using to see the effect of things like extended circles. Which I do find useful.
Would be nice, if, at some point, rather than having &#39;stream&#39; it was possible to see in a single stream all the updates from a set of circles, rather than 1 or all. (Unless that&#39;s something I&#39;ve yet to find!)
(That, and I want boolean logic for them, so I can have everyone who is in both a &amp; b, but not a or b!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/emmadw&#34;&gt;Emmadw&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iPhoneDevCamp and Hack-a-Thon</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/07/iphonedevcamp-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2007 23:19:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/07/iphonedevcamp-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/atow/750701139/&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;133&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/2007/07/08/everyone.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Everyone&#34; alt=&#34;Everyone&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I feel privileged and honored to have been part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://barcamp.org/iPhoneDevCamp&#34;&gt;iPhoneDevCamp&lt;/a&gt; this last weekend. Over 380 iPhone developers came out to the Adobe Campus in San Francisco to help each other make the best possible web pages and webapps for the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was the keynote speaker on Saturday and Master of Ceremonies for the MacHack-style &lt;a href=&#34;http://barcamp.org/iPhoneDevCampHackAThon&#34;&gt;Hack-a-Thon Demo&lt;/a&gt; on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Hack-a-Thon almost 50 iPhone web applications were demonstrated to an enthusiastic audience. Take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xeodesign.com/tilt&#34;&gt;Tilt&lt;/a&gt;, a game that takes advantage of the iPhone&#39;s motion sensor, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mxis.com/pickleview&#34;&gt;PickleView&lt;/a&gt;, which is a same-time live baseball game enhancer, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bartholo.com/devcamp/pool.html&#34;&gt;The Pool&lt;/a&gt;, an attractive social game of water droplets hitting a pool. What is remarkable about these applications is not just the quality, but that each of them was written over just the weekend by a small team of 3-4 people who hadn&#39;t met each other before Friday!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/snackfight/750214294/&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/2007/07/08/hewitt.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Hewitt&#34; alt=&#34;Hewitt&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Prizes were awarded after the Hack-a-Thon based on the spirit of openness, contribution, sharing, and participation. Prizes included 3 iPhones and some very expensive Adobe software. In particular &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joehewitt.com/&#34;&gt;Joe Hewitt&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.getfirebug.com/&#34;&gt;Firebug&lt;/a&gt; fame, was honored for his positive contributions, generous spirit, and wonderful iPhone UI &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joehewitt.com/files/iphone/navigation.html&#34;&gt;example code&lt;/a&gt;. During the demonstrations, more than one person praised Joe, saying that his assistance, his code, or his debugger made their apps possible. Personally, I think about one-third of the web apps presented used some of his code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on my experience with the same-time collaboration tool &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt; web-based games, I worked remotely with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kallealm.com/&#34;&gt;Kalle&lt;/a&gt; from Sweden and &lt;a href=&#34;http://is-here.com/&#34;&gt;Erwin&lt;/a&gt; from Kansas to present an AJAX chat application called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iphonewebdev.com/ilace/&#34;&gt;iLace&lt;/a&gt;. I am particularly proud of how well this little web application performs and how well it works using the iPhone UI. In particular, I think its melding of text entry and chat message receipt and its response to changes between portrait and landscape modes are very good examples of what can be done for chat on the iPhone. Source code is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iphonewebdev.com/ilace/about.html&#34;&gt;available&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/atow/749665338/&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;133&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/2007/07/08/keynote.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Keynote&#34; alt=&#34;Keynote&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; My keynote presentation slides are now available in &lt;a href=&#34;http://iphonedevcamp.org/stuff/iPhoneDevCamp_Keynote.pdf&#34;&gt;.pdf&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://iphonedevcamp.org/stuff/iPhoneDevCamp_Keynote.mov&#34;&gt;.mov&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;m told a live recording of the session and an .mp3 will be available soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks an online developer community that I started at WWDC called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iPhoneWebDev.com&#34;&gt;iPhoneWebDev&lt;/a&gt; has grown to over 650 members. It&#39;s now the best place to get online support for building iPhone web pages and webapps. I&#39;d like to keep the momentum from the iPhoneDevCamp going forward on this list, so if you are interested in developing for the iPhone, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iPhoneWebDev.com/examples&#34;&gt;example code&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iphonewebdev.com/&#34;&gt;join&lt;/a&gt; the discussion today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2007/07/iphonedevcamp-a.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Ready for the iPhone</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/06/getting_ready_f.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2007 20:06:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/06/getting_ready_f.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/iphone/ads/ad4/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Watereddown&#34; title=&#34;Watereddown&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/2007/06/15/watereddown.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I&#39;ve been excited about the web capabilities of the upcoming &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/iphone/&#34;&gt;iPhone&lt;/a&gt; for some time. As a reluctant laptop user (&amp;quot;oh, my aching shoulders&amp;quot;), there is real appeal to me in a better portable web browser. I have tried most of the PDA and cellphone browsers to date, and none offer more then a poor cousin to the web that we experience on the desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the iPhone offers a desktop-class browser. There is no transcoding, nor any subset of HTML such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wireless_Markup_Language&#34;&gt;WML&lt;/a&gt;. Full web pages are rendered in the small display, and when you &amp;quot;double-tap&amp;quot; with your finger the section you touch is expanded to a more readable size. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/iphone/ads/ad4/&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; available at the Apple website shows this capability in use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the iPhone&#39;s upcoming July 29th release, I decided to participate in this week&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://developer.apple.com/wwdc/&#34;&gt;Apple WWDC&lt;/a&gt; conference for Macintosh developers. There a number of announcements about the iPhone were released, and a number of technical sessions on the iPhone and iPhone-related technologies were held. Together the iPhone demonstrations at the public keynote and other demonstrations throughout the WWDC offered some real promise for when the phone is released on June 29th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=440,height=292,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/2007/06/15/iphonesteve.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;132&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/2007/06/15/iphonesteve.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Iphonesteve&#34; alt=&#34;Iphonesteve&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The biggest announcement at the public &lt;a href=&#34;http://events.apple.com.edgesuite.net/d7625zs/event/&#34;&gt;keynote&lt;/a&gt; was that there will not be an SDK for building native iPhone apps; instead, the only way for third parties to get involved is to create web applications optimized for the iPhone. This came as a big disappointment to the majority of developers participating at WWDC. However, as someone who has been involved lately in creating AJAX/Web 2.0 apps, I was less unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other significant announcement at the keynote was that a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/safari/download/&#34;&gt;Safari 3.0 beta&lt;/a&gt; for both Mac and Windows was being released and that a third Safari platform would be released on July 29th—inside the iPhone. This means that web 2.0 applications created to work with Safari on the Mac will likely also work on the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;SynchroEdit&#34; title=&#34;SynchroEdit&#34; src=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com/img/selogo-nobox-green.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Since &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source simultaneous web editor (in the style of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/&#34;&gt;SubEthaEdit&lt;/a&gt;) for Firefox that I produced last year, is one of the most sophisticated AJAX/Web 2.0 applications, I dug deeper at various WWDC sessions to see if it might be possible to make SynchroEdit work on the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest things that SynchroEdit needs in order to function is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.w3.org/TR/DOM-Level-2-Events/events.html#Events-eventgroupings-mutationevents&#34;&gt;DOM Mutation Events&lt;/a&gt;. At a party for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.webkit.org&#34;&gt;WebKit&lt;/a&gt; (the open source code underpinnings of Safari&#39;s web renderer) and in questions after a session at WWDC it was confirmed that these are available to Safari 3.0 and presumably the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other key ability that SynchroEdit requires is WYSIWYG editing. This was terribly broken in Safari 2.0, but I saw many demonstrations of it working in Safari 3.0, so I don&#39;t anticipate any problems with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SynchroEdit also requires AJAX and in particular the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.w3.org/TR/XMLHttpRequest/&#34;&gt;XMLHttpRequest&lt;/a&gt; function, and the keynote clearly said that this was available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thing that SynchroEdit needs is the ability to keep the browser at &lt;em&gt;readystate==3&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. not &amp;quot;finish&amp;quot; sending the page, so that we can continue to interactively pass updates to users as they arrive, without creating a new connection for every message. It is not clear if this will be supported on the iPhone, but there are ways to work around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in principle, it appears that we should be able to make SynchoEdit work on the iPhone. I am not sure that many iPhone users need SynchroEdit, but as an example of a very sophisticated web technology that should work on that platform, it shows the potential for what might be possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this technological capability I&#39;ve decided to begin investigating what type of social software apps could be highly useful on the iPhone and that aren&#39;t being served by the existing web 2.0 community. I am also going to continue investigating the technical issues of developing web apps for the iPhone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested as well, I invite you to participate in the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iPhoneWebDev.com/&#34;&gt;iPhoneWebDev&lt;/a&gt; community. It should be a great resource for everyone interested in getting in on the ground floor with this new web technology. I have also begun tagging relevant web pages in &lt;a href=&#34;http://del.icio.us/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;del.icio.us&lt;/a&gt; with the tag &lt;a href=&#34;http://del.icio.us/tag/iphonewebdev&#34;&gt;iphonewebdev&lt;/a&gt;—I hope that others will begin to use this tag as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have quite a bit more I&#39;d like to write about specific iPhone technology, but unfortunately I have to wait until the &lt;a href=&#34;http://developer.apple.com/wwdc/attendee/&#34;&gt;WWDC confidentiality&lt;/a&gt; expires on June 29th with the release of the iPhone, so keep an eye out here for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2007/06/getting_ready_f.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking about SynchroEdit at WikiWednesday</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/12/speaking_about_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2006 14:34:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/12/speaking_about_.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I will be speaking tonight at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.socialtext.net/wikiwed/index.cgi?wiki_wednesdays&#34;&gt;WikiWednesday&lt;/a&gt; on the topic of &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Same Time, Different Place Editing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and will be demonstrating &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit&lt;/a&gt; integration with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mediawiki.com&#34;&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.editthispage.net&#34;&gt;EditThisPagePHP&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you are interested, see you tonight (Wednesday) at 6-8pm, &lt;a href=&#34;http://maps.google.com/maps?oi=map&amp;amp;q=655+High+Street,+Palo+Alto,+CA&#34;&gt;at Socialtext&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/12/speaking_about_.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ratings: Who Do You Trust?</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2006 16:28:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My colleague, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt;, has been working on a game rating system for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpg.net&#34;&gt;RPGnet&lt;/a&gt;. This has resulted in real-world application of the principles for designing rating systems which we&#39;ve previously discussed in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt; articles. Shannon&#39;s newest article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;Ratings,
Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt; offers a look at weighting ratings based on reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/shannon_appelcline.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Shannon_appelcline&#34; alt=&#34;Shannon_appelcline&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the &lt;a href=&#34;http://index.rpg.net/&#34;&gt;RPGnet Gaming Index&lt;/a&gt; we&#39;ve put this all together to form a tree of weighted ratings that answer the question, &lt;em&gt;who do you trust&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s how we measured each type of trust, and what we did about it:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volume of Ratings for an Item.&lt;/strong&gt; Introduce a bayesian weight to offset the variability of items with low-volume ratings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volume of Ratings by a User.&lt;/strong&gt; Give each user a weight based on his volume of contribution which is applied to his ratings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depth of Content by a User.&lt;/strong&gt; Give each rating a weight based on the depth of thought implicit in the rating which is applied to that rating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These all get put together to create our final ratings for
the Gaming Index, with each user&#39;s individual rating for an item
getting multiplied by its user weight and its content weight, and then
all of that averaged with the other user ratings and the bayesian
weight too. The result is in no way intuitive, but users don&#39;t really
need to understand the back end of a rating system. Conversely we hope
it&#39;s accurate, or at least more accurate than would otherwise be true
given the relatively low volume of ratings we&#39;ve collected thus far.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of Shannon&#39;s earlier discussions about the design behind the new &amp;quot;user content&amp;quot; based &lt;a href=&#34;http://index.rpg.net&#34;&gt;RPGnet Gaming Index&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_191.phtml&#34;&gt;Encouraging
User Creativity&lt;/a&gt; - A look at the &amp;quot;XP&amp;quot; system which has helped to incentivize the creation of the database at the heart of the ratings.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt; - An examination of the nuts and bolts of RPGnet&#39;s Gaming Index database.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34;&gt;2006-01: Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Hmm, interesting on the weighting system.
Can you explain with more detail how the rating by depth of content is generated?
I&#39;m looking through the other articles, so hopefully I find the info there.
Frank
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;magicback (Frank)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-10-12T01:30:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-10-12T01:30:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
My first pass system just used a different multiplier for weight based on the type of content:
1x for just a raw rating
2x for a rating with a non-blank comment
5x for a review (which goes through a different, approved content system)
My second pass system also included &#34;volume of ratings by user&#34; and thus applied a variable multiplier depending on how many ratings the user has made:
(0-2x) for a raw rating
2x(0-2x) for a rating with comment
5x for a review
The 0-2x is calculated as (# of ratings by user)/50, to 2 max.
I&#39;m pretty sure that the core weighting system by depth is producing better results, though I haven&#39;t done any studies of that yet. The additional weighting for volume by users has definitely prevented bias by hit-and-run raters who just stop by to rate one game that they&#39;ve been asked to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-10-16T15:39:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-10-16T15:39:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using 5-Star Rating Systems</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 08:49:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt; I discuss ratings scales of various sorts, from eBay&#39;s 3-point scale to RPGnet&#39;s double 5-point scale, and BoardGame Geek&#39;s 10-point scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=373,height=239,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/stars_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/stars_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Stars_1&#34; alt=&#34;Stars_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the various ratings scales, 5-point scales are probably the most common on the Internet. You can find them not just in my own RPGnet, but also on Amazon, Netflix, and iTunes, as well as many other sites and services. Unfortunately 5-point rating scales also face many challenges in their use, and different studies suggest different flaws with this particular methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sloan.ucr.edu/category/working-papers/product-reviews/&#34;&gt;one study&lt;/a&gt; using Amazon data has shown that many &lt;em&gt;undetailed&lt;/em&gt; ratings (where the rater isn&#39;t required to add any additional information other than the rating they select) show a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bimodal_distribution&#34;&gt;bimodal distribution&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; In other words the distribution of ratings tends to cluster around two different numbers (e.g., 1 and 5) rather than offering a normal distribution where the ratings cluster around a single height (e.g., 3). Thus the median of these ratings is not an accurate reflection of product quality, but instead is a statement of conflicting opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;our own study&lt;/a&gt; using RPGnet data has shown that many &lt;em&gt;detailed&lt;/em&gt; ratings (where the rater does add additional information, in this case a full review) offer normal distributions, however it is biased toward the high end of the scale. On RPGnet, for example, we discovered that 90% of this 5-point rating system was 3 or higher with an average around 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://360.yahoo.com/profile-9lciejI3aafX1stHPoIRNmkmv4EowQ--&#34;&gt;Randy Farmer&lt;/a&gt; of Yahoo suggests that this scale limitation is particularly troublesome for fan-based ratings, such as those found on episodic TV sites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Only the fans of a show evaluate the episodes, and being fans, will never rate an episode one or two stars, ever. I&#39;ve seen this attempted over and over on the net with the same results every time: Each episode of a show is 4-stars +/- .5 stars. This goes all the way back to the Babylon-5 website, probably the first source for this kind of data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And indeed, the TV episode &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tv.com/babylon-5/tko/episode/25148/summary.html?tag=ep_list;title;14&#34;&gt;TKO&lt;/a&gt;, from &lt;em&gt;Babylon 5&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s first season, is considered an entirely atrocious episode by even the fans. Yet it has a 6.1 of 10 &amp;quot;Fair&amp;quot; rating on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tv.com&#34;&gt;tv.com&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus even when a bimodal distribution is not a problem, on a 5-point scale the upward bias often results in only 2 or 3 meaningful data points. This is problematic because it minimizes differentiation. In many cases, a 5-star rating system where most of the ratings are either 3 or 4 is actually no better then just a thumbs-up/thumbs-down rating system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, given that 5-point scales are probably here to stay, we are forced to make the best use of them we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we need to provide raters with &lt;em&gt;incentives&lt;/em&gt;, so that they provide meaningful ratings. We&#39;ve already seen that this can be done by requesting detailed ratings: when a person takes the time to write text, and knows that his name will be attached to it, he generally does a better job in his rating. There are other possible incentives techniques as well, such as RPGnet&#39;s new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_191.phtml&#34;&gt;XP System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we need to provide means for a 5-point scale to become more meaningful by encouraging raters to use not just the top half of the scale, but the bottom half as well. One method to accomplish this is to make ratings &lt;em&gt;distinct&lt;/em&gt; -- as I briefly mentioned in my previous article on this topic -- and encourage standards so that an &amp;quot;average&amp;quot; rating is 2 or 3, not 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of how to accomplish both of these goals with already existing 5-point rating scales, I&#39;ve detailed my own experiences with using ratings on two popular services -- iTunes and Amazon. By providing myself with incentives and making my use of ratings very distinctive, I have created more meaningful and useful output for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Music Ratings - iTunes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple&#39;s iTunes software offers you the ability to rate individual songs with a 0-5 Star rating. If you use iTunes with an iPod, you can change the rating of a song on your iPod and the change will be reflected in your iTunes database the next time you sync your iPod. The &amp;quot;Shuffle Songs&amp;quot; feature available on more modern iPods has an option to have songs with higher ratings be played more often. A very powerful feature, Smart Playlists, can dynamically create sophisticated playlists based on ratings. All of this makes rating music on iTunes very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Shannon and I wrote our Rating Systems article, I examined the ratings in my iTunes catalog. Using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://girtby.net/archives/2005/11/03/itunes-library-preening/&#34;&gt;Alastair&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; fabulous XLST &lt;a href=&#34;http://girtby.net/offerings/itunes-ratings-stats/&#34;&gt;iTunes rating statistics tool&lt;/a&gt;, I discovered that the ratings I created in iTunes clearly were biased overly high, matching the pattern we&#39;d described. I had far too many songs rated with 4 Stars, and almost nothing rated 1 or 2. This made my ratings less useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&#34;6&#34;&gt;Here are some statistics from your iTunes Library: 4172 tracks, 412 (10%) rated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;Cumulative % of Rated&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;% of rated&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Actual&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Target&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Shortfall&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 5 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;112&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-22&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 4 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;183&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-57&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 3 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-44&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 2 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 1 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So over the last few months I&#39;ve completely revamped my iTunes ratings. Since I can&#39;t change the user interface, I&#39;ve changed my behavior. I&#39;m also taking advantage of two other fields: &amp;quot;checked&amp;quot; which I use to give more distinctiveness to my ratings, and &amp;quot;play count&amp;quot; which shows whether or not I&#39;ve listened to something through to the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the criteria I used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 5 - Exemplars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_5_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_5_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_5_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Only my most favorite songs are rated 5. They have to meet the following criteria: they make me feel good or excite me no matter how often I listen to them, I can typically listen to them often without getting tired of them, and they are the best of their particular genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 4 - Great &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_4_checked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_4_checked&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_4_checked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; There is only a small difference between a song that is rated 4 and 5 in my ratings -- typically it doesn&#39;t excite me or make me smile quite as much, or it isn&#39;t necessarily an exemplar of its genre. However, I still can typically listen to them often without getting tired of them. Items that are rated 4 and 5 are ones that I carry on my iPod Shuffle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 4 - Great (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_4_unchecked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_4_unchecked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_4_unchecked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; There are a few songs that I do consider to be great, but that I only want to play when I&#39;m in the mood for them, or I want to only play in a specific order, or they &amp;quot;don&#39;t play well&amp;quot; with other music. For instance I love the song &amp;quot;The Highwayman&amp;quot; by Loreena McKennitt, however, it is over 10 minutes long and I just don&#39;t want to hear that type of song unless I&#39;m in the mood for it. Other examples are the 12 songs that make up Mussorgsky&#39;s &amp;quot;Pictures at an Exhibition&amp;quot;&amp;nbsp; -- I want them played in order when I do play them, and I really don&#39;t want them played in the middle of my other songs. Unfortunately, iTunes does not let you select only unchecked items, so I don&#39;t have a Smart Playlist for these; instead I keep them in a regular playlist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 3 - Good &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_3_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_3_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_3_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are songs I like. Typically I can play them regularly but not too often. Songs rated 3-5 go on my iPod Nano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 3 - Good (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_3_unchecked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_3_unchecked&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_3_unchecked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; There is a lot of music that I think is Good, but I don&#39;t want to play all the time. I have a large catalog of sound tracks from movies. All but a few of those tracks are in this category. Again, iTunes does not let you select only unchecked items in a Smart Playlist, so I have several regular playlists for these items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 2 - Ok &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_2_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_2_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_2_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; I have very diverse musical tastes, starting with jazz, various ethnic and world music, and also including quite a bit of pop, rap, R&amp;amp;B, punk, and metal that I enjoy. I don&#39;t enjoy them all the time -- but I do like them to pop up every once in a while for variety. So I rate these 2 and leave them checked. I have an old 40GB iPod that I take on long trips, and it stores everything I have that is checked and rated 2-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 2 - Ok (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_2_unchecked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_2_unchecked&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_2_unchecked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Some songs are OK, but I really have to be in the mood specifically for that song. Listening to Jimmy Buffet&#39;s &amp;quot;Margaritaville&amp;quot; can be a guilty pleasure on a lazy summer day at the beach, but it isn&#39;t something I want to regularly listen to. I have a number of special playlists for songs rated like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 1 - Don&#39;t Like &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_1_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_1_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_1_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are the songs that I don&#39;t like. They&#39;re just not my style. Many are still quality music, they just doesn&#39;t work for me. I do keep most of these for completeness -- it might just be one or two songs on the album, and I want to keep the album complete. Or I keep it in case my tastes change. But in general, once something is rate 1 Star, I&#39;ll probably never listen to it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 1 - Trash (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_1_unchecked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_1_unchecked&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_1_unchecked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are songs that not only do I not like, they just are not good music. I don&#39;t like most rap music, but I can tell that most are still quality. Some are junk -- these I rate 1 and uncheck, and are candidates for deletion the next time I purge my collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unrated &amp;amp; Listened &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_0_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; /&gt;, playcount &amp;gt; 0:&lt;/strong&gt; If I&#39;ve listened to something through to the end, but haven&#39;t rated it yet, it shows up in this Smart Playlist. Periodically I check this Smart Playlist, sort by playcount, and try to rate everything that I&#39;ve listened to more then once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unrated &amp;amp; Unlistened &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/myrating_0_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; /&gt;, play count=0:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the default when a new song is added to my library. So any song that is unrated, checked, and has a play count of 0 shows up in my &amp;quot;Unrated &amp;amp; Unlistened&amp;quot; Smart Playlist. When I&#39;m in the mood for variety, I go through this playlist and rate songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modifying my rating system in this way has caused my average rating for music to change from around 4 to somewhere between 2 and 3. It will probably, over time, become closer to 2 as I rate more of my collection. This gives me a lot of distinctiveness so that I can create Smart Playlists that work well for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&#34;6&#34;&gt;Here are some statistics from your iTunes Library: 6519 tracks, 726 (11%) rated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;Cumulative % of Rated&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;% of rated&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Actual&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Target&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Shortfall&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 5 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 4 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;144&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-15&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 3 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;211&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 2 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;270&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 1 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously rating a large music collection can become a chore -- you don&#39;t want to spend your limited music listening time always fine tuning your ratings. So I have some approaches that make it easier for me to rate my music with less effort:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, I sorted my catalog by my old ratings, and modified everything down by 1, Starting with everything rated 2 becoming 1, 3 becoming 2, etc. This gave me a good base to start with&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/exemplar_smart_playlist.png&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=512,height=216,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;84&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Exemplar_smart_playlist&#34; title=&#34;Exemplar_smart_playlist&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/exemplar_smart_playlist.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Next I created Smart Playlists for each rating, i.e. &amp;quot;Rating 5 - Exemplar&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;Match only checked songs&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Live updating&amp;quot; checked. I then added &amp;quot;Play Count&amp;quot; as a column to my view, and sorted by it. This gave me the songs that I played the most and least, and I adjusted some songs up and down accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist.png&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=512,height=241,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;94&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist&#34; title=&#34;Plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Then I created a new Smart Playlist that simply plays songs rated 3 to 5, limiting the list to the first 100 GB selected by random (i.e. everything random), and saved this Smart Playlist as &amp;quot;Plays Well With Others&amp;quot;. I play this on occasion in the background, and when I hear something that jars me I know something isn&#39;t rated right. Thus without a lot of effort I can change ratings for songs that no longer fit their rating, or uncheck items where the rating was appropriate but it &amp;quot;didn&#39;t play well with others&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I try to be aware when I&#39;m using my iPod of what a songs rating is, and change it if it seems wrong. The next time I sync the iPod my ratings will be adjusted in my iTunes catalog.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/play_count.png&#34; title=&#34;Play_count&#34; alt=&#34;Play_count&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;I also try to be aware of Play Count -- this number only goes up if you play a song to the end. So even if I&#39;m not able to take a look at the rating (for instance when I&#39;m in a car), I can at least forward to the next song. Periodically I review the play counts for songs that I&#39;ve rated and consider moving them up and down accordingly. Of course, this means that I have to be careful and not let the iPod keep running when I&#39;m not listening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tip for those of you that do put a lot of effort into your iTunes ratings: I&#39;ve learned the hard way that unlike most song information, the rating is &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; stored in the song itself, so if your iTunes database gets corrupted, or you move your music to another server, you&#39;ll lose all your ratings. One way to avoid this is to periodically backup your ratings into a field that is stored in the song itself. I personally use the &amp;quot;Grouping&amp;quot; field as it is rarely used, select all songs with the same rating and click on &amp;quot;Get Info&amp;quot;, and change the Grouping field to &amp;quot;My Rating: 5 Stars&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only have 11% of my collection rated so far, but using this system I&#39;m finding it a lot easier to manage my ratings. I&#39;m already getting many benefits from it -- I&#39;m playing my music more often, my iPods typically have the music I want on them, and various music discovery services can use my ratings to help me identify new music I might enjoy. This provides the &lt;em&gt;incentive&lt;/em&gt; to keep me entering meaningful ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Book Ratings - Amazon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon also uses a 5-Star rating system, and your ratings can be used by Amazon to help you find books that you might like. Though I like to support my local bookstores, it is this feature that brings me back to Amazon time and again. Whenever I browse through Amazon and see a book I&#39;ve already read I try to take the time to update my rating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon has a number of different tools to assist you in your ratings. If you are an Amazon customer, you can go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/yourstore/iyr/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;collection=owned&#34;&gt;Improve Your Recommendations: Edit Items You Own&lt;/a&gt; and see all the books that you&#39;ve purchased and quickly rate them with a nice AJAX interface. You can also review items that you&#39;ve already rated, whether or not you own them, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/yourstore/iyr/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;collection=rated&#34;&gt;Improve Your Recommendations: Edit Items You&#39;ve Rated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=509,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/amazon_your_media_library.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;159&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/amazon_your_media_library.png&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_your_media_library&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_your_media_library&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Amazon has also recently added a very nice web service called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/library/&#34;&gt;Your Media Library&lt;/a&gt; that can be used to help manage your media library of books, music, and dvds. I personally only have used it to manage my books and dvds, as I find rating albums useless -- it is songs that I prefer to rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After browsing through my ratings to date, I discovered the same flaws I found iTunes -- my ratings typically were too high; most were a 4. This is particularly encouraged by the popup when your cursor is over the Stars &amp;quot;1 - I hate it, 2 - I don&#39;t like it, 3 - It&#39;s Ok, 4 - I like it, and 5 - I love it&amp;quot;. I suspect if I use the same trick that I use for iTunes of making a rating of 2 Stars mean &amp;quot;Ok&amp;quot; I could potentially cause the recommendation engine to be less effective (though it could possibly make it better, I don&#39;t know). So I am being much more brutal with my ratings and pushing many more down to 3, so that my ratings of 4 and 5 have more meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/amazon_5_star.png&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_5_star&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_5_star&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These have to be the exemplars -- the best books I&#39;ve ever read, would be glad to read again, would be proud to show off on my best bookshelf, and will buy extra copies to give to friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_4_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_4_star&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/amazon_4_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These have to be really good books -- most of them I&#39;m willing to read again and I promote them by offering to loan them to my more discriminating friends. Although I may keep them on my bookshelf I&#39;d rather give them to a friend then sell them at a used book store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_3_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_3_star&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/amazon_3_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are books are decent books, and I do share them with my voracious reader friends. But I don&#39;t push them and I&#39;m much more likely to sell them at a used bookstore then keep them on my shelf. This is the rating that I significantly underused previously, and I&#39;m finding that the key discriminator for me so far is how much I feel like recommending this to friends who are more discriminating readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_2_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_2_star&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/amazon_2_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; This rating is where the Amazon rating system fails the most -- these are suppost to be books that &amp;quot;I don&#39;t like&amp;quot;, however, most of the time I don&#39;t buy books that I probably wouldn&#39;t like, much less read them, so I have very few in this category. However, I&#39;ve decided this category is for books that are just not quite good enough, or are slightly disappointing. Not bad, or disliked, but just somewhat disappointing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_1_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_1_star&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/amazon_1_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; This is where I put the books that I don&#39;t like, or worse, I hate. Not many here, but I&#39;m willing to risk more then many people are so I have some. Also books go here that just don&#39;t fit my interest, like romance novels that get recommended to me because I like some crossover fantasy-romance authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I started more accurately rating my books at Amazon, I&#39;ve found that their suggestions for other books to read to be more accurate. Thus I am getting value from rating these books, and I have &lt;em&gt;incentive&lt;/em&gt; to continue to make the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering an incentive for people to rate is important for ratings of all sorts, with both individual gain and status recognition being powerful motivators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the easiest technique for making a 5-point rating scale more useful is to make it &amp;quot;distinct&amp;quot;. If a user has a more specific meaning for each rating, ratings will slowly settle toward a truer average, and thus more of each rating scale will be used. We&#39;ve also tried this technique recently on RPGnet, with our new &lt;a href=&#34;http://index.rpg.net/&#34;&gt;Gaming Index&lt;/a&gt;; and thus far our new 10-point scale -- which has distinct meanings for each number -- is averaging &lt;a href=&#34;http://index.rpg.net/browse.phtml?count=50&amp;amp;type=Best&amp;amp;productCategory=Entries&#34;&gt;7.27&lt;/a&gt;. That&#39;s still a fair amount above the real average of 5.5, but at least it&#39;s below the 8+ rating that our old double 5-point scale resulted in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often you, as a consumer of rating systems, will be making use of rating scales designed by others, rather than those you&#39;re designing yourself. For those cases it often makes sense to design your own rules for what each number means, and to do so in such a way that your median is the average of the scale, rather than toward one of the extremes. When you do, even if you&#39;re using a tight 5-point scale you&#39;ll end up with enough differentiation for it to actually be more meaningful than a thumbs up or a thumbs down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34;&gt;2006-01: Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;See
http://web.archive.org/web/20010207224515/http://people.delphi.com/mike100000/p5summary.html#summary (or click my name below) for a summary of all the votes for the B5 Series.
Averaging all episodes you get a mean score of 8.19 with a standard deviation of 0.84 - a *very* narrow range.
Context and Motivation matter more than scale in getting reusable scores out of rating systems. As I like to tell the folks here at Yahoo! – the person creating the rating has to get something out of the transaction other than just altruism.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20010207224515/http://people.delphi.com/mike100000/p5summary.html#summary&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-08-11T09:49:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-08-11T09:49:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I thought the issue, like Randy Farmer suggests, was that only positive discrete scales always tend to their maximum.  The problem then in rating systems, like you mentioned I think earlier, is that readers have to interpret what the real norm and limits are.  Even if every rating is in the upper quartile.  You may want to check out what I did in Playerep (http://www.playerep.com), where the rating system is based on election but not a fixed scale (always norming to zero without influence).   FWIW. Thanks.
Adam
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://tidehorion.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Adam MacDonald&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-08-11T10:21:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-08-11T10:21:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I like your classification scheme for iTunes. I&#39;m going to have to work on adapting my scale (which is definitely showing signs of skewing towards the high end).
One thing, though. You mention that you can&#39;t create smart playlists to show unchecked songs. It&#39;s true that you can&#39;t do it with only one playlist, but you can do so with 2:
#1) Any playlist (for example, let&#39;s say your smart playlist for 4 star, checked songs, so you have it set (I assume) for My Rating = 4, Match Only Checked Songs = checked)
#2) Use these criteria:  My Rating = 4, Playlist Is Not &lt;playlist #1&gt;. Leave match only checked songs unchecked, and enable live updating and you have a smart playlist that shows you your unchecked 4-star songs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Andy Tinkham&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-08-16T13:55:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-08-16T13:55:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
&gt;&gt;Unfortunately, iTunes does not let you select only unchecked items, so I don&#39;t have a Smart Playlist for these; instead I keep them in a regular playlist.
You can:
Make a smart playlist called &#39;Checked&#39; with a rule that is always true (e.g. artist does not contain (leave the field emtpy), or bitrate &gt; 0). Create a smart playlist called &#39;Unchecked&#39; with the rule: &#39;Playlist is not Checked&#39;. There you have all your unchecked files.
From there you can make smart ones that use this Unchecked playlist.
I like your rating system. I have 40% on a 3star now, and around 25% for 2 and 4 stars. I might scale it down a little bit more.
hmm, after typing this I read the comments and see Adam McDonald already mentioned something similar about the unchecked items. I&#39;ll leave it here anyway...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Tino&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-10-16T11:52:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-10-16T11:52:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Christopher, I think some, if not all, of the issues with the 5-point rating system could be addressed with a better UI. For example, displaying a normal distribution curve skewed by accumulated rating to nudge raters away from the extremes. Of course, this doesn&#39;t work well if sample size is too small which usually happens on the far end of the long tail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/&#34;&gt;Don Park&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-12-17T18:25:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-12-17T18:25:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Thanks for writing this article. I found another view on 5 point music rating other than my own informational.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Jonathan&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-06T00:33:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-06T00:33:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2006 23:37:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.7em;&#34;&gt;by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This is the third in a series of articles on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt;, co-written by my collegue &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline&#34;&gt;Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt;. It will be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_179.phtml&#34;&gt;jointly posted&lt;/a&gt; in Shannon&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT.shtml&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities&lt;/a&gt; online games column at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our first article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt; we outlined a number of different types of choice systems, among them voting, polling, rating, and ranking. Since then we&#39;ve been spending some time expanding upon the systems, with the goal being to create both a lexicon of and a dialogue about systems for collective choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we&#39;re going to dig more into &lt;em&gt;comparison ranking systems&lt;/em&gt;, by focusing on &lt;em&gt;competitive&lt;/em&gt; rankings and looking more in depth at ELO Chess Ranking System and the other systems that we briefly mentioned previously. Our goal is to explicate these systems, to better address their flaws, to begin detailing the purposes of ranking systems, and to show how those purposes are critical in the design of ranking systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;subjective_vs_objective&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Subjective vs. Objective Rankings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our original article we discussed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;rating systems&lt;/a&gt; as being largely subjective and ranking systems as being objective, but the situation isn&#39;t nearly as simple as that. In truth, there&#39;s a clear spectrum of ratings and rankings with varying amounts of subjectivity and objectivity in each collective choice system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcsfootball.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Bcs_1&#34; title=&#34;Bcs_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/bcs_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.officialworldgolfranking.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/golfrankings_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Golfrankings_1&#34; alt=&#34;Golfrankings_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowl_Championship_Series&#34;&gt;Bowl Championship Series&lt;/a&gt; (BCS) for college football is a good example of a ranking system that explicitly allows a subjective component. It involves a complex mathematical formula that includes things like win/loss ratios, but also sportswriters&#39; and coaches&#39; ratings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, public opinion continues to show that people don&#39;t necessarily like seeing true ranking systems having subjective components, because they expect them to be &amp;quot;fair&amp;quot;. The BCS formula has come under attack several times in the last few years precisely due to its subjective basis. Cal Berkeley was one of several teams denied a bowl position in 2004 when many felt that they were worthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atptennis.com/en/players/raceleaderboard/rank_definitions.asp&#34;&gt;APL tennis rankings&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_rankings&#34;&gt;official world golf rankings&lt;/a&gt; also have a subjective component, but it is much more subtle. Each tournament is worth a certain number of points, and the allocation of those points is relatively arbitrary, based upon the &amp;quot;prestige&amp;quot; of each tournament and the quality of players who have traditionally played in it. The subjectivism isn&#39;t quite as near to the surface as that of the college bowls, but it&#39;s still something that can have a notable, and perhaps unwarranted, effect upon the final results.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;algorithmic_rankings&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Algorithmic Rankings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kosteniuk.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; title=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wcsrating_2.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This brings us back to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELO_rating_system&#34;&gt;ELO system&lt;/a&gt;, a ranking system originally designed for chess which is fairly well-known and well-understood. As we said in our overview article, &amp;quot;[ELO] builds a simple distribution of player ratings around a norm (typically 1500 points), then awards or deducts points based upon wins and losses, with the total sum of all points in the system staying constant. Players are then ranked according to their comparative scores.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big difference between this and the previously discussed systems is that it&#39;s almost entirely objective; in fact it uses a statistical basis to create an underlying mathematical model for rankings, rather than allowing human subjectivity to get in the way.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest formulation for an ELO rating looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span size=&#34;+2&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&#39; = R + K * (S - E)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&#39;&lt;/code&gt; is the new rating&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is the old rating&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; is a maximum value for increase or decrease of rating (16 or 32 for ELO)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; is the score for a game&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt; is the expected score for a game&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the trick is in figuring out what the (&lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;)xpected score of a game is. ELO uses the following formulas for players A and B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;E(A) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [R(B) - R(A)] / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;E(B) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [R(A) - R(B)] / 400 ) ]&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a good model because, using the two formulas, it means that a great player gains little from beating an average player, but an average player gains a lot from beating a great player. Take the following example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;R(A) = 1900&lt;br /&gt;R(B) = 1500&lt;br /&gt;
E(A) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [1500 - 1900] / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( -400 / 400) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ -4 / 4 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ -1 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / 1 + .1&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = .91&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 91%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;E(B) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [1900 - 1500] / 400) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( 400 / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ 1 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / 11&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = .09&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 9%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player A is expected to score .91 in an average game, which is to say he should win 91% of the time, and will be punished accordingly if he loses to player B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * (0 - .91)&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 - 29.12&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1871&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely a win nets him very little:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * (1 - .91)&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * .09&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 2.88&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1903&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELO is almost entirely mathematical. Players can gain or lose different amounts of points based upon playing different players, but this is all part of the formula. The only slightly subjective element is the definition of &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; -- how much a player can win or lose from a particular game. The most widely used ELO systems for Chess break &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; down into two values: 16 for masters and 32 for everyone else. So there is a subjective decision that masters should vary their score less frequently than other players. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a very minor element in an otherwise objective system, but as we&#39;ll see, more recent systems by Days of Wonder and Microsoft first reduce, then eliminate even this subjectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;days_of_wonder&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations of a Theme: Days of Wonder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daysofwonder.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Dowlogo_1&#34; title=&#34;Dowlogo_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/dowlogo_1.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
ELO is probably the most used ranking system in the world. You can find it in use for Go, &lt;em&gt;Tantrix&lt;/em&gt;, and many other games. Days of Wonder, producers of &lt;em&gt;Gang of Four&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ticket to Ride&lt;/em&gt;, and many other games use a variant of the system which they describe on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gangoffour.com/index.php?t=content&amp;amp;sub=ranking&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They identify three core problems with ELO: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New players can take a long time to ascend or descend to their correct levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highly ranked players can be hesitant to play with provisional players whose ranking might be much more uncertain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no allowances for games with more than two players.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Days of Wonder resolved the first problem by creating a new formula for provisional players, allowing them to rise and fall in the rankings much more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely when playing against provisional players, regular players can only lose a maximum of &lt;code&gt;K*n/20&lt;/code&gt; points, where n is the number of games that the provisional player has played--rather than the normal maximum loss of &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;. For example, playing someone who has just played one game, can only result in a loss of 1/20th of the regular &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; value, and so it really doesn&#39;t matter if the provisional player&#39;s ranking is wildly out of whack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these new formulas are set up to converge toward a normal ELO formula as a provisional player&#39;s number of games approaches 20 (making them a normal player at Days of Wonder).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It should be pointed out that using the number &amp;quot;20&amp;quot; to define a provisional player, and making a player less provisional in clean 5% steps, inevitably offers yet another small, subjective element into this mathematical formula; as we&#39;ll see momentarily Microsoft has more recently incorporated the idea of provisional uncertainty into their core mathematical model, much as the whole ELO system originally turned subjective win and loss statistics into tighter mathematics.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/wonder/TT/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ttrskotosrankings.png&#34; title=&#34;Ttrskotosrankings&#34; alt=&#34;Ttrskotosrankings&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, to resolve the situation of multiple players, Days of Wonder considers each game to be a set of duels, as described here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
There are 4 players in a &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gang of Four game. Let&#39;s name A the winning player, B the second one, C the third one and D the last one. We consider that there were 6 duels: A won against B, C and D. B won against C and D. C won against D. We compute independently the new scores for each duel, and then we average the values for each player&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a fairly elegant answer that not only rewards or penalizes all players separately, but also encourages playing for second place, or even third, if first isn&#39;t possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been continued discussions of the Days of Wonder ELO variant in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daysofwonder.com/index.php?t=forums&#34;&gt;their forums&lt;/a&gt;, and the questions raised there are common to many different ranking systems. Some players wanted unranked games, while others thought that having unranked games would discourage people from playing good competitors &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; in unranked games.&amp;nbsp; There has also been a lot of discussion regarding &lt;em&gt;Ticket to Ride&lt;/em&gt;, a strategy game that supports 2-5 people, and whether the ELO variant system discourages multiperson play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various lessons learned at Days of Wonder underline two basic ideas about rankings. First, even with a well-studied system like ELO, there&#39;s still a lot to understand, and, second, any ranking system needs to reflect the specifics of what it&#39;s ranking -- and what its purpose is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;xbox_360_live&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations on a Theme: XBox 360 Live&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/default.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskillxbox360&#34; title=&#34;Trueskillxbox360&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/trueskillxbox360.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An even more recent large-scale ranking system is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.microsoft.com/displayArticle.aspx?id=1361&#34;&gt;TrueSkill&lt;/a&gt; system developed by Microsoft for use with the XBox 360. It appears to be an expanded variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://math.bu.edu/people/mg/glicko/glicko.doc/glicko.html&#34;&gt;glicko&lt;/a&gt; ranking system used by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freechess.org/&#34;&gt;free internet chess server&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the problems identified by Microsoft were the same as those already noted by Days of Wonder and others, including: the uncertainty of provisional ratings and the need to rank players in multiplayer games. However, the TrueSkill system notably expands both issues. Ranking uncertainty is now defined as a mathematical concept and the rankings now support not just multiple players, but also multiple teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/trueskill.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=430,height=324,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskill&#34; title=&#34;Trueskill&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/trueskill.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;TrueSkill explicitly includes two values in any ranking: a skill level and an uncertainty level. The first, like the more common ELO ranking, tells how good a player is. The second states how sure that ranking is. The uncertainty rating is effectively a margin of error, similar to those we saw in &lt;em&gt;polling systems&lt;/em&gt;. If a first-time player has a skill rating of 25 with an uncertainty rating of 8.3 that means that his skill is probably somewhere in the range of 16.7 to 33.3, a pretty wide range, but then this is a totally untested player. According to benchmarks that Microsoft produced, 99.99% of actual skill levels were within 3x of the uncertainty rating, and 100% were within 4x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of TrueSkill&#39;s innovations are built around this model of uncertainty. All players win or lose skill points, based upon how many players they beat or lose to, and they also decrease their uncertainty rating as they play more games. However, uncertainty is decreased more for players toward the middle of a pack within a game than those around the edges (because on the edges the players could actually be much better or much worse than it is possible to see from a specific game). In addition, TrueSkill is only a zero-sum ranking system for players at the exact same level of uncertainty. The more uncertainty that an opponent possesses, the smaller the weighting of any gain or loss (much like the simpler system that Days of Wonder uses, which bases weightings of games against provisional players as &lt;code&gt;n/20&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall TrueSkill is a somewhat complex system that is described more fully at Microsoft&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/Details.aspx#How_to_Update_Skills&#34;&gt;web site&lt;/a&gt;. Some of their expansions had already been considered by others, but still their system is notably innovative in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expanding a competitive ranking system to include concepts of teams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incorporating the uncertainty of ratings further into the core mathematical model, rather than using a somewhat more subjective model such as that described by Days of Wonder for provisional players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/RankCalculator.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/trueskillcalculator_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Trueskillcalculator_1&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskillcalculator_1&#34; class=&#34;image-full&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The TrueSkill calculations are a bit complex. In general, that&#39;s not a problem for a computer-based ranking model because you can have a computer doing all the computations, and players only need to understand the results. However the two-part ranking system used by TrueSkill, which notes both skill level and uncertainty, does offer a potential problem on this latter point. &lt;em&gt;Can players understand it?&lt;/em&gt; In general, the concept of uncertainty will not be understood by people other that statisticians, thus raising a real user-interface question with the TrueSkill system -- and the exact sort of thing that designers of new ranking systems will need to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;a_tale_in_the_desert&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations on a Theme: A Tale in the Desert&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atid.com&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;A_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1&#34; title=&#34;A_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/a_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The online game, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atitd.com&#34;&gt;A Tale in the Desert&lt;/a&gt;, identified a different problem with the ELO system: &lt;em&gt;cheating&lt;/em&gt;. This is a uniquely Internet-based problem, because there users can create fake accounts, then defeat those accounts to win points. This can also be done more subtly, by having multiple additional accounts build up the rating of that fake account before the fake account is defeated. So a totally new ranking system, called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.atitd.net/tale1/EGenesis_Ranking_System&#34;&gt;eGenesis Ranking System&lt;/a&gt;, was created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each player is ranked through a 256-bit vector, half of which is initially set to 0 and half of which is set to 1 (therefore creating an average ranking of 128). Whenever a match occurs between players a hash function based on the players&#39; names mathematically selects 32 of those bits, 8 of which are then randomly selected. Among those bits, any 1s in the loser&#39;s vector which correspond to 0s in the winner&#39;s vector are &amp;quot;transferred&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple design corresponds in some ways to ELO&#39;s more complex formula. A good player will have more 1s and thus more to lose, and he will lose correspondingly more to a poor player who has more 0s in his vector. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the system also prevents the collusion earlier noted. Statistically, a single player will only ever gain 8 ranking points from another new player, since out of the 32 bit hash only eight of those will, on average, be in the correct 0-1 configuration. Expanding a group of players expands the number of points that can potentially be gained, but within real limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wowsocialmap_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Wowsocialmap_1&#34; alt=&#34;Wowsocialmap_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In fact, the eGenesis system prevents cheating by measuring the size of social networks, then limiting the number of ranking points that can be earned within a social network. It&#39;s not necessarily the only way to measure social network size, but its methodology points toward social software as an interesting area for additional study of ranking systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with XBox&#39;s TrueSkill, the eGenesis algorithms are overall fairly sophisticated and confusing, perhaps more so than TrueSkill itself. However, unlike TrueSkill the output is very simple: a skill number between 0 and 255. The intricacies are hidden by the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Competitive Ranking Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, as we mentioned when discussing Days of Wonder, any ranking system has to be measured by what it&#39;s trying to do and how well it does that. ELO and similar numerical, long-term ranking systems, are most likely trying to achieve one of three goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;heirarchy&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hierarchy:&lt;/strong&gt; Players are divided into hierarchies of success, giving players goals to constantly strive for and ways to measure their success (or failure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;matching&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matching:&lt;/strong&gt; Players can play with other players at their same skill level, rather than having to play beginners or experts who are much better than they are. This generally increases everyone&#39;s enjoyment. For computer games, the complexity of a matching system can be largely moderated by the computer, thus ensuring better competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;handicapping&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handicapping:&lt;/strong&gt; If players do play against others of different skill levels, the better players can be handicapped in automatic, appropriate ways for the game in question, again increasing the fairness of games and everyone&#39;s enjoyment. For instance, someone ranked 3-kyu in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28board_game%29&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; playing a less experienced 7-kyu player would give him a starting &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_handicap&#34;&gt;4 stone advantage&lt;/a&gt; to make for better competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ELO system may be a good matching system, which allows players to easily find other players of their same skill level and play against them. However it doesn&#39;t provide any way to handicap players, nor would the ELO method necessarily be a good one to analyze handicaps (and conversely a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_handicap&#34;&gt;golf handicap&lt;/a&gt; might not do a good job of finding like players nor measuring players&#39; ability in a hierarchy). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently the XBox system has stated that it&#39;s explicitly for matchmaking, with the goal being to always try and match up players at nearly the same skill level. It&#39;s also used for hierarchy (or &amp;quot;leaderboards&amp;quot; as it&#39;s described in the TrueSkill docs), but that&#39;s clearly a subsidiary purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these systems would be ineffective for measuring a winner in a live event, which is a very different goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tourney:&lt;/strong&gt; A single player is listed as an absolute winner, the &amp;quot;King of the Hill&amp;quot;. Often, second, third, and fourth place winners are measured too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the systems we&#39;ve discussed thus far may not be useful for measuring privileges, yet another goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threshold:&lt;/strong&gt; The best ranks of players can be given special privileges, including the ability to create games and form tournaments. Alternatively, they can be given privileges totally outside the game, again giving them something extra to strive for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each of these additional goals we may need to consider very different ranking systems, not just variations of ELO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;tourneys&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Different Themes: Tourneys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.kumc.edu/itc/staff/rknight/tourneys.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Tournament_1&#34; title=&#34;Tournament_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/tournament_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
There are a number of well-known tournament types which can be used to create a &amp;quot;King of the Hill&amp;quot; ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-elimination_tournament&#34;&gt;single-elimination tournament,&lt;/a&gt; where the winner of each competition moves on to compete with other winners, until there is only one. However, this style of tournament is quite cut-throat and is not suited very well to events where the competition may result in a draw, or where chance is a notable factor in the competition. It also has a very subjective factor in the initial &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-elimination_tournament#Seeding&#34;&gt;seeding&lt;/a&gt; of the rounds. The single-elimination tournament also does not rank the losers. However, by having the losers compete with each other in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swiss_system_tournament&#34;&gt;Swiss-style tournament&lt;/a&gt;, the relative strengths of the players can be ranked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jsoo.home.mindspring.com/articles/formats/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/pseudodoubleelimination_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Pseudodoubleelimination_1&#34; alt=&#34;Pseudodoubleelimination_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An improvement is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double-elimination&#34;&gt;double-elimination tournament&lt;/a&gt; which is now one of the best known tournament systems in sports. Players compete in series of two-player matches, and a player has to lose twice before he&#39;s eliminated. This is done through a system of winner and loser brackets, wherein people drop from the winners&#39; brackets to the losers&#39; brackets when they lose once, and drop out altogether when they lose twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem with standard double-elimination is that there are unusual situations where a significantly inferior player can still make it to the final round, or the last player to remain undefeated can lose only once and still be eliminated. These can be addressed through variants such as face-off (requiring the last two remaining competitors to compete &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; if the undefeated team is defeated for the first time in the finals) or by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jsoo.home.mindspring.com/articles/formats/&#34;&gt;reconfiguring the loser&#39;s brackets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wscgames.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wsc_1&#34; title=&#34;Wsc_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wsc_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Round-robin_tournament&#34;&gt;Round-robin tournaments&lt;/a&gt;, such as official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wscgames.com/2005/build/standing/1/topten.html&#34;&gt;Scrabble Tournaments&lt;/a&gt; involve every player playing a set number of games (24 in the 2005 World Scrabble Championship), facing opponents with similar win-lose records. They then ultimately rank players by their win-lose ratios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of these sorts of tournament over an ELO-style ranking is that they&#39;re easily understandable and seem fair. In addition, they measure ranking in a much more topical manner: how well someone is playing during a singular instant, rather than over a longer career. As a result they work much better for a live tournament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;thresholds&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Different Themes: Thresholds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we discussed in our original article on Collective Choice, thresholds are ranking barriers above which members get a special ability--or alternatively levels below which members lose a special ability. They can also act as another goal for a ranking system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usgo.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/gosmall.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Gosmall&#34; alt=&#34;Gosmall&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In the game of Go there are both &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_ranks_and_ratings#Pro_and_amateur_ranks&#34;&gt;amateur&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_ranks_and_ratings#Professional_strength&#34;&gt;professional&lt;/a&gt; players. Although they aren&#39;t technically in the same &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cns.nyu.edu/~mechner/go/kyu.html&#34;&gt;hierarchy of rankings&lt;/a&gt;, the highest Go amateur ranking&amp;nbsp; (7 dan) is approximately equal to the lowest Go professional ranking (1 dan), forming a de facto threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/uscf_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Uscf_1&#34; alt=&#34;Uscf_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Likewise the United States Chess Federation uses their ELO rankings to denote &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Chess Masters&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone who achieves 2200 UCSF is given a National Master threshold ranking and anyone who maintains it for 300 games is given a Life Master threshold ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/acblopt2_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Acblopt2_1&#34; alt=&#34;Acblopt2_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/&#34;&gt;American Contract Bridge Association&lt;/a&gt; uses a threshold system where you have to win a certain number of tournaments and thus earn &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/about/honorTitles.html&#34;&gt;masterpoints&lt;/a&gt; in order achieve official rankings such as &amp;quot;section master&amp;quot;. Furthermore, players may earn different &amp;quot;colors&amp;quot; of masterpoints depending the difficulty of the tournament, and some ranks require that you earn at least some specific colored masterpoints in order to meet the requirements for the next threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These thresholds are fairly explicitly based on other hierarchical ranking systems, but this doesn&#39;t need to be the case. Since determining the purpose of a ranking system is often the first step in designing it, as we delve further into the area of thresholds we may well find that systems specifically dedicated toward measuring thresholds are more likely to do so well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our next article we&#39;ll consider among other things the Avogadro reputation system, which manages thresholds in such a way as to prevent cheating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s actually a lot of variety in ranking systems, and even though we&#39;d like them to be totally objective, various subjective elements often creep into these systems. In addition, there&#39;s a lot of variety in what ranking systems can do. For competitive systems, hierarchy, privilege, matching, and handicapping are some of the top purposes of ranking. Determining what a ranking system is going to do is a necessary first step in designing the system, as different systems will accomplish various goals to a better or worse degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELO, in several variants, is the best studied and most used competitive ranking system. It works particularly well as a matching system. However, even ELO has flaws in it, among them: issues with new player rankings; its core two-player basis; its lack of provisions for teams; a few minor subjective elements; and problems with cheaters. New systems continue to be rolled out on the Internet to resolve these issues, and overall, it&#39;s an area of interesting new study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tournament systems and threshold systems offer a few good examples of competitive ranking systems with very different purposes, underlying the need to understand what you&#39;re doing before you do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking systems also lay very near yet another type of Collective Choice: reputation systems. We briefly addressed reputation systems when talking about threshold systems and will return to this in our next article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;A data point on ELO cheating for you: Yahoo! Games uses ELO rankings for several their two-player games. Before recent abuse mitigation changes, some people used robot to accumulate scores in excess of 6,000,000 points. The abuse-the-ranking game had become a totally seperate competition.
For now, Yahoo! has capped the ELO scores at 3,000 (I think.) This removed most of the cheating incentive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fudco.com/habitat&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-05T13:46:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-05T13:46:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;In the slashdot discussion of this blog entry http://games.slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=173988&amp;threshold=0&amp;mode=flat   there was an interesting link to beatpaths.com, which is sort of a tourney system for when you can&#39;t complete a full set of round-robin or double-elimination competitions, as what happens in NFL during the fall season.
What is also interesting to me is that it introduces a goal for ranking systems that I&#39;d not thought of before -- prediction. The purpose of the beatpath systems is actually focused on predicting the outcome the next set of the weekend games.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-14T14:31:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-14T14:31:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;No mention of Glicko and Glicko2?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://swaits.com/&#34;&gt;Stephen Waits&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-15T08:57:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-15T08:57:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;There&#39;s a ranking scheme that Mark Newman from the U of Michigan did for college football, which Yahoo Search turned up a pointer to here:
http://www.sciencenews.org/articles/20051112/mathtrek.asp
quoting:
Physicists Juyong Park and M.E.J. Newman aimed for a ranking system that&#39;s fast and easily understood by fans (in contrast to the cumbersome, opaque BCS formula). They based their ranking method on the notion that, if A beats B, and B beats C, then A also beats C, even if it may not actually play C. Hence, the method counts both direct wins by beating a team and indirect wins by beating a team that beat another team.
(end quote)
You end up with a directed graph of teams as nodes and games as edges, and compute a function of that graph that is related to a centrality metric.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://vielmetti.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Edward Vielmetti&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-02T22:18:39-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-02T22:18:39-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This article is a great survey of the subject!  I&#39;m working on the PvP ranking system for another game with some unique problems, because the teams in a PvP match can be of disparate size and widely differing power levels, which are then balanced so that wildly mismatched teams (ignoring relative rank at PvP for the moment) are actually reasonably matched.
It starts here: http://ncanson.livejournal.com/3938.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ncanson.livejournal.com/&#34;&gt;Matthew Weigel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-01-31T09:55:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-01-31T09:55:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Rating Systems</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2005 17:58:34 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.7em;&#34;&gt;by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This is the second of a series of articles on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt;, co-written by my collegue &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline&#34;&gt;Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt;. It will be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_179.phtml&#34;&gt;jointly posted&lt;/a&gt; in Shannon&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT.shtml&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities&lt;/a&gt; online games column at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our previous article we talked about the many systems available for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt;. There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html#selection_systems&#34;&gt;selection systems&lt;/a&gt;, which are primarily centered on voting and deliberation, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html#opinion_systems&#34;&gt;opinion systems&lt;/a&gt;, which represent how voting could occur, and finally &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html#comparison_systems&#34;&gt;comparison systems&lt;/a&gt;, which rank or rate different people or things in a simple, comparative manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/stars_1.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=373,height=239,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Stars_1&#34; title=&#34;Stars_1&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/stars_1.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;One purpose of our previous article was to create a dictionary of terms for talking about these related, but clearly different, systems. Another was to start offering analyses of these systems, many of which had not been well studied before their introduction onto the Internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However at best our previous article provided an overview of what should be further investigated in each system. This article provides more in-depth coverage of one of the systems we previously outlined: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html#rating_systems&#34;&gt;rating systems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we wrote in our previous article, in comparison rating systems &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;the value of individual items (most frequently goods) rise or fall based upon the largely subjective judgment of individual users.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; Ratings systems should be clearly differentiated from the closely related &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html#ranking_systems&#34;&gt;ranking systems&lt;/a&gt;. Ratings systems have a more subjective component, while ranking systems are largely objective. Amazon, Netflix, BoardGameGeek, and even the Stock Market were offered up as examples of ratings systems. Another example of a comparison rating system, and one of the earliest that appeared on the modern Internet, is eBay. The techniques they use are now beginning to show their age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;eBay: A Failed Rating Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Ebaysales&#34; title=&#34;Ebaysales&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ebaysales.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;Most rating systems center around rating content, often user-contributed content, and they frequently help apply community values and acclaim to that content. However, the idea of ratings can go far beyond that narrow niche (though that will doubtless be its greatest use as the Internet continues to expand). Early Internet site, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebay.com&#34;&gt;eBay&lt;/a&gt;, was one of the first to widely use user-submitted ratings, and it used them for a different manner: to determine the good traders on their auction site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as one of the first in this field, eBay made many mistakes which now leave their ratings system only slightly helpful. However, its failures can also provide us with insights in creating new rating systems on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eBay allows you to leave positive, negative, or (more recently) neutral feedback for each transaction you conduct in their society. These are aggregated into two numbers. &amp;quot;Feedback Score&amp;quot; is calculated as unique positive feedback received minus unique negative feedback received, and results in a whole number like &amp;quot;32&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;10,302&amp;quot;. &amp;quot;Positive Feedback&amp;quot; is calculated as positive feedback received divided by all feedback received, and results in a percentage like &amp;quot;100%&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;99.8%&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, for reasons discussed below, almost all feedback is positive, and thus the Feedback Score acts almost entirely as a track record of how many trades someone has made. The Feedback Score could be largely replaced by that single number. You can look at a score of &amp;quot;27&amp;quot;, and say, &amp;quot;That&#39;s an amateur trader, or someone just getting started&amp;quot;, at a score of &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;, and say, &amp;quot;That person may or may not know what they&#39;re doing&amp;quot;, at a score of &amp;quot;10,302&amp;quot;, and say, &amp;quot;That person has done a lot of trades.&amp;quot; But you still don&#39;t know how good the trader is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ebayprofile.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ebayprofile.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Ebayprofile&#34; alt=&#34;Ebayprofile&#34; class=&#34;image-full&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Theoretically, the Positive Feedback percentage should give a more meaningful number, but people so infrequently give bad ratings that, even when they do appear, they look like noise. Does a percentage of &amp;quot;99.8%&amp;quot; on a user with a score of &amp;quot;1,762&amp;quot; mean that the seller has a genuine problem or not? Do those 3 unhappy customers really represent another 30 who were unwilling to actually click the negative feedback? And, did those people have slightly bad experience or really bad experiences? It&#39;s pretty hard to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, eBay has a few major problems with their rating system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s &lt;strong&gt;non-granular&lt;/strong&gt;, with only two options (positive/negative), or more recently three (positive/negative/neutral).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s &lt;strong&gt;non-distinct&lt;/strong&gt;, with no useful guidelines on what behaviors should result in each rating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s &lt;strong&gt;non-statistical&lt;/strong&gt;, and thus ends up showing only a gross number of sales, not a real subjective measure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s &lt;strong&gt;bilateral&lt;/strong&gt;, with buyers and sellers rating each other simultaneously, and thus people are afraid to give bad ratings lest they get them in return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s &lt;strong&gt;meaningless&lt;/strong&gt;, because there are no good tools to control who bids on an auction based on Feedback numbers. (Technically it may be legitimate to ban low feedback bidders from an auction, then cancel their bids if they enter the auction, but this is neither obvious, automatic, nor simple.)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re going to address each of these issues in turn, to offer insight into creating new comparison rating systems. The first three topics--granularity, distinction, and a statistical basis--are the most important elements of a good comparison rating system. Bilateral &amp;amp; meaningfulness issues will only be relevant on certain sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(As a final caveat: in some ways eBay falls closer in ultimate result to a &lt;em&gt;reputation system&lt;/em&gt;, a topic which we&#39;ll be covering more in a few articles down the road, but its lessons learned are still entirely accurate for rating systems of all sorts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Granular Ratings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Smiley&#34; title=&#34;Smiley&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/smiley.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;
In general, &lt;em&gt;people want to be nice&lt;/em&gt;. There are exceptions to that rule, perhaps even great numbers of them, but the average, well-adjusted person would prefer to make other people happy, not sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a notable effect on any comparison rating system, because it means that people are less likely to use the bottom half of any rating scale. If you did a statistical run on eBay, you&#39;d certainly find that more than 99 out of every 100 ratings are positive. This is largely influenced by concerns of bilateral revenge, as discussed below, and the fact that eBay suggests other means of dispute resolution when you try and leave negative feedback. However, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpg.net&#34;&gt;RPGnet&lt;/a&gt;, a roleplaying site which reviews games, comics, books, movies, and more shows a similar trend despite the lack of bilaterality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPGnet uses two 5-points scales for reviews, resulting in a total rating of 2-10. Of all the ratings at RPGnet, 6,983 reviews have a total that&#39;s above average, a total rating of 6 or more, and 795 have a total that&#39;s below average, a total rating of 5 or less. Perhaps there are more people who sit down to write a review because they really like a game than those who do so because they really hated it, but the result of ~90% of reviews being above average is still stunning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following table shows all the ratings for each of the two categories that RPGnet uses, &amp;quot;Style&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Substance&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpg.net/reviews/archive/9/9971.phtml&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Rpgnetsettlersreview&#34; title=&#34;Rpgnetsettlersreview&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/rpgnetsettlersreview.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 15px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table cellpadding=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Substance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;210&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;687&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;590&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2127&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1583&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3337&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3242&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;42.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1554&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2153&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This evidence confirms what we&#39;d already suspected. Only 10% of raters use the bottom two ratings in a 5-point scale, and only 2% use the bottom rating. The median of the 5-point scale is actually the fourth point, with a neat bell curve arranged around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because users are innately unwilling to give bad ratings, as evidenced here, useful comparison ratings truly come about only through fractional differences between good ratings. In this case, the difference between &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;4&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;5&amp;quot; is meaningful, and becomes more meaningful as more ratings are entered. Eventually you can look at a ranked list of ratings and see that &amp;quot;4.2&amp;quot; is a good rating while &amp;quot;3.5&amp;quot; is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to do this, however, you need enough levels of good ratings to be able to distinguish between them. eBay, only offering one positive rating, does not provide enough differentiation. RPGnet, with its three positive ratings, might. However, sites that offer a 10-point scale are the ones that really seem to be able to produce meaningful statistics. On those sites we can expect that 90% of users will choose between six different numbers, from &amp;quot;5&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;10&amp;quot;, and as the number of ratings builds up, this will produce enough differentiation to be meaningful. If you have already adopted a 5-point scale, consider allowing users to select the half-points, giving users a greater ability to differentiate their ratings.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Distinct Ratings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No two users are ever going to rate the same; different rating numbers will mean different things to each person. This can introduce minor discrepencies into ratings, if a single individual rates particularly low or high. However, because most ratings are eventually used for comparisons, if that low- or high-rater rates many different things, the ratings equalize. &amp;quot;Item A&amp;quot; is rated low by this person, but so is &amp;quot;Item B&amp;quot;, and so they end up in the correct positions &lt;em&gt;in relation to each other&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bigger problem occurs when an individual is inconsistent in his ratings over time. If an individual rates everything low for a while, then rates everything high, then he has a greater chance of biasing the overall rating pool. Worse, his individual ratings aren&#39;t meaningful, because you can&#39;t look at two items, see that one is a &amp;quot;6&amp;quot; and another is an &amp;quot;8&amp;quot;, and truly believe that he likes the &amp;quot;8&amp;quot; a fair amount more than the &amp;quot;6&amp;quot;. This reduces the usability of an individual recommendation system or a friends system where one user might look at what other users thought about products, because their unaggregated numbers are not accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You thus want to help individuals to stay consistent, and the best way to do that is to make the criteria for your ratings distinct. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boardgamegeek.com&#34;&gt;BoardGameGeek&lt;/a&gt;, a board game web site that supports a 10-point rating system for games, does a good job of offering distinction in its ratings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boardgamegeek.com/game/13&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Settlers_rating_1&#34; title=&#34;Settlers_rating_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/settlers_rating_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; - Outstanding. Always want to play and expect this will never change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9 &lt;/strong&gt;- Excellent game. Always want to play it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8 &lt;/strong&gt;- Very good game. I like to play. Probably I&#39;ll suggest it and will never turn down a game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7 &lt;/strong&gt;- Good game, usually willing to play.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6 &lt;/strong&gt;- Ok game, some fun or challenge at least, will play sporadically if in the right mood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5 &lt;/strong&gt;- Average game, slightly boring, take it or leave it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4 &lt;/strong&gt;- Not so good, it doesn&#39;t get me but could be talked into it on occasion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 &lt;/strong&gt;- Likely won&#39;t play this again although could be convinced. Bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 &lt;/strong&gt;- Extremely annoying game, won&#39;t play this ever again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 -&lt;/strong&gt; Defies description of a game. You won&#39;t catch me dead playing this. Clearly broken.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you offer a distinct rating listing like this, some users will still come up with their own rating ideas, but if they do, they&#39;re more likely to remember what each number means to them. For everyone else, a very clear, s rating system is the most likely to produce meaningful and consistent results. As long as users aren&#39;t puzzled by the distinction, they&#39;ll be consistent in picking the same numbers for the same rating every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Statistical Ratings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last big topic that you have to think about in creating most comparison rating systems is whether they&#39;re statistically sound. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to make your ratings statistically sound is with volume. If you can manage thousands or tens of thousands of ratings for each item, any anomolies are going to become noise. However, the fewer ratings you have, the more likely it is that your ratings are inaccurate in relationship to your database of ratings as a whole. (And thus one of the failures for eBay is that it tries to claim meaningfulness for users with very few ratings, where there&#39;s clearly no statistical basis.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Bayes&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Bayes&#34; title=&#34;Bayes&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/bayes.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Ideally what you want to do is give items with fewer ratings among your collection less weight, and those with more ratings higher weight. One simple way to do this is to apply a &lt;em&gt;bayesian average&lt;/em&gt;. Variants of this are used by the aforementioned BoardGameGeek and by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com&#34;&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;. RPGnet is using it for some unreleased software as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind a bayesian average is that you normalize ratings by pushing them toward the average rating for your site, and you do that more for items with fewer ratings than those with more ratings. The basic formula looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt; b(r) = [ W(a) * a + W(r) * r ] / (W(a) + W(r)]&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;r&lt;/code&gt; = average rating for an item&lt;br /&gt;&lt;code&gt;W(r)&lt;/code&gt; = weight of that rating, which is the number of ratings&lt;br /&gt;&lt;code&gt; a&lt;/code&gt; = average rating for your collection&lt;br /&gt; &lt;code&gt;W(a)&lt;/code&gt; = weight of that average, which is an arbitrary number, but should be higher if you generally expect to have more ratings for your items; 100 is used here, for a database which expects many ratings per item&lt;br /&gt;&lt;code&gt;b(r)&lt;/code&gt; = new bayesian rating &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say three &amp;quot;shill&amp;quot; users had come onto your site and rated a brand new indie film a &amp;quot;10&amp;quot; because the producer asked them to. However, you use a bayesian average with a weight of 100, and thus 3 ratings won&#39;t move the movie very far from the average site rating of 6.50:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;b(r) = [100 * 6.50 + 3 * 10] / (100 + 3)&lt;br /&gt; b(r) = 680 / 103&lt;br /&gt; b(r) = 6.60&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WowWebDesigns uses a similar model and even offers a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wowwebdesigns.com/formula.php&#34;&gt;good explanation of their methods&lt;/a&gt; on their web site.&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wowwebdesigns.com/designs/id_242/ratings/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wowwebdesignsrating.png&#34; title=&#34;Wowwebdesignsrating&#34; alt=&#34;Wowwebdesignsrating&#34; class=&#34;image-full&#34; halign=&#34;middle&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With everything that&#39;s been described thus far, including granularity and distinction, a bayesian average (or some other similiar method) will probably be enough to give your ratings a good, sound statistical basis. However, sites with low volume of ratings may still be concerned with &amp;quot;shills&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;crappers&amp;quot; who come in to your site just to put &amp;quot;10&amp;quot;s on their favorite items on &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s on their least favorite. RPGnet&#39;s reviews are an example of a site that could experience this issue, because only a few people are going to ever write reviews for an individual item, and this small number of reviews could compromise the nature of any comparisons generated by the ratings sytems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short summary the following additional methods may help with this issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rate the Raters:&lt;/strong&gt; Reviews are low volume, but presumably readers of those reviews are high volume, and you can take advantage of that to then have your readers rate the reviews. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.netflix.com&#34;&gt;Netflix&lt;/a&gt; are two examples of sites which use this method by asking &amp;quot;how many readers found this helpful&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altruistic Punishment:&lt;/strong&gt; An alternative method for rating raters is to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html#altruistic_punishment&#34;&gt;altruistic punishment&lt;/a&gt;. Herein users can punish someone who does contribute to the community, but at a cost to themselves. So, a reader could flag a poor rating or a poor review at some minor cost to their own rating. Though this method may seems somewhat paradoxical, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_theory&#34;&gt;game theory&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp; suggests that it is a generally effective technique for improving the commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust Ratings Based on Ratings:&lt;/strong&gt; Ratings can be self-adjusted based upon the rater&#39;s own behavior. The simplest method here is to map a rater&#39;s average rating to the average rating for a site. For example, if the average rating of a site is 6.50 and a shill&#39;s average rating is 10.0, then those 10s should be treated as 6.50s. This has the possibility for some intensive calculations, however, and may lead to additional bias in your rating pool if shills figure out the methods you use to adjust ratings.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow Editorial Fiat:&lt;/strong&gt; Another method is to allow editorial fiat, where editors are expected to come in and remove bad ratings (or proactively not release them). This clearly results in time issues, but they may not be major since only sites with small numbers of ratings/item will have to do this type of adjusting. Further, automated systems could flag &amp;quot;suspicious&amp;quot; rating patterns which are outside the norms for average, speed of rating, etc. (RPGnet supports editorial fiat by requiring editorial release of all reviews.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of adjusting ratings based on ratings bears a bit of additional discussion because it&#39;s somewhat similar to another well-knowing rating system: slashdot. Herein you have both ratings and meta-ratings. People can rate threads and articles, then other people can agree or disagree with those ratings, which in turn makes it more or less likely that the original rater will be allowed to rate in the future (depending on if people agree or disagree with his ratings). Under a more general classification, this is probably a &lt;em&gt;meta-rating system based on a reputation system&lt;/em&gt;, so it&#39;s something we&#39;ll look at further a couple of articles down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other Issues: Bilateralism &amp;amp; Usefulness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;90% of the rating issues that sites will face are covered by the above. However eBay in particular raised two other issues -- bilateralism and usefulness -- that aren&#39;t as generally relevant but do deserve some consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ebayfeedback.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ebayfeedback.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Ebayfeedback&#34; alt=&#34;Ebayfeedback&#34; class=&#34;image-full&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Bilateralism:&lt;/strong&gt; One of the reasons that eBay&#39;s ratings fall apart is that they&#39;re bilateral. Buyers and sellers rate each other simultaneously and thus there&#39;s the fear of revenge if you rate someone badly. It&#39;s a sufficient issue that eBay has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.ebay.com/help/feedback/questions/retaliatory-feedback.html&#34;&gt;FAQ on the topic&lt;/a&gt;, though they don&#39;t offer any good answers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following solution would address some issues of bilateral revenge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Put a time limit on bilateral ratings&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release bilateral ratings simultaneously at the end of the time limit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t allow additional ratings after the time period&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would work well on an eBay, where you&#39;re unlikely to conclude an additional deal with someone you rated badly, and thus there&#39;s no possibility ever for rating revenge. On a game site, however, where people are arbitrarily put into games with each other, and thus you could end up in a game with someone you rated poorly, there might be room for later revenge, down the road. This would have to be addressed to truly feel comfortable with bilateral ratings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional investigation might reveal more variations of this method, or offer good answers for alternatives, like &lt;em&gt;anonymous ratings&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, good privacy restrictions are really needed to make bilateral ratings work, as well as Terms of Service that protect users from lawsuits for ratings. There have already been cases of physical threats based upon eBay ratings. eBay has also produced cases where people threatened slander or libel lawsuits for bad ratings, and this even further chills the possibility of true ratings appearing on the eBay server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usefulness:&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, you want to make sure your ratings are useful at your sites. Rankings are a good way to achieve this. You can see the &amp;quot;best games ever&amp;quot; ranked, or you can see the most interesting user content rise to the top of a long listing, and the least interesting sink to the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eBay offers a counter example of frustration with the usefulness of ratings. As already mentioned, you can theoretically ban &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; users from bidding on your items, and then cancel bids from these users if they appear. However, there are multiple issues with this approach. First, how do you define &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; users on eBay? Insufficient feedback? Too much negative feedback? Too high a percentage of negative feedback? Second, there is no automated method for doing this, so you must remain ever vigilant on your auctions to make sure that &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; users aren&#39;t involved. Third, there&#39;s no way to keep a bad bidder from returning after you&#39;ve cancelled his bid. Fourth, these bad bids and cancellations have the possibility of corrupting your auction, as you could lose other bidders who came in, saw the higher bid when the bad bidder was involved, then left before the bid was reduced by his removal. Finally, greed is a powerful motivator on eBay, which might lead to the retention of bad users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also need to be careful with your user interface for ratings. Here is an example of a poor UI:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/uselessratingui.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Uselessratingui&#34; alt=&#34;Uselessratingui&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparison ratings are going to be an increasingly important force as the Internet continues to mature. To produce meaningful comparison ratings for your site, you need to concentrate on four important factors: granularity, specifity, sound statistics, and usefulness. And, if you offer bilateral ratings, make sure you understand the subtleties of that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34;&gt;2006-01: Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve ran into my fair share of voting systems, but by far the worst I&#39;ve ever seen is the one used at www.animenfo.com, a database of anime products with user ratings. When giving a product a rating, a user is required to also write a constructive review on the product. However, the reviews are moderated and, often, removed from the database as &#34;unconstructive&#34; by the limited number of moderators. The problem with this approach is that the moderators are inevitably biased. A submitted, bad rating on a product, if reviewed by a moderator who personally likes the show being rated, is often removed from the database with the claim that the review was not constructive. Perhaps not entirely related, but an example of ratings-gone-awry, all the same.
-Kalle.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/userinfo.bml?user=kallewooof&#34;&gt;Kalle&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-13T10:42:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-13T10:42:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It&#39;s rarely used, but asking people to rank from -5 to +5 can be better than ranking from 0 to 10.   You make it very clear that &#34;0&#34; means average/neutral.   You won&#39;t entirely eliminate the positive bias in ratings but you can reduce it.  And you bring everybody closer to the same mean.
I&#39;ve concluded over time that in fact the response to a negative feedback on eBay should be disabled, as it contains no information.   Who, after all, is going to give a positive feedback to somebody after they have slapped a negative on you?  The likely choices there are no-feedback or neutral from a charitable person and of course a revenge negative.
So they could make it simpler.  If the first person gives a negative, the transaction is considered sour.  In your stats it would list the number of first-negatives you left for others.  (The number of negs you leave for others is already visible but harder to find.)  Ideally split buyer/seller.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ideas.4brad.com&#34;&gt;Brad Templeton&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-13T13:11:31-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-13T13:11:31-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;An interesting point missing from this good summary:
Many huge ratings sites see a clear bimodal distribution of scores when rating products(movies, cds, books, etc.)  with a simple scoring scheme, such as a single 5-star scale: The nodes are at 1 and 5 stars, with the love-or-hate scores making up more than 80% of all scores.
Clearly, some of that is a function of the intrinsic cost vs. incentive structures of completing ratings and reviews. When there is a clear direct benifit to the user (such as Netflix, Slashdot, or Yahoo! Music&#39;s Launchcast) ratings tend to distribute a bit more evenly (but just a bit.)
My point is that the actual end-user application of the rating has a large effect on the nature of the scores that will be created.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fudco.com/habitat&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-14T16:13:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-14T16:13:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I find when people give a bad rating on anything from eBay to those hotel and restaurant review sites its usually as a result of an extremely negative personal experience therefore the rating tends to be exagerated and totally not objective.
A blind system like the porposed solution to eBay bilateralism issue is probably best.
I&#39;ve been a mystery shopper for a handful of restaurants and the system works quite well. In this system the purpose is to behave exactly like a regular consumer. You sit down, ask about the specials, take mental note of everything from the bathroom sink to the temperature of the food (and a hundred other details), but you don&#39;t behave in any way that would alter the staff you are a mystery shopper (for example writing things down is strickly prohibited).
Upon returning home you complete a lengthy questionnare about all the details you were supposed to notice. In this system the rewards is for a thorough assesment, regardless of its positive or negative slant. The more detail you provide the better assignments you get next time around. Even if you totally slam a place, but you provide substantial detail, you will be &#34;promoted&#34; to a &#34;bar visit&#34; or something much more rewarding than the typical lunch visit. So, I also agree with this articles suggestion to rate the raters, akin to what Amazon does but without the bias towards volume.
I would also addd that there is no middle ground on such ratings. Whether the choices range from Strongly Agree to Strongly Dissagree, or from &#34;shortest wait&#34; to &#34;longest wait&#34; there is no &#39;neutral&#39; choice, nothing is &#34;just right&#34; as in the story about the three bears and the porridge. Even with numerical choices they are always even, not odd, so there is not chance of ranking in the middle. I like that. I think it pushes you to be more realistic. Having a middle ground leaves the undecided the opportunity to not make a decision. A &#34;middle&#34; rating is of no use to anyone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.jobmachine.net/shally/&#34;&gt;Shally&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-21T16:23:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-21T16:23:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Researcher Paul Resnick has been looking at eBay, too. His blog is at http://www.livejournal.com/users/presnick/ and has posts like eBay Live Trip Report:
http://www.livejournal.com/users/presnick/8121.html
There are a few relevant articles as well, at http://www.si.umich.edu/~presnick/#publications
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://seb.notlong.com&#34;&gt;Seb&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-29T05:53:29-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-29T05:53:29-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Good work there, and very thorough. Can we distinguish the social/transactional from the object/informational aspects of a rating situation? I&#39;m just wondering aloud. On the one hand is the fact that publishing one&#39;s rating of a transaction will reflect on the transaction partner, on oneself, and so is social. On the other hand is the fact one can indeed rate an experience with some objectivity, assuming that the soft stuff has been bracketed out. I dont see how we can bracket out the social though, at least in a way that users will be able to participate in.
There&#39;s a thing about sincerity as a type of interaction: it&#39;s an attribute of expression that cannot be stated explicitly (say that you&#39;re being sincere and you throw your sincerity into quesion immediately). Ratings may fall into that kind of category of linguistic and metalinguistic acts..
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.gravity7.com/blog/media/&#34;&gt;adrian Chan&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-04T09:47:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-04T09:47:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Wow, thorough and cogent.
Of all of the points, one missed opportunity occured to me while reading, and that is on the EBay statistical validity criticism. The phrase &#39;thus one of the failures for eBay is that it tries to claim meaningfulness for users with very few ratings, where there&#39;s clearly no statistical basis&#39; struck me as off.
Human transactions are not mechanical actions - they involve situations that often matter. Hence a particular negative may really be cause for serious concern, even if there are not yet many ratings. Also, beginners are not inherantly less important than experienced traders. So though difficult, credit, or blame, is rightly awarded even on the basis of just a few transactions. Exactly how is a subject of further refinement.
I have read some of the EBay dissection papers a while back. This post is far more comprehensive, that is wide ranging, and yet not missing clarity, accuracy or nuance. Master work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Brian Hamlin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-05-30T00:43:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-05-30T00:43:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I have an interesting brainstorm for you about the netflix challenge:
http://www.thinksketchdesign.com/2008/05/03/design/coding/does-the-netflix-challenge-have-it-backwards
cheers -
thinksketch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://thinksketchdesign.com&#34;&gt;thinksketch&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-03-03T18:56:13-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-03-03T18:56:13-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SynchroEdit: Simultaneous Editing for the Web</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2005 16:04:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the last several months I&#39;ve been working on a new open source project that I&#39;ve been calling &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit&lt;/a&gt;. SynchroEdit is a browser-based simultaneous multiuser editor, useful for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.it.bton.ac.uk/staff/rng/teaching/notes/CSCWgroupware.html&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/synchroeditmac.png&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=493,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;262&#34; height=&#34;202&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Synchroeditmac&#34; title=&#34;Synchroeditmac&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/synchroeditmac.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The basic concept is that it allows multiple users to WYSIWYG edit a single web-based document, all at exactly the same time. SynchroEdit continuously synchronizes all changes so that users always see the same version. They can also see each others&#39; changes as they type, see where each user is currently editing, and see each others&#39; changes by color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SynchroEdit is a tool for &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration, either &amp;quot;same-time, different-place&amp;quot;, as in teleconference calls, or &amp;quot;same-time, same-place&amp;quot;, during a meeting or a conference. If you&#39;ve ever used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/&#34;&gt;SubEthaEdit&lt;/a&gt; on Mac OS X, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moonedit.com&#34;&gt;MoonEdit&lt;/a&gt; for Windows or Linux, or the cross-platform &lt;a href=&#34;http://gobby.0x539.de/&#34;&gt;Gobby&lt;/a&gt;, this is a similar experience. The difference is that unlike those tools you are not limited to just plain text -- character styles (bold, italic, etc.) and paragraph styles (rulers, headers, blockquotes, etc) are synchronized as well. And of course, it all works inside your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SynchroEdit is inspired by my frustration with the lack of an easily accessible cross-platform simultaneous editor. Many times when I&#39;ve been on the phone with a colleague discussing a draft blog entry, or demonstrating some code, or on a teleconference call with others to discuss a proposal or a standard, or at a conference taking notes with others, I&#39;ve wanted to have this tool. The rare occasions that we all have been on the same platform and have been able to use an existing tool have demonstrated to me the value of having a good simultaneous editor. Having SynchroEdit available will make it easier for people to have these positive collaborative experiences.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a long history with &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration tools -- back in 1988 I was briefly executive producer at Broderbund for a same-time groupware product called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/search?q=cache:1cDDTqwlqGoJ:www.the-scientist.com/yr1988/jul/software_p22_880725.html+%2Bbroderbund+%2B%22for+comment%22+groupware&#34;&gt;For Comment&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, the success of the Nintendo game console forced Broderbund to drop all of their non-consumer product efforts. In the early 90&#39;s I worked on several different &amp;quot;same-time same-place&amp;quot; groupware tools for live meetings. Most recently, my game company &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net&#34;&gt;Skotos Tech&lt;/a&gt;, created several browser-based &amp;quot;enhanced chat&amp;quot; clients for playing in MUSH-like storytelling games, which are also &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally believe that that this capability should be a fundamental feature of the web, sort of the obvious extension of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee&#34;&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/4132752.stm&#34;&gt;vision&lt;/a&gt; of the editable web. Thus my desire to offer this tool as open source, allowing anyone to add this capability to their own software (unlike proprietary editor services such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotlive.com&#34;&gt;JotLive&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.writely.com/&#34;&gt;Writely&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge with offering SynchroEdit as open source is finding a business model -- unlike an application like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/&#34;&gt;SubEthaEdit&lt;/a&gt; or a service like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotlive.com&#34;&gt;JotLive&lt;/a&gt;, it is difficult to get revenues from individual users. Instead, we ask for contributions from companies that might find the tool useful, we offer consulting to customize it for specific purposes, and we give these companies public credit for their contributions to the common good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first company to step up to the plate is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.socialtext.com&#34;&gt;SocialText&lt;/a&gt;, an enterprise wiki company. Clearly, being able to offer this capability to their customers will give them added value, and they already have a history of using open source with their support of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kwiki.org/&#34;&gt;Kwiki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wikiwyg.net/&#34;&gt;Wikiwyg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second supporter is venture capitalist and blogger &lt;a href=&#34;http://joi.ito.com/&#34;&gt;Joichi Ito&lt;/a&gt;. He is is particularly well known for his own experiments with &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration. He runs a continuous #joiito IRC chat room, active 24 hours a day with hundreds of his friends. He also has done many live &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; experiments with chat backchannel during his talks at various conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to to financial support of SocialText and Joichi Ito, I have some offers of help from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bgiedu.org&#34;&gt;Bainbridge Graduate Institute&lt;/a&gt;, who plan to use it in its socially responsible and environmentally sustainable MBA program, and we&#39;ve also taken advantage of some code developed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of SynchroEdit is being led by Kalle Alm, a young Swedish coder I met when he was creating an online game at Skotos. Skotos has long had the vision of having games created by its members, and Kalle Alm was the first member to create a game completely from scratch using Skotos&#39; tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking more financial contributions so that we can accelerate development. Currently SynchroEdit only works in Mozilla/Firefox, and I anticipate that making it work with Internet Explorer may be quite difficult, so we&#39;ll need more partners to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/christopher_allen_web2point1_brainjam.png&#34; title=&#34;Christopher_allen_web2point1_brainjam&#34; alt=&#34;Christopher_allen_web2point1_brainjam&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;I did a demo of last year&#39;s open source project, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.EditThisPage.net&#34;&gt;EditThisPage&lt;/a&gt;, and of the SynchroEdit alpha at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.web2point1.org/&#34;&gt;Web 2.1 BrainJam&lt;/a&gt; last week; there are two videos available from Enric Teller&#39;s vBlog: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cirne.com/vlog/2005/10/10/web-21-a-brainjam-christopher-allen-presentation/&#34;&gt;Presentation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cirne.com/vlog/2005/10/10/web-21-a-brainjam-christopher-allen-qa/&#34;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in learning more, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit website&lt;/a&gt;. We have additional information on the program, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;developers wiki&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a sandbox that you can play in to demonstrate SynchroEdit in use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;m curious about what ways you think this could be useful as a teaching aid? Have you looked into particular implementations or studied existing case studies?
(I have studied this a fair amount and I don&#39;t think there are existing case studies, especially in the classroom, which is why I ask.. I&#39;m looking at ways in which chatrooms could be incorporated into classroom environments as a backchannel)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;yardi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-16T11:00:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-16T11:00:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Sidebar: Recent Bookmarks</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/04/if_you_read_my_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2005 11:40:41 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/04/if_you_read_my_.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you read my blog through an aggregator, you may not have noticed my new sidebar &amp;quot;Recent Bookmarks&amp;quot;. It is a list of web pages that I&#39;ve found interesting enough to annotate using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://del.icio.us/&#34;&gt;del.icio.us&lt;/a&gt; service. It is useful if you want to have an insight into what future blog entries I&#39;m working on, as links will often show up there before my actual blog posting is out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You alternatively can &lt;a href=&#34;http://del.icio.us/ChristopherA?setcount=10&#34;&gt;view my last 10 del.icio.us postings&lt;/a&gt;, or subscribe to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://del.icio.us/rss/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;del.icio.us RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in offering this feature in your own blog, I used the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bigbold.com/rssdigest/&#34;&gt;RSS Digest&lt;/a&gt; webservice to create a javascript applet that formats information from my del.icio.us RSS feed into a format suitable for my sidebar. There are a lot of other cool things that are possible with this service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;BTW it is also possible to use feedburner.com, with which you can add to your feed, your delicious posts, flickr posts in addition to the regular blog posts...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://amit.chakradeo.net/&#34;&gt;Amit Chakradeo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-08T17:31:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-08T17:31:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I hadn&#39;t seen that addition to the site!  Thanks for writing about it.  I do the same thing on my blog, only with my Furl.net selections (similar tool, more options I think, more friendly UI).  I do use RSS Digest as well to run the del.icio.us/tag/wiki RSS feed on my blog. (Marshall&#39;s New Web Tool Blog http://marshallk.blogspot.com)
You might enjoy checking out the folks over at http://marketingstudies.net too.  They first alerted me to the possibility of using RSS like this, and though they are all about corporate marketing, they come up with many good ideas.
Thanks for your blog, allways a pleasure to read.
Speaking of wikis (I see you intend to write about the editing dichotomy, great, have you checked out wikalong.org ?  It&#39;s great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://marshallk.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Marshall&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-12T15:49:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-12T15:49:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;As Amit says, it is possible to splice your links and your pictures through a FeedBurner feed. Now that Buzznet is supported like Flickr, I have create an Extended feed for people for people to subscribe to in addition to my main feed. You might want to consider doing the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://softtechvc.blogs.com/&#34;&gt;Jeff Clavier&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-14T01:02:33-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-14T01:02:33-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I was delighted to see that your first del.icio.us posting linked to W. Ross Ashby&#39;s An Introduction to Cybernetics. I devoured that book when it was first published in 1956, and I was a 28 year old ad copywriter. I worked through all the examples and laughed like mad over ex. 4/15, the letter which begins, &#34;Dear Friend, some years ago I bought this old house, but found it to be haunted by two ghostly noises -- a ribald Singing and a sardonic Laughter ... &#34;. I copied it out by hand and sent copies round my friends as an Xmas card that year. I don&#39;t think any of them had the faintest idea what I was on about. I still have the sixth impression of that book beside me now.
My first acquaintance with the subject must have been with Norbert Wiener&#39;s Cybernetics in 1948, while I was still an undergraduate. I understood little of it, but it did introduce me to Russell&#39;s Paradox.
I must add these to my own del.icio.us collection plus a couple of other books on symbolic logic, which deeply impressed me at the time. I&#39;ve only just discovered your blog, through John Robb, and I will add your site to my own blog Junkyard Whirlwind. You have led me to a most interesting cluster of concepts, and must explore further. Many thanks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.woccam.com/&#34;&gt;woccam&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-08-04T16:53:14-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-08-04T16:53:14-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/04/if_you_read_my_.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Topics</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/04/future_topics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2005 01:08:16 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/04/future_topics.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working on an ambitious list of topics that I&#39;d like to cover over the next year. I offer them to you here so you can have some idea the areas that I am thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Office Architecture for Innovation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Over the years I&#39;ve built or converted three offices to my specifications. From this I have learned a number of things about about how to create a productive environment innovation-oriented businesses. These include some of the obvious suggestions such as fresh air and natural light, but also include not so obvious ideas such as using magnetic paint and providing a small washer-dryer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Requisite Variety&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- This concept from cybernetics applies to social systems as well. &amp;quot;The larger the variety of actions available to a control system, the larger the variety of perturbations it is able to compensate.&amp;quot; More people, as well as a diversity of thinking styles and experience, give social software more &amp;quot;variety of actions&amp;quot;, thus this is part of the reason why social software can be so effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Art and Craft of Meme Design&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We are learning more about how to create an effective meme. Creating memes has always been an art performed by publicists, marketers, politicians, the press, and to a lesser extent by scientists and other academics. Have we learned enough to turn this art into an explicit craft?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wiki Editing Dichotomy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- One interesting possible barrier of entry to active participation in a wiki is what I call the &amp;quot;wiki editing dichotomy&amp;quot;. You have to be proud enough to believe what you are contributing is generally worthwhile to others (or at least worth your effort), but you also have to be humble enough to understand that others can improve it. I don&#39;t know of many other collaborative media that requires both pride and humility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Choice &amp;amp; Neuroeconomics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are some that say at the root of every decision is emotion. Even a &#39;rational&#39; decision appeals to a sense of balance or beauty. Recent studies using PET are establishing a neurological basis for emotions, and some reveal interesting facts about how we make choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Risk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are a variety of areas where we as humans have a difficult time being completely rational. One of these is risk assessment. It turns out we may be hard-wired to not be able toeasily understand risk that is greater then one in a hundred or so. Thus a very rare risk, say one in a thousand, will often be emotionally interpreted as having a much higher risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Persuasive Computing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- BJ Fogg&#39;s group at Stanford has done some interesting research on how computers can persuade you to do something. There are a number of useful ideas that come from this research. There are also some ethical considerations that should be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cognitive Dissonance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- This technique is central to many forms of persuasion intended to change beliefs, values, attitudes and behaviors. It is used by facilitators, businesses, military organizations, and even cults. It can be used positively or negatively. How might it be used in social software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dark Side of the Force&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- The same social tools that we use for good, can also be used for harm. How do we ethically use what we are learning about social software? Some say that almost by definition social software attracts spammers, trolls, and innappropriate sexuality. What can we do to prevent these misuses of social software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conversation vs Communication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Update and rewrite of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alacritymanagement.com/GCnC.html&#34;&gt;1990 essay&lt;/a&gt; on how social software design needs to balance conversation vs communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Emotions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We appear to have evolved a number of emotions that appear primarily to exist to support a common good, rather then to ensure our individual success. These include schadenfreude, mirth, naches, revenge, shame, pride, outrage, approbation, admiration, elevation, etc. Studies by Eckman on unconscious facial gestures, studies on the neurological basis for emotions, and studies on emotions in games, are proving that these social emotions exist. A number of them have interesting implications on social software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glances &amp;amp; Strokes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There is some old work on the amount of eye contact we make with others in small groups, as well as some research from transactional analysis on strokes, which are the amount of recognition given to others through words and deeds. Is there a neurological basis for needing a certain number of glances and strokes each day? How does this concept apply to social software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weak Links&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are some interesting social implications behind what we&#39;ve learned about weak links in social networks. How do we identify and encourage weak links in our social software systems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Negativity vs Positivity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- It is far easier for someone to respond negativel than positively. In political systems it is far easier to say no rather then yes. What social software encourages positivity, and is it possible to design social software to do so?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time Economy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Our ultimate most unrenewable resource is time. How time and attention are a basic economic unit that should be considered when looking at social software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group Life Cycle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We often focus on how groups form, emerge, and grow. Yet there are many lessons to be learned from how groups die, including that it isn&#39;t necessarily a bad thing and that keeping a group from death can be dysfunctional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groupthink&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- What causes groupthink? When is it good and when is it bad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two Thresholds in the Value of Knowledge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- In order for knowledge to be valuable, it must at minimum be more valuable then the costs to find and absorb it (costs which include bandwidth and attention). Tools like Google have tremendously increased the amount of knowledge that is worth the time and attention to find it. What types of knowledge fall below this threshold of value? Is there a limit to how much we can lower this line? Furthermore, there is another threshold where the knowledge is significantly more valuable than only bandwidth and attention. How much have internet tools impacted this second threshold? Many internet business models, in particular content models, require some ability to offer value in this upper threshold -- can they survive as this upper threshold changes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intimacy and Social Networks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Social Networks Analysis tends to focus on the connections between people, either explicitly through acknowledgement of connections (LinkedIn, Friendster) or implicitly through analysis of your communication (Spoke). None are able to measure intimacy. Yet our intimate social networks are an important component of our overall happiness and contentment within both our professional and personal lives. How does intimacy work in social networks? Also there are some concepts in psychology known as communal vs exchange relationships by Clark &amp;amp; Mills from late 70&#39;s that may apply here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- A recap of Shannon Appelcline&#39;s and my analysis of the basic forms of social games types. These include relatively well understood ones like majority control, voting, meta-voting (Nomic), auctioning, etc., but also include less well understood games like playing of roles, dominance and submission, etc. There are also links to social emotions, such as mirth and schadenfraude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lessons from Castle Marrach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We released the Castle Marrach online game in September of 2000, and it was designed from the beginning to be a game for the Bartle-type known as &amp;quot;the socializer&amp;quot;. What lessons did we learn in the five years since the release of the game? What tools are in my social software toolbox today that might have helped with the design?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lessons from F2F Facilitation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are many skilled practitioners of face-to-face facilitation, some of which are paid very high fees for their skills. What lessons can we learn from their experience that we can apply to social software? Why have so many of these facilitators failed to have success online?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More Human vs More Than Human&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Many futurists seek to offer us augmentation of our minds and bodies through technology. Many of these ideas may fundamentally change what it is to be human, and may even have unforeseen complications unanticipated by their creators. One interesting approach to looking at these technologies is to examine which make us &amp;quot;more human&amp;quot;, rather then &amp;quot;more than human&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lessons from Mental Disorders&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Most, if not all, mental disorders have their roots in survival strategies; however, they are over-expressed because of genetic or other causes. Examining the healthy behaviors hiding behind depression, autism, mania, schizophrenia, paranoia, etc. offer a number of insights on how we think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joy of being a Primate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- If you scan the surface of my writing, you may observe that I have a strong belief that our animal nature and genetics form an essential and often unconscious part of what it is to be human. You could interpret these &amp;quot;nature&amp;quot; over &amp;quot;nurture&amp;quot; ideas as limiting us to being just animals. Instead, I believe that by becoming aware of our primate nature, and choosing to leverage it or suppress it by conscious choice rather then letting it drive us unaware, is what makes us more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smart Contracts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Nick Szabo popularized the idea of using some of the primitives of cryptography in unique ways to create what he calls &amp;quot;smart contracts&amp;quot;. He hypothesized approaches to cryptographic handling of collateral, bonding, delineation of property, bearer certificates, and much more. Others have proposed various auction protocols using these concepts. One of the fundamental atomic elements of many of these smart contracts is something called a &amp;quot;reusable proof of work&amp;quot;, which Hal Finney recently demoed a version of at CodeCon 2005. What are the possibilities offered by smart contracts? What are the barriers to implementation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Club System&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- In the 80&#39;s, development of Ted Nelson&#39;s Xanadu vision was being financed by Autodesk. Unfortunately, for a variety of reasons Xanadu failed to deliver any technology. However, a couple of their ideas could be valuable today, one of which is the concept of an alternative to the &amp;quot;user and groups&amp;quot; metaphor for computer security. Xanadu turned that idea upside down and called the result the &amp;quot;club system&amp;quot;. The club system approach is particularly suited to the internet based collaboration tools, in particular wikis. I also have some insights to offer a cryptographic approach to the club system, which might allow P2P distribution of collaborative documents, while preserving group privileges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edges of Cryptographic Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- The SSL cryptographic protocol offers a choice of a number of security properties: integrity, confidentiality, encryption, one-party authentication, and two-party authentication. But there are a number of security properties that very few deployed cryptographic protocols offer. These include perfect forward secrecy, undeniability, deniability, authorization, delegation, multi-party authentication, shared secrets, etc. What are these security properties and how are they useful? Why have they not been successfully broadly deployed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SSL Story&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- When SSL was first proposed it was broken within an hour. Even when Netscape fixed those problems, it wasn&#39;t clear that SSL was going to win the battle of security protocols. SSL was competing against SHTTP which had backing of RSA and an industry consortium. The credit card companies merged their standards and were backing SET. The internet community was moving toward SSH. Microsoft was doing its own embrace and extend protocol PCT. So how did SSL win to become the broadest deployed cryptographic security protocol? The answers may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I welcome any comments or suggestions for links on these topics, or any new topics that you feel are closely related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Get to work! Soon!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Phil Mitchell&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-05T12:22:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-05T12:22:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
The SSL story would be interesting..
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;cyberhill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-13T08:10:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-13T08:10:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/04/future_topics.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Suggest Dissected</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/12/google_suggest_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2004 08:44:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/12/google_suggest_.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a former Macintosh developer, I&#39;ve always been disappointed with the user-interface of web pages. The state of the art of UI design moved backwards with the advent of the browser -- we traded connectivity for ease-of-use. With the advent of pages written in Flash, some better user-interfaces were created, but at the important cost of things like being able to copy text, have semantic and meta-data information imbedded in web pages, searchability, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I keep an eye out for innovative ideas that preserve the essence of what is so powerful about web pages, yet also offer a good ideas. My posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/map_mashup.html&#34;&gt;Map Mashup&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/09/tiddlywiki.html&#34;&gt;TiddlyWiki&lt;/a&gt; offer some interesting web UI exemplars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/webhp?hl=en&amp;amp;complete=1&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;79&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Logo_google_suggest&#34; title=&#34;Logo_google_suggest&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/logo_google_suggest.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this list of exemplars I now add &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/webhp?hl=en&amp;amp;complete=1&#34;&gt;Google Suggest&lt;/a&gt; by Google programmer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/googleblog/2004/12/ive-got-suggestion.html&#34;&gt;Kevin Gibbs&lt;/a&gt;, who wrote this as part of Google employee&#39;s ability to work 20% of the time on their own projects.
Google Suggest replaces the browser&#39;s default auto-complete with one specific to Google searching. As you type each letter of your search request, you are shown the most popular requests for that term, and how many search hits are available for that search term. You really have to try out to understand how amazing and intuitive it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogger &lt;a href=&#34;http://serversideguy.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Justus&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&#34;http://serversideguy.blogspot.com/2004/12/google-suggest-dissected.html&#34;&gt;dissected and documented&lt;/a&gt; how Google Suggest works. If you are a web developer, I recommend you read his analysis and I hope it will inspire you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This specific technique is probably not useful for all web sites -- the amount of load that even a small number of users can place on a database using this technique requires a large server infrastructure, as basically every time you type a letter a database is being hit. Google can do this as they understand server farms and how to scale large loads. However, as inspiration for other ideas, I think it is marvelous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, I didn&#39;t know you could take control over your browsers auto-complete functionality by setting autocomplete=&amp;quot;off&amp;quot; in your input field. Given this and the other techniques for display and cursor control, you could create dynamic auto-complete functionality on your own web pages, but skip the bandwidth intensive XMLHttpRequest by either caching the data in your web page, or in a user&#39;s cookie, or both. An example of this is &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bitflux.ch/&#34;&gt;BitFlux&lt;/a&gt; blog&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bitflux.ch/archive/livesearch_roundup.html&#34;&gt;LiveSearch&lt;/a&gt; functionality (which is also documented &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog4.bitflux.ch/wiki/LiveSearch&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technique for retrieving the data using XMLHttpRequest is also marvelous. This functionality has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://developer.apple.com/internet/webcontent/xmlhttpreq.html&#34;&gt;around for a while&lt;/a&gt; but this is one of the cleanest examples of how to do it on the client side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve got some other ideas on how to apply some of these techniques to Wiki pages -- hopefully in the next few months I&#39;ll have some proof-of-concept examples for you to play around with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Google Suggest is now, in a sense, a new web service from google that can be used independently. For instance Adam Stiles has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adamstiles.com/adam/2004/12/hacking_google_.html&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.netcaptor.net/adsense/suggest.php&#34;&gt;hack&lt;/a&gt; to help suggest keywords for AdSense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Google Suggest is definitely interesting, and Kevin Gibbs is to be congratulated for putting it together. It&#39;s an elegant piece of work.
I think the most intersting things, though, aren&#39;t about the ability to use RPC calls from Javascript. This is pretty old stuff. Brent Ashley released the JSRS library (http://www.ashleyit.com/rs/main.htm) some years ago (cf. these two articles at IBM from 2001: http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/library/wa-resc/?dwzone=web, http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/web/library/wa-rich/). The technique is somewhat different, using a hidden Iframe as a buffer, but the effect is the same.
On the technical side, making this workable in real time is impressive. Rather than triggering actions with they onkeypress event, the input field is checked periodically with a timer. This means you don&#39;t have to wait from a response from google when you type something - if you get three letters entered in between checks, it will still appear nearly instant. (The above referenced article by Chris Justus may cover this, I can&#39;t recall at the moment). And the server side stuff required to be able to return search result counts so quickly has to be very well put together.
On the non-developer side, what I find intersting is that something that has been possible for over three years is hitting the mainstream because Google&#39;s done it. There are tremendous boosts in usability possible using RPC calls, but in my somewhere over six years of web consulting, usability has always been the hardest sell. Now that there&#39;s a high profile application of this technique, I expect it will become as popular as CNET&#39;s orange menu bar was. (If only they had put that on the right side...).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://iconys.com&#34;&gt;dwayne&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-12-21T17:56:03-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-12-21T17:56:03-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;dwayne&#39;s exactly right - interest in Javascript RPC has increased exponentially since GMail and now Google Suggest.  I&#39;ve seen hits to my remote scripting pages go crazy, with the side effect that my referrer spam has spiralled as well.
I first started building rich UIs with MS Remote Scripting in 1998, and I haven&#39;t done any development on JSRS for a couple of years now.  If I had the time or inclination to redo it now, I would definitely use XMLHTTP.  I had to use iframe/layer at the time for wide compatibility.
The image/cookie method is a great one for smaller stuff - I use ut to great effect at http://www.blogchat.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ashleyit.com/rs&#34;&gt;Brent Ashley&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-04T11:20:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-04T11:20:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;If you like Google Suggest you will love this french tool called Pertimm. Take a look at this technology. It&#39;s really worth it. in order to access to a demo contact them at :
http://www.pertimm.com/en/contact/index.htm
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://pouncha.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Pierre Vesoul&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-22T07:35:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-22T07:35:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You might appreciate my &#34;Zuggest&#34; tool.
It uses &#34;Ajax&#34; concepts and works similarly to Google Suggest but searches against the Amazon Product database as you&#39;re typing.
Check it out: http://www.FrancisShanahan.com/zuggest.aspx
It&#39;s built with Javascript, Amazon Web Services, SOAP, XMLHttp, XML, C# and ASP.NET and SQL Server.
Would love to get some feedback on it.
-fs
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.FrancisShanahan.com&#34;&gt;Francis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-04T19:21:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-04T19:21:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I noticed that google suggest does not show same number of results as google.com itself:
http://www.nirendra.net/cms/google/suggest
-Nirendra
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.nirendra.net&#34;&gt;Nirendra Awasthi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T13:38:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T13:38:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is another case where people are astonished to learn that there isn&#39;t any black magic going on here and that the functionality is there. it just takes quite a lot of fiddling to get right and in a form that is reusable. This is why I think that there is still a component market for these kinds of things. the google suggest and gmail suggest functionality has been commercialized already here:
http://developer.ebusiness-apps.com/technologies/webdevelopment/codeandcomponents/ebawebcombov3/media/demos.htm
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alexeiwhite.com&#34;&gt;alexei&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-06-12T22:31:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-06-12T22:31:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/12/google_suggest_.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Suggest Dissected</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/12/google_suggest_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2004 08:44:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/12/google_suggest_.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a former Macintosh developer, I&#39;ve always been disappointed with the user-interface of web pages. The state of the art of UI design moved backwards with the advent of the browser -- we traded connectivity for ease-of-use. With the advent of pages written in Flash, some better user-interfaces were created, but at the important cost of things like being able to copy text, have semantic and meta-data information imbedded in web pages, searchability, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I keep an eye out for innovative ideas that preserve the essence of what is so powerful about web pages, yet also offer a good ideas. My posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/map_mashup.html&#34;&gt;Map Mashup&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/09/tiddlywiki.html&#34;&gt;TiddlyWiki&lt;/a&gt; offer some interesting web UI exemplars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/webhp?hl=en&amp;amp;complete=1&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;79&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Logo_google_suggest&#34; title=&#34;Logo_google_suggest&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/logo_google_suggest.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this list of exemplars I now add &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/webhp?hl=en&amp;amp;complete=1&#34;&gt;Google Suggest&lt;/a&gt; by Google programmer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/googleblog/2004/12/ive-got-suggestion.html&#34;&gt;Kevin Gibbs&lt;/a&gt;, who wrote this as part of Google employee&#39;s ability to work 20% of the time on their own projects.
Google Suggest replaces the browser&#39;s default auto-complete with one specific to Google searching. As you type each letter of your search request, you are shown the most popular requests for that term, and how many search hits are available for that search term. You really have to try out to understand how amazing and intuitive it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogger &lt;a href=&#34;http://serversideguy.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Justus&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&#34;http://serversideguy.blogspot.com/2004/12/google-suggest-dissected.html&#34;&gt;dissected and documented&lt;/a&gt; how Google Suggest works. If you are a web developer, I recommend you read his analysis and I hope it will inspire you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This specific technique is probably not useful for all web sites -- the amount of load that even a small number of users can place on a database using this technique requires a large server infrastructure, as basically every time you type a letter a database is being hit. Google can do this as they understand server farms and how to scale large loads. However, as inspiration for other ideas, I think it is marvelous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, I didn&#39;t know you could take control over your browsers auto-complete functionality by setting autocomplete=&amp;quot;off&amp;quot; in your input field. Given this and the other techniques for display and cursor control, you could create dynamic auto-complete functionality on your own web pages, but skip the bandwidth intensive XMLHttpRequest by either caching the data in your web page, or in a user&#39;s cookie, or both. An example of this is &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bitflux.ch/&#34;&gt;BitFlux&lt;/a&gt; blog&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bitflux.ch/archive/livesearch_roundup.html&#34;&gt;LiveSearch&lt;/a&gt; functionality (which is also documented &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog4.bitflux.ch/wiki/LiveSearch&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technique for retrieving the data using XMLHttpRequest is also marvelous. This functionality has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://developer.apple.com/internet/webcontent/xmlhttpreq.html&#34;&gt;around for a while&lt;/a&gt; but this is one of the cleanest examples of how to do it on the client side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve got some other ideas on how to apply some of these techniques to Wiki pages -- hopefully in the next few months I&#39;ll have some proof-of-concept examples for you to play around with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Google Suggest is now, in a sense, a new web service from google that can be used independently. For instance Adam Stiles has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adamstiles.com/adam/2004/12/hacking_google_.html&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.netcaptor.net/adsense/suggest.php&#34;&gt;hack&lt;/a&gt; to help suggest keywords for AdSense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Google Suggest is definitely interesting, and Kevin Gibbs is to be congratulated for putting it together. It&#39;s an elegant piece of work.
I think the most intersting things, though, aren&#39;t about the ability to use RPC calls from Javascript. This is pretty old stuff. Brent Ashley released the JSRS library (http://www.ashleyit.com/rs/main.htm) some years ago (cf. these two articles at IBM from 2001: http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/library/wa-resc/?dwzone=web, http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/web/library/wa-rich/). The technique is somewhat different, using a hidden Iframe as a buffer, but the effect is the same.
On the technical side, making this workable in real time is impressive. Rather than triggering actions with they onkeypress event, the input field is checked periodically with a timer. This means you don&#39;t have to wait from a response from google when you type something - if you get three letters entered in between checks, it will still appear nearly instant. (The above referenced article by Chris Justus may cover this, I can&#39;t recall at the moment). And the server side stuff required to be able to return search result counts so quickly has to be very well put together.
On the non-developer side, what I find intersting is that something that has been possible for over three years is hitting the mainstream because Google&#39;s done it. There are tremendous boosts in usability possible using RPC calls, but in my somewhere over six years of web consulting, usability has always been the hardest sell. Now that there&#39;s a high profile application of this technique, I expect it will become as popular as CNET&#39;s orange menu bar was. (If only they had put that on the right side...).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://iconys.com&#34;&gt;dwayne&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-12-21T17:56:03-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-12-21T17:56:03-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;dwayne&#39;s exactly right - interest in Javascript RPC has increased exponentially since GMail and now Google Suggest.  I&#39;ve seen hits to my remote scripting pages go crazy, with the side effect that my referrer spam has spiralled as well.
I first started building rich UIs with MS Remote Scripting in 1998, and I haven&#39;t done any development on JSRS for a couple of years now.  If I had the time or inclination to redo it now, I would definitely use XMLHTTP.  I had to use iframe/layer at the time for wide compatibility.
The image/cookie method is a great one for smaller stuff - I use ut to great effect at http://www.blogchat.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ashleyit.com/rs&#34;&gt;Brent Ashley&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-04T11:20:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-04T11:20:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;If you like Google Suggest you will love this french tool called Pertimm. Take a look at this technology. It&#39;s really worth it. in order to access to a demo contact them at :
http://www.pertimm.com/en/contact/index.htm
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://pouncha.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Pierre Vesoul&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-22T07:35:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-22T07:35:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You might appreciate my &#34;Zuggest&#34; tool.
It uses &#34;Ajax&#34; concepts and works similarly to Google Suggest but searches against the Amazon Product database as you&#39;re typing.
Check it out: http://www.FrancisShanahan.com/zuggest.aspx
It&#39;s built with Javascript, Amazon Web Services, SOAP, XMLHttp, XML, C# and ASP.NET and SQL Server.
Would love to get some feedback on it.
-fs
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.FrancisShanahan.com&#34;&gt;Francis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-04T19:21:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-04T19:21:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I noticed that google suggest does not show same number of results as google.com itself:
http://www.nirendra.net/cms/google/suggest
-Nirendra
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.nirendra.net&#34;&gt;Nirendra Awasthi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T13:38:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T13:38:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is another case where people are astonished to learn that there isn&#39;t any black magic going on here and that the functionality is there. it just takes quite a lot of fiddling to get right and in a form that is reusable. This is why I think that there is still a component market for these kinds of things. the google suggest and gmail suggest functionality has been commercialized already here:
http://developer.ebusiness-apps.com/technologies/webdevelopment/codeandcomponents/ebawebcombov3/media/demos.htm
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alexeiwhite.com&#34;&gt;alexei&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-06-12T22:31:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-06-12T22:31:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/12/google_suggest_.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JotSpot: Application Wiki</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/10/jotspot_applica.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2004 00:39:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/10/jotspot_applica.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotspot.com/about/index.php&#34;&gt;Joe Kraus&lt;/a&gt;, one of the co-founders of Excite, and new &lt;a href=&#34;http://bnoopy.typepad.com/bnoopy/&#34;&gt;blogger&lt;/a&gt; has long been &lt;a href=&#34;http://owt.typepad.com/blog/2004/09/wiki_and_then_s.html&#34;&gt;rumored&lt;/a&gt; to be working on a new wiki tool. Today at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.web2con.com/pub/w/32/program.html&#34;&gt;Web 2.0&lt;/a&gt; conference Joe finally unveiled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotspot.com&#34;&gt;JotSpot&lt;/a&gt;, a new type of wiki that they have named an &#34;Application Wiki&#34;. JotSpot appears to be not only an advanced wiki, but it also moves the predominantly text-based wiki toward being able to handle structured data and web application development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.jotspot.com/tours/advanced/img/slide09.jpg&#34;border=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;float: right; margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; &gt;At the JotSpot website there is an page on &lt;a href=&#34;http://jot.com/compare/index.php&#34;&gt;How JotSpot is Different&lt;/a&gt; and an &lt;a href=&#34;http://jot.com/tours/advanced/1.php&#34;&gt;Advanced Tour&lt;/a&gt; of this wiki&#39;s database capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better, however, is a demonstration that Joe Kraus and Graham Spencer gave InfoWorld reporter &lt;a href=&#34;http://weblog.infoworld.com/udell/2004/10/06.html#a1090&#34;&gt;Jon Udell&lt;/a&gt; an early &lt;a href=&#34;http://weblog.infoworld.com/udell/gems/jot.swf&#34;&gt;demo of JotSpot&lt;/a&gt;, which Jon screen-captured and has released as a 23-minute, 32MB Flash presentation. This demo is very impressive: in addition to incremental improvements to wiki, such as WYSIWYG editing, email support, indexed attachments, RSS and web page importing, etc.  Kraus and Spencer also demonstrate a very powerful forms templating interface that is very much like creating HTML forms with Javascript, and demonstrated integration with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salesforce.com&#34;&gt;SalesForce.com&lt;/a&gt; web application using SOAP. It appears that JotSpot leverages the unstructured and adhoc advantages that are a strength of wiki, yet allows structure to be added later such that the data in the wiki can be integrated with other non-wiki applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion during the demo is also very interesting. Jon Udell made an observation about JotSpot entering into Lotus Notes territory, and Kraus and Spencer discuss how JotSpot makes web application development more accessible, and expressed their desire to create a marketplace for small developers to create tools using JotSpot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I&#39;ve seen so far, JotSpot looks like it may the first of a third-generation of wikis, the first being the very simple wikis such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?WardCunningham&#34;&gt;Ward Cunningham&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki&#34;&gt;C2 Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, and second generation being database-backed wikis such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wikipedia.com&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.socialtext.com&#34;&gt;SocialText&lt;/a&gt;. If you are serious about wiki, I highly recommend you take a look at this demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Kraus also announced today that they have received a $5.2M funding round from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redpoint.com&#34;&gt;Redpoint&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://mayfield.com&#34;&gt;Mayfield&lt;/a&gt;, both top VC firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;Press Release: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotspot.com/news/jotspot_launch.php&#34;&gt;JotSpot Launches, Unveils Application Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessweek.com/technology/content/oct2004/tc2004106_2351.htm&#34;&gt;Business Week: Do-It-Yourself Software for All?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cbs.marketwatch.com/news/story.asp?guid=%7BFA9FE472%2DE293%2D41DC%2D9B96%2D144F34463C97%7D&amp;siteid=mktw&#34;&gt;CBS MarketWatch: Excite founders unveil JotSpot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mercurynews.com/mld/mercurynews/business/technology/9848041.htm&#34;&gt;Mercury News: Palo Alto start-up enhances `Wiki&#39; sites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://softtechvc.blogs.com/software_only/2004/10/jotspot_the_app_1.html&#34;&gt;JotSpot: The Application Wiki&lt;/a&gt; by Jeff Clavier&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.salon.com/0000014/2004/10/06.html#a686&#34;&gt;Joe Kraus talks about Jotspot&lt;/a&gt; by Scott Rosenberg&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidmattison.ca/wordpress/index.php?p=801&#34;&gt;WikiWiki Warfare In The Enterprise Leading To Situational Software?&lt;/a&gt; by David Mattison&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://socialsoftware.weblogsinc.com/entry/6448891678944212/&#34;&gt;JotSpot - Lego Style Wiki?&lt;/a&gt; by Judith Meskill&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posting: &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Jot Wiki kicks ass… (Live from Web 2.0 conference in San Fran)&lt;/a&gt; - by Jason Calacanis&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio: &lt;a href=&#34;http://calacanis.weblogsinc.com/common/videos/jason/jot.mp3&#34;&gt;Audio archive of JotSpot demo at Web 2.0 Conference&lt;/a&gt; recorded by Jason Calacanis&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;An article in spanish: http://www.error500.net/modules/news/article.php?storyid=997
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.error500.net&#34;&gt;Antonio&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-07T13:51:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-07T13:51:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi,
If you like the notion of Application Wikis, you should have a look at the open source project XWiki.. It includes not only a form engine but also a programming API inside wiki pages as well as un underlying relational database..
Ludovic
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.xwiki.org&#34;&gt;Ludovic Dubost&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-07T16:25:09-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-07T16:25:09-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for the wriet up Christopher. I think you asked for a beta. We&#39;re trying to provision accounts as rapidly as we can (while making sure that things are scaling ok). I should be able to guarantee you get provisioned in the next 2-3 days. If there any questions I can answer, don&#39;t hesitate to ask.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.jot.com&#34;&gt;Joe Kraus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-08T20:05:14-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-08T20:05:14-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;JotSpot is way behind other open source &#39;wikis&#39; like TWiki and ZWiki already well into this space.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://usemod.com/cgi-bin/mb.pl?SunirShah&#34;&gt;Sunir&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-14T00:42:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-14T00:42:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/10/jotspot_applica.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>