<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Privacy on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/privacy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Privacy on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 22:30:30 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Four Kinds of Privacy</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/04/the-four-kinds-of-privacy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 22:30:30 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2015/04/the-four-kinds-of-privacy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(This article has been cross-posted in &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@christophera/the-four-kinds-of-privacy-bf4b0bf222ac&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Medium&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: small;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd15c970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ssh by Katie Tegtmeyer CC-BY (crop2)&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd15c970b-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Ssh by Katie Tegtmeyer CC-BY&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Privacy is hitting the headlines more than ever. As computer users are asked to change their passwords again and again in the wake of exploits like &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://heartbleed.com/&#34;&gt;Heartbleed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/&#34;&gt;Shellshock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, they&amp;#39;re becoming aware of the vulnerability of their online data — a susceptibility that was recently verified by scores of celebrities who had their most intimate photographs stolen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any&lt;/em&gt; of us could have our privacy violated at any time… but what does that mean exactly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that&amp;#39;s a tricky question, and I say that with decades of experience in the privacy and security fields. In the early &amp;#39;90s I helped with anti-Clipper Chip activism and supported efforts to allow free export of RSAREF cryptography tools such as PGP. I&amp;#39;m also the co-author of the internet SSL standard, now the most broadly deployed security standard in the world (the &amp;quot;s&amp;quot; in &amp;quot;https&amp;quot;). I&amp;#39;ve been involved with several security companies — as an entrepreneur, a former CTO of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.certicom.com/&#34;&gt;Certicom&lt;/a&gt;, and most recently as the VP of Developer Relations at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blackphone.ch/&#34;&gt;Blackphone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all that time, I&amp;#39;ve been very careful about my use of the word &amp;quot;privacy&amp;quot;. For example, I founded a company that designed and sold the first commercial SSL toolkits. The technology clearly included privacy features, but our marketing said that SSL offered &amp;quot;message integrity&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;confidentiality&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;authentication&amp;quot;. We did not use the word &amp;quot;privacy&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This purposeful omission resulted from my feeling that the concept was too overloaded; if I promised privacy I might not be promising the same thing to everyone because people view the term in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What privacy means varies between Europe and the US, between libertarians and public figures, between the developed world and developing countries, between women and men. I think it&amp;#39;s possible to differentiate no less than four different kinds of privacy, each of which is important to different people — and I&amp;#39;m going to be defining them over the course of this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Prelude: Defining Public&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d106582b970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Cayucos Parade (Cropped, original by Mike Baird licensed CC-BY)&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d106582b970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d106582b970c-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Cayucos Parade (Cropped, original by Mike Baird licensed CC-BY)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;However, before you can define privacy, you first have to define its opposite number: what&amp;#39;s public. &lt;a href=&#34;http://meriam-webster.com/&#34;&gt;Meriam-Webster.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s first definition of &amp;quot;public&amp;quot; includes two different descriptions that are somewhat contradictory. The first is &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;exposed to general view: open&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; and the second is &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;well-known; prominent&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These definitions are at odds with each other because it&amp;#39;s easy for something to be exposed to view &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; it being prominent. In fact, that defines a lot of our everyday life. If you have a conversation with a friend in a restaurant or if you do something in your living room with the curtains open or if you write a message for friends on Facebook, you presume that what you&amp;#39;re doing will not be well-known, but it certainly &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be open to general view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is it public or is it private?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this is a very old question. When talking about recent celebrity photo thefts, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psmag.com/navigation/politics-and-law/celebrity-photo-hacking-scandal-shows-old-privacy-laws-need-serious-update-90087/&#34;&gt;Kyle Chayka&lt;/a&gt; highlighted the early 20th-century case of Gabrielle Darley Melvin, an ex-prostitute who had been acquitted of murderer. After settling quietly into marriage, Melvin found herself the subject of an unauthorized movie that ripped apart the fabric of her new life. Melvin sued the makers of the film but lost. She was told in the 1931 decision &lt;a href=&#34;https://casetext.com/case/melvin-v-reid&#34;&gt;Melvin v. Reid&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;When the incidents of a life are so public as to be spread upon a public record they come within the knowledge and into the possession of the public and cease to be private.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; So the Supreme Court of Los Angeles had one answer for what was public and what was private.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melvin&amp;#39;s case was one where public events had clearly entered the public consciousness. However today, more and more of what people once thought of as private is also escaping into the public sphere — and we&amp;#39;re often surprised by it. That&amp;#39;s because we think that private means secret, and it doesn&amp;#39;t; it just means something that isn&amp;#39;t public. Yet. &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/message/what-is-public-f33b16d780f9&#34;&gt;Anil Dash&lt;/a&gt; recently discussed this on &lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt; and he highlighted a few reasons that privacy is rapidly sliding down this slippery slope of publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, companies have financial incentives for making things &amp;quot;well-known&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;prominent&amp;quot;. The 24-hour news cycle is forcing media to report &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;, so they&amp;#39;re mobbing celebrities and publishing conversations from Facebook or Twitter that people consider private. Meanwhile, an increasing number of tech companies are mining deep ores of data and selling them to the highest bidder; the more information that they can find, the more they can sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, technology is making it ridiculously easy to take those situations that are considered &amp;quot;private&amp;quot; despite being &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;exposed to general view&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; and making them public. It&amp;#39;s easier than ever to record a conversation, or steal data, or photograph or film through a window, or overhear a discussion. Some of these methods are legal, some aren&amp;#39;t, but they&amp;#39;re all happening — and they seem to be becoming more frequent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is big enough that governments are passing laws on the topic. In May 2014, the European Court of Justice decreed that people had a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/may/14/explainer-right-to-be-forgotten-the-newest-cultural-shibboleth&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Right to Be Forgotten&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;: they should be able to remove information about themselves from the public sphere if it&amp;#39;s no longer relevant, making it private once more. Whether this was a good decision remains to be seen, as it&amp;#39;s already resulted in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/aug/02/wikipedia-page-google-link-hidden-right-to-be-forgotten&#34;&gt;removal of information&lt;/a&gt; that clearly &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; relevant to the public sphere. In addition, it&amp;#39;s very much at odds with the laws and rights of the United States, especially the free speech clause of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://constitution.findlaw.com/amendment1.html&#34;&gt;First Amendment&lt;/a&gt;. As Jeffrey Toobin said in a recent &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/09/29/solace-oblivion&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;In Europe, the right to privacy trumps freedom of speech; the reverse is true in the United States.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this means that the line between public and private remains as fuzzy as ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a deep need for the public world: both to be a part of it and to share ourselves with it. However, we also have a deep need for privacy: to keep our information, our households, our activities, and our intimate connections free from general view. In the modern world, drawing the line between these two poles is something that every single person has to consider and manage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s why it&amp;#39;s important that each individual define their own privacy needs — so that they can fight for the kinds of privacy that are important to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;The First Kind: Defensive Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd194970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Hacker (Cropped, original by Christophe Verdier licensed CC-BY-NC) &#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd194970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd194970b-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Hacker (Cropped, original by Christophe Verdier licensed CC-BY-NC) &#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The first type of privacy is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;defensive privacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which protects against transient financial loss resulting from information collection or theft. This is the territory of phishers, conmen, blackmailers, identity thieves, and organized crime. It could also be the purview of governments that seize assets from people or businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important characteristic of defensive privacy is that any loss is ultimately transitory. A phisher might temporarily access a victim&amp;#39;s bank accounts, or an identity thief might cause problems by taking out new credit in the victim&amp;#39;s name, or a government might confiscate a victim&amp;#39;s assets. However, once a victim&amp;#39;s finances have been lost, and they&amp;#39;ve spent some time clearing the problem up, they can then get back on their feet. The losses also might be recoverable — or if not, at least insurable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of privacy is nonetheless important because assaults against it are very common and the losses can still be very damaging. The latest Bureau of Justice &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/press/vit12pr.cfm&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; says that 16.6 million Americans were affected in 2012 by identity theft alone, resulting in $24.7 billion dollars being stolen, or about $1,500 per victim. Though most victims were able to clear up the problems in less than a day, 10% had to spend more than a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though defensive privacy is usually violated by illegal acts, US courts haven&amp;#39;t always recognized the need for privacy of financial records. For example, in the 1976 case &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=15052729295643479698&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;as_sdt=6&amp;amp;as_vis=1&amp;amp;oi=scholarr&#34;&gt;United States vs. Miller&lt;/a&gt; — which was about defrauding the government of whiskey tax — the Supreme Court declared that an individual&amp;#39;s financial records at a bank were not &amp;quot;private papers&amp;quot; but instead the &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;business records of the banks&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It used to be that the biggest danger to defensive privacy was someone digging through a victim&amp;#39;s trash for old bank and credit card statements. However, today the interconnectiveness of the world is making it easier than ever to trick someone out of their financial information. Phishing emails are growing increasingly sophisticated, while social scammers are taking over Facebook and email accounts to pretend to be friends in distress in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hoax-slayer.com/stranded-scam.shtml&#34;&gt;foreign country&lt;/a&gt;. The newest fad seems to be a resurrection of an old con: cold calling victims and pretending to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snopes.com/fraud/telephone/microsoft.asp&#34;&gt;Microsoft support&lt;/a&gt; in the hope of taking over a victim&amp;#39;s computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, defensive privacy is more important than ever — which is unfortunately a trend that crosses all of the kinds of privacy in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;The Second Kind: Human Rights Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d849970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Human Rights Privacy (Anne Frank Photo 1942)&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d849970d img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d849970d-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Human Rights Privacy (Anne Frank Photo 1942)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The second type of privacy is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which protects against existential threats resulting from information collection or theft. This is the territory of stalkers and other felonious criminals as well as authoritarian governments and other persons intent on doing damage to someone for personal for his or her beliefs or political views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important characteristic of human rights privacy is that violations usually result in more long-lasting losses than was the case with defensive privacy. Most obviously, authoritarian governments and hardline theocracies might imprison or kill victims while criminals might murder them. However, political groups could also ostracize or blacklist a victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Europe, human rights privacy is one of the most &lt;em&gt;crucial&lt;/em&gt; sorts of privacy. This comes from the continent&amp;#39;s history: the Netherlands in the 1930s had a very comprehensive administrative census and registration of their own population that collected a lot of personal information. The Nazis captured this data within the first three days of occupation. &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The Dark Side of Numbers&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; by William Seltzer and Margo Anderson (published in &lt;em&gt;Social Research&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 68 No. 2 — Summer 2001), reports the inevitable result: Dutch Jews had the highest death rate (73 percent) of Jews residing in any occupied Western European country — far higher than the death rate among the Jewish population of Belgium (40 percent) or France (25 percent). Even the death rate in Germany was lower than in the Netherlands because the Jews there had avoided registration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the issue of human rights privacy didn&amp;#39;t end there. As Oxford professor Viktor Mayer-Schönberge explained in Jeffrey Toobin&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2014/09/29/solace-oblivion&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, Europe continued to experience serious human rights attacks during the Cold War. Mayer-Schönberge states: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;With the Stasi, in East Germany, the task of capturing information and using it to further the power of the state is reintroduced and perfected by the society. So we had two radical ideologies, Fascism and Communism, and both end up with absolutely shockingly tight surveillance states.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, citizens are shielded from governmental abuses of human rights privacy by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/fourth_amendment&#34;&gt;Fourth Amendment&lt;/a&gt;, which protects against unreasonable searches and seizures. As a result, I personally felt good about human rights privacy in the US — until the presidency of George W. Bush and his first attorney general, John Ashcroft. Under their watch, the Patriot Act dramatically increased the ability of the US government to surveil its citizens, with some of the worst mandates of that law making it illegal for the subject of the surveillance to even talk about being target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, individuals aren&amp;#39;t the only ones facing the governmental breach of human rights privacy in the US. Ever since the 1972 Supreme Court case, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=11598860258825518787&#34;&gt;Branzburg v. Hayes&lt;/a&gt;, the press has also been fighting against governmental demands to reveal confidential sources and direct governmental assaults on sites like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/02/surveillance-and-pressure-wikileaks-readers&#34;&gt;WikiLeaks&lt;/a&gt;. Some US states have created shield laws to protect the press&amp;#39; privacy, but they&amp;#39;re often not sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today journalist James Risen faces jail for protecting a source. In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://sblog.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/13-1009.resp_.pdf&#34;&gt;court filing&lt;/a&gt;, Risen said &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;…this court should reconsider Branzburg because in recent years, subpoenas to journalists seeking the identity of confidential sources have &amp;#39;become commonplace.&amp;#39;&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; The Obama administration responded by stating, &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;…reporters have no privilege to refuse to provide direct evidence of criminal wrongdoing by confidential sources.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; The US Supreme Court refused Risen&amp;#39;s appeal in June 2014, leaving him on the hook for the information or jail time. Meanwhile, other journalists &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hrw.org/news/2014/07/28/us-surveillance-harming-journalism-law-democracy&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; that surveillance is increasingly intimidating sources, making it hard to report on government activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, these American governmental excesses are causing some corporations to consider how they can bolster the cause of human rights privacy: with the release of iOS8, Apple &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com/privacy/government-information-requests/&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that they would no longer have access to users&amp;#39; mobile passcodes, making it nearly impossible for them to turn information over to the government. Google quickly followed on by making Android encryption easier for the public to access. Predictably, the US government isn&amp;#39;t &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-switch/wp/2014/09/30/holder-urges-tech-companies-to-leave-device-backdoors-open-for-police/&#34;&gt;happy&lt;/a&gt;, and security experts are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2014/10/iphone_encrypti_1.html&#34;&gt;nonplussed&lt;/a&gt; by their complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though governments are the biggest actors on the stage of human rights breaches, individuals can also attack this sort of privacy — with cyberbullies being among the prime culprits. Though a bully&amp;#39;s harassment &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; only involve words, the attackers frequently release personal information about the person they&amp;#39;re harassing, which can cause the bullying to snowball. For example Jessica Logan, Hope Sitwell, and Amanda Todd were bullied after their nude pictures were broadcast, while Tyler Clementi was bullied after a hall-mate streamed video of Clementi kissing another young man. Unfortunately, cyberbullying often results in &lt;a href=&#34;http://nobullying.com/six-unforgettable-cyber-bullying-cases/&#34;&gt;suicide&lt;/a&gt;, showing the existential dangers of these privacy breaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if threats aren&amp;#39;t taken seriously, cyberbullying doubles back to the issue of defensive privacy, as revealed by Amanda Hess in her article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psmag.com/navigation/health-and-behavior/women-arent-welcome-internet-72170/&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Why Women Aren&amp;#39;t Welcome on the Internet&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; where she wrote: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Threats of rape, death, and stalking can overpower our emotional bandwidth, take up our time, and cost us money through legal fees, online protection services, and missed wages.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hess is just one of a long list of women who have been targeted by cyberbullies online. Programmer Kathy Sierra was largely driven out of the tech industry back in 2007 for being too influential; she recently wrote about how this is part of a long-standing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/2014/10/trolls-will-always-win&#34;&gt;pattern&lt;/a&gt; of purposeful violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, a study by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/&#34;&gt;Pew Research&lt;/a&gt; revealed that about 25% of women aged 18–24 have been stalked or sexually harassed online — numbers far in excess of their male peers. It was a timely study because Zoe Quinn, Anita Sarkeesian, and Brianna Wu all came under cyberbullying assault around the same time due to their positions as female leaders in the gaming field. When actress and gamer Felicia Day dared to speak out against this problem, her home address and personal email were revealed in a &amp;quot;doxing&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;within an hour,&lt;/em&gt; showing how fragile privacy is on the modern internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not surprising that some of my own female associates are unwilling to post pictures or other personal information online for fear of just this sort of attack. And we&amp;#39;re relatively lucky in the western world: in a hardline theocracy like Afghanistan, a woman&amp;#39;s need for privacy can be even stronger, with many women not willing to use their real names online — or a female name at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals taking part in the democratic process can also come under a personal onslaught of this sort. This has gained prominence in California in recent years when numerous people have been called to task over their contributions to Prop 8, an anti-gay-marriage ballot measure that is now widely considered homophobic and bigoted. Brendan Eich, Mozilla&amp;#39;s CEO, was forced out of his job as a result of such a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/frame_game/2014/04/brendan_eich_quits_mozilla_let_s_purge_all_the_antigay_donors_to_prop_8.html&#34;&gt;contribution&lt;/a&gt;. The fact that his donation was six years previous in a very different political climate shows how long-lasting this sort of damage can be. On the flip-side, the NRA has also been known to go after public figures with anti-gun views. Political repercussions of this sort are a more complex issue than simple cyberbullying, but they demonstrate another situation where individuals might wish they could assert their human rights privacy to shield themselves from damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;The Third Kind: Personal Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1065861970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Personal Privacy (Cropped from original %22Don&amp;#39;t Tread on Me%22 by DonkeyHotey on Flickr CC-BY-SA)&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1065861970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1065861970c-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Personal Privacy (Cropped from original %22Don&amp;#39;t Tread on Me%22 by DonkeyHotey on Flickr CC-BY-SA)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The third type of privacy is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;personal privacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which protects persons against observation and intrusion; it&amp;#39;s what Judge Thomas Cooley called &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;the right to be let alone&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, as cited by future Supreme Court Justice Louis Brandeis in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/1321160&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;The Right to Privacy&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, which he wrote for the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Law Review&lt;/em&gt; of December 15, 1890. Brandeis&amp;#39; championing of this sort of privacy would result in a new, uniquely American right that has at times been attributed to the First Amendment (giving freedom of speech within one&amp;#39;s house), the Fourth Amendment (protecting one&amp;#39;s house from search &amp;amp; seizure by the government), and the Fifth Amendment (protecting one&amp;#39;s private house from public use). This right can also be found in state Constitutions, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/.const/.article_1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Constitution of California&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which promises &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;safety, happiness, and privacy&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When personal privacy is breached we can lose &lt;em&gt;our right to be ourselves&lt;/em&gt;. Without Brandeis&amp;#39; protection, we could easily come under Panoptic observation where we could be forced to act unlike ourselves even in our personal lives. Unfortunately, this isn&amp;#39;t just a theory: a recent PEN America survey shows that 1 in 6 authors already &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pen.org/chilling-effects&#34;&gt;self-censor&lt;/a&gt; due to NSA surveillance. Worse, it could be damaging: another report shows that unselfconscious time is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/05/sunday-review/we-want-privacy-but-cant-stop-sharing.html?smid=nytcore-ipad-share&amp;amp;smprod=nytcore-ipad&amp;amp;_r=1&#34;&gt;restorative&lt;/a&gt; and that low self-esteem, depression, and anxiety can result from its lack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Brandeis almost single-handedly created personal privacy, it didn&amp;#39;t come easily. The Supreme Court refused to protect it in a 1928 wire-tapping case called &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=5577544660194763070%29&#34;&gt;Olmstead v. United States&lt;/a&gt;; in response, Brandeis wrote a famous dissenting opinion that brought his ideas about privacy into the official record of the Court. Despite this initial loss, personal privacy gained advocates in the Supreme Court over the years, who often referred to Brandeis&amp;#39; 1890 article. By the 1960s, Brandeis&amp;#39; ideas were in the mainstream and in the 1967 Supreme Court case &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=9210492700696416594&#34;&gt;Katz v. United States&lt;/a&gt;, Olmstead was finally overturned. Though the Court&amp;#39;s opinion said that personal privacy was &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;left largely to the law of the individual States&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, it had clearly become a proper expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideas that Brandeis championed about personal privacy are shockingly modern. They focused on the Victorian equivalent of the paparazzi, as Brandeis made clear when he said: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Instantaneous photographs and newspaper enterprise have invaded the sacred precincts of private and domestic life.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; He also carefully threaded the interface between public and private, saying, &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The right to privacy does not prohibit any publication of matter which is of public or general interest.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, personal privacy is the special concern of the more Libertarian-oriented founders of the Internet, such as Bit Torrent founder Bram Cohen, who demanded the &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20010710021553/http://bitconjurer.org/a_technological_activists_agenda.html&#34;&gt;basic human rights&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;to be free of intruders&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;to privacy&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;. Personal privacy is more of an issue than ever for celebrities and other public figures, but attacks upon it also touch the personal life of average citizens. It&amp;#39;s the focus of the &amp;quot;do not call&amp;quot; registry and other telemarketing laws and of ordinances outlawing soliciting and trespass. It&amp;#39;s the right at the heart of doing what we please in our own homes — whether it be eating dinner in peace, discussing controversial politics &amp;amp; religion with our close friends, or playing sexual games with our partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though personal privacy has grown in power in America since the 1960s, it&amp;#39;s still under constant attack from the media, telemarketing interests, and the government. Meanwhile, it&amp;#39;s not an absolute across the globe: some cultures, such as those in China and parts of Europe, actively preach against it — advocating that community and sharing trump personal privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Fourth Kind: Contextual Privacy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d864970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Contextual Privacy (Post Secret #2 by Meg Wilis, licensed CC-BY) &#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d864970d img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d864970d-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Contextual Privacy (Post Secret #2 by Meg Wilis, licensed CC-BY) &#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The fourth type of privacy is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;contextual privacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which protects persons against unwanted intimacy. This is what danah boyd calls &lt;a href=&#34;http://many.corante.com/archives/2004/04/16/the_ickiness_factor.php%29&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The Ickiness Factor&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Ickiness is the guttural reaction that makes you cringe, scrunch your nose or gasp &amp;#39;ick&amp;#39; simply because there&amp;#39;s something slightly off, something disconcerting, something not socially right about an interaction…. The ickiness factor is tightly coupled with issues [of] feeling vulnerable or getting the sense that someone else is vulnerable because of a given situation.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to defend contextual privacy can result in the loss of relationships with others. No one presents the same persona in the office as they do when spending time with their kids or even when meeting with other parents. They speak different languages to each of these different &amp;quot;tribes&amp;quot;, and their connection to each tribe could be at risk if they mispoke by putting on the wrong persona or speaking the wrong language at the wrong time. Worse, the harm from this sort of privacy breach may also be increasing in the age of data mining, as bad actors can increasingly put together information from different contexts and twist them into a &amp;quot;complete&amp;quot; picture that simultaneously might be damning and completely false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it&amp;#39;s easy to understand what can be lost with a breach of contextual privacy, the concept can still be confusing because contextual privacy overlaps with other sorts of privacy; it could involve the theft of information or an unwelcome intrusion, but the result is different. Where theft of information might make you feel disadvantaged (if a conman stole your financial information) or endangered (if the government discovered you were whistle blowing), and where an intrusion might make you feel annoyed (if a telemarketer called during dinner), a violation of contextual privacy instead makes you feel emotionally uncomfortable and exposed — or as boyd said, &amp;quot;vulnerable&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that this feeling of vulnerability often comes from an inappropriate level of intimacy. Some of the more professional social networks seem particularly prone to it: I felt uncomfortable when I realized that my professional colleagues on one of the earliest social networks could see that I was in a committed relationship, and in turn I could see that some of them were in open marriages. Not that I had any problem with the information, but did I &amp;quot;need to know&amp;quot; in the context of business?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably won&amp;#39;t find any case law about contextual privacy, because it&amp;#39;s a fairly new concept and because there&amp;#39;s less &lt;em&gt;obvious&lt;/em&gt; harm. However social networks from Facebook and LinkedIn to Twitter and LiveJournal are all facing contextual privacy problems as they each try to become the home for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; sorts of social interaction. This causes people — in particular women and members of the LGBT communities — to try and keep multiple profiles, only to find &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/chris.cox/posts/10101301777354543&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;real name&amp;quot; policies&lt;/a&gt; working against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, some social networks make things worse by creating artificial social pressures to reveal information, as occurs when someone tags you in a Facebook picture or in status update. To date, Google+ is one of the few networks to attempt a solution by creating &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/+/learnmore/circles/&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;circles&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, which can be used to precisely specify who in your social network should get each piece of information that you share. However, it&amp;#39;s unclear how many people use this feature. A related feature on Facebook called &amp;quot;Lists&amp;quot; is rarely used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a lack of personal privacy causes you to &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;not be yourself&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, a loss of contextual privacy allows other to &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;not see you as yourself&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;. You risk being perceived as &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;other&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; when your actions are seen out of context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All four of these kinds of privacy can intersect. For example, some social networks allow you to reveal your sexual orientation, which could be used secretly by an employer to discriminate against you (&lt;em&gt;defensive privacy&lt;/em&gt;) or by a future Ashcroftian government to violate your civil rights (&lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;). It might lead you to being bothered at home because of people who either agree with or disagree with your orientation (&lt;em&gt;personal privacy) _and often is an inappropriate revelation for casual professional acquaintances (&lt;/em&gt;contextual privacy_).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies of current events offer more examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The First Case: Celebrity Hacking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d870970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Jennifer Lawrence SDCC 2013 X-Men (by Gage Skidmore. licensed CC-BY)&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d870970d img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb0820d870970d-320wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Jennifer Lawrence SDCC 2013 X-Men (by Gage Skidmore. licensed CC-BY)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The recent unauthorized release of nude pictures of Jennifer Lawrence and others demonstrates the complex permutations of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, it highlighted the problematic divide between public and private. There&amp;#39;s no doubt that the pictures were intended to be private, and unlike some of the more troublesome uses of recording devices, these private situations &lt;em&gt;weren&amp;#39;t&lt;/em&gt; made public through the uncomfortable use of surveillance technology. Instead, the photos were publicized following theft. Unfortunately, now that they&amp;#39;re in the public eye, they&amp;#39;re unlikely to go away, ever. In other words, the genie&amp;#39;s out of the bottle. All that the celebrities can do is make the photos less accessible by asserting their copyright (if they can to get search engines to de-link the information).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Europe&amp;#39;s Right to Be Forgotten will someday help to remove this type of occurrence from the internet. Or perhaps something like California&amp;#39;s recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/13-14/bill/sen/sb_0251-0300/sb_255_bill_20130507_amended_sen_v98.html&#34;&gt;SB 255&lt;/a&gt; might make it illegal to distribute nude photos without the model&amp;#39;s permission. Alternatively, it could be social mores that win out, if we follow &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;the ethics of looking away&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, as advocated by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2014/09/leaked-photos-nude-celebrities-abuse/379434/&#34;&gt;Jessica Valenti&lt;/a&gt;); Jennifer Lawrence herself agreed there are ethical problems, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vanityfair.com/vf-hollywood/2014/10/jennifer-lawrence-cover&#34;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Anybody who looked at those pictures, you&amp;#39;re perpetuating a sexual offense.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; However for now, the pictures are out there &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; being viewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When considering the four kinds of privacy, these celebrities primarily suffered from an unwanted intimacy with the entire world (&lt;em&gt;contextual privacy&lt;/em&gt;). Lawrence explained the problem succinctly, saying: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;I didn&amp;#39;t tell you that you could look at my naked body.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Celebrities and other high-profile victims might also face financial repercussions (&lt;em&gt;defensive privacy&lt;/em&gt;). Ariana Grande was one of the younger victims of the theft and one of the few to risk the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streisand_effect&#34;&gt;Streisand Effect&lt;/a&gt; by saying her photos weren&amp;#39;t authentic. She should never have had to make such a statement one way or the other, but one understands why she would: as a teen pop star recently featured on a pair of Nickelodeon shows, she risks the greatest fiscal damage of any of the victims. But even Lawrence worried, stating: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;I didn&amp;#39;t know how this would affect my career.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Sullivan offered some of the most adroit commentary on the theft when he &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtv.com/news/1918278/jennifer-lawrence-photos-not-a-scandal/&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Don&amp;#39;t call it a scandal&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;. By calling this a scandal and smugly shaking our heads, we&amp;#39;re blaming the victims, not the criminals. Worse, we&amp;#39;re embarking on a slippery slope where we suggest that people take away their own freedoms through self-censorship. By calling it a scandal, we are saying that even in their own homes, using their own cameras, these people shouldn&amp;#39;t be themselves (&lt;em&gt;personal privacy&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_8&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Second Case: #GamerGate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1065886970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Zoe Quinn (by Zoe Quinn, licensed CC-BY-SA)&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1065886970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1065886970c-320wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Zoe Quinn (by Zoe Quinn, licensed CC-BY-SA)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The widespread and ongoing harassment of game designer Zoe Quinn is a somewhat frightening example for its intense focus on the repeated privacy violations of a single person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started with a blog post by Quinn&amp;#39;s ex-boyfriend that accused her of infidelity. This once more highlights the troubled modern divide between public and private. Though some countries &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; protect the release of information of this sort using defamation laws, it seems unlikely that the US&amp;#39;s slander or libel laws would do so. Despite the likely legality of that initial post, the public still learned inappropriate information about Quinn (&lt;em&gt;contextual privacy&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, worse privacy violations followed: the online community 4chan &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doxing&#34;&gt;doxed&lt;/a&gt; Quinn by collecting considerable semi-public information about her (more &lt;em&gt;contextual privacy)&lt;/em&gt;, which allowed online harassment to evolve into threatening phone calls (&lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;). The information revealed during the harassment included the fact that Quinn had dated a game industry journalist, which could impact Quinn&amp;#39;s ability to sell games in the future or even to get reviewed (&lt;em&gt;defensive privacy&lt;/em&gt;). Obviously, the continual harassment has also violated Quinn&amp;#39;s personal space and her right to be let alone (&lt;em&gt;personal privacy&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the initial assaults on Quinn, the #GamerGate mob has moved on to harass other female game designers, including Anita Sarkeesian and Brianna Wu, as well as gamer and actress Felicia Day — all using the same privacy-busting methodology of cyberbullying and doxing. The movement may have reached its height when terrorist threats were made against a talk planned by Sarkeesian, forcing her to cancel it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, it was difficult for groups of individuals to work together to violate the privacy rights of an individual; there also wasn&amp;#39;t a medium that could be used to publish personal details about someone unless there was a clear public interest. The cyberbullying stemming from #GamerGate shows that&amp;#39;s all changed in the modern age. Which is why privacy is such a major concern for so many people on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_9&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Third Case: The NSA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd1c6970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;National_Security_Agency&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd1c6970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd1c6970b-320wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;National_Security_Agency&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Though it&amp;#39;s become very easy for individuals to violate the privacy of celebrities like Jennifer Lawrence or individuals like Zoe Quinn, the government has also been stepping up its act in the 21st century, especially since 9/11. In the United States, it&amp;#39;s the NSA who&amp;#39;s been at the heart of the privacy controversies (with a little help from their friends in the FBI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the new privacy-busting powers of these organizations originated with the USA &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/PLAW-107publ56/pdf/PLAW-107publ56.pdf&#34;&gt;Patriot Act&lt;/a&gt;, but follow-up laws like the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/STATUTE-121/pdf/STATUTE-121-Pg552.pdf&#34;&gt;Protect America Act&lt;/a&gt; of 2007 and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/&#34;&gt;FISA Amendment Act&lt;/a&gt; of 2008 are equally invasive. We only know how these laws are actually being utilized thanks to the whistle-blowing of Edward Snowden and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most obviously, these types of laws have allowed the collection of private data in large quantities (&lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;). We now know that the NSA uses a previously secret program called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/06/12/heres-everything-we-know-about-prism-to-date/&#34;&gt;PRISM&lt;/a&gt; to coordinate data collection using court orders and that they also appear to have broken into &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/nsa-infiltrates-links-to-yahoo-google-data-centers-worldwide-snowden-documents-say/2013/10/30/e51d661e-4166-11e3-8b74-d89d714ca4dd_story.html&#34;&gt;communication links&lt;/a&gt; to tap major data centers. There are claims that they also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-04-11/nsa-said-to-have-used-heartbleed-bug-exposing-consumers.html&#34;&gt;exploited the Heartbleed bug&lt;/a&gt; for years in order to collect data, though they deny this. The human rights repercussions of this multi-pronged, largely unfettered data collection are mind-boggling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most worrisome issues with this sort of large-scale data collection is that it can result in mistakes when something is taken out of context (&lt;em&gt;contextual privacy&lt;/em&gt;). Someone might feel like they have nothing to fear from the government — until they&amp;#39;re arrested for something they said while roleplaying in an MMORPG. Unfortunately, this isn&amp;#39;t an unfounded concern: Snowden&amp;#39;s whistleblowing revealed that the NSA spies on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-12-10/nsa-infiltrating-online-video-games-leaked-documents-show/5147394&#34;&gt;video game chats&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, this type of contextual disconnect has already caused problems in other legal contexts, such as when firefighter Lt. Philip Lyons was falsely charged with arson based on the purchase of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://seattletimes.com/html/localnews/2002055245_arson06m.html&#34;&gt;fire-starter&lt;/a&gt; that was revealed through loyalty card records. Reports similarly indicate that the FBI was tracking the sale of &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20071221122513/http://cqpolitics.com/wmspage.cfm?parm1=5&amp;amp;docID=hsnews-000002620892&#34;&gt;Middle Eastern foods&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco as a terrorist-finding tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union has much more mature protections against data collection of this sort, thanks to the Data Protection Directive of 1995, which is now in the process of being &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/&#34;&gt;reformed&lt;/a&gt;. Sadly, the US has only responded in a piecemeal way that largely depends on private corporations&amp;#39; privacy policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning to the US, we find that many of these data collection and spying laws have been wrapped up with authoritarian regulations that go after individuals — such as one of Edward Snowden&amp;#39;s email providers, LavaBit founder Ladar Levison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levison wrote an article about his interactions with the FBI that reads like an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/may/20/why-did-lavabit-shut-down-snowden-email&#34;&gt;Orwellian parody&lt;/a&gt;. He described how the FBI served him papers seven times and forced him to appear in a court 1,000 miles from home without an attorney as part of their heavy-handed attempt to acquire Snowden&amp;#39;s encryption keys. His company, LavaBit, was eventually shut down as a result. Because Levison tried to protect the privacy of one of his customers, he was threatened with jail and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/&#34;&gt;compelled to silence&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;personal privacy&lt;/em&gt;). Even Yahoo&amp;#39;s CEO Marissa Meyer is personally worried about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/sep/11/yahoo-ceo-mayer-jail-nsa-surveillance&#34;&gt;trend&lt;/a&gt;. She says tech companies aren&amp;#39;t talking more about the government&amp;#39;s surveillance because they&amp;#39;re afraid: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Releasing classified information is treason and you are incarcerated.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue of compelled silence arises from the National Security Letters authorized by the USA Patriot Act. It&amp;#39;s particularly troublesome because it threatens democracy just as much as a lack of voting anonymity would. Because the Letters can&amp;#39;t be discussed, there&amp;#39;s no way to assess whether the government is doing a good job or not — and thus no way to punish a government at the voting booth if they&amp;#39;re stepping over the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_10&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Fourth Case: Americans in Afghanistan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd1ca970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Afgan Social Media Summit (cropped, original by Luisa Whalmsey, licensed CC-BY)&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd1ca970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c77cd1ca970b-500wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Afgan Social Media Summit (cropped, original by Luisa Whalmsey, licensed CC-BY)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;My final case study is a personal one. I&amp;#39;ve regularly taught &amp;quot;Digital Influence&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Using the Social Web for Social Change&amp;quot; classes in the Bainbridge Graduate Institute&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://bgi.pinchot.edu/&#34;&gt;MBA in Sustainable Systems&lt;/a&gt; program at Pinchot University. One of my students there was Luisa Walmsley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While at BGI, Luisa met a woman who had co-founded Afghanistan&amp;#39;s largest telecommunications company. Luisa later went to work at the company, then started her own consultancy doing operations and business development for Afghan media and technology companies — in the process helping women in Afghanistan to become better entrepreneurs. She&amp;#39;s also been involved with Afghanistan&amp;#39;s first-ever &lt;a href=&#34;http://socialmediasummit.af/&#34;&gt;social media summit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, being a female professional in Afghanistan can still be quite dangerous. Women have only been able to widely reenter the work force in the last decade, since the 2001 overthrow of the Taliban, and today they are sometimes still attacked or threatened for doing so. This makes Luisa&amp;#39;s need for privacy important (&lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luisa&amp;#39;s situation also demonstrates the sorts of divides you can find in a human rights privacy case. While in Afghanistan, Luisa follows basic security procedures to protect her privacy from both terrorists and the government — such as varying the times of day that she travels to the office. She&amp;#39;s still willing to use social media but is careful, for example occasionally lying about her location or not talking about her travel plans or waiting days to post pictures that might reveal information as to her whereabouts. However Luisa has to be even more careful with the human rights concerns of the women she&amp;#39;s working with, who could be assaulted or killed for their decision to make a career for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even outside of her work proper, Luisa has run into other sorts of privacy issues in Afghanistan. She was once asked by an Afghan government agency to remove a Facebook post that reprinted an international organization&amp;#39;s security alert concerning elections security, which she&amp;#39;d reposted in order to warn her friends. She&amp;#39;s also received phone harassment (&lt;em&gt;personal privacy&lt;/em&gt;) that would be unthinkable in the US: in Afghanistan men cold call phone numbers and when they hear a woman&amp;#39;s voice on the other side, they continuously call back. Luisa was often able to stop the calls, but some of her female friends would receive over 200 harassing phone calls of this sort a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Luisa&amp;#39;s work also runs straight back into the privacy problems originating with the NSA. In 2013, the NSA admitted that they tracked phone calls of people &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2013/07/you-may-already-be-a-winner-in-nsas-three-degrees-surveillance-sweepstakes/&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;two to three hops&amp;quot; away&lt;/a&gt; from suspected terrorists. However in Afghanistan, &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; working in human rights or in the media is going to have some &lt;em&gt;direct&lt;/em&gt; contact with the Taliban. Luisa surely has (one hop), so as soon as she calls or emails me (two hops), I&amp;#39;m suddenly in the NSA jackpot (more &lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;). And how does the NSA get that information? In 2014 we learned that they&amp;#39;re recording nearly all domestic &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; international &lt;a href=&#34;https://wikileaks.org/WikiLeaks-statement-on-the-mass.html&#34;&gt;phone calls in Afghanistan&lt;/a&gt; (massive &lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we know that the FBI once though it was relevant to track falafel sales, and because I gained an appreciation for Middle Eastern music 15 years ago, I could easily become a serious terror suspect myself (yet more &lt;em&gt;human rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;). Worse, if you&amp;#39;re reading this article (&lt;em&gt;three hops&lt;/em&gt;), you now might be in the NSA&amp;#39;s sights too. Hope you don&amp;#39;t like &lt;em&gt;hummus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;baba ghannouj&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_11&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy is important — perhaps more so than ever due to the assaults by con artists, governments, the press, and social media in the 21st century. However, in order to protect your own privacy, you must define your terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, that requires: understanding the difference between private and public; considering how to prevent information from escaping from the one to the other; and thinking about how that might interact with free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it requires understanding the different kinds of privacy, and figuring out which one is most topical to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Is it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;defensive privacy?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;_ W_here you worry about conmen, phishers, or other thieves stealing from you? Do you fear the finances loss?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Is it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;human rights privacy?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;_ W_here you&amp;#39;re threatened by the actions of a government or other entity? Do you fear the loss of your life or your freedom?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Is it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;personal privacy?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Where you just want to be be left alone? Do you fear the loss of the freedom to be yourself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Is it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;contextual privacy?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Where you want to partition different portions of your life? Do you fear the loss of your relationships?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people will have some concerns about multiple sorts of privacy, but there will probably be one or two that strike a chord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;#39;s important to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_12&#34;&gt;About the Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Allen is a technologist and entrepreneur with a long history of work in the privacy and security fields. As the founder of Consensus Development, he led and co-authored the IETF-TLS (SSL 3.0) standard and sold the first commercial SSL toolkits. He&amp;#39;s also the former CTO of the cryptographic security company &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.certicom.com&#34;&gt;Certicom&lt;/a&gt; (now part of Blackberry). Recently he was VP of Developer Relations for the secure smartphone company &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.Blackphone.ch&#34;&gt;Blackphone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.Blackphone.ch,&#34;&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; building on his experience with mobile software industry . He has produced a number of iOS apps, spoken at conferences, and organizes developer hackathons at such events as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iOSDevCamp.org&#34;&gt;iOSDevCamp&lt;/a&gt;. Christopher also teaches Technology Leadership in the &lt;em&gt;MBA in Sustainable Systems&lt;/em&gt; program at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bgi.pinchot.edu&#34;&gt;Bainbridge Graduate Institute&lt;/a&gt; at Pinchot University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is based on an original post written in 2004 in Christopher&amp;#39;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html&#34;&gt;Life With Alacrity&lt;/a&gt;, and presentations on the topic of privacy used in his classes and posted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://slideshare.net/christophera&#34;&gt;slideshare.net&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_13&#34;&gt;Image Credits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Image&lt;/strong&gt; is cropped from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/katietegtmeyer/&#34;&gt;Katie Tegtmeyer&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;Talk Shows on Mute&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/katietegtmeyer/67865829/&#34;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public&lt;/strong&gt; is cropped from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mikebaird/&#34;&gt;Mike Baird&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;July 4th Parrade in Cayucos, CA&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mikebaird/4761150137/&#34;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive Privacy&lt;/strong&gt; is cropped from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/cverdier/&#34;&gt;Christophe Verdier&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;Day 342 — Hacker&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/cverdier/4837773532&#34;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY-NC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human Rights Privacy&lt;/strong&gt; is from an image in Ann Frank Diary, and is offered under fair use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Privacy&lt;/strong&gt; is cropped from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/donkeyhotey/&#34;&gt;DonkeyHotey&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;Dont Tread on Me&amp;quot; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/donkeyhotey/5468570321/&#34;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY-SA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contextual Privacy&lt;/strong&gt; is from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/whatmegsaid/&#34;&gt;Meg Willis&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;Post Secret #2&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/whatmegsaid/3172360305&#34;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt; and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portrait of Jennifer Lawrence&lt;/strong&gt; is by Gage Skidmore &amp;quot;Jennifer Lawrence SDCC 2013 X-Men&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%B8%E3%82%A7%E3%83%8B%E3%83%95%E3%82%A1%E3%83%BC%E3%83%BB%E3%83%AD%E3%83%BC%E3%83%AC%E3%83%B3%E3%82%B9#/media/File:Jennifer_Lawrence_SDCC_2013_X-Men.jpg&#34;&gt;Japanese Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&#34;&gt;CC-BY-SA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self Portrait of Zoe Quinn&lt;/strong&gt; is by Zoe Quinn from &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoe_Quinn#/media/File:Zoe_Quinn_Car_2014.jpg&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&#34;&gt;CC-BY-SA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSA Seal&lt;/strong&gt; is from converted from svg image on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Security_Agency#/media/File:National_Security_Agency.svg&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and is Public Domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portrait of Ladar Levison&lt;/strong&gt; is cropped from a photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/user?screen_name=Jose_Pagliery&#34;&gt;Joe Paglieri&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://money.cnn.com/2014/07/22/technology/security/dark-mail/&#34;&gt;CNN Money&lt;/a&gt;, and is offered under fair use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luisa Walmsley at Afgan Social Media Summit&lt;/strong&gt; is cropped from a photo by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LuisaWalmsley&#34;&gt;Luisa Whalmsey&lt;/a&gt; and is licensed &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_14&#34;&gt;Appendices &amp;amp; Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the following post &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@christophera/the-four-kinds-of-privacy-appendices-bibliography-d2b75b269d2d&#34;&gt;The Four Kinds of Privacy: Appendices &amp;amp; Bibliography&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2015/04/the-four-kinds-of-privacy.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing your Social Graph with Google&#43; [Google Plus]</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563798/&#34; title=&#34;Trust Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Trust Circle&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3230/3055563798_5355b9b99c_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With Google+ almost two weeks into its test phase, conversation about this new social network service seems to be going in circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because Circles is the Google+ feature that users are generating the most buzz about. It’s Google’s answer to the problem of organizing your social graph online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_graph&#34;&gt;social graph&lt;/a&gt; it’s a map of everyone you know and how they are related to you. Social graphs are tricky; as you try to define them you’ll inevitably run into some complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete Pachal, news director of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387808,00.asp&#34;&gt;@PCMag&lt;/a&gt; comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;“People want things easy, and Google Circles isn’t easy. It puts the burden on users to take the time to think about each and every contact and put them in a specific bucket. To use the feature effectively, users will certainly have to create new Circles, and that requires even more thought. After using Google+ for a few minutes last night, I was often unsure which Circles to put certain people in and, more to the point, which to leave them out of. And what if you create a new Circle that should include some of the people in other Circles you already have?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circles are lists that you’ve created by grouping people together and giving them a name. They’re important in Google+ because when you post you must explicitly say which “Circles” you wish to share with. Posting to a limited list of people is a big change from existing social networks such as Facebook, where posts are sent to all mutual friends by default, or Twitter, where posts are public. This change forces you to think more deeply about your social graph and who should see each item you post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BwvygI2xKGM&#34; width=&#34;560&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yourinitialsetofcircles&#34;&gt;Your Initial Set of Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google+ will present you with 4 suggested set of Circles: Friends, Family, Acquaintances, and Following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d image-full&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-800wi&#34; title=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Google+ also defines five special Circles: Two are only for reading: &amp;quot;Stream&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; and &amp;quot;Incoming&amp;quot; which is are posts that are shared to you by people not in your Circles. Then are three special Circles managed by Google only for posting: &amp;quot;Your Circles&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; “Extended” which is everyone in your Circles plus the people in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; Circles; and “Public” which is &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few find this default set to be sufficient. As a result, most Google+ users are soon creating new Circles, moving people around, renaming Circles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sound reasons for people finding the default Circles limiting. Sociological research shows that everyone has a number of concentric personal circles (see my blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt; for more details). These circles are sometimes called “ego-centric” social graphs as the individual is located in the center. This sort of graph is the model I used when I began reorganizing my own Google+ Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out using Support (for my Support Circle), Close (for my Sympathy Circle), Trusted (for my Trust Circle), and Colleagues (for my Emotional Circle), but that didn’t work for very long. I’ve since been experimenting with a number of different ways to organize my Circles. I wanted an initial set that would offer useful early advice for using Google+ but would still be applicable for when expanded to hundreds of people. (I now have over 600 people in my Circles.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One insight I’ve had is to avoid the word ‘friends’, which has been corrupted to almost meaninglessness in recent years. So instead I use terminology like Peers for my trust circle and Kith for the combination of my support and sympathy circles. (Kith may be familiar to you from the phrase “kith and kin”. The root of kith means “to know”, thus it’s those people that you know very well and that know you very well.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that sub-Circles exist within Circles. Using a ‘general ledger’ system of naming Circles with numbers—which I’ll demonstrate in a moment—helps me keep these Circles and sub-Circles in order and allows me to easily add new Circles when I need to. Hopefully Google+ will in the future introduce features that allow us to order Circles as we please, but until then this numbering system works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Google+ has also shown me that some Circles are for reading and other Circles are for posting. I’ll talk a little more about this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has only been a week, but by combining these insights to organize my Circles I’ve improved my ease of use and become better able to manage my time while using Google+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my recommended initial list of Circles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 ME&lt;/strong&gt; - a simple Circle with just yourself in it, for saving posts, for drafts, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.0 KIN&lt;/strong&gt; - your family &amp;amp; extended family&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt; 2.0 KITH&lt;/strong&gt; - your best friends, your confidants (i.e. those with whom one shares a secret or private matter, trusting them not to repeat it to others)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.0 PEERS&lt;/strong&gt; - your trusted colleagues, those who you work closely with, your collaborators&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.0 LOCAL&lt;/strong&gt; - your neighbors, parents of your children&amp;#39;s friends, people you&amp;#39;d invite to a party&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.0&lt;/strong&gt; {various groups &amp;amp; interests}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;/strong&gt; - people you know, but that you don&amp;#39;t know well or that don’t know you well&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;/strong&gt; - people who follow you on Google+, who you may or may not know&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;/strong&gt; - people whose posts you read, but who don&amp;#39;t necessarily read your posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 9.0 SPECIAL&lt;/strong&gt; - useful for special lists &amp;amp; exceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expandingcircles&#34;&gt;Expanding Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people will find my default set of ~10 Circles to be very useful, and need only add a few more. However, the design of this set is to allow for much greater expansion should you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like those “personal circles” that I wrote about previously, most of the Circles above are ego-centric: they’re fundamentally centered on your own personal social graph. This isn’t the only potential type of Circle, however. Socio-centric Circles aren’t centered on you, though they still have some sort of membership boundaries, while info-centric Circles are based on topics instead of being based on relationships. These socio-centric and info-centric Circles will support many relationships better than ego-centric Circles do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone seems to write a lot about a particular topic, I put him or her into an appropriate info-centric Circle. My own info-centric Circles thus include people who post about topics like iOS Development, the Social Web, Sustainability/Green, and Entrepreneuring. If a number of people are all part of a group or all come from a certain geographical area then I put them together in a socio-centric circle. After creating the Circles, I put the ones that were geographic into 4.0 of my ledger, then placed the others in 5.0. (I tried separating out groups and interests, and found that didn’t work, so now I keep them together.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now have over 600 people in my Google Plus+ social graph. All together my Circles now look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 Read Later&lt;br /&gt; 0.1 Drafts&lt;br /&gt; 0.2 Book Project&lt;br /&gt; 0.3 iPad Project&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 1.0 ALL KIN&lt;br /&gt; 1.1 Immediate Family&lt;br /&gt; 1.2 Extended Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 2.0 ALL KITH&lt;br /&gt; 2.1 Close Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.2 Old But Distant Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.3 Distant Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 3.0 ALL PEERS&lt;br /&gt; 3.2 Collaborators&lt;br /&gt; 3.3 Current Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt; 3.4 Former Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 4.0 ALL LOCAL&lt;br /&gt; 4.1 Local Kith, Kin &amp;amp; Peers&lt;br /&gt; 4.2 Local Berkeley&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Seattle&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Portland&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 5.0 ALL GROUPS &amp;amp; INTERESTS&lt;br /&gt; 5.1 Entrepreneurs&lt;br /&gt; 5.2 Apple &amp;amp; iOS&lt;br /&gt; 5.3 - iOSDevCamp&lt;br /&gt; 5.4 Green &amp;amp; Sustainability&lt;br /&gt; 5.5 - BGIedu&lt;br /&gt; 5.6 Social Web&lt;br /&gt; 5.7 - Jerry’s Kids&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;br /&gt; 6.1 Familiar Strangers&lt;br /&gt; 6.2 Friendly Strangers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;br /&gt; 7.1 Core Audience&lt;br /&gt; 7.2 Commented or Shared My Posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;br /&gt; 8.2 Pundits&lt;br /&gt; 8.3 Celebrities&lt;br /&gt; 8.4 Noisy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 9.0 ALL&lt;br /&gt; 9.1 Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy&lt;br /&gt; 9.2 Read Daily&lt;br /&gt; 9.3 Read Weekly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future blog post I’ll share my ongoing experience with using this approach to Circles, but this example shows how easy it is to separate and add Circles as your interests change and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;managingyourcircles&#34;&gt;Managing Your Circles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, enjoy social networks in large part because we get to interact with people. Managing your Circles is thus about more than just understanding your social graph. It also allows you to manage your time effectively when you read and share with other people on Google+. Here is my approach for how to manage the time you spend reading, sharing, and managing your social graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforreading&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Reading&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it useful to think about Circles that are explicitly for reading as different from Circles intended for sharing. I have a few of these read-only Circles. Thus, my “Pundits” Circle contains people that share a lot and for whom I don’t always want to read everything. My “Read Daily” Circle is conversely for people for whom I want to read everything they post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also found Circles helpful for close collaborators. It’s easy in Google+ to have a conversation with someone directly by simply typing their name as +&amp;lt;name&amp;gt; into the share field of posts. However, I find these direct posts get lost over time. To resolve this problem, create a Circle dedicated to just the two of you: a dyad. I have a number of people that I’m collaborating with closely and I use these small Circles to both keep track of our mutual posts and to see what they are thinking about at the moment. Examples of this kind of two-person Circle include my “Book Project” and “iPad Project”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofreadingcircles&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Reading Circles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day I look first at my “ALL KIN”, “ALL KITH” and and “ALL PEER” Circles to see what is going on with my support, sympathy and trust cliques. Then I’ll read my “Read Daily” Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading these daily basics (which I try to keep to a limited number), I’ll typically pick an interest, a geography, or a group, depending on what I’m doing that day. (My personal time-management style is to only follow one interest per day, e.g. if I am working on my iPad app then I’m not reading Social Web posts.) If I’m preparing a blog post and want to see what my audience is thinking I might review “Core Audience”, or “FOLLOWS ME”. If I’m traveling I might read one of my non-local Circles such as “Seattle”. If I’m doing ‘weak-signal research’ I might start with “ALL INTERESTS”, but if I’m particularly tolerant of noise I might read “Familiar Strangers”, “FOLLOWS ME”, “Everyone but Pundits &amp;amp; Strangers”, “Pundits”, or even “ALL”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;postingtocircles&#34;&gt;Posting to Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the important reasons for creating Circles in the first place is so that you can share with groups of people. I’ve developed some strategies for this as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforposting:&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Posting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it useful to create a Circle that only contains yourself. I have two of these — “Read Later”, and “Drafts”. If I’m reading and I see something interesting but don’t have time for it immediately, I’ll share it with my “Read Later” Circle so that I can quickly go back to it. Similarly, if I need to do some more research before writing and sharing, I’ll share my immediate thoughts in “Drafts”. As new features are added to Google+ these Circles will hopefully become obsolete, but they are useful for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofprivateposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Private Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sharing, you want to ask yourself if this is ‘private’ post, a ‘quasi-public’ post or a ‘public’ post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My private posts tend to go “KIN”, “KITH”, a dyad project, or one of the sub-Circles of PEER depending on their context. Some posts that are of only geographic interest (say a party, or local event) will be shared privately to the appropriate local Circle. If you are using my ledger system of using numbers in Circle names, these are the lower numbers—5.0 and below are Circles where I’m more sensitive about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once shared, these more personal posts will be labeled as “Limited” instead of using the “Public” label that allows anyone to see them. If a recipient tries to share a “Limited” post, a box will pop up reminding the person: “This post was originally shared with a limited audience – remember to be thoughtful about who you share it with”. Unlike Facebook or Twitter, one purpose of Circles on Google+ is to determine who gets what information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it may be easy to create Circles to segregate those with whom you wish to share private information, the recipients of your posts have no such limitations and could share outward beyond your intent (though they will be warned if they try to, as noted above). To enable further privacy you can disable resharing of these personal posts made to your Circles. To do so, share your post to a non-public Circle, then you select the arrow in the upper-right-hand corner where you can edit, delete or disable the post, and click on the final option, “Disable Reshare”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another privacy issue: by clicking the grey “Limited” label, a message’s recipient can see all others you shared the post with. This could potentially result in privacy problems, as the reader could discover who is in one of your Circles. There are ways of eliminating this by going into your Privacy account settings, which I will cover in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofquasi-publicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Quasi-Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call posts “quasi-public” when they’re of narrow interest to a specific group or a topic that isn’t really relevant to other members of my audience. I find these quasi-public posts happen the most for my more esoteric interests—for instance, when I’m sharing a complex iPhone development article that is really only interesting to a narrow group of my contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Google Reader, I typically wouldn’t share these articles at all because there were so many of my contacts that wouldn’t be interested in them and it would only be noise to them. Ditto with Twitter. I found that sometimes people would stop following me after a conference I attended because I posted regularly and the conference was not of interest to them. This could be quite frustrating at times. Though these posts were not private by any means, I only wanted to share them with a specific group, such as an iPhone group. Now with Circles, I can share this information easily with my “Apple &amp;amp; iOS” Circle. I find that this feature is what makes Google+’s Circles so potentially powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I might offer much of this more esoteric information as “quasi-public” posts to a specific group or interest, I’ll probably offer the best of them to the “Public”. Sometimes that is what it means to be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maven&#34;&gt;Maven&lt;/a&gt;—you share across social network boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofpublicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing a post to your “Your Circles” is effectively public, as is sharing to “Extended Circles”. Ask yourself if there is really some reason why you don’t want to make a post totally “Public” so that it is searchable by those who are not members of Google+. If there is some reason, consider sharing to your “ALL” Circle or some other more limited circle instead, as you’ll have more control and can turn off resharing or commenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;managingyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;Managing Your Social Graph&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining your Circles can take away from the time you can spend on reading and sharing. I’ve come up with the following strategy to limit the time I spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, I have some basic rules for which Circles to place people in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone is following me, I add them to “FOLLOWS ME” and an appropriate other Circle. If I vaguely recognize a follower’s name or face, I put them in “Familiar Strangers”. If I don’t recognize them at all but they look interesting, I add them to “Friendly Strangers”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone has +1’ed, commented, or mentioned me in a post, I add them to “Core Audience” and the appropriate sub-Circle. I will also make sure that the other Circles they are in are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I discover while I’m reading that someone is too noisy for the Circle I selected, I’ll move them to a more appropriate Circle—or place them in the “Noisy” Circle or even block them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Your Social Graph&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition I review a few of my Circles every day. I do so by going to “Manage Circles”, then selecting “People in your Circles” and sorting by last name. I choose that letter of the alphabet that corresponds to the day of the month and hover my mouse over each name. (For example, I look at names starting with “L” on July 12th, as “L” is the 12th letter.) Google+ highlights the Circles that each person is in. If they’re in the wrong Circle, I move them. I might even click on some people and review their profile so that I can see who they are—or (if I already know them) see what they are up to lately, update my address book, and maybe send them a brief email. At the end of the month (on the 27th through the 31st) I review my overall Circles lists. This way, over the course of each month I briefly review my entire social network, without spending too much time on it. (I try to spend 10 minutes or so a day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Periodically (right now weekly, but hopefully eventually monthly) I do some larger scale management of my Circles. Learning how to do this the first time is a pain, but once you know how it only takes a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to “Manage Circles” and select “People Who Have Added You”. I sort that list by “Not Yet in Circles”, “Select All” and add the people revealed to “FOLLOWS ME”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then do the same with all of my Circles to update my “ALL” Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I copy my “ALL” circle to “Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy” and remove any Pundits, Celebrities or Noisy people from that Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When managing your Circles, remember the motto “Perfection is the Enemy of the Good”. You are the only one that sees who is in which Circle, and you can place people in multiple Circles. So your Circles don’t have to be perfect, just good enough. If you share a lot of private posts, concentrate on making sure that those more personal Circles are more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these approaches, you should find Circle management quick, and you won’t get mired down in Circle management for hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish I had this organization when I started on Google+ two weeks ago. By using some of these techniques from the beginning I would have made my life a lot easier. Over the next month I now have to go back and re-organize people and re-Circle them. I hope sharing these tips will make your use of Google+ simpler from the start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I expect that Google will be adding new features to make Google+ easier. For instance I’m hoping for #hashtags (the ability to tag posts into topic categories), favorites (the ability to tag posts into a persistent archive, hopefully with an option tag), ordering Circles, concentric Circles, and better integration with Google Reader. (I share my favorite blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/reader/shared/ChristopherA&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; at &amp;#0160;and my best of best articles and posts in &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ChristopherA/favorites&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Twitter Favorites&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;or &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/christophera&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Delicious&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any new online feature, people are finding out new things and coming up with new ideas every day. So what are &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; methods for organizing your Circles and social graph?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to follow me on Google+, I’m at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/about&#34;&gt;+Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#39;d like to comment using Google+, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/posts/2eYjBB2CpNm&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;public comment thread&lt;/a&gt; about this post.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you would like to subscribe to my Google+ posts in Google Reader, use my &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;feed://plusfeed.appspot.com/113059510043663667610&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlusFeed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts from my blog related to this post:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some recent high signal-to-noise blog posts on Google+ and/or managing your Circles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107631581023945167601/about&#34;&gt;+Matt Stratton&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattstratton.com/tech-tips/how-i-set-up-my-circles-in-google-plus&#34;&gt;How I Set Up My Circles in Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113551191017950459231/about&#34;&gt;+Anson Alex&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ansonalex.com/tutorials/managing-circles-in-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Guide to Working with Circles in Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/101746196094367799224/about&#34;&gt;+Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/?p=2616&#34;&gt;The promise of Google+ for organizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104681313125038107957/about&#34;&gt;+Sterling Ledet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.weteachthecoolstuff.com/2011/07/09/a-thought-on-circles-privacy-vs-relevance/&#34;&gt;A Thought on Google+ Circles – Privacy vs. Relevance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/118432652629200965858/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Dave Pollard&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtosavetheworld.ca/2011/07/11/google-plus-on-communities-circles-friendship-and-love/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google+: On Communities, Circles, Friendship and Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethkanter.org/np-google/&#34;&gt;Are You Going To Adopt Google+ for Professional Learning/Networking? Why or Why Not?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104181568670836761473/about&#34;&gt;+Damon Morda&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brandedclever.com/five-steps-to-configuring-privacy-on-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Five Steps to Configuring Privacy on Google Plus (+)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some quality recent public Google+ posts regarding Google+ or managing your Circles (be sure to look over the comments):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/about/&#34;&gt;+Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/posts/ghn6Bu6tsmM&#34;&gt;My tips for newer users of Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/1SdhSBqwAmA&#34;&gt;Where circles can go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/D9bRJCmjJRV&#34;&gt;Sharing Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/XHvCRURHidx&#34;&gt;Is Google plus public or private?It’s neither, and both!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/posts/DV8QxNzTxaF&#34;&gt;Insightful Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/about&#34;&gt;+Craig Kanalley&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/posts/52dmpNDbWtp&#34;&gt;Tips &amp;amp; Thoughts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/about/&#34;&gt;+Paul Goode&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/posts/W9CaNrwku3x&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Sketch on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on related to this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;personal circles&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the of personal limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;familiar strangers&lt;/a&gt; - those people you recognize by face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustration by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;, Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/102320045646237908121/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Elyn Andersson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;for their assistance with this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I really like the idea of using circles for social time management. One big problem I have with networks is that I feel committed (obligated?) to a certain, indistinct, level of communication - particularly with those people that social media has now kept me in &#39;contact&#39; with, and whom in the old days I would have lost touch with. The end result is always a big time defecit and multiple layers of guilt. The idea of being able to apply some kind of equitable rationing/priority to circles may be a bit geeky... but it&#39;s preferable to non-specific angst  ;0)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/grimbold&#34;&gt;Grimbold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I like your ideas; I&#39;ve also been trying to play about with the circles &amp; work out something that works for me.
How, however, do you manage to add people to them, when you have quite so many (looking at the second list with the 1.3 etc) - I can only see 1.5 rows of circles! (OK, I know you can add someone by right clicking &amp; going for the add to circle, but that&#39;s fiddly if you&#39;re block adding them!)
I&#39;ve also got in the (equivalent of the) me circle my &#39;other&#39; G+ account, that I&#39;ve been using to see the effect of things like extended circles. Which I do find useful.
Would be nice, if, at some point, rather than having &#39;stream&#39; it was possible to see in a single stream all the updates from a set of circles, rather than 1 or all. (Unless that&#39;s something I&#39;ve yet to find!)
(That, and I want boolean logic for them, so I can have everyone who is in both a &amp; b, but not a or b!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/emmadw&#34;&gt;Emmadw&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Kinds of Privacy</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2004 02:00:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been thinking about the nature of privacy a lot lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve long been associated with issues of preserving privacy. I helped with anti-Clipper Chip activism in the early 90s and supported various efforts to free cryptography such as PGP and other tools built with RSAREF from export control. However, my efforts in these areas wasn&#39;t really focused on privacy -- instead my focus was on issues of trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve always tried to be precise here. For instance, one of the uses of the SSL encryption software that I designed and sold at Consensus Development was to preserve privacy; however, I never sold it with privacy as a feature. Instead I clearly stated that SSL offered &#34;message integrity&#34;, &#34;confidentiality&#34; and &#34;authentication&#34;. Part of the reason that I never used the word privacy with SSL was that I felt that the concept of privacy was too overloaded -- or possibly orthogonal to issues of cryptographic security. Promising privacy was promising too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently issues of privacy have been coming up in my study of social software. It got started with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html&#34;&gt;my post about privacy issues in Orkut&lt;/a&gt; and a general &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;insecurity and discomfort&lt;/a&gt; with information made available in various social networking services. Later I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html&#34;&gt;handcrafting my FOAF&lt;/a&gt; which required me to re-think how and what information I wished to reveal about myself. More recently I was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html&#34;&gt;stung by Zero Degrees&lt;/a&gt; which still disturbs me greatly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this has stewed in my head until I arrived at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cfp2004.org&#34;&gt;Computers, Freedom and Privacy Conference&lt;/a&gt; this week here in Berkeley, where I met many of my friends and colleagues in the cryptographic security business, as well as advocates on issues of privacy in organizations such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eff.org&#34;&gt;EFF&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epic.org&#34;&gt;EPIC&lt;/a&gt;. My thoughts have now gelled sufficiently to make some observations about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people speak about privacy, they may actually be talking about very different forms of privacy: defensive privacy, human-rights privacy, personal privacy, and contextual privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive privacy&lt;/em&gt; is the first form: it&#39;s about protecting information about myself that makes me vulnerable or makes me feel at risk. This type of information can include things like my social security number, my credit report, or non-financial things such as my medical records or my home address. For some of my female friends this includes things like their photographs and email addresses. All of this information can be misused by other individuals or organizations in one way or another to mess up my life -- and in fact defensive privacy is usually centered around protecting this critical information from those singular individuals or organizations, be they con men, stalkers, or the Mafia. Most of the current privacy issues on the Internet seem to fall into this category. This form of privacy has also not fared well in the US courts -- for instance, in 1974 the Supreme Court decided that your bank records belong to the bank, to do with as they see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closely intersecting defensive privacy is the category of &lt;em&gt;human-rights privacy&lt;/em&gt;. When you are speaking with a European about privacy, this often is the type of privacy they are speaking of. This comes from their history: the Netherlands in the 1930s had a very comprehensive administrative census and registration of their own population, and this information was captured by the Nazis within the first three days of occupation. Thus Dutch Jews had the highest death rate (73 percent) of Jews residing in any occupied western European country -- far higher than the death rate among the Jewish population of Belgium (40 percent) and France (25 percent). Even the death rate in Germany was less then the Netherlands because the Jews there had avoided registration. (source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.findarticles.com/cf_dls/m2267/2_68/77187772/p4/article.jhtml&#34;&gt;The Dark Side of Numbers&lt;/a&gt;). Human-rights privacy differs from defensive privacy in that it is about how governments can abuse information, rather then individuals abusing information. I used to feel safe about human-rights privacy in the US, that there was no way that what happened in Europe could happen here, but now I have lost such confidence because of Bush and Ashcroft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third kind of privacy, &lt;em&gt;personal privacy&lt;/em&gt;, is more unique to the United States. It is what Supreme Court Justice Brandeis in 1890 called &#34;the right to be left alone&#34;. This form of privacy is often what the more Libertarian-oriented founders of the Internet mean when they talk about privacy. Personal privacy covers things like the &#34;do not call registry&#34;, the various rights to do as we please in our own houses -- such as view pornography or play S&amp;M games with our partners -- and the general right to not be interrupted or interfered with unnecessarily at home. This form of privacy has more basis in US law; the concept is based on an interpretation of the First, Fourth, and Fifth amendments of the US Constitution, but is not explicitly defined there. However, this form of privacy is guaranteed by the State of California Constitution which assures residents that they may pursue and obtain &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.privacy.ca.gov/code/declaration.htm&#34;&gt;safety, happiness, and privacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;em&gt;contextual privacy&lt;/em&gt; is what &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/&#34;&gt;Danah Boyd&lt;/a&gt; calls the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/04/14/why_privacy_issues_matter_to_me.html#004117&#34;&gt;ickiness factor&lt;/a&gt; in her blog, and also in her post at &lt;a href=http://www.corante.com/many/archives/2004/04/16/the_ickiness_factor.php&#34;&gt;Many-To-Many&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ickiness is the guttural reaction that makes you cringe, scrunch your nose or gasp &#34;ick&#34; simply because there’s something slightly off, something disconcerting, something not socially right about an interaction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p/&gt;This category is very difficult to define, and is easily confused with other forms of privacy, but I believe it has more to do with an inappropriate level of intimacy. An example of this is when I discovered that my professional colleagues on Orkut could see that I was in a committed relationship, and in turn I could see that some of them were in open marriages. I don&#39;t think there is very much harm that can come from this information being revealed, however, it was &#34;icky&#34; because it was an inappropriate level of intimacy for a professional context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All four of these forms of privacy can intersect -- for instance, Orkut allows you to reveal your sexual orientation, which could be used secretly by an employer to discriminate against you (defensive privacy), or by a future Ashcroftian government to violate your civil rights (human-rights privacy), might lead you to being bothered at home because of people who either agree with or disagree with your orientation (personal privacy), and often is inappropriate for casual professional acquaintances to be told about (contextual privacy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t think any of this answers the question of how to solve problems of privacy, but I do believe that it can help when you are discussing privacy to be sure that you try to convey and understand each others&#39; ideas of what privacy means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Your exploration of types of privacy has been posted on the Linking Integrity Blog.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://linkingintegrity.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Carolyn L Burke&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-23T09:03:03-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-23T09:03:03-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I came across this post looking for an information taxonomy in general and a taxonomy of identity in particular.
I&#39;d like to know if you have any thoughts on the subject - or your readers.
As a beginning:
Civil identity information
Social identity information
Role identity information
Biometric identity information
Transaction identity information
Thanks!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://drhassen.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;ebhdoc&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-06-01T10:20:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-06-01T10:20:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post RSA Conference Wrapup</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/post_rsa_confer.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2004 03:50:41 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/post_rsa_confer.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent most of last week at the RSA Conference in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like last year, I found little that excited me. I overheard from a convention staffer that they had 30% more attendees, so the conference is growing again, but my week there also reinforced my opinions regarding the industry as a whole as I describe in my previous blog posting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/security_crypto.html&#34;&gt;The Bad Business of Fear&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked a number of random people what they thought of the conference. Some agreed with me, saying that they were troubled by the lack of innovation. Others said that they actually liked it -- it showed that the industry was being run by businessmen finally, and not by geeks. Others said that it was just the inevitable maturation of an industry. Tim Oren wrote in his blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pacificavc.com/blog/2004/02/27.html#a565&#34;&gt;Due Diligence&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;blockquote&gt;Every year the show is less about cryptography per se. I&#39;m sure this has something to do with RSA&#39;s attempts to diversify as its patents expire, but I do think it reflects the state of the field. Crypto has become a standardized component of security solutions, and the biggest perceived threats are not in the privacy area.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hilight of the conference to me was hearing respected cryptographer Whitfield Diffie say to me that he had read my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/security_crypto.html&#34;&gt;The Bad Business of Fear&lt;/a&gt; and that he liked it. Apparently it had been sent to him by someone at Sun who had thought that it was saying many of the things that Diffie has been saying as well. Diffie said that he had some specific criticisms, so I hope that he&#39;ll comment here someday on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Caller-ID for Email&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big announcement of the week was that Microsoft will be be releasing their own spam solution, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://windows-help.net/cgi-bin/2004/7.08.cgi?70801&#34;&gt;Caller ID&lt;/a&gt; for email addresses, starting this summer in HotMail and in their mail servers. Basically the way this works is that every domain holder publishes inside their DNS records the IP addresses of any valid outbound email server. This information is stored using XML in a special signed format. After a mail is sent, the receiving system queries the DNS to confirm that the outbound server is not being spoofed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very similar technique to what a number of other companies are proposing, for instance AOL is backing a proposal called &lt;a href=&#34;http://spf.pobox.com/execsumm.html&#34;&gt;SPF (Sender Policy Framework)&lt;/a&gt; or sometimes &#34;Sender Permitted From&#34;, and Yahoo is backing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,4149,1430976,00.asp&#34;&gt;Domain Keys&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, Microsoft&#39;s Caller-ID proposal requires XML, which makes implementation much more complicated. It requires the entire email to be received by the server first, before looking up the DNS record, then validating a signature -- all of which introduces more burdens on the mail server. Lastly, this XML may exceed the 512-character limit for DNS requests, which can cause DNS servers to send via TCP rather then UDP, which may introduces even more uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is good to see that Microsoft, AOL and Yahoo are taking spam seriously, but I do worry that that the burden of supporting more then one of these standards may be significant. This could mean that only large corporations, educational institutions, and ISPs could host email, whereas small companies, third-world organizations, and individuals could not. I would prefer that one solution be broadly and easily adopted. &lt;font color=red&gt;&lt;s&gt;Daniel Goldman&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;Yakov Shafranovich&lt;/font&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shaftek.org/blog/archives/000061.html&#34;&gt;NetWizard&#39;s blog&lt;/a&gt; is also concerned about patent claims and lack of IETF participation:&lt;blockquote&gt;At the same time none of these proposals have been submitted to any standards bodies such as the &lt;A HREF=&#34;http://www.ietf.org&#34;&gt;IETF&lt;/A&gt;, and as a matter of fact &lt;A HREF=&#34;https://www1.ietf.org/mail-archive/working-groups/asrg/current/msg09082.html&#34;&gt;Microsoft was invited&lt;/A&gt; to submit &#34;Caller ID&#34; and participate in &lt;A HREF=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/ietf/04mar/marid.txt&#34;&gt;this week&#39;s meeting at the IETF on the subject&lt;/A&gt;, but &lt;A HREF=&#34;http://www.imc.org/ietf-mxcomp/mail-archive/msg00023.html&#34;&gt;they declined&lt;/A&gt;. At the same time the community had jumped on Caller ID&#39;s patent license by declaring a (and &lt;A HREF=&#34;http://www.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=04/02/26/1448253&amp;mode=thread&#34;&gt;a possible incompatibility with the GPL&lt;/A&gt;). Of course it remains to be seen what exactly does Caller ID claim to patent since RMX and other prior art existed at least since 1998, and if Caller ID ever makes it to the IETF, Microsoft will have to deal with &lt;A HREF=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3669.txt&#34;&gt;the new IPR guidelines (RFC 3669)&lt;/A&gt; which favor non-patented technologies.&lt;/blockquote&gt;I&#39;m also not convinced that even if these techniques are deployed (Gartner group &lt;a href=&#34;http://informationweek.securitypipeline.com/news/18201583&#34;&gt;predicts&lt;/a&gt; less then 25% will implement these in the next two years) that they will not return us to early 1990&#39;s levels of spam, only just slow down the onslaught. For instance, in a similar fashion to current WiFi war-chalking, a spammer could wait until an authenticated user logged in a mail server and hijack that connection. Unless the link is encrypted and authenticated, it is possible for a spammer to impersonate the legitimate user without anyone being the wiser. Related, these techniques do not necessarily help with the growing threat of &#34;phishing&#34; -- emails that lure unsuspecting users to enter credit card or bank account information into fake web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also concerned that all of these standards require some measure of public-key infrastructure, including management of public-keys, which many security analysts believe that we are not doing a good enough job now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some good thoughtful analysis of these three standards by Larry Seltzer of eWeek in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eweek.com/print_article/0,1761,a=120536,00.asp&#34;&gt;Who will Win the SMTP Authentication Wars&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;More Security in Windows XP SP2&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill Gates also discussed new security features in the upcoming Windows XP SP2. In addition to some interesting &#34;Active Protection Technology&#34; to prevent overflow attacks, he discussed built-in virus protection and an improved built-in firewall that also warns of outbound connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out in the hall I heard some people saying that announcement was a good basis for selling Symantec short, while others countered that Microsoft never gets these type of things right and there would always be business for Symantec. Companies that offer more minor features like preventing browser popups will be hurt. However, as these solutions are already free and ubiquitous, this is one of the few cases where I prefer for these to be in the default Microsoft install. However, I do worry for the smaller but more innovative security vendors like ZoneAlarm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sessions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years the sessions at RSA have become more managerial and corporate in nature, but there were a couple of good technical sessions that I attended or friends commented on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was pleased by the Cryptographer&#39;s Panel response to Bill Gates&#39; announcements: &#34;We have a lot of great levers in cryptography, but we&#39;re missing the OSes and platforms that can really serve our keys,&#34; said Ronald Rivest. &#34;Bill Gates didn&#39;t talk about simplifying things, but that&#39;s the only way we are going to get security. We&#39;re not smart enough to handle the complexity of this stuff. You have to get the complexity out of there,&#34; continued Paul Kocher. Whitfield Diffie criticized security the upcoming Windows Longhorn release because &#34;For the first time, you will have a PC that does NOT do what you tell it to.&#34; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cryptographer&#39;s Panel also spoke on the topic of electronic voting, and supported calls for paper ballots to supplement and verify votes cast with new electronic voting technology. Rivest cautioned &#34;We know only too well the difficulties of securing complex electronic systems.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also heard good things about the &#34;Hacking VM Machines&#34; and &#34;Analyzing Topologies of Trust&#34; sessions, and the closing keynote by PJ O&#39;Rouke, but I missed them -- anyone have any notes? Where there some other good sessions I missed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Exhibits&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exhibit floor was again a bit droll for me.  Like in previous years the floor was dominated by vendors selling rather high-end corporate systems that might have excited me more if I was in the market for one, but I was looking for less expensive systems for smaller businesses. Like last year there were lots of dedicated devices, such as firewalls, spam prevention, VPN and intrusion detection hardware, and fewer companies offering software to use with my existing hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did like some of the biometric hard drives, but investigating more deeply I just can&#39;t trust them yet. No one yet offers a good solution for redundant key storage yet for these, as a backup in case of a physical failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did see one company &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.authenex.com&#34;&gt;Authenex&lt;/a&gt; that was offering free USB keys that supposedly allow you to encrypt files on your system and email them to someone else with a different key -- it looks like some public key technique is being used, with the key serving as a pre-generated private key storage. More interestingly, they claim that if you register your USB key at their website, they can send you a replacement key that you can use to decrypt your old files. I&#39;ll have to do some more investigation of the technology behind this, and if they&#39;ve had adequate study by cryptographers that I trust. If they have, and they start offering storage on those keys as well, they may have something useful that I&#39;ll buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSA had an demo of it&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsasecurity.com/company/news/releases/pr.asp?doc_id=3376&#34;&gt;prototype RFID blocker tag&lt;/a&gt; that they suggest is a possible solution to some of the fears that some of us privacy advocates have been worrying about. &lt;a href=&#34;http://scottmace.typepad.com/imanager/2004/02/cool_demo_rsa_r.html&#34;&gt;Scott Mace&lt;/a&gt; has a good description of the demo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each booth visitor selects from one of three demo prescriptions -- &#34;tranquility pills,&#34; &#34;wisdom pills,&#34; or &#34;happiness pills.&#34; (I chose wisdom, naturally.) The RSA Labs crew requests a name from the visitor, then hands over an appropriately-tagged bottle (mine contained jellybeans). They scan the bottle on an RFID tabletop scanner and visitors see the details of the prescription, including type of prescription and patient&#39;s name. Then, they insert the bottle into an ordinary paper pharmacy bag that happens to contain a paper &#34;blocker tag&#34; that then blocks any attempt for an RFID reader to scan the bottle while it&#39;s in the bag.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Though a cool demo, I&#39;m not as confident that this solution will work. Now in addition to the previous &#34;foil bag&#34; theft techniques, what prevents someone from building one of these into a watch or a PDA? Sending a signal to burn-out the RFID is one of the other proposals out there, it has similar problems -- what if someone goes into a WalMart and burns-out every RFID in the place?
&lt;p&gt;RSA was also demoing its latest SecurID integration with Windows, which will extend the life of this security token for RSA customers for many years. I spoke to Scott Schnell, VP of Marketing, afterwards at a party and he explained to me some of the details of how they made it work with Windows laptops. Apparently the system will cache up to several weeks worth of SecurID information such that the laptop owner can use his SecurID token to log on to his laptop even though he is not connected to the network. I neat trick, though I&#39;d like to see some more security reviews before I&#39;d deploy it broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the most interesting, but least useful to me, was a booth for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.magiqtech.com/&#34;&gt;Magiq Technology&lt;/a&gt;, who offer a commercial quantum cryptography solution. Quantum cryptography is the ultimate in secret key exchange at a distance -- you can sort of say that the universe protects you from snoopers. However, you have to have a fiber-optic connection between the two devices, which limits its practicality. But it is still cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;NetWizard&#39;s blog is actually mine, not Daniel Goldman&#39;s (who is a good friend of mine). The patent issues important and in the ASRG which I co-chair, they have come up before with C/R patents held by MailBlocks (you can find some juice tidbits at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.solidmatrix.com/research/asrg/asrg-ipr.html).&#34;&gt;http://www.solidmatrix.com/research/asrg/asrg-ipr.html).&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.shaftek.org&#34;&gt;Yakov Shafranovich&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-05T13:09:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-05T13:09:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Sorry Yakov! I&#39;ve corrected the attribution above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-05T23:19:47-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-05T23:19:47-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/03/post_rsa_confer.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Security &amp; Cryptography: The Bad Business of Fear</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/security_crypto.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2004 14:12:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/security_crypto.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I head out next week to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://2004.rsaconference.com/&#34;&gt;RSA Conference&lt;/a&gt; I realized that it has been 13 years since I attended the first one. I remember fondly the potential and power of cryptography technology in 1991 -- public keys, digital certificates, new possibilities for privacy, digital cash, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 8 more years I left the compujter security industry on March 15, 1999. The computer security industry also seemed to be filled with as much potential as it did back in 1991. Amazon, EBay, and other Internet notables were still riding high, and driving before them the need for secure Internet transactions. The government&#39;s attempt to cripple the industry through their Clipper chip initiative was all but dead, and we were slowly winning the rights to export our technologies without severe and unnecessary government restrictions. We were beginning to truly see how Certificate Authorities worked in practical usage, and were coming up with plans for smaller, more efficient certs, to help bring security to wireless devices and set-top boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem strange that I left the industry at such a height, but I&#39;d accomplished my own personal goals. I helped midwife the startup of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.verisign.com&#34;&gt;VeriSign&lt;/a&gt;, and digital certificates were now broadly available for both servers and clients. I&#39;d helped fight Clipper, and freed RSAREF so that it could be used by Open Source software before the expiration of the patent. I&#39;d grown Consensus Development, a company I founded almost a decade before, from a small engineering house into the premiere SSL developer. I&#39;d lead the team that developed the SSL Reference version for Netscape, and had completed the IETF&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2246.txt&#34;&gt;RFC 2246&lt;/a&gt; that described the future of SSL called TLS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus I found myself at the heart of a burgeoning Internet commerce industry. When &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.certicom.com&#34;&gt;Certicom&lt;/a&gt;, a leading cryptography company, had expressed a desire to purchase my company, I considered the returns for my investors, the value to my employees -- I was pleased with the results, and agreed. So I made an exit from the security industry, and as part of my agreement with Certicom I signed a non-compete which gave them a few years&#39; head start before I dipped my foot back into the security industry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, five years more have gone by. My non-compete with Certicom has expired and for over a year I have slowly been easing my way back into the world of security and cryptography. I must admit, I was a bit uncertain at first. Five years ago I had seen the industry perched on the edge of the next big change. It had been prepared to secure the hundreds of new applications that were proliferating on the net; to broadly adopt TLS, the newest version of SSL; to really look at the practical applications of certificate authorities and recreate the entire concept as a second generation of ideas. I wondered how far behind I would be, if I&#39;d recognize the industry at all. Internet time had still been moving fast back in 1999 and I wasn&#39;t sure how many generations had gone by in the security industry. One, two, more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So last year I started attending security related conferences again, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/meetings/meetings.html&#34;&gt;IETF Meetings&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://2004.rsaconference.com/&#34;&gt;RSA Conference&lt;/a&gt;, and others. I was ready to come as a student, to soak up the new knowledge imparted in the talks and tutorials, to glory in the changes that the last five years had brought. Instead I discovered, almost nothing had changed. If anything, the industry had been moving backward, just a tiny bit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What had happened to an industry that just five years ago had been rapidly pushing forward the frontiers of technology? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, more important, how could it move forward? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The State of the Industry: Living off of Fear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I find the state of the security industry to be a bit sobering for its lack of momentum in recent years. This slowdown can be seen nowhere as easily as upon the exhibit floor of RSA Conference, the premiere conference for this industry, which I attended last year and will attend again next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking the floors of RSA last year, in the immense exhibit hall at the San Jose Convention Center, I did feel a sense of energy. The floor was still packed, and the carefully cut kiosks and the garish banners bespoke the millions put into the show by the exhibitors. The constant chatter was a deafening white noise, and whenever I veered too near a booth, there was a salesman very eager to tell me about his company&#39;s latest and greatest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, to a certain extent, that energy felt to me like a facade. There was nothing new; instead all the exhibitors were showing off the same technology that they were displaying five years ago. There was a bit of glitz and some extra chrome, perhaps a carefully redesigned product name, but beyond that there was a weird feeling of deja vu. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were the same old tools that we&#39;ve been using to deter hackers since the advent of the Morris Worm way back in 1989: products to detect intruders and safeguard your machines against them; firewalls; and VPNs. Maybe we&#39;ve gotten a little better at figuring out expert rules, maybe we&#39;ve improved our user interfaces, but these are slow, gradual upgrades, not quantum leaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email still seems to be the newest battlefield upon which security wars are being fought, and you could find any number of new anti-spam tools at RSA. The Bayesian filters are a new and interesting way to statistically classify spam, but at the core level they&#39;re a dynamic outgrowth of keyboard filters that have been around for as long as we&#39;ve been fighting unsolicited commercial email. RSA&#39;s big release of the year, Nightingale, was simply another way to protect sensitive online information, a competitor to Microsoft&#39;s Wallet technology. We had the ubiquitous hardware tokens too, and discussion of the recently approved AES encryption standard, but nothing dramatically new and exciting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose I shouldn&#39;t have been too surprised, based on my experiences at IETF a month before. Most of the Security Area working groups were still working on the same problems that they&#39;d been discussing five years before. S/MIME is pushing forward on yet another draft of a standard that has never been broadly deployed. IPSEC is similarly continuing to work on the same problems, now years old. TLS was widely implemented and specified, but not widely adopted -- the world still uses SSL 3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last year since those two conferences I had lunch with various professional colleagues that I had lost track of, continued to watch as a bystander the leading edge of security and cryptography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I overview the industry I have begun to feel that we&#39;d largely abandoned the most interesting and innovative security techniques that were being discussed just five years ago. What happened to alternative public key infrastructures? What happened to attribute or role certificates? What happened to &#34;authorization&#34; being the next step after &#34;authentication&#34;, or separating &#34;security&#34; from &#34;privacy&#34;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remarkably, if any of these topics are being considered, they seem to be moving outside of the traditional security industry. Such is the case with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=security&#34;&gt;SAML, the Security Assertion Markup Language&lt;/a&gt;, a branch of XML which seems to be doing some of the only work on attribute certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With so many technologies abandoned utterly, or else given up to another computer fields, we must ask: why are we stagnating, moving backward rather than forward? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fear: Outlining the Problem&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought, could it be the result of the dot-bomb and subsequent recession? Perhaps that is part of it, but we are in denial unless we face the deeper cause. If we go on as we are the security industry will not recover with the next boom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decline of the security industry is based upon a basic disconnect between the business world and the security world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the security industry we base our models of trust upon mathematics. We strive to continually push the envelope by codifying security and improving it. On the other hand the business industry bases its models of trust upon risk. It balances the risk of a bad outcome, the cost of that bad outcome, and the cost of reducing that risk. Even if a system is technically insecure, the business world will accept it if the risk of a security breach is low, the cost of a security breach is low, or the cost of closing that breach is high. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where our model is mathematics, theirs is economics. These two models worked well in tandem for quite a few years; the need for a security industry was initially obvious because of the totally undefined risks and the potentially high costs that were out there, waiting to be taken advantage of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, years later, we&#39;ve done our job too well. We&#39;ve taken all those undefined risks and codified them -- made them real and quantifiable. We&#39;ve offered real demonstrations of online security through years of ecommerce, and in doing so we&#39;ve proven lower rates of credit card fraud, and almost total proof from high-cost offline problems like extortion and bad reputation. We&#39;ve helped fill out business&#39; risk models and so shown when we were necessary and when weren&#39;t. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we have dug ourselves into a hole. Thus it shouldn&#39;t be surprising that the newer security technologies are stagnating ... because we&#39;ve carefully, cleverly, and constantly diminished our revenues by staying with a business model in which &#39;good enough&#39; security will become ever cheaper. We&#39;ve turned our security business into a cheaper alternative to insurance, where business only pay for security if their insurance premiums would otherwise be too high. As the bulk of the risk is now handled by old, cheap technology, what remains for new sales is not enough to keep us truly innovating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent statistics underline the decreasing value of innovative, new security to businesses. According to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gocsi.com/press/20030528.jhtml?_requestid=105732&#34;&gt;CSI/FBI 2003 Computer Crime and Security Survey&lt;/a&gt;, the annual cost of computer crime has decreased in almost every category. From 2001 to 2003, the cost for theft of proprietary information is down from $151.2M to $70.2M. System penetration by outsiders is down from $19.1M to $2.8M. Insider abuse of network access is down from $35.0M to $11.8M. The only computer crime up in dollar damage inflicted is denial-of-service attacks, a very small part of the security pie. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With costs due to computer crime plunging year after year, clearly companies are not incentivized to put money in new prevention technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To simplify, as long as the risks were unknown, we were in a business feeding off of &#39;fear&#39; and our security industry &#39;pie&#39; was growing. But as we and our customers both understand the risks better, and as we get better at mitigating those risks cheaply, this &#34;fear&#34; shrinks and thus the entire &#39;pie&#39; of the security industry becomes smaller. Yes, new &#39;threats&#39; keep on coming: denial-of-service, worms, spam, etc., but businesses understanding of past risks make them believe that these new risks can be solved and commodified in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the philosophy and culture of the business world is hundreds of years old, going back to at least the Italian merchants of the Renaissance, business isn&#39;t going to change its model of how business works. Thus, it is up to us to rework the basic beliefs and understanding of our security industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to get out of this hole we need to dramatically rethink how we approach, develop, and market security services. To do this requires us to reconsider our own security models, based upon a better understanding of core business models. Some possibilities: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#insurance&#34;&gt;Enter the Insurance Business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#reliabiliy&#34;&gt;Move into Reliability Improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#enabling&#34;&gt;Move into Enabling Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;insurance&#34;&gt;Solution #1: Entering the Insurance Business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entering the insurance business is an old idea. It was once an important part of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.verisign.com&#34;&gt;Verisign&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; business plan, and no doubt of others as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its simplest level, we can enter the insurance business by offering a guarantee against damages with a product. The main benefit of this approach is that it lets us approach security in a more rational and realistic fashion. No longer do we have to engage in an endless quest for improved security, no matter how small the risk. Instead we can assess our risks and prepare ourselves to accept manageable losses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are risks implicit in this solution as well. For the most part, those of us in the security industry are unfamiliar with the insurance business model, and thus we&#39;re entering particularly uncharted waters. In addition, we need to understand that some losses will be huge and unavoidable, such as was the case with the Code Red worm. We thus need to create business models that are acceptable to our customers, but which do not leave us entirely liable for the next utterly unforeseen worm which gets set loose on the Internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may also be some limitations with this particular model, if the valuations of security companies are too low to insure the losses of a large corporation, such as a GM. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we need to ask ourselves the question: &#34;What value does insured security provide over simple insurance?&#34; I suspect there are some real values to customers in saved productivity and time, but further market research would be required to truly assess this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A security company could offset most of these risks by a partnership with an insurance company or another business within the insurance industry. We would need deep reserves and to work together with imaginative actuaries. Together we could offer insurance against the damages of security breaches. We would be the guardians against break-ins and the fixers if they did occur. The insurance company would help estimate risks, collect premiums and pay. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we chose to go it alone, we could offer risk mitigation services to insurance companies. We would guard and provide disaster mitigation services for a monthly premium. For example, when offering an anti-breakin security system, we could offer a guarantee to rebuild all certified systems if an intrusion does occur. This way we would take some, but not all, of the risks. Perhaps our presence would reduce insurance premiums enough to pay for our fees. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, despite potential risks, I believe that using an insurance model is a strong possibility for the security industry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;reliability&#34;&gt;Solution #2: Improving Reliability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of us in the security business may feel like we are already providing reliability, because many of our products prevent catastrophic risks due to break-in, theft, and other malevolent acts. However, what we generally tend to offer is data security, not data reliability. Perhaps paradoxically, at the more personal, day-to-day level, the security industry has actually reduced data reliability in the name of improved data security. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can personally testify to this fact because I have, recently, lost data due to security. I encrypted a directory in Windows XP, then was later forced to rebuild my system. Apparently some of the required info to decrypt the directory was stored in some unrecoverable registry entry, because I can no longer access it. The data is totally secure, but also unavailable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This anecdote isn&#39;t unusual for the security industry. Forgotten keys can often cause cryptographic-related data loss. Likewise, VPNs and firewalls introduce single points of failure into networks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSA&#39;s Nightingale technology of last year is a fairly standard security-based technology. It uses &#34;secret-splitting&#34; technology to divide sensitive data among two different locations, thus removing what RSA calls &#34;a single point of compromise&#34;; you can&#39;t get access to the data unless you compromise two machines. Clearly, there is improved data security. However it raises the same old problem of data reliability, because now data can be lost if either of two servers is lost. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improving reliability of extant security protocols is a good move forward in this expansion of the industry. For example in a classic cryptography situation we might unlock data with multiple secrets, but only require a set number of those secrets to unlock the data, not all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a company who is encrypting some of their most sensitive sales and marketing data. Ten company officers might each possess a secret which together can be used to decrypt all the data. However, this introduces a clear reliability problem, as the departure of any officer could leave all sales and marketing data unreadable. (Likewise, just restricting this data access to one specific secret, such as that of the VP of Sales, introduces this single-point-of-failure condition.) Instead we could offer a high reliability, but secure situation where any five (of ten) secrets together could decrypt the data. Therefore, if an individual officer disappears, leaves for a rival company, or otherwise makes his secret unavailable, not only can he himself not access the data alone, but even if he leaves with the secret the remainder of the company&#39;s access is unaffected. And, if a company didn&#39;t think that &#34;5 of 10&#34; executive was the right number, they could instead only require &#34;3 of 10&#34; to decrypt the data ... or &#34;7&#34; or &#34;9&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By thinking in this new methodology, by measuring security against reliability, we can offer our customers real choices and let them each choose the level of security that works best for them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the underlying bases of cryptography let us go a step further than this. Even without considering security implications, we can make use of our existing cryptographic algorithms in order to allow for more reliable access to and retrieval of all sorts of data. In other words, we can offer protection against not just hackers, but also backup errors, system crashes, and other catastrophic failures that are actually much more likely to affect the average user than an Internet security breach is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/ips-charter.html&#34;&gt;iSCSI&lt;/a&gt;, a remote SCSI protocol, offers very good potential for interaction with cryptography. A redundancy caching technique, somewhat like RAID 5, could be integrated with a secret share system where, e.g., the data could be read as long as 80% of the remote drives (and thus their keys) could be accessed; this allows for a very high reliability storage system because individual storage drives could be distantly located, and at the same time uses cryptographic techniques to offset reliability problems that could potentially be caused by the uncertain and fluid nature of Internet connectivity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even issues like load balancing and methods to deal with machine down-time might all be improved by some of our cryptographic techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;enabling&#34;&gt;Solution #3: Leaving Behind Fear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In talking about insurance and reliability I feel like I&#39;m largely expanding upon a fairly well-known and conservative way of using cryptography. These are good first steps for companies that wish to move forward in a cryptography market that is shrinking due to our own success, but they&#39;re not necessarily enough for a major breakout into revenue sources that will make this once again an exciting industry from a business point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is required, I believe, is a major paradigm shift. We need to leave the whole business of fear behind and instead embrace a new model: using cryptography to enable business rather than to prevent harm. We need to add value by making it possible to do profitable business in ways that are impossible today. There are, fortunately, many cryptographic opportunities, if we only consider them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptography can be used to make business processes faster and more efficient. With tools derived from cryptography, executives can delegate more efficiently and introduce better checks and balances. They can implement improved decision systems. Entrepreneurs can create improved auction systems. Nick Szabo is one of the few developers who has really investigated this area, through his work on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.firstmonday.dk/issues/issue2_9/szabo/&#34;&gt;Smart Contracts&lt;/a&gt;. He has suggested ways to create digital bearer certificates, and has contemplated some interesting secure auctioning techniques and even digital liens. Expanding upon his possibilities we can view the ultimate Smart Contract as a sort of Smart Property. Why not form a corporation on the fly with digital stock certificates, allow it to engage in its creative work, then pay out its investors and workers and dissolve? With new security paradigms, this is all possible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federated identity is another area for potential expansion. Secure, federated identities could offer many benefits for consumers. Imagine being able to visit a third-party seller on the Internet, automatically charge a sale to your Amazon account, then automatically ship it to your standard address, all through a single secured identity token. Federated network identity also has real applicability in the business world, as is shown by the work being done by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projectliberty.org/&#34;&gt;Liberty Alliance&lt;/a&gt;. Through a business system like this, an auto parts manufacturer could offer his products to General Motors as part of a larger bid, all without having to specifically arrange identity with GM itself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are notable challenges in the area of federated identity -- challenges which a new-paradigm security industry could lead the way in solving. Distinctions must be made regarding various levels of identity security, so that, e.g., your VPN couldn&#39;t be accessed if someone gained access to your Amazon password. In addition there are real concerns from users about controlling their user information, due to worries over spam and privacy; some users, for examples, might not want information about their politics, sexuality, or interests federated with information about their family or job. For instance do we really want our information on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt; to be used by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com&#34;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;?. These challenges demonstrate why federated identity is still a leading edge possibility for the security industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond business processes and federated identity there are many other areas that the security industry should be considering, as it moves beyond the business of fear. The whole idea of Public Key Infrastructures should perhaps be rethought, and maybe we should resuscitate lost technologies such as Attribute Certificates, and some of the ideas such as local name spaces as in described Rivest&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://theory.lcs.mit.edu/~cis/sdsi.html&#34;&gt;SDSI&lt;/a&gt;. There are also some interesting possibilities for trusted peer-to-peer environments that can be dynamically expanded on the fly. The possibilities are only limited by our imagination, if we can just think beyond current possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already seen the first wave of security technology; now we need to initiate a second, for I believe with the next wave the best is yet to come.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Just thought I would comment that  in building actuarial tables, insurance companies have a relatively small set of policy-holder behaviors and traits. Auto insurance underwriters look at  age, vehicle model and model year, zip code, driving history, and maybe a few more traits. How do you even start to build a table for the computer industry? You&#39;re running Windows? Fine, double your premiums. You&#39;re running Windows 95? Great, double them again. You haven&#39;t updated your router firmware in three months? Well... what does that do the measure of risk? Anything?
I&#39;ve always really liked the idea of IT insurance as a way to drive effective, practical security protections, but  I think we&#39;re light-years away from collecting enough information to build a reliable actuarial table.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.cryptonomicon.net/&#34;&gt;Matthew S. Hamrick&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-03T14:30:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-03T14:30:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I enjoyed this article.
The RSA expo floor really makes me feel sad nowadays.  It has really driven home the lesson that security is not, as I once believed, a tool that naturally lends itself to increasing freedom.  Instead, like all tools, it cuts either way depending on the hand that guides it.
I remain hopeful that capability access control will be deployed and will enable, in Mark Miller&#39;s phrase, &#34;cooperation without vulnerability&#34;.  The concept of mutually untrusting code (operating on behalf of mutually untrusting people) cooperating in a single address space is a paradigm that the MUD culture has been practicing for at least a decade and that the Java culture is likely to discover in 2004.
The increasing importance of virtualization, Trusted/Treacherous Computing, and the like also lead us closer to this paradigm.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://zooko.com/log.html&#34;&gt;Zooko O&#39;Whielacronx&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-04T05:48:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-04T05:48:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
So then one day this guy discovers the answer to the Reimann Conjecture and now Fear and risk are en vogue again. I was curious what you think might be the replacement for prime number pki?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Joe&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-09-07T06:23:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-09-07T06:23:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/02/security_crypto.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Advice to Social Networking Services</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2004 11:39:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have now had CEOs of three different social networks send me emails asking me to compare Orkut to their service. I&#39;ve not had a chance to dig deeply into good answers for each specific one, but I did have some general advice that I wanted to offer given my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;recent experiences with Orkut.com&lt;/a&gt;, and my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html&#34;&gt;evaluation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/followup_to_eva.html&#34;&gt;followup&lt;/a&gt; on various social networking services in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Privacy&lt;/h4&gt;
First, be extremely careful about privacy issues. For some of you outside the US, you may not know about what has been going on in the area of identity theft, but it has become a significant problem. I am not a privacy fanatic, but I am concerned that social networking services encourage people to reveal too much information too broadly, and that this will be someday be taken advantage of by identity thieves. For instance, many services ask for birthday and reveal it to everyone. You can ask for the birthday, but don&#39;t display it -- give the person&#39;s age, or birth month, but don&#39;t give the full info. I personally am particularly wary of billing address, billing zip code, birthday, and potential common security questions like name of pet, mother&#39;s maiden name, etc. These are in addition to the obvious targets of identity theft like SSN, full name, and account numbers.
&lt;p&gt;Orkut&#39;s interface for selectively allowing some fields to be visible &#34;only to myself&#34;, &#34;to friends&#34;, or to &#34;friends of friends&#34; is nice, but I wish it was for all fields. I also think every field by default should be set to &#34;only to myself&#34;. In fact, all security parameters should default to reveal the least information, and have the tightest limits -- allow the user to open selectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are going to support all different kinds of social networks (dating, friendships, activities, business) consider finding ways to make sure that those people who are not using the service for dating are not asked for that info, and don&#39;t see it for others who are dating. People who are only using it for dating shouldn&#39;t see business info. If someone is using a service for all types of relationships, allow people to selectively set what they reveal to each group, say two columns of &#34;only to connections who are dating&#34; or &#34;only to business connections&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never reveal someone&#39;s email address or other critical information without them knowing about it. In particular there are issues with emails sent among members. The only safe way is to do redirection through your site (although that will cost you bandwidth.) But if you can&#39;t do that, then just tell people &#34;your email will be revealed if you do this&#34; -- that is enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard on your TOS and Privacy terms. Don&#39;t let your lawyers rule you here too much -- find some way to get your principles out there and still cover yourself against problems. Make all the personal information that people give you be their information -- they are only leasing it to you temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make it easy for someone to quit the system. Maybe offer to them to export their information in case they want to rejoin later, and give them an opportunity to send a last message to any connections they may have. Be friendly at all times, and as the market shakes out they may come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Connections &amp; Invites&lt;/h4&gt;
If possible, find some other way to call the connections between people &#34;friends&#34; -- maybe even use a unique trademarkable term. There is some power in the emotions behind the word friends that helps with the virus-like nature of social networking software, but I think in the long term it is a bad idea. LinkedIn and Spoke use the word connections which sounds too mechanical, but I think it is better then &#34;friends&#34;.
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t encourage the &#34;how many friends do my friends have&#34; game. It sets up bad behaviors, and as you grow you don&#39;t want to have barriers of entry to new people who feel that they can&#39;t compete in that game. This means don&#39;t sort friends or groups etc. by the number of friends they have by default -- it can be an option, but just not be default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t encourage people to by default upload their address book. Have that feature be off of some optional utility page. Have the default option for it to just scan for people that are already members of your system and to forget the rest -- that is effectively what I do with systems that ask for address book information, and they make it hard for me to do so. Don&#39;t store people&#39;s address information for them unless you can sync them with people&#39;s personal contact books -- save that for version 2.0, not 1.0 beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t focus on people contacting new people that are not already their connections. It is not the number of connections, but the quality. Instead, focus on helping people with their weak connections. It is &#39;reconnection&#39; that is the most powerful feature of these social network services, not new connections. You can also help with &#34;triage&#34; -- how do I maximize the value of my existing weak connections with the least effort?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow people to opt-out with a custom message. What this means is that if someone sends an email to someone who has opted out, they will get something like. &#34;Thanks for inviting me to Orkut -- I&#39;ve decided for now not to join, but you can find me on Tribe.&#34; However, keep a list of people who have tried to connect to that opted-out user, and if that user does change their mind later, it will make it easier for them to have an initial list of friends that may already be on the service. Yes, I know that this risks sending people to other services, but there are so many now that you can get good buzz by doing the right thing, and recovering those people later when they have confidence in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to have better methods of handling invites from unknowns without saying no. For instance &#34;I&#39;m not sure I know you, have I forgotten?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related, don&#39;t fill out default text for invitations and other request forms -- force people to put something personal into the request, don&#39;t allow it to be blank. Never do what Orkut does and not give the opportunity to offer text when you invite someone who is already on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid anything beyond friends of friends as a primary part of your service. It bugs me that I see by default 3 degrees away in many services -- 2 degrees should be max by default, as that is the level that real referral can work. 3 degrees is too far for users to trust (though it can be optional for some purposes, or useful internally.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=6080f857- 4784-4679-8e41-c6881ed933ce&#34;&gt;Friendship Circle&lt;/a&gt; may also be a good idea, though perhaps how you classify people should be private. You may mark someone as being &#34;family&#34; &#34;intimate&#34; or &#34;acquaintance&#34; or &#34;business&#34;, or whatever, however, no one else should see that; they should just see &#34;connection&#34; unless they have named you, and you in turn should not say that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Profiles&lt;/h4&gt;
Find some better way then simple lists to do profiles. Someone&#39;s profile needs to express the richness of who they are -- it also needs to change and grow and flow over time, so make it easy for people to annotate and grow over time. Consider asking for only a few things at first, not make the process of filling out the profile feel daunting, then after each login prompt them to add one small thing that is useful based on how they used the service recently. For instance &#34;You have joined the AnyoneButBush2004 group -- do you want to enter information to share with others about your political interests?&#34;.
&lt;p&gt;Right now lots of people are experimenting on their blog sidebars how best to profile themselves -- learn from them. Look at hundreds of examples, look for patterns beyond the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow people to have multiple affiliations, whether they be work or play. I&#39;m a bad edge case personally, with too many hats to name, but almost everyone I know has at least two professional hats &#34;Sysadmin by day, Writer by night&#34;, &#34;Laywer on weekdays, Carpenter on weekends&#34; , as well as several affiliation hats &#34;Bay Area Costumer Guild president, member of League of Women Voters&#34;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now LinkedIn has the best looking professional profile, but it is still hard for some people to use. I like LinkedIn&#39;s use of multiple professional affiliations, however, I wish I could mark some as major or minor; for instance, there is a big difference between being an Advisor to MG Taylor and being CEO of Consensus. It also doesn&#39;t handle professional associations and lesser affiliations, much less non-professional affiliations and interests. Also, being able to arbitrarily order them would be nice, LinkedIn does it by date which can make for some confusing emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reputation &amp; Endorsements&lt;/h4&gt;
Be very careful of the design of rating systems and reputation systems. They are extremely difficult to design well, as they too often can be gamed, or fall into reciprocity such that they are meaningless. My personal advice is just don&#39;t do it at first -- save it for a 2.0 version of the product, not 1.0 beta. If you are going to do it now, really study it -- there is a lot of good academic research on issues of reputation. It can be hard to slog through but it is worth it. Offer a grant to Danah&#39;s school for them to do research for you on the topic.
&lt;p&gt;Endorsements are a best way of doing reputation for now. They is also is imperfect and vulnerable to reciprocity games, however, as least you can see if two people are playing that game just by looking at the endorser and endorsee. If you find too much reciprocity you can basically ignore both players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow endorsements at a more granular level. For instance, if you are offering dating and professional information, segregate the endorsements. Even more ideally, do like LinkedIn and allow endorsements of relatively small things in a profile, for instance &#34;I really enjoy Chris&#39; blog&#34; against the blog profile item, and &#34;I like what Chris says about the environment&#34; against my affiliation with a group. Consider allowing endorsements of groups: &#34;Of the three groups here on Wiki, I find this one fits me the best&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can afford it, consider hiring a game designer from the online game industry who understands behavior incentives in online games. If you can&#39;t, study it. Part of the reason why EverQuest is the largest MMPORG is because it incentivizes certain kinds of social behaviors. In fact, it could be considered to be a type of social network service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Launch &amp; Support&lt;/h4&gt;
Be careful with your beta launch -- a culture for a community forms in the first few weeks, and our experience from online games is that the nature of this culture can make or break a project. Find ways to encourage the kinds of behaviors you want, and discourage those that you don&#39;t.
&lt;p&gt;Be very careful of labeling people who are gaming your product in ways you don&#39;t like. Being in Orkut&#39;s &#39;jail&#39; is almost becoming a badge of honor. There is no reason why people who invite too many friends to join, submit too many posts to forums, or sends too many messages to friends of friends, should be put under the same label as those people who put child pornography up on your system and thus you&#39;ve banned them. Instead, slow down the overly active people, just say in advance &#34;If you invite this number of people, you may not invite more people for 24 hours, do you want to continue?&#34;, or &#34;If you invite this person, you must wait an hour before inviting another.&#34;, etc. Also, if you do lock people out of a feature, don&#39;t lock them out of all features, just the one that they are over-using. If someone gets locked out of lots of features at the same time, then they should be looked at for possibly banning, but not if they are doing just one thing -- you want to encourage their enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you give feedback to anyone that tries to be helpful, for instance in reporting a bug. Ideally public reports should be encouraged public (as this encourages other people to be helpful) but even private reports should be encouraged, and as promptly as possible including &#34;Thanks for taking time to write up this, we are logged this problem and hope to get to it as soon as we can given limited resources.&#34; Find other ways to give feedback, such as a weekly report, or a group developers blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create multiple stages for your beta, for instance &#34;profile features beta&#34;, &#34;group features beta&#34;, &#34;scaling beta&#34;, &#34;load beta&#34;, etc. Tell people in your beta what you want to hear about and not hear at each stage. As each stage ends, find some way to publically thank those who made the biggest difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set up a bug tracking system like TypePad has (like Bugzilla but hugely simpler to use). From help menu at the top you can click to post a new report, see all open reports, or see all closed reports. Every help page can have at the bottom to open a report on that topic. If anything goes wrong there (404, various system error messages, etc) you should give you an opportunity to open a report. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Features&lt;/h4&gt;
Figure out how to use RSS everywhere for input and output -- if Orkut or Tribe&#39;s group features supported RSS feeds, they could be very powerful competition to the hugely funded Friendster. Figure out how to use trackbacks with your system, and make them simpler for users. Make group bookmarks and other lists available as OPML. I&#39;m not a huge fan of FOAF yet, but figure out how to use it anyhow (and maybe vCards) until something better comes along, if nothing else but allow someone to import it and export it.
&lt;p&gt;My personal take is that if you can combine a substantial number of these &lt;br /&gt;
features, you could have a great product that gives the others a run for the &lt;br /&gt;
money:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Offering intentional groups (like Tribe and Orkut) is essential. It is Friendster&#39;s and LinkedIn&#39;s weakest link.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eVite/Meetup style invitations for both private functions (come to my birthday party), friend functions (anyone near 00301 want to have lunch Thursday?) and groups (Let&#39;s all meet for dinner next week to discuss this).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to import via RSS the recent items from my blog to my profile page&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional blogging-style home pages (FunChain &amp; Live Journal) for those who don&#39;t already have blogs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended family support as an explicit type of group, grandmother, mother, child in college&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Couples can be a form of a group also&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better ways to organize groups of groups&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better support for user-optional presence &#34;There are members of this group who are reading it right now who have said that they are available online to members to this group, 3 via Skype, 12 via AIM&#34;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=94333937-ecd8-4d08-994d-7f4c96c523dd&#34;&gt;Permachat&lt;/a&gt; at a group level is an interesting idea. I hate that I can&#39;t see chat text before the point I logged in&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of group management support, for instance:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ability to have multiple admins (eGroups, Live Journal)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group moderation (Slashdot, Kuro5hin, Advogato, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional group shared links (eGroups)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional group shared calendar (eGroups)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polling inside groups (no one that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invitation or approval of entry by different methods, such as by vote, by 1 reference from existing member, etc. (none that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to merge groups (none that I know of) &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wiki-style areas available for groups (no one that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine all the above with good innovative RSS and optionally Atom (FunChain, SocialText)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports the various blog submission APIs for blogs, wiki, and groups (none that I know of)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a great job for those who don&#39;t use RSS and those APIs to use email instead, including email submission (you can mail pages to a SocialText wiki)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to be federated, i.e. I could still use my existing blog (you just mirror it), RSS aggregation, my FOAF file could be synced, you sync with my addressbook at Yahoo, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Business Models&lt;/h4&gt;
Business models for social networking services is going to be one of the biggest issues. Even those social networking sites with lots of money behind them are going to have difficulty because there are so many.
&lt;p&gt;The paid subscriber model is probably dead until some of the VC funded startups go out of business. Advertising can be a good model, but be careful not to make it obtrusive -- remember, Google has made good money with very simple ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t have VC funding, find ways to co-opt partners -- build from the beginning support for Google AdSense and Adwords, Amazon APIs, etc. If you are small, consider federating with another company. Figure out what you can do to differentiate yourself from both your competitors and partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t be evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Me&lt;/h4&gt;
I am interested in getting more professionally involved with social software. I think we are still in Apple II days of social software -- we see the promise of things to come, but we are still typing in ALL CAPS. Given the overfunding in this field, my own ability to start a company as an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alacrityventures.com&#34;&gt;angel investor&lt;/a&gt; is insufficient, so I&#39;m looking to partner with others. I&#39;ve been involved with online communities, groupware, collaboration, and security for over 20 years. If you are interested in an executive in this area, see my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;profile on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Some notes:
a) On privacy -- the list of people who tried to reach you is two-edged,
you may want to point that out, because it gathers my list of friends,
and somebody else might come and get it, but it is pretty useful.
b) All these ideas and many others are good, and I have my own lists
of useful features,  but there&#39;s some huge feature creep and it will
be tough for the people doing this software to cherry pick.
c) I have notes in the orkut forum (I presume you posted this there)
about dealing with people you don&#39;t remember.  It doesn&#39;t work to force
me to send them a note saying &#34;where do I know you from?&#34; because if
you forgot them it&#39;s still embarassing.   You need to establish a principle
in advance that people doing an invite include where they know you from.
Unless they are intimate friends.
d) On dating/non-dating, I agree that we don&#39;t want to see that our
business associate is in an open marriage.  However I am not sure the
moded UI (you are either in biz mode or dating mode) will fly.  I had
big plans for such modes, on backburner for now.
A better idea would be to only show you dating info on people who are
potential dates.   Ie. if you are an M seeking F, you only see dating
info of F seeking Ms.  People want the serendipity of knowing, &#34;Oh, that
women I met at the conference is single and looking?&#34;
Best of all it doesn&#39;t require new UI.
The other big thing with Orkut is going to be the FoF spam.  The mail
volume must be limited some way.  We&#39;ve got many thousands of FoF it
seems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ideas.4brad.com&#34;&gt;Brad Templeton&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-03T14:24:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-03T14:24:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Good advice overall.  You might want to take a fast look at how phpbb does polls (re your &#34;polling inside groups&#34; note).  It&#39;s integrated into the comment posting interface so you can very quickly turn any entry into a poll, with a few simple options.
I&#39;d also be interested in seeing your comments on pay vs. free membership options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://web.media.mit.edu/~wex/&#34;&gt;Alan Wexelblat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-04T07:40:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-04T07:40:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Fantastic post, Christopher.  I&#39;ll never again claim you only flog Orkut; you&#39;re very fair and constructive with your observations, too!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ifindkarma.typepad.com/relax/&#34;&gt;Adam Rifkin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-07T13:38:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-07T13:38:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What do you think about the political applications of friendster-like sites?  Think how it helps solve the problems associated with the ghetto email petitions of the past, and how it could create a non-intrusive, viral fundraising medium.  Do you agree with me?
Given the multiple kinds of ways that people want to use social software (e.g., business networking, dating, politics), will there be specific sites for each kind of activity or will there be some sharing model?
Anyway, we&#39;re thinking about leveraging this trend and it would be helpful to get your thoughts as we consider build vs. partnering, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.e-thePeople.org&#34;&gt;Michael Weiksner&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-09T14:54:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-09T14:54:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;FriendBlend is another new social networking site you might want to take a look at - it combines match-making with blogs, moblogs, online photo sharing and a lot of the group features such as polling and quizes that you mention. Great post!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.friendblend.com&#34;&gt;David Jenness&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-20T18:04:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-20T18:04:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;another cool site to check out is for College &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.collegester.com&#34;&gt; Social Networking&lt;/a&gt; is http://www.collegester.com . Also a hip site for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lloydbankster.com&#34;&gt;Lloyd Banks&lt;/a&gt; is worth peaking at..... I&#39;ve seen the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bestnetsoftware.com&#34;&gt;Social Networking Software&lt;/a&gt; for sell at http://www.bestnetsoftware.com for those interested in starting their own social networking site or community!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.collegester.com&#34;&gt;Social Networking&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-09T07:42:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-09T07:42:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;my friend http://www.ryanleslie.com is planning a social networking site for musicians
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.tcgss.org&#34;&gt;ricky&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-21T10:50:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-21T10:50:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
http://www.egrupos.com/
is virtually unknown in the US but becoming very popular in Spain and Latin America, and they&#39;re becoming a trend-setter, integrating email groups (a la YahooGroup but perhaps even more customizable), social networking tools and online auctions. A weird combination that however it seems to be working ok so far.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Pepe B.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-15T12:01:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-15T12:01:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is kind of a neat personals site that&#39;s looking to add in social network functionality. Email through the site if you&#39;re interested in partnerships.
http://www.itsjustcoffee.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.itsjustcoffee.com&#34;&gt;ItsJustCoffee&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-12-03T16:48:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-12-03T16:48:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi...I put up a site dedicated to the social networking niche of gated online communities at
http://www.gatedonlinecommunities.com
Any comments on the subject are appreciated!
Thanks Marc
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.gatedonlinecommunities.com&#34;&gt;Marc L GatedOnlineCommunities.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-10-24T14:24:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-10-24T14:24:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Eerst Europa Doelstellingen: De Ci2i Verzekering (Ci2i) zal het nummer een gebrandmerkte pan Europese commoditized online verzekeringsmakelaar door 2010 zijn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.firsteuropa.nl&#34;&gt;Alice Mike&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-12-03T22:37:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-12-03T22:37:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for posting this your section about privacy is very useful. There are some issues regarding privacy and social networking sites that have not been addressed properly and may cause the downfall of social networking sites such as stalkers and identity fraudsters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://scribblesheet.co.uk/article/can_i_have_my_life_back_please&#34;&gt;Vince&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-27T14:15:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-27T14:15:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 17:12:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another Orkut user and I have confirmed a privacy hole in Orkut whenever you send a message to someone via Orkut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, whenever I send a message to anyone in the system that is forwarded by email, in the message headers it will read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
From: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;member@orkut.com&amp;gt;
Reply-To: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;christophera@alacritymanagement.com&gt;;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone reads the message in their email software, the &#34;From:&#34; line will be my name but the fake email of &amp;lt;member@orkut.com&amp;gt; -- however, when you reply to it, it will use my real email address. This appears to happen whether or not I have my privacy settings to reveal my email address. For instance, I can set it so that no one (not friends, not friends of friends, only myself) can see my email address, but the address will still be revealed when I send an email&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had reported what I thought was a security flaw when you emailed to &#34;friends of friends&#34; a couple of days ago, but I was mistaken, as I reported in my blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;Insecurity at Orkut&lt;/a&gt;.  However, as I didn&#39;t want risk &#34;crying wolf&#34; this time, so my friend and I triple checked this and have confirmed this privacy flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;They only way that I know of to avoid this is in your prefences to set that all of your messages should be sent to you via the web, not email.&lt;/s&gt; [Updated: I was wrong, there is no way currently to avoid this other then not using an email address you care about.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some that will say that this is a feature, i.e. when using email &#34;what good is communicating with someone if there is no chance of a response&#34; -- my answer to this is that an expectation has been set that email addresses can remain private, and if this is to be a feature, then users should be warned before sending an email &#34;Your email address user@domain will be revealed when you send this.&#34; More ideally, like other social networking services, the &#34;Reply-to:&#34; should be to a special email address at Orkut that will do the lookup and forward appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the essential problems that Orkut needs to fix very soon is how to report problems like these, and if you are trying to help how to know that these problems exist. I want my criticism to be constructive, but it is very hard when you have no idea what is the best way to offer feedback. I&#39;ve had many people reply to me in my blog and via email that they feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, right now there are 6 Orkut groups about Orkut:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=617&#34;&gt;What Should Orkut Do?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=2026&#34;&gt;Flaws in Orkut&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=3982&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=1289&#34;&gt;Orkut Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=781&#34;&gt;Orkut: Tips, Feedback, ?&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=4556&#34;&gt;Orkut Members&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which groups should I post this problem to? Which will will be read by the Orkut staff?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;ve said in another of my blog postings &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html&#34;&gt;Followup on Orkut&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;blockquote&gt;Part of the problem is that even though Orkut is in beta, there is no organized feedback system. For instance they could offer a forum read by the developers, or even better a bug/issues tracking system like TypePad has, or Bugzilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, feedback is a two-way street -- they could do a lot by offering a developers daily blog, or some type of regular announcement of what feature they wanted beta testers to test that day, or even acknowledgement &#34;we already know that is an issue&#34;. Also, they need to show respect for good feedback publicly, as that will encourage more good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is happening at this time, which means that people get frustrated, which also makes it easy rumors and conspiracy to spread. I want to be a constructive critic, but Orkut makes it hard for me to be so.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I recommend that these type of bug reports go into &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Community.aspx?cmm=6048&#34;&gt;Orkut Beta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;. Why not in &#34;Flaws in Orkut&#34; or in one of the other groups? Because I feel that focusing on &#39;Flaws&#39; is too strongly negative, and none of the others quite fit. I&#39;ve been a software developer -- everything is a compromise and good design is hard. By staying on the topics of current features, feature requests, bugs, suggestions, and by encouraging constructive critism and a balance of both positive and negative feedback, this group will be the best community for us to help Orkut until they offer us better alternatives.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;In the above I said &#34;They only way that I know of to avoid this is in your prefences to set that all of your messages should be sent to you via the web, not email.&#34;
However, this is incorrect, it will still send your email address in the
&#34;Reply-To:&#34;
At this time there is no way I know of to avoid this flaw if you are concerned about your email address other then changing it to a temporary one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-01T21:47:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-01T21:47:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;That&#39;s a pretty big &#34;bug&#34; (or unpublished feature) indeed (!)
For example, personally I try to keep my work email address off the net as much as possible, and have set pretty strict privacy settings on orkut, assuming they&#39;d keep it private...
Coincidentally (!!??) the amount of spam I&#39;m receiving at my work email address has gone up vastly since joining Orkut... A very odd coincidence...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.jacobsen.no/anders/blog/&#34;&gt;Anders&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-03T04:14:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-03T04:14:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I discovered why I got &#39;jailed&#39; for a third time today. Two of us appear to have been jailed because of a bug when posting to groups. What happens is that if you write a long post, rather then the system tell you something is wrong, your posting form will just be refreshed. This will prompt you to submit a few more times, unsuccessfully. Then you realize it must be because your post is too long, so you&#39;ll remove text a few times, and submit. At some point in this process, typically before you successfully trim it down enough to successfully post, you will discover you are in Orkut jail.
Of course, that makes us long-winded bloggers particularly vulnerable ;-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-03T07:17:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-03T07:17:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
my suggestion for forum:  orkut design, because orkut the man himself is a member of that community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;reader&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-04T17:18:21-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-04T17:18:21-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;beta testing for www.swakto.com social networking is open
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.swato.com&#34;&gt;jemai&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-14T12:40:16-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-14T12:40:16-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
ive been banned on orkut. what is the maximum time you are banned or when they reply to you?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;sherrzz&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-18T19:06:48-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-18T19:06:48-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i don&#39;t know much more about orkut i just want to know what this side about of side.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;nawin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-12T00:51:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-12T00:51:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/02/confirmed_email.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Followup on Orkut</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 13:21:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve read of emails, Orkut messages, and blog postings since my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;post yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, so I thought I would share some with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been a number of good posts, as well as user comments at Danah Boyd&#39;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/&#34;&gt;Apophenia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danah Boyd writes &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/02/01/correcting_marc_canters_perception_of_my_views.html#004011&#34;&gt;Correcting Marc Canter&#39;s Perception of My Views&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Marc - i don&#39;t believe that users should take these relationships more seriously; i believe that YOU should. Users will do whatever they damn well please, and i think that we should learn from them. But out of respect to the creators of these systems, many of whom are our friends, i truly believe that we should respect their goals and not engage in behavior that disrespects their intentions. Furthermore, i believe that we should never be the exceptions on any given service, the ones who push the boundaries. We are not average users. We should sit back and watch what average users do, not try to top them. By engaging in disrespectful behavior, we make it much harder for our friends and colleagues to execute their business plans as they&#39;re busy policing us.&lt;/blockquote&gt;When I first read this, I thought of something else. When I saw Danah&#39;s &#34;YOU&#34;, I was thinking of myself and Marc Canter as developers. I&#39;m not currently involved in developing Social Software, but I come from the developer mind set. &#34;WE&#34; developers &#34;should take these relationships more seriously&#34;. That means that although our users will game, will play, and stretch the system, we should design it as seriously as possible those who are serious, concerned, and value their relationships.  &#34;Calling someone a friend&#34; &lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt; mean something -- something important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danah Boyd asks in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/31/banned_from_orkut.html&#34;&gt;Banned from Orkut&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I keep hearing about folks who have been kicked off or &#34;jailed&#34; from Orkut. I&#39;d love to hear more about this. Who all is getting banned? Why? Are you given explanations? What happens when you try to fight?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offered in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/31/banned_from_orkut.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments there&lt;/a&gt; some of my observations on being &#34;jailed&#34; now there twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danah asks &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/what_is_beta_in_the_context_of_social_software.html&#34;&gt;What is Beta in the context of Social Software?&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;What does the term &#39;beta&#39; mean in social software? It&#39;s become an ongoing joke since Friendster is *still* in beta.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
I find it quite disconcerting that people want to label their distributions &#34;beta&#34; for over a year because it hasn&#39;t been perfected, because new versions are coming out. This, to me, seems like an abuse of the term beta. New versions always come out. Is beta simply an excuse?&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
I am really uncomfortable with public distributions of software being labeled as beta (or alpha), particularly when the population joining it is not aware of it being truly an alpha/beta.&lt;/blockquote&gt;I think this is important -- just saying something is &#39;beta&#39; is too easy. We&#39;ve have learned this in the online game industry -- how beta is managed sets the culture of your community very early on, and has a huge effect on &#34;buzz&#34;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darkageofcamelot.com&#34;&gt;Dark Ages of Camelot&lt;/a&gt; Game Designer Dave Rickey wrote an excellent column on this at Skotos last month &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/engines13.phtml&#34;&gt;Plan Your Fight&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The problems arise because of the differing agendas of the parties involved in bringing the games to and through the beta process, and their differing expectations of what they are supposed to accomplish. The fact is, our traditional Alpha/Beta division does not serve the needs of these games well. Well before the full featureset is in place, the complexity surpasses the point where internal QA processes are adequate to cope. You simply can&#39;t even make a serious attempt at full-regression organized QA; the manpower requirements are far too high.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
Beyond that, there are the marketing implications. Ideally, Beta isn&#39;t about marketing, it&#39;s about making the games work. In the real world, only a fool ignores the impact of &#34;beta buzz&#34;. Beta testers telling their friends &#34;You&#39;ve got to try this game&#34; is the most powerful marketing force in the industry. A few thousand evangelists working their personal social networks is better than millions of dollars of paid advertising. By the same token, beta testers saying &#34;don&#39;t bother, it sucks&#34; can kill a game, no matter how much money is spent on marketing.&lt;/blockquote&gt;He further recommends that beta be actually broken into more categories &lt;b&gt;Development Beta&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Playtesting Beta&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Scaling Beta&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;Load Beta&lt;/b&gt;. Part of the problem with Orkut is that they are lost in Scaling and Load Beta, when they need more Development and Playtesting Beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting blog entry found from in a comment at Danah&#39;s site, written by Jeremy Zawodny: &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeremy.zawodny.com/blog/archives/001504.html&#34;&gt;Why Google needs Orkut&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;What surprises me is that nobody has looked at it the other way around: What problems might Orkut solve that Google would otherwise find significantly more challenging?&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
Suddenly they&#39;re able to set a *.google.com cookie that contains a bit of identifying data (such as your Orkut id) and that would greatly enhance their ability to mine useful and profitable data from the combination of your profile and daily searches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we know that the &#34;big three&#34; already do this sort of thing to some degree or another. But Google&#39;s lack of intimate knowledge of their users is surely holding them back from doing some of the things they&#39;d love to do. Many folks think it&#39;s just a matter of time before they try to get &#34;real&#34; users signed up.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally don&#39;t think Google is institutionally really that aware of Orkut. If anything, the negativity that the beta has raised may actually be causing this skunkworks group some headaches, given that Google is trying to go public. But yes, in the long term if Orkut is successful and absorbed into Google, this information will be used this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/02/01/correcting_marc_canters_perception_of_my_views.html#comments&#34;&gt;comment to Danah&#39;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bladam.com/&#34;&gt;Adam Lasnik&lt;/a&gt; writes:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I have agreed with the majority of your complaints about orkut, danah, and indeed, have found myself also disappointed in what I feel is the lost opportunity (so far) for what Orkut (the guy) and Google (the company) could have set up from the get go. They have the means, the finances, and so on to have set up a truly sophisticated and thoughtful social network. I still optimistically think that orkut.com will amount to something impressive (useful and/or just damn fun) someday, though I wish the structure had been more sophisticated from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, I do have to agree with what I read from someone else recently (apologies -- the specific source is escaping me!) about how perhaps the ambiguity and unsophisticated structure of orkut.com is intentional... letting members shape things as they go along, almost as folks might build a sim-city from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps. And perhaps not. I don&#39;t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&#39;ll continue to use orkut.com until it&#39;s either no longer fun and useful for me, or I feel it has no hopes of BECOMING fun and useful. At that time (and probably before), I&#39;ll be airing my concerns privately to the orkut.com team and publicly on my blog... but I&#39;ll maintain my respect for Orkut, orkut.com, Google, and the service terms to which I agreed to when I signed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish others would do the same.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Adam further points to his blog entry &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bladam.com/archives/0401302002.htm&#34;&gt;Don&#39;t like it? Go home and don&#39;t come back&lt;/a&gt;:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;But on the whole, I think folks who are unhappy with orkut (or any other privately-owned-and-run service) have exactly two choices:
&lt;li&gt;stick with the service, but publicly or privately express concerns&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quit the service (and, yep, still publicly or privately express concerns if they wish)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general I agree with Adam, if you are unhappy quit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, his first choice was &#34;publicly or privately express concerns&#34;. I&#39;ve been chastised for expressing publicly concerns about Orkut. For instance I was sent this message from someone by the Orkut message system:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;You are a bit annoying, and you seem to go about making things a better in the same way a child goes about crying to his mom because he didn&#39;t get his 4th lemon pop in a row.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Other then my first mistaken email about a possible &#34;friends of friends&#34; email security issue, I feel that my comments have been constructive. Yet obviously I&#39;ve hit some nerves (probably a good thing for Orkut that people are feeling that passionate to be defensive about it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that even though Orkut is in beta, there is no organized feedback system. For instance they could offer a forum read by the developers, or even better a bug/issues tracking system like TypePad has, or Bugzilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, feedback is a two-way street -- they could do a lot by offering a developers daily blog, or some type of regular announcement of what feature they wanted beta testers to test that day, or even acknowledgement &#34;we already know that is an issue&#34;. Also, they need to show respect for good feedback publicly, as that will encourage more good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is happening at this time, which means that people get frustrated, which also makes it easy rumors and conspiracy to spread. I want to be a constructive critic, but Orkut makes it hard for me to be so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also received some interesting comments via email or Orkut messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one about my concern about emails revealed when you send to &#34;friends of friends&#34;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;When you give your trust to anyone, they can choose to abuse it, just like in real life. For example, I don&#39;t know how delighted Megan is that you chose to compose your glorious-whistle-blowing-yeah-look-at-me-I-pretended-I-was-friends-with-these-people-but-I am-not-and-I-am-so-r337-in-exposing-a-&#34;security hole&#34;-in-this-site message, but, as always, these actions can be remedied. For example, she can choose to remove you from her friends list, just like in real life &#34;friends&#34; who abuse someone&#39;s trust are not their friends anymore. This way you also very efficiently negatively advertise yourself to all of her friends so that they now know to stay away from you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if this type of behavior will happen? So far on any of these social networking services I&#39;ve never seen a message &#34;you have been removed from X&#39;s friend list&#34;. It is possible that I have been removed by someone, but so far I have not been told. And will someone look at someone friends list and say &#34;ah, he is no longer on there, so I will remove him&#34;. Right now, I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite messages sent to me on Orkut:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I don&#39;t like that it&#39;s not easy to opt out. I&#39;ve already had to delete a flame from my &#34;scrapbook&#34; and I could see how this could turn ugly quickly. Without an opt-out I don&#39;t see how I have any way of getting out of there quickly if there&#39;s a problem. Maybe what they need is a way for me to put myself in jail for a period of time.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Dear,
I liked your alacrity... first I didn´t know what is it and then I looked for that word in the diccionarie. Ok, I think the life must be made for alacrity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.angelfire.com/ar/rosa01&#34;&gt;Ana Rosa&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-30T09:19:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-30T09:19:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I like your comment!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Julia Machado&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-18T22:33:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-18T22:33:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;yoosef&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-02T04:21:08-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-02T04:21:08-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
heloo     25   iran   neam;yoosef
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;yoosef&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-02T04:28:06-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-02T04:28:06-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i live in great country that their goverments use filters for internet sites
if you can help me in this way pls give me one way to break this filters
tnx
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;nana&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-09T14:02:08-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-09T14:02:08-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;please rejester me for orkut           Thank u
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.typepad.com/t/trackback/427094&#34;&gt;nina&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-21T16:31:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-21T16:31:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Get me one Okay????
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Teddy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T22:01:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T22:01:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Orkut is plural of rather sensitive word in finnish language (sexual climax). Just to mention.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.url.com&#34;&gt;Somebody&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-03T03:32:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-03T03:32:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Well,from my first impressions of orkut,what i gather is that,u have to be careful in who u select as friends(incase of a stranger sending u a friend request).As for getting familiar with a person that can always be done by sending a few messages through the scrap book(before u accept the frind invite).Other very useful feature of the scrapbook is that it almost serves the purpose of an instant messenger(conversations being publicly viewable though),with the community feature you can make friends with like minded people by joiing communities.Havent gone through all the features yet,but if you dont go too much into the nitty gritties then it is all in all quite a decent product.And of course with a popular name like google backing it,this can only improve (google wont shelve it as it just has become way too popular in the beta stage itself)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Kiran&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-07-12T06:46:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-07-12T06:46:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>