<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Relationships on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/relationships/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Relationships on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2005 16:35:17 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/relationships/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2005 16:35:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In yesterday&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/templates/rundowns/rundown.php?prgId=2&#34;&gt;All Things Considered&lt;/a&gt;, NPR commentator &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakehalpern.com/news.html&#34;&gt;Jake Halpern&lt;/a&gt; questions why you feel like you have a relationship with the characters in your favorite TV shows. His answer: &amp;quot;That&#39;s because you do.&amp;quot; This idea is interesting not just to help us understand how we relate to imaginary characters, but also to correlate with our own understanding of &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; relationship limits and how they might relate to this concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4772145&#34;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt;, Bostonian Jake Halpern considers two academic ideas, &amp;quot;belongingness theory&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;para-social relationships&amp;quot;, and how they affect the relationships we develop with television characters. He puts it all in the context of the 1990s TV show &lt;em&gt;Cheers&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/cheers.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Cheers&#34; alt=&#34;Cheers&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&amp;quot;My preoccupation with &lt;/em&gt;Cheers the Bar&lt;em&gt; puzzled me until I stumbled upon a rather obscure but quite fascinating academic notion called &lt;/em&gt;belongingness theory&lt;em&gt;.The argument goes something like this: in ancient times humans who stuck together increased the chances that they would survive and reproduce. So, when it came time to, say, hunt a large animal, or defend the cave against marauders, groups fared better then the guy on his own. In addition, adults in the group would have been more likely to find mates, reproduce, and raise their children. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The likely result of all this evolutionary selection is the creation of an internal mechanism that makes human beings crave social acceptance. The way I figured it, my irrational fondness for &lt;/em&gt;Cheers the Bar&lt;em&gt; was just my belongingness mechanism kicking. I just wanted to be part of the gang.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belongingness theory seems to have a good scientific basis. In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy.fsu.edu/faculty/baumeist.dp.html&#34;&gt;Baumeister&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Leary&#39;s 1995 paper on Belongingness Theory, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;amp;db=PubMed&amp;amp;a mp;list_uids=7777651&amp;amp;dopt=Abstract&#34;&gt;The Need to Belong&lt;/a&gt;, they stated that in order for belongingness to be considered a fundamental human motivation (as opposed to a want), it would have to be universal, affect a broad range of behaviors, lead to ill effects when thwarted, and elicit goal-oriented behavior designed to satisfy it. They found evidence for all of these. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&#39;m quite comfortable with the idea that evolution has encouraged us to have a number of &amp;quot;social emotions&amp;quot;, and that these may include a strong desire to belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halpern continues in his commentary with a discussion of &lt;em&gt;para-social relationships&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;And this brings to yet another academic theory, that of &lt;/em&gt;para-social relationships&lt;em&gt;. According to academics Horton and Wohl, who originated this concept, television gives viewers the &amp;quot;illusion of a face-to-face relationship with the performer&amp;quot;. Gradually over the course of many episodes, viewers come to feel that they &#39;&lt;/em&gt;know&lt;em&gt;&#39; a persona.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I totally buy it. After watching dozens of Cheers episodes, I felt as if I knew the personas in the show intimately. In fact there were times when I had seen more of the characters on Cheers then I seen of the people in my own family. So, yeah, I definitely had some para-social relationships going on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The truth is, we all yearn for companionship. The only problem is, that for many of us, myself included, the notion of a well-functioning family and a welcoming group of friends and co-workers, is occasionally more easily found on television or in the movies, than in life itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After all, in order to maintain &lt;/em&gt;&#39;real&#39;&lt;em&gt; relationships, you have to put in a tremendous amount of effort: making phone calls; returning emails; planning weekends together; etc. To maintain para-social relationships, however, all you have to do is flick on the TV.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I&#39;m being honest with myself, I have to admit that at times, Norm, Cliff, Carla, and Sam have formed, well, a kind of para-family to which I yearn to belong. I suppose that hideously hackneyed as it sounds, it&#39;s just like the show&#39;s theme song goes: &lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;Sometimes you want to go where everybody knows your name, and they&#39;re always glad you came.&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt; Only, they &lt;strong&gt;don&#39;t&lt;/strong&gt; know your name, and they really don&#39;t know you came.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jake&#39;s description of Horton &amp;amp; Wohl&#39;s theory on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aber.ac.uk/media/Modules/TF33120/horton_and_wohl_1956.html&#34;&gt;para-social relationships&lt;/a&gt; definitely parallels my thoughts in a previous post &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt; where I ask &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; As Jake said, it&#39;s difficult because you have to make the effort: the phone calls, the emails, meeting in person, and all the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the concept of having real relationships with television characters might give us enlightenment into some other relationship issues. I personally find it difficult to reconcile the mismatch between my number of connections and my own limits due to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;; intuitively I feel that limiting my television watching can help. This is because these TV relationships are what I call &amp;quot;junk relationships&amp;quot;. Sometimes when I talk about the concept of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;, I said that we may have difficulty even reaching the Dunbar limit of 150 people because of the &amp;quot;junk relationships&amp;quot; we maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does every ongoing para-social relationship with an ongoing series character, such as Cliff on Cheers or Kate on Lost, lower the number of relationships we can have with real people? I believe that this may be so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, if so, the answer to maintaining more connections with real people may be simply to turn off the television and tune in the real world instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some related posts about group behavior:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;That does not bode well for those of us with &#34;relationships&#34; to multiple blogs we read regularly.....
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.BenYehudaPress.com&#34;&gt;Reb Yudel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-08-04T19:23:31-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-08-04T19:23:31-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;How did the link to this blog get into the blog on server side browser. That blog does not even allow comments so that one can ask questions like that. That blog has given links to some 100 blogs that have nothing to do with server side browsing.
I hope I&#39;d be in order if I enter a link to one such blog below.
http://www.newerawisp.blogspot.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/users/fakir005/335.html&#34;&gt;Satish Bhardwaj&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-09-15T13:05:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-09-15T13:05:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What about characters in books?  Should I stop reading the Diskworld series?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.lib.umn.edu/denis036/thisweekinevolution/&#34;&gt;Ford&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-01T10:20:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-01T10:20:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great Social Networking Posts</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/great_social_ne.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2004 08:05:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/great_social_ne.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I&#39;ve been out attending the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sxsw.com&#34;&gt;SXSW Music, Movie and Interactive Conference&lt;/a&gt; there has been a flurry of high-quality postings about Social Networking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike many of my fellow bloggers, I find it difficult to post meaningful blogs while I&#39;m on the road. It has been my policy in my own blog postings to also be &#34;high-signal, low-noise&#34;, so normally I don&#39;t just post links without solid additional commentary, however, I&#39;m making an exception this time because of the quality and depth of these entries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How Do We Categorize Relationships&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clay Shirky writes in Many to Many &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.corante.com/many/archives/2004/03/16/relationship_a_vocabulary_for_describing_relationships_between_people.php&#34;&gt;RELATIONSHIP: A vocabulary for describing relationships between people&lt;/a&gt; which is a commentary on a new proposal for &lt;a href=&#34;http://purl.org/vocab/relationship/&#34;&gt;mapping relationships&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/&#34;&gt;FOAF&lt;/a&gt; (see also my previous blog on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html&#34;&gt;FOAF&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, just in case you were wondering, is how you should be characterizing your relationships with one another:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;friendOf, acquaintanceOf, parentOf, siblingOf, childOf, grandchildOf, spouseOf, enemyOf, antagonistOf, ambivalentOf, lostContactWith, knowsOf, wouldLikeToKnow, knowsInPassing, knowsByReputation, closeFriendOf, hasMet, worksWith, colleagueOf, collaboratesWith, employerOf, employedBy, mentorOf, apprenticeTo, livesWith, neighborOf, grandparentOf, lifePartnerOf, engagedTo, ancestorOf, descendantOf, participantIn, participant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Describing relationships with a controlled vocabulary can sound credible right up to the moment you see the vocabulary, but this thing is a mess.&lt;br/&gt;
...&lt;br/&gt;
The RELATIONSHIP list should make it obvious that explicit linguistic clarity in human relations is a pipe dream. It probably won’t though — the madness of the age is to assume that people can spell out, in explicit detail, the messiest aspects of their lives, and that they will eagerly do so, in order to provide better inputs to cool new software.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you read the comment&#39;s in Clay Shirky&#39;s blog entry -- some good discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ian Davis writes a response to Clay&#39;s posting in &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetalchemy.org/2004/03/clayShirkyOnRELATIONSHIP&#34;&gt;Clay Shirky on Relationship&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a number of themes in Clay&#39;s post. The primary theme appears to be one of completeness: Clay&#39;s thesis is that the vocabulary is incomplete because it doesn&#39;t provide properties to model composite relationships: what if you are employed by a colleague you collaborate with?. Clay seems to be implying that he expects the terms to be exclusive. Of course they&#39;re not. It&#39;s perfectly meaningful to assert that Jane employedBy John and Jane collaboratesWith John. RDF supports this kind of assertion and you can also express it with the HTML method outlined in the vocabulary.&lt;br/&gt;
...&lt;br/&gt;
Obviously I&#39;m pleased that Clay has taken the vocabulary seriously enough to critique in detail. Somehow the thought that everyone would ignore it caused me more concern than the fear that everyone would hate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all the obvious thought Clay put into his piece, he still managed to overlook the raison d&#39;etre for the relationship vocabulary. Indeed it&#39;s the raison d&#39;etre for all vocabularies. Without these vocabularies, incomplete and imperfect as they are, we would be mute in the machine readable web, unable to express ourselves in any meaningful way. You only have to look at the etymology to realise that vocabularies give you a voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Clay I too am concerned with this relationship proposal, for a variety of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I&#39;m not sure that I like the &#34;negative&#34; relationships. There is a good argument against using negative relationships in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://gmpg.org/xfn/background#positive&#34;&gt;XFN Background&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negative relationship terms have been omitted from XFN by design.  The authors think that such values would not serve a positive ends and thus made the deliberate decision to leave them out. Such terms (we won&#39;t even bother naming them here) while mildly entertaining in a dark humor sort of way, only serve to propagate negativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors do not deny that such negative relationships exist in the real world today.  Of course they exist.  However, we see no need nor benefit to standardizing such relationships and capturing them in a form which would spread on the Web.  There is enough hatred in the world.  We should work to eliminate hatred, not to spread it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we do realize that by creating &lt;a href=&#34;http://gmpg.org/xfn&#34;&gt;XFN&lt;/a&gt; and the mechanisms it uses (&lt;a href=&#34;http://gmpg.org/xmdp/&#34;&gt;XMDP&lt;/a&gt;), we have opened a Pandora&#39;s box, and have made it easier for those that would create and propagate negative relationships.  We can only hope that our positive creation wins out over any such negative creations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I am uncomfortable with both the relationships in &lt;a href=&#34;http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/&#34;&gt;FOAF&lt;/a&gt; and parallel ideas in &lt;a href=&#34;http://gmpg.org/xfn&#34;&gt;XFN&lt;/a&gt; because they in both proposals these are &#34;exposed&#34; publicly. I am comfortable with saying that I &#34;knowOf&#34; someone, but when forced to categorize publicly everyone even more precisely, I become uncomfortable. Am a I committing a faux-pas when I say that I am a &#34;friendOf&#34; someone when they think I&#39;m a &#34;closeFriendOf&#34;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I&#39;m concerned about complexity -- once you start down the slippery slope of defining relationships, things can get incredibly complex. Even if don&#39;t include concerns about ethnocentricity (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michael.bauser.name/20031225T045828Z&#34;&gt;Michael Bauser writes&lt;/a&gt;), there just seems to be no end in sight to how specific you might be required to be. Becoming more specific typically results in more precision, but in this case, as these are very fluid human (or even primate) definitions, wrought with emotion, may result in them being less precise. Maybe the real answer should be much simpler four: knowsOf, professionalColleagueOf, personalFriendOf, and shareFamilyWith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Are Social Networks Useful?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judith Meskill asks in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meskill.net/archives/000565.html&#34;&gt;Musings On Autonomic Social &amp; Knowledge Networks&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;If you utilize one or more of the current entrants in this swell of online SNS offerings [such as LinkedIn, Friendster, Orkut, Ryze, and/or Tribe] - what value, if any, do you derive from them? And, harkening back to the citation with which I started this post, has one [or more] of these services assisted in helping you to successfully reduce the &#39;traffic congestion&#39; at the &#39;intersections&#39; in your life? And, in closing, any insights, comments, or ponderings on the recent and future blurring of lines between &#39;wetware,&#39; &#39;software,&#39; and &#39;hardware&#39; in an infinitely connected wireless world?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuart Henshall answers in Unbound Spiral &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.henshall.com/blog/archives/000817.html&#34;&gt;Social Networking is Broken&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;p&gt;This slightly facetious statement: &#34;My social networks are broken... at least I think they are.&#34; reflects my conclusion that the social networks I&#39;ve been playing in are for the most part associative networks. While they have a social element the socializing for the most part takes place by blogs, forums, IM / e-mail, phone and in face to face visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s time to put a stop to categorizing these &#34;things&#34; as social networks. Call them &#34;Associative Networking Tools&#34; or &#34;Structured Association Tools&#34; or something similar. Then you can create a bucket for them. The reason there is no real business model is they are just part of / or component towards building our capabilities to enhance &#34;presence&#34; and connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have we learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;We don&#39;t socialize rather only associate through the Orkuts while we socialize using messaging, telephone and face to face visits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The opportunity to connecting through friends is much greater than generally understood. Some successes have been achieved. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual connections mean managing ones connections and presence has never been more important. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structured services are creating problems where there were none before. From categories to access. And designating &#34;artificial&#34; forced levels of buddies or friendship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fragmenting association systems does not enable better connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration on to my desktop (address book / IM systems) at minimum and preferably into my cellphone is required for there are few you can synch with and while one can upload addresses you can seldom download. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sites themselves are seldom responsible for the association, the connective knowledge is broader than the networking sites. eg blogs, blogrolls, online forums etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Denise Klarquist writes in &lt;a href=&#34;http://weblog.cheskin.net/blog/archives/000216.html&#34;&gt;SNAM - Too much of a good thing?&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0121664/2004/03/17.html#a394&#34;&gt;Dinah Mehta&lt;/a&gt;):
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Each time I&#39;m invited to join or add someone (frequently unknown to me) to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/&#34;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt; network, or asked to update my contact information via &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plaxo.com/&#34;&gt;Plaxo&lt;/a&gt; (again, usually by someone I barely know) I wonder how far my online social network extends. And how useful it really is. I&#39;m still intrigued and excited by the possibilities of online social networking. But I&#39;m hoping to see more of the benefits before the noise dampens my enthusiasm.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;A href=&#34;http://www.chriscorrigan.com/parkinglot/&#34;&gt;Chris Corrigan&lt;/A&gt; offers a similar concern in a comment in Dinah Mehta&#39;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0121664/2004/03/17.html#a395&#34;&gt;Social Networking - Too Much Noise?&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;P&gt;&#34;Seems to me that social networks have a hard time existing in the absence of a reason to do so. I have played around on Ryze and Orkut and to be honest they hold no glamour for me. I have a number of real life social networks from whence my business comes, and my weblog provides me with another social network from which I derive a lot of learning.&lt;/P&gt;
&lt;P&gt;But I could never find a reason for the Ryze&#39;s and Orkuts of the world. And without a reason to network, networking becomes just noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;P&gt;One application for these types of things that I am working with a little is using social networking software to support emerging Aboriginal leaders here in British Columbia Canada who are working on interesting things in remote and far flung communities and who will really benefit from have some contact with each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;P&gt;But I wouldn&#39;t dream of inviting them to Ryze. Interesting, eh?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;SXSW Social Networking Transcripts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast Company blogger Heath Row has been doing a fantastic job capturing transcripts from sessions here at the SXSW conference, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Friendster founder Jonathan Abrams SXSW keynote &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.fastcompany.com/archives/2004/03/16/what_the_heck_is_social_networking.html&#34;&gt;What the Heack is Social Networking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transcript of &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.fastcompany.com/archives/2004/03/15/the_aesthetics_of_social_networks.html&#34;&gt;The Aesthetics of Social Networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transcript of &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.fastcompany.com/archives/2004/03/15/ridiculously_easy_group_forming.html&#34;&gt;Ridiculously Easy Group Forming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transcript of Ethan Watters&#39; talk on &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.fastcompany.com/archives/2004/03/15/urban_tribes_and_social_dark_matter.html&#34;&gt;Urban Tribes and Social Dark Matter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;.&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Great Post, Chris. I linked to it and added a comment. &lt;a href=&#34;http://eureksterblog.blogspot.com/2004_03_18_eureksterblog_archive.html#107962521571269734&#34;&gt;http://eureksterblog.blogspot.com/2004_03_18_eureksterblog_archive.html#107962521571269734&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.whizspark.com/pete&#34;&gt;Peter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-18T08:21:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-18T08:21:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/03/great_social_ne.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Followup on Orkut</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 13:21:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve read of emails, Orkut messages, and blog postings since my &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;post yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, so I thought I would share some with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been a number of good posts, as well as user comments at Danah Boyd&#39;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/&#34;&gt;Apophenia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danah Boyd writes &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/02/01/correcting_marc_canters_perception_of_my_views.html#004011&#34;&gt;Correcting Marc Canter&#39;s Perception of My Views&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Marc - i don&#39;t believe that users should take these relationships more seriously; i believe that YOU should. Users will do whatever they damn well please, and i think that we should learn from them. But out of respect to the creators of these systems, many of whom are our friends, i truly believe that we should respect their goals and not engage in behavior that disrespects their intentions. Furthermore, i believe that we should never be the exceptions on any given service, the ones who push the boundaries. We are not average users. We should sit back and watch what average users do, not try to top them. By engaging in disrespectful behavior, we make it much harder for our friends and colleagues to execute their business plans as they&#39;re busy policing us.&lt;/blockquote&gt;When I first read this, I thought of something else. When I saw Danah&#39;s &#34;YOU&#34;, I was thinking of myself and Marc Canter as developers. I&#39;m not currently involved in developing Social Software, but I come from the developer mind set. &#34;WE&#34; developers &#34;should take these relationships more seriously&#34;. That means that although our users will game, will play, and stretch the system, we should design it as seriously as possible those who are serious, concerned, and value their relationships.  &#34;Calling someone a friend&#34; &lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt; mean something -- something important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danah Boyd asks in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/31/banned_from_orkut.html&#34;&gt;Banned from Orkut&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I keep hearing about folks who have been kicked off or &#34;jailed&#34; from Orkut. I&#39;d love to hear more about this. Who all is getting banned? Why? Are you given explanations? What happens when you try to fight?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offered in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/31/banned_from_orkut.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments there&lt;/a&gt; some of my observations on being &#34;jailed&#34; now there twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danah asks &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/what_is_beta_in_the_context_of_social_software.html&#34;&gt;What is Beta in the context of Social Software?&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;What does the term &#39;beta&#39; mean in social software? It&#39;s become an ongoing joke since Friendster is *still* in beta.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
I find it quite disconcerting that people want to label their distributions &#34;beta&#34; for over a year because it hasn&#39;t been perfected, because new versions are coming out. This, to me, seems like an abuse of the term beta. New versions always come out. Is beta simply an excuse?&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
I am really uncomfortable with public distributions of software being labeled as beta (or alpha), particularly when the population joining it is not aware of it being truly an alpha/beta.&lt;/blockquote&gt;I think this is important -- just saying something is &#39;beta&#39; is too easy. We&#39;ve have learned this in the online game industry -- how beta is managed sets the culture of your community very early on, and has a huge effect on &#34;buzz&#34;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.darkageofcamelot.com&#34;&gt;Dark Ages of Camelot&lt;/a&gt; Game Designer Dave Rickey wrote an excellent column on this at Skotos last month &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/engines13.phtml&#34;&gt;Plan Your Fight&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The problems arise because of the differing agendas of the parties involved in bringing the games to and through the beta process, and their differing expectations of what they are supposed to accomplish. The fact is, our traditional Alpha/Beta division does not serve the needs of these games well. Well before the full featureset is in place, the complexity surpasses the point where internal QA processes are adequate to cope. You simply can&#39;t even make a serious attempt at full-regression organized QA; the manpower requirements are far too high.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
Beyond that, there are the marketing implications. Ideally, Beta isn&#39;t about marketing, it&#39;s about making the games work. In the real world, only a fool ignores the impact of &#34;beta buzz&#34;. Beta testers telling their friends &#34;You&#39;ve got to try this game&#34; is the most powerful marketing force in the industry. A few thousand evangelists working their personal social networks is better than millions of dollars of paid advertising. By the same token, beta testers saying &#34;don&#39;t bother, it sucks&#34; can kill a game, no matter how much money is spent on marketing.&lt;/blockquote&gt;He further recommends that beta be actually broken into more categories &lt;b&gt;Development Beta&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Playtesting Beta&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Scaling Beta&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;Load Beta&lt;/b&gt;. Part of the problem with Orkut is that they are lost in Scaling and Load Beta, when they need more Development and Playtesting Beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting blog entry found from in a comment at Danah&#39;s site, written by Jeremy Zawodny: &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeremy.zawodny.com/blog/archives/001504.html&#34;&gt;Why Google needs Orkut&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;What surprises me is that nobody has looked at it the other way around: What problems might Orkut solve that Google would otherwise find significantly more challenging?&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
Suddenly they&#39;re able to set a *.google.com cookie that contains a bit of identifying data (such as your Orkut id) and that would greatly enhance their ability to mine useful and profitable data from the combination of your profile and daily searches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we know that the &#34;big three&#34; already do this sort of thing to some degree or another. But Google&#39;s lack of intimate knowledge of their users is surely holding them back from doing some of the things they&#39;d love to do. Many folks think it&#39;s just a matter of time before they try to get &#34;real&#34; users signed up.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally don&#39;t think Google is institutionally really that aware of Orkut. If anything, the negativity that the beta has raised may actually be causing this skunkworks group some headaches, given that Google is trying to go public. But yes, in the long term if Orkut is successful and absorbed into Google, this information will be used this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/02/01/correcting_marc_canters_perception_of_my_views.html#comments&#34;&gt;comment to Danah&#39;s blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bladam.com/&#34;&gt;Adam Lasnik&lt;/a&gt; writes:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I have agreed with the majority of your complaints about orkut, danah, and indeed, have found myself also disappointed in what I feel is the lost opportunity (so far) for what Orkut (the guy) and Google (the company) could have set up from the get go. They have the means, the finances, and so on to have set up a truly sophisticated and thoughtful social network. I still optimistically think that orkut.com will amount to something impressive (useful and/or just damn fun) someday, though I wish the structure had been more sophisticated from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, I do have to agree with what I read from someone else recently (apologies -- the specific source is escaping me!) about how perhaps the ambiguity and unsophisticated structure of orkut.com is intentional... letting members shape things as they go along, almost as folks might build a sim-city from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps. And perhaps not. I don&#39;t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&#39;ll continue to use orkut.com until it&#39;s either no longer fun and useful for me, or I feel it has no hopes of BECOMING fun and useful. At that time (and probably before), I&#39;ll be airing my concerns privately to the orkut.com team and publicly on my blog... but I&#39;ll maintain my respect for Orkut, orkut.com, Google, and the service terms to which I agreed to when I signed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish others would do the same.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Adam further points to his blog entry &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bladam.com/archives/0401302002.htm&#34;&gt;Don&#39;t like it? Go home and don&#39;t come back&lt;/a&gt;:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;But on the whole, I think folks who are unhappy with orkut (or any other privately-owned-and-run service) have exactly two choices:
&lt;li&gt;stick with the service, but publicly or privately express concerns&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quit the service (and, yep, still publicly or privately express concerns if they wish)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general I agree with Adam, if you are unhappy quit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, his first choice was &#34;publicly or privately express concerns&#34;. I&#39;ve been chastised for expressing publicly concerns about Orkut. For instance I was sent this message from someone by the Orkut message system:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;You are a bit annoying, and you seem to go about making things a better in the same way a child goes about crying to his mom because he didn&#39;t get his 4th lemon pop in a row.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Other then my first mistaken email about a possible &#34;friends of friends&#34; email security issue, I feel that my comments have been constructive. Yet obviously I&#39;ve hit some nerves (probably a good thing for Orkut that people are feeling that passionate to be defensive about it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that even though Orkut is in beta, there is no organized feedback system. For instance they could offer a forum read by the developers, or even better a bug/issues tracking system like TypePad has, or Bugzilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, feedback is a two-way street -- they could do a lot by offering a developers daily blog, or some type of regular announcement of what feature they wanted beta testers to test that day, or even acknowledgement &#34;we already know that is an issue&#34;. Also, they need to show respect for good feedback publicly, as that will encourage more good feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is happening at this time, which means that people get frustrated, which also makes it easy rumors and conspiracy to spread. I want to be a constructive critic, but Orkut makes it hard for me to be so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also received some interesting comments via email or Orkut messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one about my concern about emails revealed when you send to &#34;friends of friends&#34;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;When you give your trust to anyone, they can choose to abuse it, just like in real life. For example, I don&#39;t know how delighted Megan is that you chose to compose your glorious-whistle-blowing-yeah-look-at-me-I-pretended-I-was-friends-with-these-people-but-I am-not-and-I-am-so-r337-in-exposing-a-&#34;security hole&#34;-in-this-site message, but, as always, these actions can be remedied. For example, she can choose to remove you from her friends list, just like in real life &#34;friends&#34; who abuse someone&#39;s trust are not their friends anymore. This way you also very efficiently negatively advertise yourself to all of her friends so that they now know to stay away from you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if this type of behavior will happen? So far on any of these social networking services I&#39;ve never seen a message &#34;you have been removed from X&#39;s friend list&#34;. It is possible that I have been removed by someone, but so far I have not been told. And will someone look at someone friends list and say &#34;ah, he is no longer on there, so I will remove him&#34;. Right now, I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite messages sent to me on Orkut:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I don&#39;t like that it&#39;s not easy to opt out. I&#39;ve already had to delete a flame from my &#34;scrapbook&#34; and I could see how this could turn ugly quickly. Without an opt-out I don&#39;t see how I have any way of getting out of there quickly if there&#39;s a problem. Maybe what they need is a way for me to put myself in jail for a period of time.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Dear,
I liked your alacrity... first I didn´t know what is it and then I looked for that word in the diccionarie. Ok, I think the life must be made for alacrity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.angelfire.com/ar/rosa01&#34;&gt;Ana Rosa&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-30T09:19:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-30T09:19:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I like your comment!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Julia Machado&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-18T22:33:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-18T22:33:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;yoosef&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-02T04:21:08-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-02T04:21:08-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
heloo     25   iran   neam;yoosef
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;yoosef&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-02T04:28:06-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-02T04:28:06-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i live in great country that their goverments use filters for internet sites
if you can help me in this way pls give me one way to break this filters
tnx
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;nana&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-09T14:02:08-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-09T14:02:08-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;please rejester me for orkut           Thank u
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.typepad.com/t/trackback/427094&#34;&gt;nina&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-21T16:31:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-21T16:31:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Get me one Okay????
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Teddy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T22:01:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T22:01:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Orkut is plural of rather sensitive word in finnish language (sexual climax). Just to mention.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.url.com&#34;&gt;Somebody&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-03T03:32:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-03T03:32:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Well,from my first impressions of orkut,what i gather is that,u have to be careful in who u select as friends(incase of a stranger sending u a friend request).As for getting familiar with a person that can always be done by sending a few messages through the scrap book(before u accept the frind invite).Other very useful feature of the scrapbook is that it almost serves the purpose of an instant messenger(conversations being publicly viewable though),with the community feature you can make friends with like minded people by joiing communities.Havent gone through all the features yet,but if you dont go too much into the nitty gritties then it is all in all quite a decent product.And of course with a popular name like google backing it,this can only improve (google wont shelve it as it just has become way too popular in the beta stage itself)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Kiran&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-07-12T06:46:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-07-12T06:46:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insecurity at Orkut</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2004 13:58:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like many others, I&#39;ve been paying attention to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=2789681602836776519&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt; in the last couple of weeks. I&#39;ve answered more requests to be &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut then I have of any of the other half-dozen Social Networking Services I&#39;ve tried, and I&#39;ve looking at other people&#39;s friends to see if I know anyone. I&#39;ve yet to ask someone to join Orkut that wasn&#39;t already a member, and I&#39;ve been careful to not have anyone as a &amp;quot;friend&amp;quot; that I didn&#39;t know reasonably well and I thought knew me. Currently I have 68 Orkut &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot;, many more then I have on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, which I&#39;ve been using for several months and have 50 &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this activity on Orkut, I&#39;ve been reading a lot of blogs about other people&#39;s experiences on Orkut. In particular, I&#39;ve found Danah Boyd&#39;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/&#34;&gt;Apophenia&lt;/a&gt; a great source for thought on social networking services, so I&#39;ve got it near the top of my RSS aggregator. I&#39;d just read her rant &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/venting_my_contempt_for_orkut.html&#34;&gt;venting my contempt for Orkut&lt;/a&gt; when I saw a follow up post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/orkut_pissyness_round_2.html&#34;&gt;orkut pissyness round 2&lt;/a&gt; where I read:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wanna see a big phat privacy hole on Orkut? Go to messages. Click compose. Click &amp;quot;friends and friends of friends.&amp;quot; Click next. Copy &amp;amp; paste all of your friends and their friends&#39; email addresses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tested this out, and discovered she was correct, when I clicked &amp;quot;friends of friends&amp;quot; I got a long web page of names and email address. So I sent to this list I&#39;d generated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A serious security hole? Yep.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just was shown 1137 friend and friends of friends email address, including your email address. As reported by Zephoria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/orkut_pissyness_round_2.htm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got a lot of replies back like &amp;quot;What did you expect?&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;That is why I don&#39;t use my main email for Orkut&amp;quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got a reply from Orkut Buyukkokten via email:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Could you please send an email to your friends and friends of friends to tell them that there is no security hole?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked very hard to ensure that the privacy of our members is not compromised in any way. I don&#39;t want our members to get the wrong impression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would greatly appreaciate it if you could pass the following message to you friends (:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll only see the e-mail addresses of people who chose to share them with you: if you mark your email address as not to be shared with friends and friends of friends, they won&#39;t be able to get your address this way. If you look at the list of people it&#39;s addressed to, you&#39;ll see that some are listed without addresses (unless you&#39;ve got very permissive friends).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat abashed, I checked, and since the last time I&#39;d sent an email, the interface changed. I discovered that only 356 of 1137 of my friends of friends were actually allowing their email to be shown, and the rest now showed a &amp;quot;lock&amp;quot; icon next to their name. Of course, the first 100 or so on that list coincidentally allowed their emails to be shown, so I had assumed incorrectly that all had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I sent Orkut&#39;s reply out to my &amp;quot;friends of friends&amp;quot; and added links to my blog and this comment:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m still quite uncomfortable with privacy issues of Orkut.com at this time. I&#39;ve had to reveal more information then I&#39;m comfortable, and the software is too lax in letting me see other people&#39;s info, for instance &amp;quot;relationship status&amp;quot; when I&#39;ve marked myself as not interested in that. Maybe Orkut is just trying to be too much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sent an email back to Orkut saying that I&#39;d sent this email, then continued to get a lot of replies to my original email, and I discovered that I was now in Orkut &amp;quot;jail&amp;quot;. This meant that I could not send messages, could not add friends or groups, etc. No reason was given for why I was in jail. The only reason why I&#39;d seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.it/0100198/2004/01/29.html#a2216&#34;&gt;other people in jail&lt;/a&gt; was because they had added too many friends too fast. I had only 50+ friends at the time, so I knew that wasn&#39;t the reason. I could only assume the worse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m out of Orkut &amp;quot;jail&amp;quot; this morning, but I still don&#39;t have any explanation of why. I continued to get replies both in support of my concerns:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tend to agree with you. I&#39;ve learned more information than I expected about people. Also it&#39;s been a little odd to see people I know professionally on orkut, since I first conceptualized it as a social-friends service. (Then again, I&#39;ve found professors on Friendster, which is much more explicitly social, so perhaps I&#39;d better just accept that these people have lives.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think that Orkut&#39;s attempt to be all things to all people has helped it take off. I feel easier asking professional contacts to join orkut than I would for Friendster. It seems like less of a big deal to add someone to your orkut list rather than on another more focused service, as there is a level of plausible deniability as to intention. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as comments like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t want to be too harsh, but if perhaps you, and Danah, and Cory don&#39;t want to play then really no one is forcing you to play. But whining about things that you don&#39;t like is just, well, unseemly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took a break to think on why I responded so negatively when Orkut has the appearance of doing something wrong (first, the &#39;security hole&#39; that was a feature, and secondly the &#39;jail&#39;). Then it came to me:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&#39;m insecure about orkut.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the definitions of &#39;insecure&#39; are &lt;em&gt;not firm or firmly fixed; likely to fail or give way; lacking self-confidence or assurance; not safe from attack; lacking in security or safety; not financially safe or secure;&lt;/em&gt;. The one that fits me the best is &amp;quot;lacking self-confidence or assurance&amp;quot;. Why do I feel this way about Orkut?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess my insecurity started out at the very beginning. As it is in beta, you can&#39;t join Orkut, you have to be invited. This made the place seem &#39;exclusive&#39; and thus possibly safer. Yet right off it asks you some fairly personal questions: What is your relationship style? What is your sexual orientation? Who are you living with? What are your politics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I find out by looking at other people&#39;s information that this is all completely public. It isn&#39;t limited to just friends, or friends of friends, but instead is prominent. In fact, other then your name and how many &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; you have, your relationship style is the most prominent thing listed. Do I really want to know that my business acquaintance that I see only at technical conferences 2 or 3 times a year is in an open marriage? Or divorced? Or gay?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live in the Bay Area and I&#39;ve seen it all, and consider myself open and try to be consciously non-prejudiced. That&#39;s not to say that I&#39;m comfortable when I&#39;m hit on by another man, but for that matter, I&#39;m not that comfortable when I&#39;m hit on by a woman. The point is that I don&#39;t think about someone&#39;s sexual and personal choices when I interact with them. I don&#39;t care if you are gay, into S&amp;amp;M, or any other radical lifestyle. I don&#39;t care if your straight, chaste, and christian. What I do care about is your relationship to me -- if you feel that it is important to your identity to let me know, well that is between us. But I&#39;m not going to pry. I once had a male employee in my office that wore a dress to work -- I still don&#39;t know if he is gay or not. It didn&#39;t matter to me and he didn&#39;t tell me -- what mattered was that he was good employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This started my &#39;insecurity&#39; about Orkut. Later I read that you couldn&#39;t delete your pictures or profiles. This worried me. Then I read that the system was down because of a XML hack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Orkut came back after the hack, a new feature was added, fans and ratings. This made me yet even more uncomfortable. Did I really want to have to not say I was a fan of someone that said they were a fan of me? Wasn&#39;t endorsing someone a far better signifier of fan? What does Trustworthy mean? Cool? I refused to enter anything for Sexy. I worried if someone could see my ratings, or reverse socially engineer it, or hack it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus these insecurities of mine led me to think the worst and to post too quickly about the &amp;quot;Friends of Friends Security Hole&amp;quot; and still feel uncomfortable about why I was put in &amp;quot;jail&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I&#39;ve had no abuses of me by Orkut -- I&#39;ve had only two people ask me to be friends that I don&#39;t know, and so far I&#39;ve not been told that someone is my fan whom I&#39;m not willing to honestly say that I&#39;m a fan back. I&#39;ve even found some old friends that I&#39;d lost track of, which is exactly why I still &amp;quot;play&amp;quot; and not leave Orkut. I do believe that there may be something useful in these social network services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet I feel that my old blog entry &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html&#34;&gt;Evaluating Social Network Services&lt;/a&gt; that concluded with my take on &lt;strong&gt;The Perfect Social Network Service&lt;/strong&gt; is still quite on track:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My ideal service would have the multiple professional affiliation features of LinkedIn, but also allow me to show non-professional affiliations. It would allow me to form intentional communities like Tribes.Net, but would also let me do a Wiki in addition to a message board. It would have meeting/party invite services like eVite, and blogging features like LiveJournal. It would have an endorsement system like LinkedIn integrated not only with professional endorsements, but personal endorsements as well, and you could even endorse intentional communities. It would let me better map and control my network, giving different friends different privileges. It would handle the release of my personal information like Ryze, but less clunky.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d add to that list that I&#39;d like to have more control over my information, in particular, relationship information. That I&#39;d like to see more &amp;quot;progressive disclosure&amp;quot; where there was more granularity of what was revealed at public, friends of friends, friends, fans, fans who I&#39;ve endorsed, etc. Finally, I&#39;d really not like to see things that are not applicable to me, such as relationship information of other people when I&#39;m not looking for relationships, or professional information of others if I&#39;m only using Orkut for dating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Update: another Orkut user and I found a different privacy hole when sending emails -- see &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/confirmed_email.html&#34;&gt;Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The only reason why I&#39;d seen other people in jail was because they had added too many friends too fast.
There is no basis in this assumption other than, maybe, a little hubris. The constant repetition of this unfounded claim speaks volumes about the research and professionalism of those perpetuating it. Marc, at least, had a question mark after that sentence.
Fact is, some people have been &#34;jail&#34;-ed for violating the Orkut TOS, namely the posting of images of children or nude photography. One person I know of has been suspended for posting copyrighted images. Now, one may think that the limitations are overly stupid and should be changed, but as it stands a look at Marc&#39;s profile shows, that he has been most likely suspended for the images of his children. I think is is safer to assume, he has been &#34;jailed&#34; for violating the TOS, than for having too many &#34;friends&#34;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.netwarriors.org&#34;&gt;Jonas M Luster&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T14:25:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T14:25:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hmm, nothing in the message said anything about TOS. In fact, I later received an email from Orkut saying &#34;Your account was blocked by the system automatically. The block is temporary. Your account should be fine now. I apologize for the inconvenience.&#34;
I still don&#39;t know why I was in &#34;jail&#34; last night, and in fact, now I&#39;m in &#34;jail&#34; again late today, so I can only assume that it is because I sent another email to &#34;friends of friends&#34; as that is the only common event between last night and today.
If they use the &#34;jail&#34; for TOS as well as for slowing down people like Marc and I, then I think that is a big mistake to use the same name for both purposes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T14:33:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T14:33:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What is your proof for the &#34;slowing down&#34; of Marc?
His assertions aside, Marc is by far not the most prolific linker, and has not been adding friends as fast as some others, who are neither in Jail nor suspended. Other, much less prolific linkers, have been suspended, all of which share the fact that their actions (the posting of children pics) violated an admittedly stupid TOS provision. At this point, it&#39;s Marc&#39;s assumption (&#34;they don&#39;t like me, because I link a lot of people&#34;) against a trend in suspensions that is closely related to what images have been posted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.netwarriors.org&#34;&gt;Jonas M Luster&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T14:48:16-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T14:48:16-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I too am concerned about a lot of things regarding Orkut, and working on a post of my own about it. But, just to contribute to this, I&#39;ve sent two messages to friends of friends and haven&#39;t been in Jail or anything yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.seanbonner.com&#34;&gt;sean bonner&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T15:26:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T15:26:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Later I find out by looking at other people&#39;s information that this is all completely public. It isn&#39;t limited to just friends, or friends of friends, but instead is prominent. In fact, other then your name and how many &#34;friends&#34; you have, your relationship style is the most prominent thing listed.
That I&#39;d like to see more &#34;progressive disclosure&#34; where there was more granularity of what was revealed at public, friends of friends, friends, fans, fans who I&#39;ve endorsed, etc.&lt;/i&gt;
There&#39;s quite a bit of granularity already, since launch, which you continue to ignore. Every one of your hypothetically incomfortable tidbits of information are filterable by social distance, that is, yourself, friends, friends of friends, everyone. And I can only expect that you will be able to filter by karma/fan, since that would be one of the only primary benefits to the end user of the karma system.
I&#39;m not sure what you mean by &#34;XML hole&#34;. Perhaps you meant XSS? To my knowledge, the precise reasoning for Orkut&#39;s shutdown has not been revealed, but judging by what I&#39;ve noticed has changed, it seems like they took it down to remove the ability of users to broadcast messages to the everyone on the site. The reply-to-all button is gone, and you can no longer send a message to a saved search.
I can think of more applicable (and offensive) words for the orkut-bashing chicken-littles than &#34;unseemly&#34;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://aramchek.net&#34;&gt;dreww&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T18:25:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T18:25:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I don&#39;t like that it&#39;s not easy to opt out. I&#39;ve already had to delete a flame from my &#34;scrapbook&#34; and I could see how this could turn ugly quickly. Without an opt-out I don&#39;t see how I have any way of getting out of there quickly if there&#39;s a problem. Maybe what they need is a way for me to put myself in jail for a period of time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://peaceandlove.com/&#34;&gt;Trash Averse&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T22:31:52-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T22:31:52-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve joined a few social networks, revealing things about myself that I don&#39;t mind if everyone reads.  Things I don&#39;t want &#39;everyone&#39; to know, I don&#39;t add to these networks.
I also choose my communities/tribes/groups knowing everyone will be able to see my interests, and have avoided joining some I considered interesting but don&#39;t want linked to my profile.
I use disposable email addresses for social groups; when weaknesses are found, I&#39;m not disturbed by it.  I think others might be though, because they might reveal more about themselves that what I did.  I&#39;ve changed my settings to not expose my address to everyone (I think, there&#39;s a lot of places to check).
I think it&#39;s good that weaknesses are exposed, even publicly.  Not picking on any particular network, but if a person found a weakness in it, and reported it to them, there&#39;s a chance it would be missed/overlooked/ignored.
Perhaps there are some that would take a reported weakness about their network very seriously, probably not as many though.
So by making the weaknesses public, I think it puts a fire under the developers to patch the hole.  Would Orkut&#39;s hole have been patched as quickly as it was if the persons that found the hole had reported it to them instead of publicly?  Maybe, maybe not.
If a network does take immediate measures to patch holes as soon as they&#39;re reported, I&#39;d think it would be nice to give them advance notification before going public with the breach.  But I&#39;m pessimistic about this, and think it probably takes threat of bad publicity to get some networks to patch.
Keep up the good works; your blog is very interesting, and I&#39;ve subbed your RSS in my Bloglines.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://shreela.f2o.org&#34;&gt;Sherri&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-16T05:44:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-16T05:44:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I also felt insecure about Orkut, I went to jail maybe because of too many friends in short time (281), but I did not receive any explanation, do not know when the jail will be open and do not know why and when it could be closed again.
http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=13086236090759842440
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ecuaderno.com&#34;&gt;Jose Luis Orihuela&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-16T13:29:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-16T13:29:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Regarding your perfect vision of a social networking service:  I guess one could say there maybe other features that someone else might like and visa versa.  So, maybe the perfect service would allow you to pick and choose from a menu of features and services.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;bardia&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-24T16:46:35-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-24T16:46:35-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
hey...invite me to orkut...ive been trying to find someone whos a member so thell invite me...but ur the onlyone i know
thanx!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;CamilA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-02T16:24:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-02T16:24:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I realize this is kind of late to respond... But Every bit of information other than your name is pretty much optional. You only have to tell Orkut what you want to tell it, and the visibility of what you tell it is controllable by defining when strangers/friends/etc can see... I&#39;m thinking part of your paranoia is a misunderstanding of how the system works.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;CbiMerrow&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-06T10:22:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-06T10:22:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I got put in Orkut jail! Here&#39;s why. I had created a community for those critical of the Macintosh and the mac zealots all ganged up and marked me as bogus user! I sent a fed-ex to Orkut demanding he remove from his system all of the Mac users who abused the &#34;bogus user&#34; button. So far, no reply
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Reuven&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-18T21:59:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-18T21:59:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
please, i just want to know what the word orkut means, etimological or eletronic one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Antonio Carlos&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-26T23:40:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-26T23:40:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Al I have to say to is that if you are so unconfortable with Orkut, just get out, and don&#39;t be a part of the communite. I&#39;m not trying to defend orkut or something, but I&#39;ve found a lot o friends that i&#39;ve not seen for many years and that is the power of orkut.. find or be together friends
I guess that make you unconfortable too... if you don&#39;t like don&#39;t try to finish with a whole ideia, that in my point of view is very good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Marcelo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-25T11:19:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-25T11:19:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Al I have to say to is that if you are so unconfortable with Orkut, just get out, and don&#39;t be a part of the communite. I&#39;m not trying to defend orkut or something, but I&#39;ve found a lot o friends that i&#39;ve not seen for many years and that is the power of orkut.. find or be together friends
I guess that make you unconfortable too... if you don&#39;t like don&#39;t try to finish with a whole ideia, that in my point of view is very good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Marcelo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-25T11:19:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-25T11:19:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
There are other reasons to be in jail. Some people say that people that &#34;spam&#34; a lot go to jail.
There are a link under the photo of any person that anyone can click. That link says report as bougus.
But I realy don´t know...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Marcelo Vergara&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-27T15:26:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-27T15:26:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
plz make me a member of orkut.com  plz.....
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;maliya&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-08-05T07:25:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-08-05T07:25:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Hi... I&#39;d like to ask how Orkut works...
Do i need to be invited to use Orkut??
thanks ... bye ...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;rafael&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-01T14:32:47-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-01T14:32:47-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Hi again :) ... People really go to jail because of orkut?!!?
They&#39;r real life is destroyed because a fucking idiot computer program???
if this is true......
Orkut users are a bunch of dumb people who riscs they&#39;r freedom at this idiot program of &#34;&#34;FRIENDS&#34;&#34;
thanks.... bye ....
sorry if i offended someone...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;rafael&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-01T14:36:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-01T14:36:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
well i dont know if u had experienced this but i found a different hole. i browsed throught friends and friends of friends and went to community search added a community and when i went to create one i found out that somebody in india is owner of it. i hit the home button and here i was at the home page of that indian guy. with all access from changing his profile to terminate his account.
well if i got there somebody can get to mine.
ANZ
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;amyn&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-06T13:30:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-06T13:30:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I have been playing around with Orkut a lot in the last 24 hours. One thing I don&#39;t understand about these Social Networking Platforms is why they ask for useless information and why they don&#39;t ask for the interesting things.
Example: Orkut gives me five large textareas to explain things like what I have learned from my past relationships. It lets me give Karma-Points to Phil Wolff if I think he is sexy. It lets me upload photos of my cat.
But it does not ask me if I have ever met Phil in person. (I have.) It does not ask me for how long I have known him. It does not distuinguish between &#34;friend&#34; and &#34;acquaintance&#34;.
It asks &#34;Is xxx your friend?&#34; and I am supposed to give a &#34;thumbs-up&#34; or a &#34;thumbs-down&#34;. (And if I say &#34;no&#34; I cannot even add an explanation to that. I hope I haven&#39;t hurt anybody.)
I don&#39;t get it. It would be so easy to gather this information and it would be so valuable. A simple &#34;have met in person&#34;-flag or something like &#34;How often have you met X?&#34; - &#34;never - once - several times - often - meet regularly&#34; would do it and give so much more depth to the network.
What is it that I am missing? Why is Orkut not gathering more data about the relationships of its members? (Like most of the information it could be optional - I bet many people would share it.) Please enlighten me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.edgenericpills.com&#34;&gt;Robin Smith&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-09T20:07:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-09T20:07:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
hi
i wnt to become a member of orkut
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;nasir&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-15T14:44:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-15T14:44:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i came across lifewithalacrity a while ago [6:20 pm GMT, Nov 18, 2004] while i was searching for answers regarding &#39;identity theft&#39; on orkut after suffering a harrowing experince on that social networking site. i&#39;ve been a member of Orkut for no more than 2 months now. i&#39;m a journalist and work for a satellite tv channel in Pakistan. i have so far added 16 friends to my freind&#39;s list on Orkut who r either journalists, or celebrated singers, or tv actors/actresses in my country. this is the first ever social networking forum i&#39;ve joined primarily becuase i have always had security concerns regarding privacy on other forums and because it was in affiliation with Google, offering a degree of reliability. throughout the time i have been a member of Orkut, i have sufferd loging and access problems on the site. there were times i culd not log into my account at all, or access my messages or access my friends. logging out was especially a major hassle becuase 8 out of 10 times i culdn&#39;t log out at the end of a session because when i tried to log out i got a messgae saying that the page i was trying to access was no longer available. i&#39;d try a couple of times and then close the browser window which was always a source of concern becuase i use cablenet connection and remain apprehensive of leaving my account open and vulnerable on the network server if i dont log out. i duly reported all of this to the orket team via emails but all they ever sent me were automated replies telling me that due to the rapid expansion of Orkut these problems wuld come up especially since the software was beta. Today however i got a real shock when i logged into my account at about 1:15 pm GMT. There were horrible messages sent from account to all my freinds [scribbled on their scrapbooks mostly], messages like &#39;hey guys i am gay&#39; and &#39;you suck!&#39;. my user name and password to my account are known only to me. i dont knwo how someone got access to my account and sent these messages to all my freinds and made posts in my name on the communities i am a member of.
my first instinct was to remove my account altogether from orkut. but then i thought that this was precisly what the malicious act was meant to do, to intimidate me ne and annoy me.
but i am seriously not sure what i should do to ensure my id is not stolen again. any suggestions?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;tahir&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-18T10:55:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-18T10:55:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;please ask me to orkut
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://us.f524.mail.yahoo.com/ym/login?.rand=bkhibvtb9dj1d&#34;&gt;mohamad&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-09T19:07:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-09T19:07:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Well dear, yet I have not been invited by any one to join orkut. Can you help me to join orkut.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Abbas&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-18T04:45:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-18T04:45:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;i can not go in orkut site cus of proxy how can i passed it iam living in iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com&#34;&gt;mani&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-31T01:06:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-31T01:06:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;hi mani,
Access http://www.openproxies.com
[]&#39;s
Weber Ress
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://weber.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Weber Ress&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-31T07:37:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-31T07:37:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
give me ID in orkut
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;snopy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-04T04:04:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-04T04:04:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i can not go in orkut site cus of proxy how can i passed it iam living in iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;sara&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-13T12:25:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-13T12:25:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i can not go in orkut site cus of proxy how can i passed it iam living in iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;neda&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-21T07:45:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-21T07:45:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Some guy named Junaid from Karachi, Pakistan put up my cell no. on orkut in the call girls&#39; list. I have been receiving countless phone calls from guys asking me how much i charge. This is pathetic because i don&#39;t even know any Junaid and i had never heard of this site till some guy called and told me that my cell no. was on display and so was my name under the call girl list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Maheen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-23T05:09:00-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-23T05:09:00-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>