<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Advice on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/advice/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Advice on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 23:55:42 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/advice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Mini Resume Card for Conference Season</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 23:55:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Between the business of the March/April conference season and leaving Blackphone, I&#39;ve run out of business cards. Rather than rush to print a bunch of new ones, I&#39;m created this mini-resume for digital sharing and a two-sided Avery business card version that I am printing on my laser printer and sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not as pretty as my old Life With Alacrity cards, but effective in getting across the diversity of my professional experience and interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; style=&#34;display: inline; border-style: solid; border-width: 2px; border-color: black;&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d0f2961e970c-pi&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d0f2961e970c image-full img-responsive&#34; title=&#34;Christopher Allen Micro Resume&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d0f2961e970c-800wi&#34; alt=&#34;Christopher Allen Micro Resume&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who teaches Personal Branding in my courses at BGI@Pinchot.edu, I always find it hard to practice as I preach to ask for advice and suggestions. In this case I&#39;m trying to tame my three-headed Cerebus of a profession with Privacy/Crypto/Developer Community, an Innovative Business Educator/Instructional Designer head, and my Collaborative Tools, Processes, Games and Play head. All come tied together in my body as ultimately being about collaboration, but it is hard to explain some of the correspondences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2015/03/mini-resume-card-for-conference-season.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing your Social Graph with Google&#43; [Google Plus]</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563798/&#34; title=&#34;Trust Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Trust Circle&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3230/3055563798_5355b9b99c_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With Google+ almost two weeks into its test phase, conversation about this new social network service seems to be going in circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because Circles is the Google+ feature that users are generating the most buzz about. It’s Google’s answer to the problem of organizing your social graph online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_graph&#34;&gt;social graph&lt;/a&gt; it’s a map of everyone you know and how they are related to you. Social graphs are tricky; as you try to define them you’ll inevitably run into some complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete Pachal, news director of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387808,00.asp&#34;&gt;@PCMag&lt;/a&gt; comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;“People want things easy, and Google Circles isn’t easy. It puts the burden on users to take the time to think about each and every contact and put them in a specific bucket. To use the feature effectively, users will certainly have to create new Circles, and that requires even more thought. After using Google+ for a few minutes last night, I was often unsure which Circles to put certain people in and, more to the point, which to leave them out of. And what if you create a new Circle that should include some of the people in other Circles you already have?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circles are lists that you’ve created by grouping people together and giving them a name. They’re important in Google+ because when you post you must explicitly say which “Circles” you wish to share with. Posting to a limited list of people is a big change from existing social networks such as Facebook, where posts are sent to all mutual friends by default, or Twitter, where posts are public. This change forces you to think more deeply about your social graph and who should see each item you post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BwvygI2xKGM&#34; width=&#34;560&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yourinitialsetofcircles&#34;&gt;Your Initial Set of Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google+ will present you with 4 suggested set of Circles: Friends, Family, Acquaintances, and Following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d image-full&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-800wi&#34; title=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Google+ also defines five special Circles: Two are only for reading: &amp;quot;Stream&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; and &amp;quot;Incoming&amp;quot; which is are posts that are shared to you by people not in your Circles. Then are three special Circles managed by Google only for posting: &amp;quot;Your Circles&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; “Extended” which is everyone in your Circles plus the people in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; Circles; and “Public” which is &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few find this default set to be sufficient. As a result, most Google+ users are soon creating new Circles, moving people around, renaming Circles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sound reasons for people finding the default Circles limiting. Sociological research shows that everyone has a number of concentric personal circles (see my blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt; for more details). These circles are sometimes called “ego-centric” social graphs as the individual is located in the center. This sort of graph is the model I used when I began reorganizing my own Google+ Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out using Support (for my Support Circle), Close (for my Sympathy Circle), Trusted (for my Trust Circle), and Colleagues (for my Emotional Circle), but that didn’t work for very long. I’ve since been experimenting with a number of different ways to organize my Circles. I wanted an initial set that would offer useful early advice for using Google+ but would still be applicable for when expanded to hundreds of people. (I now have over 600 people in my Circles.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One insight I’ve had is to avoid the word ‘friends’, which has been corrupted to almost meaninglessness in recent years. So instead I use terminology like Peers for my trust circle and Kith for the combination of my support and sympathy circles. (Kith may be familiar to you from the phrase “kith and kin”. The root of kith means “to know”, thus it’s those people that you know very well and that know you very well.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that sub-Circles exist within Circles. Using a ‘general ledger’ system of naming Circles with numbers—which I’ll demonstrate in a moment—helps me keep these Circles and sub-Circles in order and allows me to easily add new Circles when I need to. Hopefully Google+ will in the future introduce features that allow us to order Circles as we please, but until then this numbering system works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Google+ has also shown me that some Circles are for reading and other Circles are for posting. I’ll talk a little more about this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has only been a week, but by combining these insights to organize my Circles I’ve improved my ease of use and become better able to manage my time while using Google+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my recommended initial list of Circles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 ME&lt;/strong&gt; - a simple Circle with just yourself in it, for saving posts, for drafts, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.0 KIN&lt;/strong&gt; - your family &amp;amp; extended family&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt; 2.0 KITH&lt;/strong&gt; - your best friends, your confidants (i.e. those with whom one shares a secret or private matter, trusting them not to repeat it to others)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.0 PEERS&lt;/strong&gt; - your trusted colleagues, those who you work closely with, your collaborators&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.0 LOCAL&lt;/strong&gt; - your neighbors, parents of your children&amp;#39;s friends, people you&amp;#39;d invite to a party&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.0&lt;/strong&gt; {various groups &amp;amp; interests}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;/strong&gt; - people you know, but that you don&amp;#39;t know well or that don’t know you well&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;/strong&gt; - people who follow you on Google+, who you may or may not know&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;/strong&gt; - people whose posts you read, but who don&amp;#39;t necessarily read your posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 9.0 SPECIAL&lt;/strong&gt; - useful for special lists &amp;amp; exceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expandingcircles&#34;&gt;Expanding Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people will find my default set of ~10 Circles to be very useful, and need only add a few more. However, the design of this set is to allow for much greater expansion should you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like those “personal circles” that I wrote about previously, most of the Circles above are ego-centric: they’re fundamentally centered on your own personal social graph. This isn’t the only potential type of Circle, however. Socio-centric Circles aren’t centered on you, though they still have some sort of membership boundaries, while info-centric Circles are based on topics instead of being based on relationships. These socio-centric and info-centric Circles will support many relationships better than ego-centric Circles do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone seems to write a lot about a particular topic, I put him or her into an appropriate info-centric Circle. My own info-centric Circles thus include people who post about topics like iOS Development, the Social Web, Sustainability/Green, and Entrepreneuring. If a number of people are all part of a group or all come from a certain geographical area then I put them together in a socio-centric circle. After creating the Circles, I put the ones that were geographic into 4.0 of my ledger, then placed the others in 5.0. (I tried separating out groups and interests, and found that didn’t work, so now I keep them together.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now have over 600 people in my Google Plus+ social graph. All together my Circles now look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 Read Later&lt;br /&gt; 0.1 Drafts&lt;br /&gt; 0.2 Book Project&lt;br /&gt; 0.3 iPad Project&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 1.0 ALL KIN&lt;br /&gt; 1.1 Immediate Family&lt;br /&gt; 1.2 Extended Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 2.0 ALL KITH&lt;br /&gt; 2.1 Close Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.2 Old But Distant Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.3 Distant Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 3.0 ALL PEERS&lt;br /&gt; 3.2 Collaborators&lt;br /&gt; 3.3 Current Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt; 3.4 Former Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 4.0 ALL LOCAL&lt;br /&gt; 4.1 Local Kith, Kin &amp;amp; Peers&lt;br /&gt; 4.2 Local Berkeley&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Seattle&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Portland&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 5.0 ALL GROUPS &amp;amp; INTERESTS&lt;br /&gt; 5.1 Entrepreneurs&lt;br /&gt; 5.2 Apple &amp;amp; iOS&lt;br /&gt; 5.3 - iOSDevCamp&lt;br /&gt; 5.4 Green &amp;amp; Sustainability&lt;br /&gt; 5.5 - BGIedu&lt;br /&gt; 5.6 Social Web&lt;br /&gt; 5.7 - Jerry’s Kids&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;br /&gt; 6.1 Familiar Strangers&lt;br /&gt; 6.2 Friendly Strangers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;br /&gt; 7.1 Core Audience&lt;br /&gt; 7.2 Commented or Shared My Posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;br /&gt; 8.2 Pundits&lt;br /&gt; 8.3 Celebrities&lt;br /&gt; 8.4 Noisy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 9.0 ALL&lt;br /&gt; 9.1 Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy&lt;br /&gt; 9.2 Read Daily&lt;br /&gt; 9.3 Read Weekly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future blog post I’ll share my ongoing experience with using this approach to Circles, but this example shows how easy it is to separate and add Circles as your interests change and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;managingyourcircles&#34;&gt;Managing Your Circles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, enjoy social networks in large part because we get to interact with people. Managing your Circles is thus about more than just understanding your social graph. It also allows you to manage your time effectively when you read and share with other people on Google+. Here is my approach for how to manage the time you spend reading, sharing, and managing your social graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforreading&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Reading&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it useful to think about Circles that are explicitly for reading as different from Circles intended for sharing. I have a few of these read-only Circles. Thus, my “Pundits” Circle contains people that share a lot and for whom I don’t always want to read everything. My “Read Daily” Circle is conversely for people for whom I want to read everything they post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also found Circles helpful for close collaborators. It’s easy in Google+ to have a conversation with someone directly by simply typing their name as +&amp;lt;name&amp;gt; into the share field of posts. However, I find these direct posts get lost over time. To resolve this problem, create a Circle dedicated to just the two of you: a dyad. I have a number of people that I’m collaborating with closely and I use these small Circles to both keep track of our mutual posts and to see what they are thinking about at the moment. Examples of this kind of two-person Circle include my “Book Project” and “iPad Project”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofreadingcircles&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Reading Circles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day I look first at my “ALL KIN”, “ALL KITH” and and “ALL PEER” Circles to see what is going on with my support, sympathy and trust cliques. Then I’ll read my “Read Daily” Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading these daily basics (which I try to keep to a limited number), I’ll typically pick an interest, a geography, or a group, depending on what I’m doing that day. (My personal time-management style is to only follow one interest per day, e.g. if I am working on my iPad app then I’m not reading Social Web posts.) If I’m preparing a blog post and want to see what my audience is thinking I might review “Core Audience”, or “FOLLOWS ME”. If I’m traveling I might read one of my non-local Circles such as “Seattle”. If I’m doing ‘weak-signal research’ I might start with “ALL INTERESTS”, but if I’m particularly tolerant of noise I might read “Familiar Strangers”, “FOLLOWS ME”, “Everyone but Pundits &amp;amp; Strangers”, “Pundits”, or even “ALL”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;postingtocircles&#34;&gt;Posting to Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the important reasons for creating Circles in the first place is so that you can share with groups of people. I’ve developed some strategies for this as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforposting:&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Posting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it useful to create a Circle that only contains yourself. I have two of these — “Read Later”, and “Drafts”. If I’m reading and I see something interesting but don’t have time for it immediately, I’ll share it with my “Read Later” Circle so that I can quickly go back to it. Similarly, if I need to do some more research before writing and sharing, I’ll share my immediate thoughts in “Drafts”. As new features are added to Google+ these Circles will hopefully become obsolete, but they are useful for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofprivateposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Private Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sharing, you want to ask yourself if this is ‘private’ post, a ‘quasi-public’ post or a ‘public’ post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My private posts tend to go “KIN”, “KITH”, a dyad project, or one of the sub-Circles of PEER depending on their context. Some posts that are of only geographic interest (say a party, or local event) will be shared privately to the appropriate local Circle. If you are using my ledger system of using numbers in Circle names, these are the lower numbers—5.0 and below are Circles where I’m more sensitive about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once shared, these more personal posts will be labeled as “Limited” instead of using the “Public” label that allows anyone to see them. If a recipient tries to share a “Limited” post, a box will pop up reminding the person: “This post was originally shared with a limited audience – remember to be thoughtful about who you share it with”. Unlike Facebook or Twitter, one purpose of Circles on Google+ is to determine who gets what information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it may be easy to create Circles to segregate those with whom you wish to share private information, the recipients of your posts have no such limitations and could share outward beyond your intent (though they will be warned if they try to, as noted above). To enable further privacy you can disable resharing of these personal posts made to your Circles. To do so, share your post to a non-public Circle, then you select the arrow in the upper-right-hand corner where you can edit, delete or disable the post, and click on the final option, “Disable Reshare”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another privacy issue: by clicking the grey “Limited” label, a message’s recipient can see all others you shared the post with. This could potentially result in privacy problems, as the reader could discover who is in one of your Circles. There are ways of eliminating this by going into your Privacy account settings, which I will cover in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofquasi-publicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Quasi-Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call posts “quasi-public” when they’re of narrow interest to a specific group or a topic that isn’t really relevant to other members of my audience. I find these quasi-public posts happen the most for my more esoteric interests—for instance, when I’m sharing a complex iPhone development article that is really only interesting to a narrow group of my contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Google Reader, I typically wouldn’t share these articles at all because there were so many of my contacts that wouldn’t be interested in them and it would only be noise to them. Ditto with Twitter. I found that sometimes people would stop following me after a conference I attended because I posted regularly and the conference was not of interest to them. This could be quite frustrating at times. Though these posts were not private by any means, I only wanted to share them with a specific group, such as an iPhone group. Now with Circles, I can share this information easily with my “Apple &amp;amp; iOS” Circle. I find that this feature is what makes Google+’s Circles so potentially powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I might offer much of this more esoteric information as “quasi-public” posts to a specific group or interest, I’ll probably offer the best of them to the “Public”. Sometimes that is what it means to be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maven&#34;&gt;Maven&lt;/a&gt;—you share across social network boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofpublicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing a post to your “Your Circles” is effectively public, as is sharing to “Extended Circles”. Ask yourself if there is really some reason why you don’t want to make a post totally “Public” so that it is searchable by those who are not members of Google+. If there is some reason, consider sharing to your “ALL” Circle or some other more limited circle instead, as you’ll have more control and can turn off resharing or commenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;managingyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;Managing Your Social Graph&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining your Circles can take away from the time you can spend on reading and sharing. I’ve come up with the following strategy to limit the time I spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, I have some basic rules for which Circles to place people in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone is following me, I add them to “FOLLOWS ME” and an appropriate other Circle. If I vaguely recognize a follower’s name or face, I put them in “Familiar Strangers”. If I don’t recognize them at all but they look interesting, I add them to “Friendly Strangers”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone has +1’ed, commented, or mentioned me in a post, I add them to “Core Audience” and the appropriate sub-Circle. I will also make sure that the other Circles they are in are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I discover while I’m reading that someone is too noisy for the Circle I selected, I’ll move them to a more appropriate Circle—or place them in the “Noisy” Circle or even block them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Your Social Graph&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition I review a few of my Circles every day. I do so by going to “Manage Circles”, then selecting “People in your Circles” and sorting by last name. I choose that letter of the alphabet that corresponds to the day of the month and hover my mouse over each name. (For example, I look at names starting with “L” on July 12th, as “L” is the 12th letter.) Google+ highlights the Circles that each person is in. If they’re in the wrong Circle, I move them. I might even click on some people and review their profile so that I can see who they are—or (if I already know them) see what they are up to lately, update my address book, and maybe send them a brief email. At the end of the month (on the 27th through the 31st) I review my overall Circles lists. This way, over the course of each month I briefly review my entire social network, without spending too much time on it. (I try to spend 10 minutes or so a day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Periodically (right now weekly, but hopefully eventually monthly) I do some larger scale management of my Circles. Learning how to do this the first time is a pain, but once you know how it only takes a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to “Manage Circles” and select “People Who Have Added You”. I sort that list by “Not Yet in Circles”, “Select All” and add the people revealed to “FOLLOWS ME”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then do the same with all of my Circles to update my “ALL” Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I copy my “ALL” circle to “Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy” and remove any Pundits, Celebrities or Noisy people from that Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When managing your Circles, remember the motto “Perfection is the Enemy of the Good”. You are the only one that sees who is in which Circle, and you can place people in multiple Circles. So your Circles don’t have to be perfect, just good enough. If you share a lot of private posts, concentrate on making sure that those more personal Circles are more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these approaches, you should find Circle management quick, and you won’t get mired down in Circle management for hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish I had this organization when I started on Google+ two weeks ago. By using some of these techniques from the beginning I would have made my life a lot easier. Over the next month I now have to go back and re-organize people and re-Circle them. I hope sharing these tips will make your use of Google+ simpler from the start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I expect that Google will be adding new features to make Google+ easier. For instance I’m hoping for #hashtags (the ability to tag posts into topic categories), favorites (the ability to tag posts into a persistent archive, hopefully with an option tag), ordering Circles, concentric Circles, and better integration with Google Reader. (I share my favorite blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/reader/shared/ChristopherA&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; at &amp;#0160;and my best of best articles and posts in &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ChristopherA/favorites&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Twitter Favorites&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;or &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/christophera&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Delicious&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any new online feature, people are finding out new things and coming up with new ideas every day. So what are &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; methods for organizing your Circles and social graph?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to follow me on Google+, I’m at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/about&#34;&gt;+Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#39;d like to comment using Google+, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/posts/2eYjBB2CpNm&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;public comment thread&lt;/a&gt; about this post.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you would like to subscribe to my Google+ posts in Google Reader, use my &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;feed://plusfeed.appspot.com/113059510043663667610&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlusFeed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts from my blog related to this post:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some recent high signal-to-noise blog posts on Google+ and/or managing your Circles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107631581023945167601/about&#34;&gt;+Matt Stratton&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattstratton.com/tech-tips/how-i-set-up-my-circles-in-google-plus&#34;&gt;How I Set Up My Circles in Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113551191017950459231/about&#34;&gt;+Anson Alex&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ansonalex.com/tutorials/managing-circles-in-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Guide to Working with Circles in Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/101746196094367799224/about&#34;&gt;+Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/?p=2616&#34;&gt;The promise of Google+ for organizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104681313125038107957/about&#34;&gt;+Sterling Ledet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.weteachthecoolstuff.com/2011/07/09/a-thought-on-circles-privacy-vs-relevance/&#34;&gt;A Thought on Google+ Circles – Privacy vs. Relevance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/118432652629200965858/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Dave Pollard&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtosavetheworld.ca/2011/07/11/google-plus-on-communities-circles-friendship-and-love/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google+: On Communities, Circles, Friendship and Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethkanter.org/np-google/&#34;&gt;Are You Going To Adopt Google+ for Professional Learning/Networking? Why or Why Not?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104181568670836761473/about&#34;&gt;+Damon Morda&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brandedclever.com/five-steps-to-configuring-privacy-on-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Five Steps to Configuring Privacy on Google Plus (+)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some quality recent public Google+ posts regarding Google+ or managing your Circles (be sure to look over the comments):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/about/&#34;&gt;+Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/posts/ghn6Bu6tsmM&#34;&gt;My tips for newer users of Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/1SdhSBqwAmA&#34;&gt;Where circles can go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/D9bRJCmjJRV&#34;&gt;Sharing Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/XHvCRURHidx&#34;&gt;Is Google plus public or private?It’s neither, and both!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/posts/DV8QxNzTxaF&#34;&gt;Insightful Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/about&#34;&gt;+Craig Kanalley&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/posts/52dmpNDbWtp&#34;&gt;Tips &amp;amp; Thoughts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/about/&#34;&gt;+Paul Goode&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/posts/W9CaNrwku3x&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Sketch on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on related to this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;personal circles&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the of personal limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;familiar strangers&lt;/a&gt; - those people you recognize by face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustration by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;, Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/102320045646237908121/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Elyn Andersson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;for their assistance with this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I really like the idea of using circles for social time management. One big problem I have with networks is that I feel committed (obligated?) to a certain, indistinct, level of communication - particularly with those people that social media has now kept me in &#39;contact&#39; with, and whom in the old days I would have lost touch with. The end result is always a big time defecit and multiple layers of guilt. The idea of being able to apply some kind of equitable rationing/priority to circles may be a bit geeky... but it&#39;s preferable to non-specific angst  ;0)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/grimbold&#34;&gt;Grimbold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I like your ideas; I&#39;ve also been trying to play about with the circles &amp; work out something that works for me.
How, however, do you manage to add people to them, when you have quite so many (looking at the second list with the 1.3 etc) - I can only see 1.5 rows of circles! (OK, I know you can add someone by right clicking &amp; going for the add to circle, but that&#39;s fiddly if you&#39;re block adding them!)
I&#39;ve also got in the (equivalent of the) me circle my &#39;other&#39; G+ account, that I&#39;ve been using to see the effect of things like extended circles. Which I do find useful.
Would be nice, if, at some point, rather than having &#39;stream&#39; it was possible to see in a single stream all the updates from a set of circles, rather than 1 or all. (Unless that&#39;s something I&#39;ve yet to find!)
(That, and I want boolean logic for them, so I can have everyone who is in both a &amp; b, but not a or b!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/emmadw&#34;&gt;Emmadw&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Being an Angel</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/on_being_an_ang.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2006 18:17:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/on_being_an_ang.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alumni.unh.edu/connection/archives/12_03_04.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; title=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; src=&#34;http://www.alumni.unh.edu/connection/images/12_03_04/angel_investor.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In the last month or so I&#39;ve received a number of links to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Life With Alacrity&lt;/a&gt; as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ventureblogs.com/&#34;&gt;venture capital blog&lt;/a&gt;, and to myself as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.siliconbeat.com/entries/2006/01/09/two_more_silicon_valley_vc_bloggers_guy_kawasaki_christopher_allen.html&#34;&gt;venture capitalist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; However, I don&#39;t consider myself a venture capitalist. Instead, I am what is known as an &amp;quot;angel investor&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week has also seen a new topic enter the blog zeitgeist: the topic of reforming or reinventing venture capital. This topic was initially raised by &lt;a href=&#34;http://scripting.wordpress.com/2006/01/28/how-to-reform-the-vc-industry-in-five-easy-steps/&#34;&gt;Dave Winer&lt;/a&gt;, followed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://scobleizer.wordpress.com/2006/01/28/the-ventures-we-need/&#34;&gt;Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itgarage.com/node/737&#34;&gt;Doc Searls&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sapventures.typepad.com/main/2006/01/the_broken_vc_m.html&#34;&gt;Jeff Nolan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ensight.org/archives/2006/01/28/disrupting-venture-capital/&amp;gt;Jeremy Wright&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;a href=&#34; http://www.crunchnotes.com/?p=&#34;134&#34;&gt;Michael Arrington&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thatedeguy.com/archives/2006/01/the-future-of-vc&#34;&gt;Thatedeguy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.technorati.com/search/scripting.wordpress.com%2F2006%2F01%2F28%2Fhow-to-reform-the-vc-industry-in-five-easy-steps%2F&#34;&gt;many more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All types of venture investment -- seed, angel, venture, and institutional alike -- carry with it great risks and great rewards. But before we can reinvent venture capital and related venture funding methods like angel capital, we need to understand how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So What is a Venture Capitalist?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A venture capitalist is a partner or associate in a venture capital management firm, which manages money on behalf of large institutional investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, a large institutional investor (such as a pension fund or an insurance company) can statistically afford to invest a small part of their portfolio -- perhaps from 1% to as much as 5% -- in high-risk, long-term investments. If they lose the money outright, their other more stable investments have a good chance of making up the loss. But if the high risk investment does well, they can substantially improve their IRR (internal rate of return). To a certain extent they can&#39;t lose if they are careful. So these institutional investors invest in a number of types of high-risk funds, including such investments as venture capital funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A venture capital management company will manage one or more of these funds, investing in private companies. These VC management firms operate off of a management fee, from 2% to 3% of the capital invested to date. Thus all of the salaries for the staff of a VC management firm are paid, even if the investments are a failure. In addition, if any of the investments are successful, the VC management company earns 20% off of the top of the gain (called a &amp;quot;carry&amp;quot;), which is distributed to all of the full partners in the VC management firm, and sometimes a little of it to the associates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the VC associates that do the brunt of the work for a VC management firm. They make a good salary, but the real return is if they are able to do well in identifying, managing, and selling new startups; then they are invited to become a partner the next time the VC management firm raises a fund. Then if the fund that they are a partner in does well, they can make a true fortune, or even start their own VC management firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the odds are against the VC associate. It&#39;s common wisdom that an associate can&#39;t easily manage more the 7 firms at a time. Other common wisdom says that 1 in 5 investments will survive to break even and that 1 in 20 will &amp;quot;make the fund&amp;quot;, i.e. pay for all the losses in the other 19 investments. Some newer firms say 1 in 10, but I&#39;ll go with the older more conservative numbers. Thus associates are incentivized to try to manage more then 7 investments and to be smarter than their peers in the firm, so that at least one of their investments will be the 1 in 20 that makes the fund. This makes it easier for the associate to become a partner in the future, as at best 1 in 3 or 1 in 5 associates becomes a partner. Cutthroat competition between associates exists in some firms. This pressure often adds the perception that associates don&#39;t give enough attention to companies in their portfolio; they want their startups to do well, but the odds are it is another company that will make it, or a startup managed by peer associates. So they divide their attention. This is not unrelated to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Triage&lt;/a&gt; problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem that VC management firms face is the number of investments they are able to effectively handle. If there are 5-6 associates and 2-4 partners, there is probably a max of 50 investments that they have time to manage. If they are managing a $500 million dollar fund, that means that they have to invest at least $10M in a company, but in fact that is more likely to be $25M over time. If 1 in 20 makes the fund, that $25.0M has to give a return of $250M.&amp;nbsp; Thus when entrepreneurs complain that VCs will not invest in their company, it is often because the VCs can&#39;t figure out how to invest a minimum of $25M and turn out at the end with $250M. A related problem is that a startup that might have a successful business model that could grow into a profitable $50M annual revenues will be encouraged to take a more risky route so that they can go public, which requires a minimum of $100-200M annual revenues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of variety in VC management firms; some VCs have smaller funds under management, others give their associates more of a share, others have different management fees or carry percentages, and most specialize in some way: either vertically in a particular field, or horizontally in a particular stage of investment. For instance, there are some VC firms known as mezzanine firms that only invest in your company right before they think it can go public. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the way most VC management firms work. Periodically a new VC management firms will explore and push the limits of the above boundary conditions, but the more edges they attempt, the more likely they will fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Three Angels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is an angel investor? I learned a lot of what I know from the 3 angel investors that invested in my software startup, Consensus Development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gifford Pinchot -- Partner Angel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/gif_and_libba.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=467,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;145&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Gif_and_libba&#34; title=&#34;Gif_and_libba&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/gif_and_libba.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Gifford Pinchot, with his wife Libba, was my first angel investor in Consensus Development. We met at a Maxis meeting where Gifford had been asked to facilitate the formation of a new startup to create simulation software. At the end of the meeting we left frustrated with the results of the meeting, but Gifford liked what he heard about my broader vision. Gifford flew me to San Diego, where we walked the beach and discussed my vision for collaborative software. He liked what he heard, and later in the month flew me to his home in Connecticut, where I stayed for a month in a barn guest house near his home while we worked on our first business plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gifford only invested a low 5 figures, which got me started. However, it wasn&#39;t his money that was his most valuable contribution -- it was his time. Over the years he probably put 5-10% of his into time as Chairman of Consensus Development working with me, talking to me, advising me, and coached me. When our first software effort, InfoLog (a folksonomy tagging program like del.icio.us that was a decade too early) failed, he didn&#39;t walk away and instead encouraged me to continue. I dug deeper into the problem, discovered that trust and security were a key obstacle, and created a profitable consulting business. But Gifford encouraged me when I said we were going to take the risk of dropping all of our profitable consulting and focusing on a product, SSL Plus. Later, when this company was being shopped around to various buyers, Gifford spent lots of time doing due diligence, and ultimately came on half-time as CEO so that I could concentrate on selling the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, Gifford earned probably 7 figures on his initial 5 figure investment, close to a hundred-fold return on the dollars he invested. However, his real investment was the time he spent with me -- almost 10 years of never giving up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scott Loftesness -- Seed Angel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sjl.us&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;People_scott&#34; title=&#34;People_scott&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/people_scott.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I met &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sjl.us/&#34;&gt;Scott Loftesness&lt;/a&gt; when he was the executive vice president at &lt;a href=&#34;http://corporate.visa.com&#34;&gt;Visa International&lt;/a&gt;. We learned of each other through CompuServe, where we both were sysops in the 80s. I did some consulting for him at Visa in the groupware area over a couple of years and we grew to respect and trust each other. I came to him when I branched out from groupware consulting and began to include consulting on cryptographic security. I&#39;d seen an opportunity--I had a potential contract from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsasecurity.com&#34;&gt;RSA Data Security&lt;/a&gt; to be a distributor of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csm.ornl.gov/~dunigan/rsaref.txt&#34;&gt;RSAREF&lt;/a&gt;--but in order to take advantage of this opportunity I needed some seed capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott invested over twice what Gifford invested, but still 5 figures. However, like Gifford, what I gained from my association with Scott was a lot more then the seed capital. He had a respected name in the industry -- a friend at Visa USA told me &amp;quot;Scott is where all innovation at Visa flows from.&amp;quot; He joined my board of directors, supported our risky choice to drop all groupware and cryptographic consulting to focus on our SSL project, helped tremendously in doing due diligence on potential buyers, and was pivotal to the negotiations to close our final sale of Consensus Development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, Scott Loftesness also did quite well in his investment in Consensus Development. His involvement on the day-to-day operation of Consensus Development was significantly less, but he was always around to support and advise us when we needed him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jim Bidzos -- Hands-Off Angel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/bidzos.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Bidzos&#34; alt=&#34;Bidzos&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;
Jim Bidzos was the CEO of RSA Data Security, whose firm had a critical patent on almost all meaningful cryptographic security. Over the years I did a lot of consulting for him to support various projects like RSAREF in standards, to create client tools for their Certificate Services Division, and to help with the founding of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.verisign.com&#34;&gt;Verisign&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I told Jim that RSAREF would never be successful in his goal of promoting the RSA algorithm in security standards as long as it could only be sold through RSA salespeople. They preferred to sell RSA&#39;s premiere toolkit, BSAFE. I somewhat jokingly proposed that maybe Consensus Development should sell it instead. To my surprise, he agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years later I leveraged the fact that Consensus Development had the only RSA toolkit available other then RSA&#39;s own to get the contract to develop the reference implementation of SSL 3.0 for Netscape. I took this Netscape contract back to Jim and said that I needed some investment to make this successfully. He invested a middle six figures in Consensus Development in return for a percentage that was roughly equivalent to that of Gifford and Scott, but because of his involvement as CEO of RSA Data Security he could not be on our board of directors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this investment, Jim had very little to do with Consensus Development. In fact, he had spread his angel money so widely in the cryptographic security industry that he was also invested in a couple of our competitors. In the end his investment was worth roughly 10 times what he invested, but the cachet of being able to tell others that Jim Bidzos was an investor made Consensus Development much more &amp;quot;legitimate&amp;quot;, which also added significant value to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Founding of Alacrity Ventures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I left &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.certicom.com/&#34;&gt;Certicom&lt;/a&gt;, the company that had purchased my firm, Consensus Development (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/security_crypto.html&#34;&gt;Bad Business of Fear&lt;/a&gt; for more info), I wondered what I should do next. I could theoretically retire if I abandoned the Bay Area, but I was not ready for that and I thought I had maybe enough capital to start one more business of my own instead. Under a non-compete from Certicom, I was not sure what type of non-cryptographic business I wanted to start. So I decided that one thing I could do was some angel investing. In part this was to make money, but a larger part of it was that I enjoyed working with entrepreneurs. I wanted to do for others what Gifford Pinchot had done for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did some study about how venture economics works, how angels and venture capital firms invest, and became concerned. I saw that being an angel investor in many ways is much harder then being a venture capitalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest challenges is that angels share all the problems of the institutional investor, of the VC management firm, and of the VC associate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first challenge is deciding how much to invest. The institutional investors only risk 1%-5% of their capital. If I limited myself to that amount I could maybe invest in a couple of companies. I decided I was still young and could risk investing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem was no management fee -- unlike a VC firm, angels don&#39;t get a management fee to cover salaries, legal fees, other expenses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third problem was my time. Most angels still work for a living -- being an angel investor is part-time, a venture capitalist typically works full-time. If only 1 in 20 investments &amp;quot;make the fund&amp;quot;, but I could at most manage 7 investments, that meant that I had a 2/3rd&#39;s chance of losing my entire investment. I might be able to argue that for some kinds of businesses I might more informed than the average VC, and thus might be able to make better choices, but not &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/harold.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Harold&#34; alt=&#34;Harold&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;
The key, I decided, was to work with at least 2 other angel investors. That would theoretically allow us to invest in 21 companies, diversify our portfolios, and split the work. I approached my first angel investor, Gifford Pinchot, and he agreed to be one of the partners. The second was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alacrityventures.com/shattuck.html&#34;&gt;Harold Shattuck&lt;/a&gt;, who had done some due diligence and operations consulting for Consensus Development, and had been VC once before, but enjoyed being closer to the actual building of a new company with some operating interaction. I was the managing partner for files and accounting, but we all brought to the table our &amp;quot;deal flow&amp;quot;, performed due diligence together, and worked closely with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons from Alacrity Ventures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alacrity Ventures is over 6 years old, and I have learned many lessons from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I feel that we did a good job selecting our investments, during a time in which being an angel investor was very difficult. I discovered that Gifford, Harold and I were really good at due diligence; our differing skills, Gifford&#39;s in coaching and evaluating the management team, Harold&#39;s in operations and business models, and mine in technology truly complemented each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I could say that the good news was that that out of 13 investments, all but 1 were still in business. However, we were never able to invest in the 21 investments that we planned because we discovered a significant problem in angel investing: the VC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The angel investor can only really afford to invest early on, as a seed investor, or in an early investment round such as series A. However, the firms we invested in needed more money along the way; in fact, almost all firms need money at more then one point. The venture climate at the time was such that the VCs required in their term sheets that previous investment rounds lose their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.feld.com/blog/archives/2004/07/liquidation_pre.html&#34;&gt;liquidation preferences&lt;/a&gt;, and ultimately their investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give a specific example -- we invested in a first round of an enterprise software company in 2000 that is still around today. In 2002 they needed more money, and because of the difficulty in getting VC investment, the lead VC insisted that the preferences from the previous rounds be removed, effectively making us common stock, unless we participated in this subsequent round. We reluctantly did invest some more, but because we don&#39;t have the funds that a VC has, we were only able to protect some of our preferred stock. A year and half later, the software company needed more money, and the VC did it again. This time, all our stock was converted to common. Now it is 2006, and the company might be acquired this year; however the VCs, because of their liquidation preferences, will get the first $65 million (or more). As I doubt the firm is worth more then $50M, we will not get anything, nor will any of the other founders that are no longer involved with the firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has repeated itself over and over again. We made a decent choice and did our due diligence well, but subsequent VC investors have pushed us out. A few of our ventures have failed outright. That is understandable given our original 1 in 20 expectations. But what we didn&#39;t expect was how difficult it was going to be to participate in the upside. Yes, we had preferences in our early rounds that should have protected us, but they didn&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So of our 13 investments, only 2 remain that may &amp;quot;make the fund&amp;quot;: a very innovative high-tech titanium powder manufacturer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itponline.com/&#34;&gt;ITT&lt;/a&gt;, and a high-tech manufacturer of ceramic devices &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vapore.com/&#34;&gt;Vapore&lt;/a&gt;. But even as these two investments survive, they are still vulnerable to requiring additional investment and possibly forcing us out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the rest: one of our early investments sold to VeriSign at a 50% premium, our investment in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salon.com&#34;&gt;Salon.com&lt;/a&gt; will give us a small return, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com&#34;&gt;MG Taylor&lt;/a&gt; paid off its loan, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt; may someday pay back its original investment. The other 8 are being written off as a loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advice to Angels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in spite of the odds, you still want to become an angel investor? Here is some advice...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborate with other angels:&lt;/strong&gt; Going it alone is dangerous -- there are a number of angel investor networks, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://gatheringofangels.com/&#34;&gt;Gathering of Angels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bandangels.com/&#34;&gt;Band of Angels&lt;/a&gt; and others in listed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inc.com/articles/2001/09/23461.html&#34;&gt;Directory of Angel-Investor Networks&lt;/a&gt;. Be careful, though, the enthusiasm of others can be contagious -- don&#39;t always go with the herd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do your own due diligence:&lt;/strong&gt; I can&#39;t emphasize this enough. Talk to the entrepreneurs and meet their staff. Read their business plan and tear it apart. Find the hidden assumptions. Understand their business model. It needs to feel realistic. Try to get more eyes on the job: different people see different things. Don&#39;t follow others; they may have different investment criteria then your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be an advisor first:&lt;/strong&gt; Be an advisor first -- if the entrepreneurs don&#39;t listen to your advice, don&#39;t invest. If you have to invest to become an advisor, invest only a small amount, or have part of the money be contingent on a meaningful goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guard your upside:&lt;/strong&gt; When negotiating terms, don&#39;t worry about the downside. It is the VCs that need items on the term sheet for when things go wrong -- what you need to guard is for when things go right. Watch for changes in the executive staff -- they may be incentivized differently than you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider a secured loan:&lt;/strong&gt; Somewhat contrary to the &amp;quot;guard your upside&amp;quot; advice, rather then investing only in stock, consider investing via a secured loan as well. The security can not only be on hard company assets, but intellectual property such as copyrights, trademarks or patents. Your return will be lower on the loan, but if you can get all of your investment back early and get a small percentage of the company, it can be a good way to balance risk. Just remember to file the property documents to make sure that the assets are properly secured, and be prepared that someday you may own that asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Save $2 for every $1:&lt;/strong&gt; Almost every company you invest in, even if successful, will need additional funding. Make sure that you keep on hand $2 for every $1 initially invested. This will also help you from being squeezed out by later VC investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invest in acquisition targets:&lt;/strong&gt; Let the VCs take companies public -- the companies that you should be interested are the companies that will eventually be acquired. Creating an acquisition target requires the management to think differently -- coach them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the founders dilemma:&lt;/strong&gt; There are many &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessleader.com/bl/mar01/feature1.html&#34;&gt;founders dilemmas&lt;/a&gt;, however, one is particularly important to the angel investor. A founder may be incentivized to sell sooner then his early investors. Remember that most often, the only significant asset that a founder has is his company. If the founder has an opportunity to sell early and buy a house, he might, even if it may not be enough return on investment for the risk that the angel took. Find ways to keep your interest aligned with that of the founders, which may include even buying some stock directly from the founder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider alternative exits:&lt;/strong&gt; There are lots of boutique opportunities that are too small for VCs. I know of a local Berkeley software company that was number one in their market, but too small to go public. They had $20M in annual revenues, and profits of almost $10M, but little opportunity for growth -- early investors could have gotten their money back in dividends rather than sale of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time the cycle:&lt;/strong&gt; We didn&#39;t invest at the ideal time for the angel investor. We picked well considering the times, but had we waited for a few years it would have been easier. Not to say that timing is everything; we&#39;d have lost our titanium powder opportunity if we&#39;d waited for better market timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respect people:&lt;/strong&gt; Treat the people you invest in like a paying client. Respect their time and concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be prepared that the plan will change:&lt;/strong&gt; I&#39;ve never been involved with a business where the business plan doesn&#39;t significantly change. As an angel investor you need to help your businesses to plan for those changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advice to Entrepreneurs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you want investment from an angel investor? Some advice...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recognize the odds:&lt;/strong&gt; The angel investor is taking a substantial risk investing in your company -- you need to be able show a scenario where the investor might be able to make 10x or 20x their investment. So if you are looking for $100K, you need to show how the angel can ultimately have stock worth $1M to $2M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider their advice:&lt;/strong&gt; Angel investors may not always be right, but show them that you are listening. If you use angels for more then just a source of money, you&#39;ll get a lot more value from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Draft your business plan:&lt;/strong&gt; An angel investor does not need as complete a business plan as a VC does, but they need to see how you think. You should clearly identify what the product or service is, who is going to buy it, what is the marketplace that those buyers may find it in, what differentiates your product or service and why your team is good enough to deliver. Angel investors know that your plan will change, probably drastically, but if they understand your thinking process they can be more confident that your company will survive change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It takes time:&lt;/strong&gt; Don&#39;t count on the money from an angel investor (or any investor) until you get the check. Investors are always selecting from a number of choices, often very competitive choices. No matter how optimistic you are, it is likely it will take 6 months or likely more to raise angel money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team with Many Hats:&lt;/strong&gt; Angel investors don&#39;t recruit new team members for you. You don&#39;t necessarily have to have your whole team in place, but there at least needs to be someone who has experience managing, someone with development experience, someone with marketing experience, and someone with sales experience. Whatever team is there, they need to be able to juggle all of those hats. Financial, HR, and administrative positions can all be part-time or farmed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advice to Venture Capitalists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value the angel investor:&lt;/strong&gt; The angel investor serves a point in the marketplace that you are not able to serve. Rather then driving them out, find some way for them to continue to participate so that they can find other ventures for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Angels are not VCs:&lt;/strong&gt; The angel investor can&#39;t afford to invest in later rounds -- their model is different than yours. It may make sense to force participation in subsequent rounds by other VCs, but carve out some room for angels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The future of Alacrity Ventures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I&#39;ve enjoyed some aspects of being an angel investor, I enjoy working with creative people to innovate new products more. I expect to spend most of my time in the next few years continuing to explore social software and collaboration tools, and the new product opportunities that may evolve from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus I expect that any future angel investments I make will be more along the lines of Gifford&#39;s style of investment in Consensus Development: a small investment of money and a large investment of time. Harold and Gifford both feel the same way. Currently we plan to continue monitoring our existing investments, but don&#39;t plan any new investments unless we can take a more active role in the firm -- for instance Harold is a board member in Vapore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gifford is now dedicating his life to building a better world by transforming business education. He is a co-founder and President of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bgiedu.org&#34;&gt;Bainbridge Graduate Institute&lt;/a&gt;, which provides an MBA program integrating sustainability, green economics, the internet, and open source within a traditional MBA program. As an open source school, he helps other schools to use BGI’s curriculum. Check out his blog entry on &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pinchot.com/gifsplace/2006/02/angel_philanthr.html&#34;&gt;Angel Philanthropy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#39;s one thing we&#39;ve learned from six years of angel investing, one thing that may be more valuable than all the nuts and bolts I describe here, it&#39;s that Gifford Pinchot&#39;s partner-style of angel investment is what suits our investing style, not Jim Bidzos&#39; style of hands-off angel investing, and that&#39;s a lesson that we&#39;re going to carry forward with Alacrity Ventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Excellent article.  advice for everyone through lessons learned.  I love it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.osilla.com&#34;&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-01T08:38:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-01T08:38:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;m with a company that is more hungry for advice than money. If a company contacted you strictly for the purpose of seeking your advice on building a social network, would you consult with them in exchange for equity?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://tablesturned.com&#34;&gt;Marcus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-01T17:40:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-01T17:40:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It depends on the product and the people behind it. Typically I&#39;ll charge to offer consulting in areas of my expertise, but offer to reduce my fees in return for equity. If it interests me and it isn&#39;t going to take too much time, I will consider offering advice for equity only. If it something that really turns me on, I&#39;ll offer to be on an advisory board for equity. So the range of possibilities is pretty broad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-01T23:33:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-01T23:33:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
In response to &#34;Angel Philanthropy from Gifs Place&#34;
(Currently in Dublin, Ireland) Was at an excellent presentation a few weeks ago for something which you might consider an angel fund for not-for-profits.
In a nutshell they provide a support and a series of levels where someone with an idea for a not-for-profit can be supported through a variety of levels
Level 1 is designed to help new ideas become real projects. Level 1 is aimed at individuals who are not yet working full time on their projects to help with the running costs. Awards consist of once-off investments
Level 2 is designed to support existing social entrepreneur led projects. Level 2 will include financial support towards the living expenses of award winners allowing them to work full time on their projects. Awards consist of 2 year investments
They support individuals who have a passion for a particular not-for-profit concept rather than an organisation
Linky is http://www.socialentrepreneurs.ie/
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;TomB&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-02T13:36:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-02T13:36:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
This post is great.  I am a founder of a start-up that raised some money via the &#34;friends and family&#34; network and are now working on setting ourselves up for another round of capital.  Your comment on being ready for the business plan to change is incredibly true.  Our current model and products (even though not entirely different) is not what they were when we initially started.  BUT I believe that is how a startup grows and better positions itself.  You learn as you go along and work hard to make sure you are constantly improving your business.
I do have a question about business plans.  We did do an extensive business plan the first time around.  It took me a very long time plus 6 versions to get to that point.  What is your view on how in depth a plan really needs to be?  Should we do a traditional 30 page plus plan or stick to something short and concise that answers the important questions?
Thanks.  Again this post was inspiring.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Michael Prichard&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-08T16:24:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-08T16:24:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;&gt; What is your view on how in dept a plan needs to be?
I&#39;m somewhat torn here on what advice to give. The reality is that the executive summary is the most that most investors will ever see, however, if you make it past that hurdle, the business plan must be a good answer to &#34;how&#34; questions raised by the summary. Also, no &#34;complete&#34; business plan is going to compensate for the basic facts of the business -- do you have a team that has the ability to deliver the product? I&#39;ve read many good business plans where I was unconvinced the team could execute on it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-08T23:25:22-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-08T23:25:22-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thank you Christopher for discussing your experience as an angel.  This is an important post because is provides detail and data to support the notion that one part of our capital market for creating new companies is broken.  I say broken because there are well-intentioned people (angels, friends and family) that are being invited to invest money in a situation where they really do not understand the risk:  that they are setting themselves up to be crammed down upon the next round of financing.  Some times the people writing the placement memorandums are not making this particular risk explicit and similarly there are entrepreneurs pitching deals that are not proactively addressing this issue - either by telling investors there is a fair change of being crammed down, or taking a strong position on protecting first round investors.
Now, let&#39;s say risks are made clear and they are understood.  The entrepreneurs and individuals who manage other people&#39;s money are certainly going to do what is in their economic interest.  Hopefully it is clear that the &#34;innovation industry&#39;s&#34; long run economic interest just might include respecting the angel class of risk capital.  If not, high net worth investors will find better ways to play; and of course, this is exactly what continues to happen.  Investors who are committed to investing as angels are organizing themselves and their industry.  Founders are understanding the need to protect their friends, family and angel investors by getting them series a preferred stock rather than LLC shares or common stock with warrants; and there are some VCs who are want angels do well as much as they want their fund to be the first capital in.  All this suggests that perhaps the only problem is one of education and awareness, and I am glad that Christopher&#39;s post will help provide people both.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fountainpartners.com/Research.html&#34;&gt;Tom Carter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-27T02:14:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-27T02:14:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;&gt; Founders are understanding the need to
&gt; protect their friends, family and angel
&gt; investors by getting them series a
&gt; preferred stock rather than LLC shares
&gt; or common stock with warrants
Unfortunately, even participating in a Series-A Preferred doesn&#39;t protect you -- subsequent rounds of investment can have priority, and often VCs are requiring that previous rounds preferences are removed.
We as Series-A investors as a class could theoretically deny the VC, and probably bankrupt the company. However, in practice that is impossible as enough of the Series-A investors are either committed to the current management team that they&#39;ll vote yes, or sufficient of the Series-A investors think that they&#39;ll get $0.10 on the dollar vs zero, or sufficient Series-A investors participated in later rounds that they are willing to write-off the Series-A round.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-27T11:27:03-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-27T11:27:03-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This post was excellent. Getting the chance to walk in the shoes of both the entrepreneur seeking capital and an angel investor managing investments is rare and valuable.
One thing that can also help entrepreneurs looking at angel investors is understanding the culture of the industry. There&#39;s a great podcast at this URL:  http://www.fundinguniverse.com/podcasts/bill-payne2-fundinguniverse.mp3 by the name in angel investing: Bill Payne. He shares what he&#39;s learned from his many investing experiences and gives some great info on what to expect as an entrepreneur seeking angel money.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://fundinguniverse.com&#34;&gt;SBarth&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-03-20T15:07:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-03-20T15:07:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris, what a thoughtful, well-considered and accurate post! It&#39;s always interesting to see how the paths we wend in life cross and re-cross. [Chris and I first met over 20 years ago in the ferment of the early Mac and online days, when both of us were Sysops on Compuserve, among other things.] For my part I started entrepreneuring in the tech space in the late 1980s, and eventually rode the cycles of booms and busts up and down to great heights and great depths. Along the way I, like you, began angel investing (after my long-suffering spouse refused to let me start another startup :-), with a mix of companies in both the active and passive angel mode. Coincidentally, one of my most active investments is in a network security company, KoolSpan (www.koolspan.com), that is doing some insanely neat stuff you might find of interest.
Also like you, I quickly realized the great benefits of cooperative angel investing, and also started up an angel group, spun out of the erstwhile New York New Media Association. New York Angels (www.newyorkangels.com) has grown over the past several years to over 65 members (including people like Esther Dyson, Alan Patricof, Gideon Gartner and a bunch of other well-known investors) and half a dozen early stage VC funds, who work and play well with us, and value the role that angels occupy in the life-cycle of early stage companies. In the past three years we&#39;ve invested over $14 million in over 20 companies, which actually brings us close to the scale of a small VC fund (although everyone still decides and funds individually).
However, as you well know, once an entrepreneur, always an entrepreneur, and after several years of sideline-investing, I finally got permission from The Boss to start up another company, and thus, combining both my technical background and my angel background, was created...Angelsoft! For the past two years we&#39;ve been working on developing a comprehensive platform for supporting angel investors and entrepreneurs, and the result will finally be unveiled next week at the annual summit meeting of the Angel Capital Association, which is being held in New York.
Angelsoft, which is currently in beta with over two dozen angel groups around the world (including that of Bill Payne, who is appropriately cited by the previous commenter as a wonderful resource for angels and entrepreneurs) is a soup-to-nuts solution (www.angelsoft.net/tour) designed specifically to remove as much friction as possible from the angel investment process, and thus help get more investments into more early stage deals. I&#39;ll be fascinated to hear your thoughts on it if you get a chance to take a look.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.newyorkangels.com/members/david_rose.html&#34;&gt;David S. Rose&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-04-22T08:03:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-04-22T08:03:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris: after reading this post I realized that we had more in common than just our mutual &#34;investment&#34; in MG Taylor. After 20 years of founding and leading companies to either sucessful exit or failed &#34;no-exit&#34;, I became a VC partner in a medium size Venture Firm-and after finding the process not to my liking joined the Band of Angels as an early member. I found my experiences on all 3 sides of the early stage investing practice - Entrepreneur/Founder, VC Partner, Angel Investor calibrate well with what you report and advise in your post.
As an active Angel member of the Band of Angels, I spent several years with Matt and Gail Taylor at Knowhere in Palo Alto attempting to learn how to apply many of the processes that were in practice at Knowhere to the due diligence investigation of startup companies. Feeling that we had found a unique way to conduct the practice of investing and managing a portfolio of startups, in late 2000, we opened a venture development &#34;accelerator&#34; called VentureStream fashioned along the lines of the advice you provide in your post.
- Along with an almost complete committment of the first tranche of a $100 Million Fund, we had aggregated over 100 top-flight advisor/investors to help what we hoped would be a select cadre of successful startups. We built the VentureStream Accelerator with Knowhere-style furniture, hired some of the MGT alumni to help us with the graphical facilitation we were applying to our due diligence and startup investigation process, and partnered with Ernst and Young, who had just bought out their Design Shop license from the Taylors.
I figured with that combination we would have a very promising future.
Our timing on raising $100Million for VentureStream was exactly wrong and so, and as the dotcom bubble began to burst,  we were unable to close on the necessary funding to proceed, and we closed Venturesteam having made only one investment in a spinout partnership from Ernst and Young named RealFoundations. Must have done something right since I just received a very nice cash return on my investment and my ex-partners have gone on to very successful practices themselves.
LESSON: TIMING IS EVERYTHING - and I should have learned it from my first investor/mentor Sam Bodman(then head of Fidelity Ventures, and now Secy of Energy in Bush&#39;s cabinet) Sam said &#34;At a time when feeding frenzy drives the VC industry and startups can get exorbitant first round valuations, and when deals have to be made in &#34;internet time&#34; = that&#39;s the time to sit on the sidelines with your money and wait until the bubble bursts.
I think the investment practice of both my previous professional VC partnership and more particularly the Band of Angels was very haphazard and given to very impulsive decision making. I was trying with VentureStream to do better but our timing was not right.  I think both Angels and VCs have it better now that the bubble frenzy has segued into more reasonable valuations and time to do the diligence. However, other than good timing, skillful creation and filtering of prime deal flow and outstanding and continuous project management of the portfolio companies, nothing substitutes for having enough experienced bandwidth in partners/associates/angels as you so wisely point out.
Having left VentureStream five years ago to be an historical footnote on the Wayback Machine, I am content to meander the field of venture philanthropy as a social venture catalyst - seeking to find companies who have that unique hybrid makeup that my friend Jed Emerson calls the Blended Value Proposition. Gifford Pinchot would know what I mean and I would guess you do too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.thoughts-illustrated.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Dave Davison&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-05-12T17:23:39-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-05-12T17:23:39-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I came across this post thanks to your reply to the question in LinkedIn about angel investors.  I recently began organizing a startup for a subscription based career management website which is a new experience for me.  Your effort to share has increased my understanding.  Thank you for the great information and advice.
cheers,
Todd
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/in/toddthigpen&#34;&gt;Todd Thigpen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2007-01-07T11:29:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2007-01-07T11:29:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Thanks for this candid insider account of angel investing from the trench. One thing strikes me as a bit ironic though: if all business plans don&#39;t go as planned, why are we fussing about driving it down to details in due diligence, apart from it being a good exercise? I would think that the vision/mission for a venture should stay in the same direction, though the tactics and specific routes to get there tend to develop and adjust over time. Otherwise, you are basically funding a different company than what you originally set out to back, isn&#39;t that true? I would argue that companies discarding their original plan rather than just tweaking some details tend to fail more often, or at least having less of a chance of making it really big.
I guess I&#39;ve heard too much on how the original plan turns out to be something totally different and want to offer a balance: we can and shall still value our in-depth thought put in upfront. There are still high quality ideas to be had at the onset.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Joshua Zhao&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2007-01-11T16:40:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2007-01-11T16:40:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2006/01/on_being_an_ang.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Advice to Social Networking Services</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2004 11:39:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have now had CEOs of three different social networks send me emails asking me to compare Orkut to their service. I&#39;ve not had a chance to dig deeply into good answers for each specific one, but I did have some general advice that I wanted to offer given my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;recent experiences with Orkut.com&lt;/a&gt;, and my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html&#34;&gt;evaluation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2003/12/followup_to_eva.html&#34;&gt;followup&lt;/a&gt; on various social networking services in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Privacy&lt;/h4&gt;
First, be extremely careful about privacy issues. For some of you outside the US, you may not know about what has been going on in the area of identity theft, but it has become a significant problem. I am not a privacy fanatic, but I am concerned that social networking services encourage people to reveal too much information too broadly, and that this will be someday be taken advantage of by identity thieves. For instance, many services ask for birthday and reveal it to everyone. You can ask for the birthday, but don&#39;t display it -- give the person&#39;s age, or birth month, but don&#39;t give the full info. I personally am particularly wary of billing address, billing zip code, birthday, and potential common security questions like name of pet, mother&#39;s maiden name, etc. These are in addition to the obvious targets of identity theft like SSN, full name, and account numbers.
&lt;p&gt;Orkut&#39;s interface for selectively allowing some fields to be visible &#34;only to myself&#34;, &#34;to friends&#34;, or to &#34;friends of friends&#34; is nice, but I wish it was for all fields. I also think every field by default should be set to &#34;only to myself&#34;. In fact, all security parameters should default to reveal the least information, and have the tightest limits -- allow the user to open selectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are going to support all different kinds of social networks (dating, friendships, activities, business) consider finding ways to make sure that those people who are not using the service for dating are not asked for that info, and don&#39;t see it for others who are dating. People who are only using it for dating shouldn&#39;t see business info. If someone is using a service for all types of relationships, allow people to selectively set what they reveal to each group, say two columns of &#34;only to connections who are dating&#34; or &#34;only to business connections&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never reveal someone&#39;s email address or other critical information without them knowing about it. In particular there are issues with emails sent among members. The only safe way is to do redirection through your site (although that will cost you bandwidth.) But if you can&#39;t do that, then just tell people &#34;your email will be revealed if you do this&#34; -- that is enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard on your TOS and Privacy terms. Don&#39;t let your lawyers rule you here too much -- find some way to get your principles out there and still cover yourself against problems. Make all the personal information that people give you be their information -- they are only leasing it to you temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make it easy for someone to quit the system. Maybe offer to them to export their information in case they want to rejoin later, and give them an opportunity to send a last message to any connections they may have. Be friendly at all times, and as the market shakes out they may come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Connections &amp; Invites&lt;/h4&gt;
If possible, find some other way to call the connections between people &#34;friends&#34; -- maybe even use a unique trademarkable term. There is some power in the emotions behind the word friends that helps with the virus-like nature of social networking software, but I think in the long term it is a bad idea. LinkedIn and Spoke use the word connections which sounds too mechanical, but I think it is better then &#34;friends&#34;.
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t encourage the &#34;how many friends do my friends have&#34; game. It sets up bad behaviors, and as you grow you don&#39;t want to have barriers of entry to new people who feel that they can&#39;t compete in that game. This means don&#39;t sort friends or groups etc. by the number of friends they have by default -- it can be an option, but just not be default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t encourage people to by default upload their address book. Have that feature be off of some optional utility page. Have the default option for it to just scan for people that are already members of your system and to forget the rest -- that is effectively what I do with systems that ask for address book information, and they make it hard for me to do so. Don&#39;t store people&#39;s address information for them unless you can sync them with people&#39;s personal contact books -- save that for version 2.0, not 1.0 beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t focus on people contacting new people that are not already their connections. It is not the number of connections, but the quality. Instead, focus on helping people with their weak connections. It is &#39;reconnection&#39; that is the most powerful feature of these social network services, not new connections. You can also help with &#34;triage&#34; -- how do I maximize the value of my existing weak connections with the least effort?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow people to opt-out with a custom message. What this means is that if someone sends an email to someone who has opted out, they will get something like. &#34;Thanks for inviting me to Orkut -- I&#39;ve decided for now not to join, but you can find me on Tribe.&#34; However, keep a list of people who have tried to connect to that opted-out user, and if that user does change their mind later, it will make it easier for them to have an initial list of friends that may already be on the service. Yes, I know that this risks sending people to other services, but there are so many now that you can get good buzz by doing the right thing, and recovering those people later when they have confidence in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to have better methods of handling invites from unknowns without saying no. For instance &#34;I&#39;m not sure I know you, have I forgotten?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related, don&#39;t fill out default text for invitations and other request forms -- force people to put something personal into the request, don&#39;t allow it to be blank. Never do what Orkut does and not give the opportunity to offer text when you invite someone who is already on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid anything beyond friends of friends as a primary part of your service. It bugs me that I see by default 3 degrees away in many services -- 2 degrees should be max by default, as that is the level that real referral can work. 3 degrees is too far for users to trust (though it can be optional for some purposes, or useful internally.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=6080f857- 4784-4679-8e41-c6881ed933ce&#34;&gt;Friendship Circle&lt;/a&gt; may also be a good idea, though perhaps how you classify people should be private. You may mark someone as being &#34;family&#34; &#34;intimate&#34; or &#34;acquaintance&#34; or &#34;business&#34;, or whatever, however, no one else should see that; they should just see &#34;connection&#34; unless they have named you, and you in turn should not say that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Profiles&lt;/h4&gt;
Find some better way then simple lists to do profiles. Someone&#39;s profile needs to express the richness of who they are -- it also needs to change and grow and flow over time, so make it easy for people to annotate and grow over time. Consider asking for only a few things at first, not make the process of filling out the profile feel daunting, then after each login prompt them to add one small thing that is useful based on how they used the service recently. For instance &#34;You have joined the AnyoneButBush2004 group -- do you want to enter information to share with others about your political interests?&#34;.
&lt;p&gt;Right now lots of people are experimenting on their blog sidebars how best to profile themselves -- learn from them. Look at hundreds of examples, look for patterns beyond the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow people to have multiple affiliations, whether they be work or play. I&#39;m a bad edge case personally, with too many hats to name, but almost everyone I know has at least two professional hats &#34;Sysadmin by day, Writer by night&#34;, &#34;Laywer on weekdays, Carpenter on weekends&#34; , as well as several affiliation hats &#34;Bay Area Costumer Guild president, member of League of Women Voters&#34;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now LinkedIn has the best looking professional profile, but it is still hard for some people to use. I like LinkedIn&#39;s use of multiple professional affiliations, however, I wish I could mark some as major or minor; for instance, there is a big difference between being an Advisor to MG Taylor and being CEO of Consensus. It also doesn&#39;t handle professional associations and lesser affiliations, much less non-professional affiliations and interests. Also, being able to arbitrarily order them would be nice, LinkedIn does it by date which can make for some confusing emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reputation &amp; Endorsements&lt;/h4&gt;
Be very careful of the design of rating systems and reputation systems. They are extremely difficult to design well, as they too often can be gamed, or fall into reciprocity such that they are meaningless. My personal advice is just don&#39;t do it at first -- save it for a 2.0 version of the product, not 1.0 beta. If you are going to do it now, really study it -- there is a lot of good academic research on issues of reputation. It can be hard to slog through but it is worth it. Offer a grant to Danah&#39;s school for them to do research for you on the topic.
&lt;p&gt;Endorsements are a best way of doing reputation for now. They is also is imperfect and vulnerable to reciprocity games, however, as least you can see if two people are playing that game just by looking at the endorser and endorsee. If you find too much reciprocity you can basically ignore both players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow endorsements at a more granular level. For instance, if you are offering dating and professional information, segregate the endorsements. Even more ideally, do like LinkedIn and allow endorsements of relatively small things in a profile, for instance &#34;I really enjoy Chris&#39; blog&#34; against the blog profile item, and &#34;I like what Chris says about the environment&#34; against my affiliation with a group. Consider allowing endorsements of groups: &#34;Of the three groups here on Wiki, I find this one fits me the best&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can afford it, consider hiring a game designer from the online game industry who understands behavior incentives in online games. If you can&#39;t, study it. Part of the reason why EverQuest is the largest MMPORG is because it incentivizes certain kinds of social behaviors. In fact, it could be considered to be a type of social network service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Launch &amp; Support&lt;/h4&gt;
Be careful with your beta launch -- a culture for a community forms in the first few weeks, and our experience from online games is that the nature of this culture can make or break a project. Find ways to encourage the kinds of behaviors you want, and discourage those that you don&#39;t.
&lt;p&gt;Be very careful of labeling people who are gaming your product in ways you don&#39;t like. Being in Orkut&#39;s &#39;jail&#39; is almost becoming a badge of honor. There is no reason why people who invite too many friends to join, submit too many posts to forums, or sends too many messages to friends of friends, should be put under the same label as those people who put child pornography up on your system and thus you&#39;ve banned them. Instead, slow down the overly active people, just say in advance &#34;If you invite this number of people, you may not invite more people for 24 hours, do you want to continue?&#34;, or &#34;If you invite this person, you must wait an hour before inviting another.&#34;, etc. Also, if you do lock people out of a feature, don&#39;t lock them out of all features, just the one that they are over-using. If someone gets locked out of lots of features at the same time, then they should be looked at for possibly banning, but not if they are doing just one thing -- you want to encourage their enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you give feedback to anyone that tries to be helpful, for instance in reporting a bug. Ideally public reports should be encouraged public (as this encourages other people to be helpful) but even private reports should be encouraged, and as promptly as possible including &#34;Thanks for taking time to write up this, we are logged this problem and hope to get to it as soon as we can given limited resources.&#34; Find other ways to give feedback, such as a weekly report, or a group developers blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create multiple stages for your beta, for instance &#34;profile features beta&#34;, &#34;group features beta&#34;, &#34;scaling beta&#34;, &#34;load beta&#34;, etc. Tell people in your beta what you want to hear about and not hear at each stage. As each stage ends, find some way to publically thank those who made the biggest difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set up a bug tracking system like TypePad has (like Bugzilla but hugely simpler to use). From help menu at the top you can click to post a new report, see all open reports, or see all closed reports. Every help page can have at the bottom to open a report on that topic. If anything goes wrong there (404, various system error messages, etc) you should give you an opportunity to open a report. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Features&lt;/h4&gt;
Figure out how to use RSS everywhere for input and output -- if Orkut or Tribe&#39;s group features supported RSS feeds, they could be very powerful competition to the hugely funded Friendster. Figure out how to use trackbacks with your system, and make them simpler for users. Make group bookmarks and other lists available as OPML. I&#39;m not a huge fan of FOAF yet, but figure out how to use it anyhow (and maybe vCards) until something better comes along, if nothing else but allow someone to import it and export it.
&lt;p&gt;My personal take is that if you can combine a substantial number of these &lt;br /&gt;
features, you could have a great product that gives the others a run for the &lt;br /&gt;
money:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Offering intentional groups (like Tribe and Orkut) is essential. It is Friendster&#39;s and LinkedIn&#39;s weakest link.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eVite/Meetup style invitations for both private functions (come to my birthday party), friend functions (anyone near 00301 want to have lunch Thursday?) and groups (Let&#39;s all meet for dinner next week to discuss this).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to import via RSS the recent items from my blog to my profile page&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional blogging-style home pages (FunChain &amp; Live Journal) for those who don&#39;t already have blogs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended family support as an explicit type of group, grandmother, mother, child in college&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Couples can be a form of a group also&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better ways to organize groups of groups&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better support for user-optional presence &#34;There are members of this group who are reading it right now who have said that they are available online to members to this group, 3 via Skype, 12 via AIM&#34;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=94333937-ecd8-4d08-994d-7f4c96c523dd&#34;&gt;Permachat&lt;/a&gt; at a group level is an interesting idea. I hate that I can&#39;t see chat text before the point I logged in&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of group management support, for instance:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ability to have multiple admins (eGroups, Live Journal)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group moderation (Slashdot, Kuro5hin, Advogato, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional group shared links (eGroups)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional group shared calendar (eGroups)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polling inside groups (no one that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invitation or approval of entry by different methods, such as by vote, by 1 reference from existing member, etc. (none that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to merge groups (none that I know of) &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wiki-style areas available for groups (no one that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine all the above with good innovative RSS and optionally Atom (FunChain, SocialText)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports the various blog submission APIs for blogs, wiki, and groups (none that I know of)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a great job for those who don&#39;t use RSS and those APIs to use email instead, including email submission (you can mail pages to a SocialText wiki)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to be federated, i.e. I could still use my existing blog (you just mirror it), RSS aggregation, my FOAF file could be synced, you sync with my addressbook at Yahoo, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Business Models&lt;/h4&gt;
Business models for social networking services is going to be one of the biggest issues. Even those social networking sites with lots of money behind them are going to have difficulty because there are so many.
&lt;p&gt;The paid subscriber model is probably dead until some of the VC funded startups go out of business. Advertising can be a good model, but be careful not to make it obtrusive -- remember, Google has made good money with very simple ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t have VC funding, find ways to co-opt partners -- build from the beginning support for Google AdSense and Adwords, Amazon APIs, etc. If you are small, consider federating with another company. Figure out what you can do to differentiate yourself from both your competitors and partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t be evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Me&lt;/h4&gt;
I am interested in getting more professionally involved with social software. I think we are still in Apple II days of social software -- we see the promise of things to come, but we are still typing in ALL CAPS. Given the overfunding in this field, my own ability to start a company as an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alacrityventures.com&#34;&gt;angel investor&lt;/a&gt; is insufficient, so I&#39;m looking to partner with others. I&#39;ve been involved with online communities, groupware, collaboration, and security for over 20 years. If you are interested in an executive in this area, see my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;profile on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Some notes:
a) On privacy -- the list of people who tried to reach you is two-edged,
you may want to point that out, because it gathers my list of friends,
and somebody else might come and get it, but it is pretty useful.
b) All these ideas and many others are good, and I have my own lists
of useful features,  but there&#39;s some huge feature creep and it will
be tough for the people doing this software to cherry pick.
c) I have notes in the orkut forum (I presume you posted this there)
about dealing with people you don&#39;t remember.  It doesn&#39;t work to force
me to send them a note saying &#34;where do I know you from?&#34; because if
you forgot them it&#39;s still embarassing.   You need to establish a principle
in advance that people doing an invite include where they know you from.
Unless they are intimate friends.
d) On dating/non-dating, I agree that we don&#39;t want to see that our
business associate is in an open marriage.  However I am not sure the
moded UI (you are either in biz mode or dating mode) will fly.  I had
big plans for such modes, on backburner for now.
A better idea would be to only show you dating info on people who are
potential dates.   Ie. if you are an M seeking F, you only see dating
info of F seeking Ms.  People want the serendipity of knowing, &#34;Oh, that
women I met at the conference is single and looking?&#34;
Best of all it doesn&#39;t require new UI.
The other big thing with Orkut is going to be the FoF spam.  The mail
volume must be limited some way.  We&#39;ve got many thousands of FoF it
seems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ideas.4brad.com&#34;&gt;Brad Templeton&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-03T14:24:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-03T14:24:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Good advice overall.  You might want to take a fast look at how phpbb does polls (re your &#34;polling inside groups&#34; note).  It&#39;s integrated into the comment posting interface so you can very quickly turn any entry into a poll, with a few simple options.
I&#39;d also be interested in seeing your comments on pay vs. free membership options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://web.media.mit.edu/~wex/&#34;&gt;Alan Wexelblat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-04T07:40:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-04T07:40:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Fantastic post, Christopher.  I&#39;ll never again claim you only flog Orkut; you&#39;re very fair and constructive with your observations, too!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ifindkarma.typepad.com/relax/&#34;&gt;Adam Rifkin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-07T13:38:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-07T13:38:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What do you think about the political applications of friendster-like sites?  Think how it helps solve the problems associated with the ghetto email petitions of the past, and how it could create a non-intrusive, viral fundraising medium.  Do you agree with me?
Given the multiple kinds of ways that people want to use social software (e.g., business networking, dating, politics), will there be specific sites for each kind of activity or will there be some sharing model?
Anyway, we&#39;re thinking about leveraging this trend and it would be helpful to get your thoughts as we consider build vs. partnering, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.e-thePeople.org&#34;&gt;Michael Weiksner&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-09T14:54:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-09T14:54:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;FriendBlend is another new social networking site you might want to take a look at - it combines match-making with blogs, moblogs, online photo sharing and a lot of the group features such as polling and quizes that you mention. Great post!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.friendblend.com&#34;&gt;David Jenness&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-20T18:04:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-20T18:04:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;another cool site to check out is for College &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.collegester.com&#34;&gt; Social Networking&lt;/a&gt; is http://www.collegester.com . Also a hip site for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lloydbankster.com&#34;&gt;Lloyd Banks&lt;/a&gt; is worth peaking at..... I&#39;ve seen the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bestnetsoftware.com&#34;&gt;Social Networking Software&lt;/a&gt; for sell at http://www.bestnetsoftware.com for those interested in starting their own social networking site or community!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.collegester.com&#34;&gt;Social Networking&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-09T07:42:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-09T07:42:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;my friend http://www.ryanleslie.com is planning a social networking site for musicians
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.tcgss.org&#34;&gt;ricky&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-21T10:50:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-21T10:50:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
http://www.egrupos.com/
is virtually unknown in the US but becoming very popular in Spain and Latin America, and they&#39;re becoming a trend-setter, integrating email groups (a la YahooGroup but perhaps even more customizable), social networking tools and online auctions. A weird combination that however it seems to be working ok so far.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Pepe B.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-15T12:01:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-15T12:01:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is kind of a neat personals site that&#39;s looking to add in social network functionality. Email through the site if you&#39;re interested in partnerships.
http://www.itsjustcoffee.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.itsjustcoffee.com&#34;&gt;ItsJustCoffee&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-12-03T16:48:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-12-03T16:48:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi...I put up a site dedicated to the social networking niche of gated online communities at
http://www.gatedonlinecommunities.com
Any comments on the subject are appreciated!
Thanks Marc
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.gatedonlinecommunities.com&#34;&gt;Marc L GatedOnlineCommunities.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-10-24T14:24:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-10-24T14:24:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Eerst Europa Doelstellingen: De Ci2i Verzekering (Ci2i) zal het nummer een gebrandmerkte pan Europese commoditized online verzekeringsmakelaar door 2010 zijn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.firsteuropa.nl&#34;&gt;Alice Mike&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-12-03T22:37:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-12-03T22:37:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for posting this your section about privacy is very useful. There are some issues regarding privacy and social networking sites that have not been addressed properly and may cause the downfall of social networking sites such as stalkers and identity fraudsters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://scribblesheet.co.uk/article/can_i_have_my_life_back_please&#34;&gt;Vince&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-27T14:15:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-27T14:15:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>