<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conversation on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/conversation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conversation on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2009 16:19:40 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/conversation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Facilitating Small Gatherings Using “The Braid”</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/facilitating-small-gatherings-using-the-braid.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2009 16:19:40 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/facilitating-small-gatherings-using-the-braid.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theworldcafe.com/bank_book.htm&#34; style=&#34;float: right; margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Power of Conversation&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5f61c98970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5f61c98970c-320wi&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I was musing as I was preparing for next week&amp;#39;s Intensive at &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/teaching-using-the-social-web-for-social-change-at-bgiedu.html&#34;&gt;BGI&lt;/a&gt; that I have 21 students in my class, an uncomfortable size. That&amp;#39;s because it lies between a smaller size where good conversations naturally occur, and a larger size where you can take full advantage of different activities that work well for larger groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talk about this a bit in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;Group Threshold&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; posts, where I call the group threshold size of between 10 and 24 people the&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2008/09/group-threshold.html#Judas_Number&#34;&gt;“Judas Number”&lt;/a&gt; nadir, or low point. These group threshold nadirs exist when groups are too large for some processes to function effectively, but too small for others to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am particularly aware of this threshold when I host small parties at my home. At 7 or so people everything just seems to work — conversations flow, everybody gets to participate, and everyone has fun. A the numbers climb past 10 I find that I as the host have to work harder, to be more aware of making sure that everyone is having a good time and that no one is left out. At some point as a party gets larger things just begin to flow again, as there are enough people that small groups can form and conversation flows well once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve also seen this at business meetings. When my entrepreneurial companies were small an “all hands” meeting could be incredibly effective. All the issues and ideas got brought up, and everyone felt committed to our decisions. However, as these meeting grew, at some point the “all hands” meeting took too long and started requiring process and rules to be effective. The energy this consumed also diminished much of the efficacy of the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/files/Four%20Table%20Braid.pdf&#34; style=&#34;float: left; margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; border=1&#34; title=&#34;Four Table Braid&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Four Table Braid&#34; height=&#34;137&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2434/3959741597_77ffe2ca15_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;border-top-width: 1px; border-right-width: 1px; border-bottom-width: 1px; border-left-width: 1px; border-top-style: solid; border-right-style: solid; border-bottom-style: solid; border-left-style: solid; border-top-color: black; border-right-color: black; border-bottom-color: black; border-left-color: black; &#34; title=&#34;Card from Four Table Braid&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;One tool that I&amp;#39;ve used to manage these odd-sized groups in the past is what I call “The Braid”. It is derived from a group process called the Café Method, of which &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theworldcafe.com/&#34;&gt;The World Café&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conversationcafe.org/&#34;&gt;Conversation Café&lt;/a&gt; are excellent examples. In The Café Method, people meet in smaller groups around tables, and then flow from table to table sharing ideas, but ideally keeping each table at 4-7 people. There is an excellent free PDF guide to the Café Method offered by The World Café called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theworldcafe.com/articles/cafetogo.pdf&#34;&gt;Cafe To Go&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Braid is a little more organized then the more ad-hoc Café Method. When you start a meeting you are given a small card that tells you which table to sit at for each round. Each table is assigned a scribe for each round to take notes at the table, and to report out the notes to everyone who arrives for the next round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One nice thing about the organization of The Braid is that over the course of a number of rounds you&amp;#39;ll have a brand new group of people to talk to during each round. Thus over the course of an hour or so you&amp;#39;ll actually get to have a relatively short yet rich conversation with almost everyone in the room, rather than with just a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?key=tSZvgWmkax0xsBfKY3Lj69Q&amp;amp;gid=0&#34; style=&#34;float: right; margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Four Table Braid&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Four Table Braid&#34; height=&#34;453&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2622/3960601974_652a29b96f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;433&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are different forms of The Braid for different numbers of tables and sizes of groups, but my favorite is the Four Table Braid for groups of a minimum of 16 to a maximum of 28 people. One of the peculiar things about this Braid is that it seems to function well if people arrive at different times. The Braid fills first table A with 4 people so that they can begin talking, then fills table B, C, and D the same way. Once those tables are full, new arrivals are woven into The Braid one at a time until all tables have 5 people, then 6, then the max of 7 for a total of 28 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another nice thing about the Four Table Braid is that no one needs to be the scribe more then once; the task is equally shared among all but the last 8 to arrive in a group of 28. Also, in just 4 rounds with 16 people, 90%+ of the participants have met. With 28 people, you simply only need 5 rounds to match the same 90%+ meeting percentage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find The Braid useful for a variety of different situations. The simplest usage is as a group warming and introduction exercise. You need not do more then two or three rounds in order for more than half of the people to have met each other. The Braid is also useful with a focused objective. For instance, I once used it after a game designers&amp;#39; conference, with each table having a list of &amp;quot;game design laws&amp;quot; where the participants were asked to either give an example that was in favor of the law or contradicted the law. It also can be useful in combination with a variety of other group process techniques, for instance after an MG Taylor Take-A-Panel, where each participant first creates a page telling a story about themselves 15 years in the future and then the group uses The Braid to discover common insights. The Braid can also be good before an Open Space or other unconference event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am including here my templates for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/files/Four%20Table%20Braid.pdf&#34;&gt;Four Table Braid&lt;/a&gt;. It includes 28 cards for printing on Avery business card paper, 4 table pages with instructions for participants, and 1 page with instructions for the host. I make these available as &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/&#34; rel=&#34;license&#34;&gt;CC-BY-NC-SA&lt;/a&gt; license. I welcome any DTP folks out there who would like to make these documents more functional or more attractive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Three Table Braid is easy to figure out by hand, but larger Braids are more difficult. I&amp;#39;ve never figured out an algorithm for designing these quickly (any math wizzes out there?) so I&amp;#39;ve posted my &lt;a href=&#34;http://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?key=tSZvgWmkax0xsBfKY3Lj69Q&amp;amp;gid=0&#34;&gt;spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; for the Four Table Braid for those of you who might wish to figure out how to implement larger numbers of tables. I would love to have a Ten Table Braid as a warm up exercise for a small unconference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/&#34; rel=&#34;license&#34; style=&#34; float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Creative Commons License&#34; src=&#34;http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/88x31.png&#34; style=&#34;border-width:0&#34; title=&#34;Creative Commons License&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span property=&#34;dc:title&#34; xmlns:dc=&#34;http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/&#34;&gt;Four Table Braid&lt;/span&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34; property=&#34;cc:attributionName&#34; rel=&#34;cc:attributionURL&#34; xmlns:cc=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/ns#&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt; is licensed under a &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/&#34; rel=&#34;license&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States License&lt;/a&gt;. Based on a work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com/2009/09/facilitating-small-gatherings-using-the-braid.html &#34; rel=&#34;dc:source&#34; xmlns:dc=&#34;http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/&#34;&gt;www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#0160;Permissions beyond the scope of this license may be available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://ChristopherA.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34; rel=&#34;cc:morePermissions&#34; xmlns:cc=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/ns#&#34;&gt;ChristopherA.LifeWithAlacrity.com&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#0160;The Power of Conversation graphic is used with permission from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theworldcafe.com/bank_book.htm&#34;&gt;The World Cafe Image Bank&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2009/09/facilitating-small-gatherings-using-the-braid.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Shared Language and Shared Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 01:13:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://worldatuningfork.com/John/medusaosxPDF.pdf#page=203&#34; style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Poem: Language&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577a68d970b &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577a68d970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px;&#34; title=&#34;Poem: Language&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We live in a world of conversation, of language; all full of words. Mastery of language requires learning the meanings of thousands of words. The average native English language speaker uses in the realm of 12,000 to 20,000 words, whereas a college graduate would use 20-25,000 words. Shakespeare actively used more then 30,000 words, and his vocabulary was estimated to be over 66,000 words. Yet there are, at the very least, a quarter of a million distinct English words, excluding inflections, and words from technical and regional vocabularies. The Oxford English dictionary defines more then 600,000 words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But mastery of words is not enough to allow effective conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is because words themselves don&amp;#39;t have meaning; the meaning is provided by the people who use them. Meaning is in the mind, not in the words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words also require context, outside of which they may have different meanings. For instance, consider the word &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot;. To a banker or CPA &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot; is a property held by someone to manage for someone else&amp;#39;s benefit. To a cryptographer it is the confidence in a future outcome based on probabilistic mathematics and past experience. Finally, to the lay person &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot; is about honesty. &amp;quot;Spin&amp;quot; is another example of a word that changes with context; to a weaver it is the production of thread, to a physicist it is a property of elemental particles, to an athlete it is a type of exercise class, and to a politician or public relations professional it is a way to tell a story to sway pubic opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Creating a Shared Language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Life With Alacrity Wordle&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b-320pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Life With Alacrity Wordle&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Every time a new group of people meet together — whether in a team, in a marketplace, or in a community — one of the first activities they must do together is create a shared language. They do this in order to communicate more effectively together, to put a context on the words that they have in common, to construct a shared understanding in their minds based both on available information and their individual diversity of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t forget that the linguistic root of communication is the Latin verb&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.18:3557.lewshort&#34; title=&#34;Latin definition of commūnĭco&#34;&gt;commūnĭco&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;&amp;#0160;— which doesn&amp;#39;t mean &amp;quot;to communicate&amp;quot; but instead means &amp;quot;to share something with someone, to take or receive a part of, to partake, to participate in&amp;quot;. Thus the creation of a shared language takes us to the roots of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without taking the time time to create shared language, groups have a difficult time forging mutual trust. Without a shared language there will be no clarity on mutual goals — whether it involves working together, transacting a trade, or creating something. Without a shared language commitments can be hard to make, and if misunderstood can lead to disagreements. These group formation phases — trust building, goal clarification, and commitment — are essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the art of creating a shared language together is not taught. Some individuals and groups do it intuitively while others will just let it evolve naturally over time. However, some facilitators have learned that one of the best ways to help a group form a shared language is by having the group create together a shared artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Using Shared Artifacts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shared artifact is the creation of an object or shared space that is created collaboratively. It allows the individuals participating to ask the questions: &amp;quot;Is this what you mean when you are talking about this? I use these words, so suppose we change it to this? Is that what you mean? Does this reflect our new shared understanding?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;WatsonCrick&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c-120pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px;&#34; title=&#34;WatsonCrick&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Napkin-idea-original-concept-300x293&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c-120wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Examples of shared artifacts include Watson &amp;amp; Crick&amp;#39;s Tinker-Toy DNA model. Each scientist would work on the model separately, then use grad students to carry the model around to his partner to express certain ideas. Both Compaq Computer and Southwest Airlines were reportedly established after their founders wrote their ideas down together on a table napkin, another shared artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these examples show an important factor in shared artifacts — if the shared artifact is not constrained then it will be too large or complex for the group to reach some measure of completion. Finishing the shared artifact really helps establish trust and the connections between the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shared artifact is also useful because flooding someone with information and terms gives no assurance that the recipient has gained knowledge of the subject. Instead, the act of creation confirms to both parties that the knowledge was successfully assimilated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage to creating a shared artifact is that it isolates any problems to the task at hand. Often there are differences in status, purpose, or perspective that can get in the way of group formation, but a focus on a common task of the creation of a neutral shared artifact allows those issues to come later as the participants develop the trust and shared language required to talk about those tough issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best facilitators know what kinds of shared artifacts work best for different groups under different circumstances. Sometimes a shared artifact is just a model of a process drawn on a white wall. Often it is a creation of a mission statement or joint objectives. I personally like taking old mind maps and trying to recreate them anew with more recent knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Future of Shared Language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of shared language is changing in the 21st century. The conjoined social networks in the blogosphere — via Facebook, Twitter, or the attendee-focused Unconference — cause new terminology and new language to form ever faster. I&amp;#39;ve personally seen words like &amp;quot;retweet&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;attribution&amp;quot; gain important contextual meaning within my social networks. As with any shared language, newcomers have difficulty discovering their meanings only by osmosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tagging is another means by which shared language is rapidly expanding. Certain words are gaining context through common use at Delicious.com, Technorati, Flickr, and other tag-enabled web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a certain extent, all of these new shared languages are built upon shared artifacts. Twitter, Facebook, Delicious.com and others sites each create constraints on how language is shared and with whom. However, there is little purposeful social design being applied to these new shared languages. Though there may be shared artifacts, they are not purposefully facilitated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will these increasingly organic shared languages prove better than more purposefully created ones or worse? Is social language facilitation the next big thing in social network? Or is there just not enough space for it within the tightly constrained social artifacts of the internet? These are questions that we as social software technologists need to address as the future of the internet increasingly becomes the present of our social groupings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I learned the concept of Shared Language in 1990 from Michael Schrage&amp;#39;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Shared-Minds-New-Technologies-Collaboration/dp/0394565878&#34;&gt;Shared Minds: The New Technologies of Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. It is out of print, but there is a new edition retitled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/No-More-Teams-Mastering-Collaboration/dp/0385476035/&#34;&gt;No More Teams!: Mastering the Dynamics of Creative Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. The use of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com/mgtaylor/glasbead/modexpl.htm&#34;&gt;modeling language&lt;/a&gt; to facilitate group formation I learned from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.matttaylor.com&#34;&gt;Matt Taylor&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/worthyprojects&#34;&gt;@worthyprojects&lt;/a&gt;) of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com/&#34;&gt;MG Taylor Corporation&lt;/a&gt;, though the use of the term shared artifacts and approach is my own. I make passing reference to the early stages of team formation (&amp;quot;trust building&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;goal clarification&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;commitment&amp;quot;) which come from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grove.com/site/ourwk_gm_tp.html&#34;&gt;Drexler/Sibbet Team Peformance Model&lt;/a&gt;. The poem is by excerpt of a larger work by &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldatuningfork.com/John/&#34;&gt;John Campion&lt;/a&gt; and is reprinted with permission — the work reflects the poet&amp;#39;s Ecotropic concerns and are part of his third
book-length poem Medusa. Look at the work under the Medusa Project link. The table napkin photo is from an excellent post on &lt;a href=&#34;http://createtheconditions.com/?p=304&#34;&gt;The Idea Napkin&lt;/a&gt; by Morry Potoka and is also reprinted with permission. The Watson-Crick photo is public domain, and the Life With Alacrity graphic was produced using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordle.net/&#34;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;m wondering whether the creation of such language is adding to an intellectual, generational and cultural divisiveness that is already prevalent in our society. Can we design tools that serve as bridges? Using the web for social change is a powerful concept, particularly if we can broaden the audience. This is a fascinating topic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Julie  Mihalisin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-09-21T10:45:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-09-21T10:45:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve not really thought of Shared Language in the context of divisiveness — Shared Language tends to be a function of small groups. Thus I more think of the divisiveness is coming from the fact that Shared Language typically evolves naturally in a small group, but fails to evolve naturally in larger groups. Possibly a better understanding of how Shared Language and tools to facilitate it like Shared Artifacts function will make it easier for larger groups to grow a Shared Language together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-09-21T14:06:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-09-21T14:06:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Shared artifacts are also known as models; the best form of understanding of business that I have found yet is when you develop simulators with practitioners. The quality of the the output is only surpassed by the shared understanding created through healthy challenge to the way things actually work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Dave Carter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-05-05T04:15:41-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-05-05T04:15:41-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future Topics</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/04/future_topics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2005 01:08:16 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/04/future_topics.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working on an ambitious list of topics that I&#39;d like to cover over the next year. I offer them to you here so you can have some idea the areas that I am thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Office Architecture for Innovation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Over the years I&#39;ve built or converted three offices to my specifications. From this I have learned a number of things about about how to create a productive environment innovation-oriented businesses. These include some of the obvious suggestions such as fresh air and natural light, but also include not so obvious ideas such as using magnetic paint and providing a small washer-dryer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Requisite Variety&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- This concept from cybernetics applies to social systems as well. &amp;quot;The larger the variety of actions available to a control system, the larger the variety of perturbations it is able to compensate.&amp;quot; More people, as well as a diversity of thinking styles and experience, give social software more &amp;quot;variety of actions&amp;quot;, thus this is part of the reason why social software can be so effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Art and Craft of Meme Design&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We are learning more about how to create an effective meme. Creating memes has always been an art performed by publicists, marketers, politicians, the press, and to a lesser extent by scientists and other academics. Have we learned enough to turn this art into an explicit craft?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wiki Editing Dichotomy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- One interesting possible barrier of entry to active participation in a wiki is what I call the &amp;quot;wiki editing dichotomy&amp;quot;. You have to be proud enough to believe what you are contributing is generally worthwhile to others (or at least worth your effort), but you also have to be humble enough to understand that others can improve it. I don&#39;t know of many other collaborative media that requires both pride and humility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Choice &amp;amp; Neuroeconomics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are some that say at the root of every decision is emotion. Even a &#39;rational&#39; decision appeals to a sense of balance or beauty. Recent studies using PET are establishing a neurological basis for emotions, and some reveal interesting facts about how we make choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assessing Risk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are a variety of areas where we as humans have a difficult time being completely rational. One of these is risk assessment. It turns out we may be hard-wired to not be able toeasily understand risk that is greater then one in a hundred or so. Thus a very rare risk, say one in a thousand, will often be emotionally interpreted as having a much higher risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Persuasive Computing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- BJ Fogg&#39;s group at Stanford has done some interesting research on how computers can persuade you to do something. There are a number of useful ideas that come from this research. There are also some ethical considerations that should be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cognitive Dissonance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- This technique is central to many forms of persuasion intended to change beliefs, values, attitudes and behaviors. It is used by facilitators, businesses, military organizations, and even cults. It can be used positively or negatively. How might it be used in social software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dark Side of the Force&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- The same social tools that we use for good, can also be used for harm. How do we ethically use what we are learning about social software? Some say that almost by definition social software attracts spammers, trolls, and innappropriate sexuality. What can we do to prevent these misuses of social software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conversation vs Communication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Update and rewrite of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alacritymanagement.com/GCnC.html&#34;&gt;1990 essay&lt;/a&gt; on how social software design needs to balance conversation vs communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Emotions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We appear to have evolved a number of emotions that appear primarily to exist to support a common good, rather then to ensure our individual success. These include schadenfreude, mirth, naches, revenge, shame, pride, outrage, approbation, admiration, elevation, etc. Studies by Eckman on unconscious facial gestures, studies on the neurological basis for emotions, and studies on emotions in games, are proving that these social emotions exist. A number of them have interesting implications on social software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glances &amp;amp; Strokes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There is some old work on the amount of eye contact we make with others in small groups, as well as some research from transactional analysis on strokes, which are the amount of recognition given to others through words and deeds. Is there a neurological basis for needing a certain number of glances and strokes each day? How does this concept apply to social software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weak Links&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are some interesting social implications behind what we&#39;ve learned about weak links in social networks. How do we identify and encourage weak links in our social software systems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Negativity vs Positivity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- It is far easier for someone to respond negativel than positively. In political systems it is far easier to say no rather then yes. What social software encourages positivity, and is it possible to design social software to do so?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time Economy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Our ultimate most unrenewable resource is time. How time and attention are a basic economic unit that should be considered when looking at social software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group Life Cycle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We often focus on how groups form, emerge, and grow. Yet there are many lessons to be learned from how groups die, including that it isn&#39;t necessarily a bad thing and that keeping a group from death can be dysfunctional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groupthink&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- What causes groupthink? When is it good and when is it bad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two Thresholds in the Value of Knowledge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- In order for knowledge to be valuable, it must at minimum be more valuable then the costs to find and absorb it (costs which include bandwidth and attention). Tools like Google have tremendously increased the amount of knowledge that is worth the time and attention to find it. What types of knowledge fall below this threshold of value? Is there a limit to how much we can lower this line? Furthermore, there is another threshold where the knowledge is significantly more valuable than only bandwidth and attention. How much have internet tools impacted this second threshold? Many internet business models, in particular content models, require some ability to offer value in this upper threshold -- can they survive as this upper threshold changes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intimacy and Social Networks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Social Networks Analysis tends to focus on the connections between people, either explicitly through acknowledgement of connections (LinkedIn, Friendster) or implicitly through analysis of your communication (Spoke). None are able to measure intimacy. Yet our intimate social networks are an important component of our overall happiness and contentment within both our professional and personal lives. How does intimacy work in social networks? Also there are some concepts in psychology known as communal vs exchange relationships by Clark &amp;amp; Mills from late 70&#39;s that may apply here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- A recap of Shannon Appelcline&#39;s and my analysis of the basic forms of social games types. These include relatively well understood ones like majority control, voting, meta-voting (Nomic), auctioning, etc., but also include less well understood games like playing of roles, dominance and submission, etc. There are also links to social emotions, such as mirth and schadenfraude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lessons from Castle Marrach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- We released the Castle Marrach online game in September of 2000, and it was designed from the beginning to be a game for the Bartle-type known as &amp;quot;the socializer&amp;quot;. What lessons did we learn in the five years since the release of the game? What tools are in my social software toolbox today that might have helped with the design?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lessons from F2F Facilitation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- There are many skilled practitioners of face-to-face facilitation, some of which are paid very high fees for their skills. What lessons can we learn from their experience that we can apply to social software? Why have so many of these facilitators failed to have success online?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More Human vs More Than Human&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Many futurists seek to offer us augmentation of our minds and bodies through technology. Many of these ideas may fundamentally change what it is to be human, and may even have unforeseen complications unanticipated by their creators. One interesting approach to looking at these technologies is to examine which make us &amp;quot;more human&amp;quot;, rather then &amp;quot;more than human&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lessons from Mental Disorders&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Most, if not all, mental disorders have their roots in survival strategies; however, they are over-expressed because of genetic or other causes. Examining the healthy behaviors hiding behind depression, autism, mania, schizophrenia, paranoia, etc. offer a number of insights on how we think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joy of being a Primate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- If you scan the surface of my writing, you may observe that I have a strong belief that our animal nature and genetics form an essential and often unconscious part of what it is to be human. You could interpret these &amp;quot;nature&amp;quot; over &amp;quot;nurture&amp;quot; ideas as limiting us to being just animals. Instead, I believe that by becoming aware of our primate nature, and choosing to leverage it or suppress it by conscious choice rather then letting it drive us unaware, is what makes us more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smart Contracts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- Nick Szabo popularized the idea of using some of the primitives of cryptography in unique ways to create what he calls &amp;quot;smart contracts&amp;quot;. He hypothesized approaches to cryptographic handling of collateral, bonding, delineation of property, bearer certificates, and much more. Others have proposed various auction protocols using these concepts. One of the fundamental atomic elements of many of these smart contracts is something called a &amp;quot;reusable proof of work&amp;quot;, which Hal Finney recently demoed a version of at CodeCon 2005. What are the possibilities offered by smart contracts? What are the barriers to implementation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Club System&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- In the 80&#39;s, development of Ted Nelson&#39;s Xanadu vision was being financed by Autodesk. Unfortunately, for a variety of reasons Xanadu failed to deliver any technology. However, a couple of their ideas could be valuable today, one of which is the concept of an alternative to the &amp;quot;user and groups&amp;quot; metaphor for computer security. Xanadu turned that idea upside down and called the result the &amp;quot;club system&amp;quot;. The club system approach is particularly suited to the internet based collaboration tools, in particular wikis. I also have some insights to offer a cryptographic approach to the club system, which might allow P2P distribution of collaborative documents, while preserving group privileges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edges of Cryptographic Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- The SSL cryptographic protocol offers a choice of a number of security properties: integrity, confidentiality, encryption, one-party authentication, and two-party authentication. But there are a number of security properties that very few deployed cryptographic protocols offer. These include perfect forward secrecy, undeniability, deniability, authorization, delegation, multi-party authentication, shared secrets, etc. What are these security properties and how are they useful? Why have they not been successfully broadly deployed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SSL Story&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- When SSL was first proposed it was broken within an hour. Even when Netscape fixed those problems, it wasn&#39;t clear that SSL was going to win the battle of security protocols. SSL was competing against SHTTP which had backing of RSA and an industry consortium. The credit card companies merged their standards and were backing SET. The internet community was moving toward SSH. Microsoft was doing its own embrace and extend protocol PCT. So how did SSL win to become the broadest deployed cryptographic security protocol? The answers may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I welcome any comments or suggestions for links on these topics, or any new topics that you feel are closely related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Get to work! Soon!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Phil Mitchell&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-05T12:22:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-05T12:22:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
The SSL story would be interesting..
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;cyberhill&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-13T08:10:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-13T08:10:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/04/future_topics.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>