<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>social networking on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/social-networking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in social networking on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2004 16:25:05 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/social-networking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hand-Crafting My FOAF</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2004 16:25:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/handcrafting_my.html</guid>
      <description>While at eTech, I attended a number of &#34;social software&#34; sessions. One thing I heard was a persistent call from folk like Marc Canter for all the vendors to support something called FOAF. FOAF is a standard for &#34;Friend of a Friend&#34; files, and is an attempt to make machine readable information about people, groups, companies, and other online resources. In particular, it is focused on representing the information that you might typically put on your personal home page in a form such that meta-data tools can interpret it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 17:12:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</guid>
      <description>Another Orkut user and I have confirmed a privacy hole in Orkut whenever you send a message to someone via Orkut.
For instance, whenever I send a message to anyone in the system that is forwarded by email, in the message headers it will read:
 From: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;member@orkut.com&amp;gt; Reply-To: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;christophera@alacritymanagement.com; When someone reads the message in their email software, the &#34;From:&#34; line will be my name but the fake email of &amp;lt;member@orkut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Followup on Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 13:21:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve read of emails, Orkut messages, and blog postings since my post yesterday, so I thought I would share some with you.
There have been a number of good posts, as well as user comments at Danah Boyd&#39;s blog Apophenia.
Danah Boyd writes Correcting Marc Canter&#39;s Perception of My Views
Marc - i don&#39;t believe that users should take these relationships more seriously; i believe that YOU should. Users will do whatever they damn well please, and i think that we should learn from them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insecurity at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2004 13:58:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</guid>
      <description>Like many others, I&#39;ve been paying attention to Orkut in the last couple of weeks. I&#39;ve answered more requests to be &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut then I have of any of the other half-dozen Social Networking Services I&#39;ve tried, and I&#39;ve looking at other people&#39;s friends to see if I know anyone. I&#39;ve yet to ask someone to join Orkut that wasn&#39;t already a member, and I&#39;ve been careful to not have anyone as a &amp;quot;friend&amp;quot; that I didn&#39;t know reasonably well and I thought knew me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
