<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Slashdot on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/slashdot/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Slashdot on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 May 2005 12:25:27 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/slashdot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple, AirVideo, and Immersive vs Ambient Media</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/05/airvideo_and_im.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2005 12:25:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/05/airvideo_and_im.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reading on &lt;a href=&#34;http://slashdot.org/&#34;&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt; a discussion about &lt;a href=&#34;http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/05/10/0235212&#34;&gt;iTune 4.8&lt;/a&gt; and its new capability to purchase videos from the iTunes Music Store, when I read two things that just made me say &amp;quot;duh&amp;quot; with their obviousness, yet I&#39;d never thought of them before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these &amp;quot;duh&amp;quot; moments were inspired by the comments by an anonymous Apple engineer with the handle &lt;a href=&#34;http://slashdot.org/~As%20Seen%20On%20TV&#34;&gt;As Seen on TV&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everybody&#39;s wrong about the video iPod thing. A video iPod would be a dumb idea for lots of reasons, some technical, some psychological. If you want to know where we&#39;re going with video playback, look not to the iPod but to its considerably less famous little brother, AirPort Express.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;He didn&#39;t explain himself further, but I grokked it immediately. The current &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/airportexpress/&#34;&gt;Airport Express&lt;/a&gt; already offers digital output of audio in a feature called &amp;quot;AirTunes&amp;quot;. It isn&#39;t much of a stretch to believe that they could add the capability to offer video. If they added a dedicated H.264/MPEG4 decoder chip to the Airport Express, you could just plug in an HD-capable monitor and offer internet delivery of video and movies. The bandwidth wouldn&#39;t be an issue, as you are talking only 2 Mbps for the most popular HD compressed format, and even the full resolution 1080i compressed only requires 8-9 Mbps -- all of which will fit amply the bandwidth available to 802.11g. Thus &amp;quot;AirVideo&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;As Seen on TV&amp;quot; continues with more insights on Apple&#39;s strategy:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And the iPod is not repeat not gonna say it one more time not meant to be a video-playback device. It’s not even remotely designed for it. The iPod has a tiny hard drive that’s designed for embedded applications, and a 32 MB (I think it is) RAM buffer cache that’s optimized for dealing with song-sized chunks of data. That’s about 4 MB. Even a half hour of HD content is gonna be half a gigabyte. There’s basically no way for the iPod to play that without constantly keeping the hard drive running, and that will burn out the drive very quickly. Seriously, under constant use, the iPod hard drives’ life spans are measured in tens of hours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(How can we do photos, then? Easy. Photos are even smaller than songs. And unlike video, people often do want to carry photos around with them. Keep reading.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember when I said the problem was part technology and part psychology? People like to listen to music while they do other things: Ride on the train, exercise, shop. People like to multi-task with their music.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video, whether short-form like TV or long-form like movies, isn’t like that. Video is an immersive experience. You sit down and you watch it, and you don’t do anything else until it’s over. That’s a totally different interaction model than music.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So there’s basically zero reason for video to be portable. You’re not going to carry it around with you. You’re going to watch it at home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exceptions? Sure. But Apple isn’t a company that makes a habit of marketing to the exceptions. We shoot for a pretty clearly defined target market and let the exceptions buy their gadgets somewhere else. Chiefly because there aren’t nearly enough exceptions out there to make it worth going after, financially speaking. We’d never be able to recover what we invest in R&amp;amp;D and design by selling a few hundred thousand units. We have to sell millions of units per quarter, otherwise the business plan just doesn’t work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This all made sense, but it this comment that brought it home: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All you have to do is pay attention to the way people interact with their media. The difference between immersive media and ambient media jump out at you immediately.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d guess never really understood intuitively the concept that there are really two major media types: ambient and immersive. Now that I understand it, it seems obvious. I just never internalized the difference. Yes, sometimes TV is an ambient media, sometimes music is immersive, but only rarely. As I think about it more it makes me wonder about other types of ambient vs immersive media, such as games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll close with more last quote from &amp;quot;As Seen on TV&amp;quot;: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I know you’re going to say I’m being a dick here, but I’m going to give you the pure, unvarnished truth: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neither Apple’s management nor Apple’s shareholders give a shit about what the “alpha geeks” think. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I know, I know. It’s harsh. But it’s absolutely true. See, the “alpha geeks” are not our market. We don’t sell to them. The “alpha geeks” are defined by one key characteristic: they’re irrational. Now, I’m not trying to insult you. I mean it literally. Geeks are not rational. They base their purchasing decisions on things that, from a rational point of view, just don’t make any sense. Things like politics, lack “openness,” like “customizability.” Things that just don’t add up in the cost-benefit analysis. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That’s fine. That’s totally legitimate. But it’s not our business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We sell products to people who want them to work. We don’t sell products to people who want to take them apart. There are other companies that do that. We don’t seek to dominate them or to put them out of business. We don’t see them as competition at all, because the kinds of people who buy our products would never buy a motherboard. They’d never buy Linux. Never in a million years. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there some overlap? Sure. We love the fact that some prominent hard-core geeks use Macs. But we’re not going to abandon our business plan to woo them. We’re not going to turn our backs on the vast and untapped market for next-generation content delivery services, a market which we basically created, in order to please some Internet message board guys. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Again, I’m sorry for sounding so harsh here. I don’t mean to be rude. I’m just not going to sugar-coat it for you. You do your thing, whatever makes you happy. We’ll do ours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Very well put. I&#39;d never thought about it that way before - but it makes a lot of sense. Wireless video.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.newathens.org&#34;&gt;Trevor&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T20:20:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T20:20:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
the ambient and immersive stuff is very similar, if not the same as, some of mcluhan&#39;s theories on media
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T20:33:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T20:33:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Simpsons Did It!
...errr... I mean... Sony. x2 read...
exhibit A) The Location Free Television - http://www.sonystyle.com/is-bin/INTERSHOP.enfinity/eCS/Store/en/-/USD/SY_DisplayProductInformation-Start?ProductSKU=LFX5&amp;Dept=tvvideo&amp;CategoryName=tv_LocationFreeTVs
exhibit B) Media Roomlink - Which was an older product as well.. http://www.sonystyle.com/is-bin/INTERSHOP.enfinity/eCS/Store/en/-/USD/SY_DisplayProductInformation-Start?CategoryName=acc_PCAccessories_roomlink&amp;ProductSKU=VGPMR100U&amp;INT=sstyle-cpu_accessories-catpfeature-VGPMR100U
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.existence2.com/&#34;&gt;Dranore&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T20:47:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T20:47:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The &#34;ambient vs immersive&#34; stuff is not new - it was what Steve Jobs called &#34;background vs foreground activity&#34;, a point he made when called to comment on the possibility of video iPods, about a year ago or so.
(That said, this is an important and useful rule.)
As for this paragraph:
&#34;And the iPod is not repeat not gonna say it one more time not meant to be a video-playback device. It’s not even remotely designed for it. The iPod has a tiny hard drive that’s designed for embedded applications, and a 32 MB (I think it is) RAM buffer cache that’s optimized for dealing with song-sized chunks of data. That’s about 4 MB. Even a half hour of HD content is gonna be half a gigabyte. There’s basically no way for the iPod to play that without constantly keeping the hard drive running, and that will burn out the drive very quickly. Seriously, under constant use, the iPod hard drives’ life spans are measured in tens of hours.&#34;
Disclosures:
1. I couldn&#39;t care less about a video iPod at the moment
2. I don&#39;t think these have a chance of success as it is
But, that said, why&#39;s he mentioning HD along with the iPod? Do I *have* to view the videos on my iPod in my HD format? What&#39;s wrong with compressed/lossy formats?
Do you *have* to listen to your tunes in uncompressed (WAV/AIFF) format when using your iPod?
Sure, we won&#39;t achieve tiny filesizes when compressing video, but we won&#39;t be near HD-territory either.
If you take this under consideration, this argument of his carries much less weight.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://kostas.yoink.com/&#34;&gt;Konstantinos&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T21:18:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T21:18:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve not purchased one, but now I&#39;m quite curious about the level of movie immersiveness when using the Sony PSP http://www.us.playstation.com/psp.aspx -- Sony is reportedly going to be offering 70+ movies for the PSP. If the experience is sufficiently immersive, then maybe that is the form factor for a &#34;video iPod&#34;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T23:00:16-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T23:00:16-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
ok, let´s put two and two together then. see here:
http://www.macobserver.com/article/2005/05/10.18.shtml
and then you know: instead of vidpod, think vidpad. this also explains why the first h.264 videos (consider them test videos) are being run through itunes (not iphoto) - it&#39;s well integrated with airport...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Philip R&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T00:01:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T00:01:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You don&#39;t have to watch videos on your videom iPod in HD, but files compressed down to iPod file size (&lt; 10Mb) are going to be really, really crappy for any non-trivial piece.
I watched an iTMS video in small size and frankly, it was a chore.
One thing interested me:
&#34;We sell products to people who want them to work.&#34;
Hm. Apple certainly sells iPods to people who want them to work. I reckon there&#39;s a large percentage of Mac owners who are power users, as compared to Wintel PCs and iPods (even ignoring the business space - we&#39;re just talking consumers here).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://pauldwaite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Small Paul&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T02:29:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T02:29:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Apple also tends to put images of products its pushing in the itunes installer, and this revision happened to feature airport express, at least for me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Gnubardt&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T12:59:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T12:59:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It&#39;s pretty obvious that regardless of what they call it Apple will offer a portable video player at SOME point in the future.
Do people want to watch video content on the go?  Other technology companies sure think so.  Even cell phones are starting to be able to display low-res video.  Sprint just launched a new campaign for NBC to go, etc.
And now the PSP brings high-quality video on the go in a small package.
I watch videos on my Palm Tungsten more than I do on my laptop due to its portability.  I can compress PVRed video from the night before while I&#39;m in the shower and watch the shows on my Palm while I&#39;m on the train.  I&#39;d love to have something that was a little more robust in terms of video decompression (i.e. with a dedicated hardware GPU that could decompress Divx on the fly) and Palm&#39;s new &#34;Lifedrive&#34; 4Gb model will work pretty well for my needs, I think, but a 100Gb video iPod would be even better if they could dedicate hardware to video encoding/decoding.
HD is still years away from a portable because the small screen resolutions are still pretty low.  The PSP seems about the best portable video has to offer at this time, but there are other portable media center devices that also work well.
And the sales of those little portable DVD players with screens are through the roof.
So Apple can&#39;t be blind to the fact that people do want video on the go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://jough.com&#34;&gt;Jough Dempsey&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T13:10:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T13:10:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Portable video has a mass appeal and not just to alpha geeks, but the ambient/immersive distinction does make sense.
Would also be nice if it had better games them pong!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://timewarp-tshirts.com&#34;&gt;Timewarp&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T23:18:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T23:18:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Whether Apple will choose to go there in the near future, I don&#39;t know, but as for this statement:
&#34;You sit down and you watch it, and you don’t do anything else until it’s over. That’s a totally different interaction model than music.&#34;
I think this is a little short sited, all told.
The reason we have that model is that we&#39;ve never had portable video devices. There are already ways to extract information from our environments with digital cameras [1], why should we assume there will be no new applications of portable video?
[1] http://www.hpl.hp.com/news/2004/apr-jun/beyond_film.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ruphus.com/blog&#34;&gt;Patrick Hall&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-12T20:34:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-12T20:34:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I hope this blog does not mind I &#39;ve a put an extended post at http://blog.startup.gr/blog/_archives/2005/9/10/1214941.html
which can serve as a comment on this post.
Have a look
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.startup.gr&#34;&gt;startup&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-09-10T04:30:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-09-10T04:30:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/05/airvideo_and_im.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:38:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my post about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; I offered some evidence on the levels of satisfaction of various group sizes based on some empirical data from online games. There I was able to show that even though the Dunbar Number might predict a mean group size of 150 for humans, that in fact for non-survival oriented groups the mean was significantly less, probably between 60 to 90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/groupsatisfaction.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=436,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;272&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Groupsatisfaction&#34; title=&#34;Groupsatisfaction&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/groupsatisfaction.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I also offered a second hypothesis, that there is a dip in satisfaction level of groups at around the size of 15. Unfortunately, I could only offer anecdotal evidence that this threshold existed. My personal belief was that this dip was caused by not enough &amp;quot;attention&amp;quot; being given to everyone and that group gatherings of this size risk becoming too noisy, too boring, too long, or some combination thereof. Yet groups of this size are not large enough to allow for different perspectives (i.e. insufficient &lt;a href=&#34;http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/REQVAR.html&#34;&gt;requisite variety&lt;/a&gt;) or for other group processes to come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading through the current (12 March) issue of &lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt;, and found an interesting table in the article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=mg18524901.600&#34;&gt;Charity Begins at Homo Sapiens&lt;/a&gt;. It stood out to me as it showed a dip approaching zero average cooperation for group sizes of 16 -- almost precisely same place that my hypothesis predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging further, I found the original source for this table was published in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; back in October 2003, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/papers/NatureOfHumanAltruism.pdf&#34;&gt;The Nature of Human Altruism&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/&#34;&gt;Ernst Fehr&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fischbacher/&#34;&gt;Urs Fischbacher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=495,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;309&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1&#34; alt=&#34;Nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What the chart shows is actually not empirical data from human experiments, but instead data from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_theory&#34;&gt;game theory&lt;/a&gt; simulation of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&#34;&gt;prisoner&#39;s dilemma&lt;/a&gt;. This is the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-sum&#34;&gt;zero-sum game&lt;/a&gt; where if you cooperate, the joint payoff of the players is higher. However, in zero-sum games there is also incentive for the players to cheat by defecting and thus taking less risk. Robert Axelrod showed in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0465021212/102-0974708-1794504&#34;&gt;The Evolution of Cooperation&lt;/a&gt; back in 1985 that in spite of the statistical best individual strategy being that of defection, cooperation inevitably evolves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fehr and Fischbacher, in their &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; article, took this idea a bit further by creating 100 independent simulations with group sizes ranging from 2 to 512, and then executing each simulation 1,000 to 2,000 times. Each generation of the &amp;quot;players&amp;quot; was allowed to evolve different strategies of cooperation vs defection, the classic successful strategy being &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tit_for_tat&#34;&gt;Tit for Tat&lt;/a&gt;. They would then evaluate the percentage of players who had cooperative strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If punishment of defections was ruled out, they discovered that over the 1,000+ generations of the simulation that the rate of cooperation quickly crashes, such that at the group size of 8 a little over 50% cooperation evolved, and for groups that are larger than 16 none cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next they added to the simulation &amp;quot;&lt;a name=&#34;altruistic_punishment&#34;&gt;Altruistic Punishment&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. This is the ability for players to punish those who did not cooperate -- however, such punishment is at some cost to the punisher. Earlier game theory &lt;a href=&#34;http://ideas.repec.org/cgi-bin/get_doc.pl?urn=RePEc:wpa:wuwpmi:0305006&amp;amp;url=http://econwpa.wustl.edu:8089/eps/mic/papers/0305/0305006.pdf&#34;&gt;research on altruistic punishment&lt;/a&gt; has shown that cooperation flourishes if there is some price for punishing defectors -- if you allow punishment at no cost then cheating strategies emerge. This earlier research determined that allowing individuals to punish at some cost that yields them no material gain will paradoxically result in an average gain for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding altruistic punishment to the simulation increased the amount of cooperation that evolved, such that groups with the size of 32 would have 50% cooperation. But even this had limits; at the group size of 128 no cooperation would evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if they added to the simulation the ability to punish those who did not participate in punishing (i.e. didn&#39;t pay the cost to punish defectors), then the percentage of cooperation that evolved was never less then 60%, and in fact got better as groups got larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very interesting result. To explain it in different terms, if you have a system that depends on sharing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons&#34;&gt;commons&lt;/a&gt; and there are no process or trust metrics, a group as small as 16 may find themselves not cooperating very effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of commons can be as simple as how much speaking time participants in a meeting share. The time that each participant uses during the meeting can be considered the shared &amp;quot;commons&amp;quot;. If there are no enforced rules, with a group size of 16 there will inevitably be someone who will abuse the time and speak more than their share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some simple rules (some type of process to partition time more fairly), or through some trust metrics (punish those who abuse the commons), larger groups can gain value from cooperating, but even these groups have limits. As long as there is some effort required to punish those who abuse the process, eventually the price for that effort becomes too high, and no one is willing to punish any longer. You see this in moderated discussion groups, where the guardians of the common good have to spend too much time moderating, given the number of people that wish to participate. Moderated newsgroups and early versions of SlashDot moderation had this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting observation from this simulation is that for larger groups, you needed to have a system to punish those who did not participate in punishing -- or to put it another way, get everyone involved with the process, not just a few. I think that this explains something that I&#39;ve always wondered about SlashDot&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usemod.com/cgi-bin/mb.pl?MetaModeration&#34;&gt;meta-moderation&lt;/a&gt; system -- with this feature you grade those who have moderated, and if someone abuses it they will no longer be able to moderate. What I suspect, given these results, is that if you don&#39;t participate in the meta-moderation system, you have less a chance of being able to moderate; thus SlashDot has a system that punishes those who are not involved in participating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have some questions based on this simulation -- I would like to see results with more granularity then powers of 2. I&#39;d also like to know the percentage of players participating in punishment -- I suspect that you&#39;ll find a very small number of &amp;quot;moderators&amp;quot; are required in the middle graph, even when cooperation evolves successfully. I&#39;m curious as to how many moderators are required to participate in punishing the non-punishers for cooperation to evolve in the third scenario. Also, in meta-moderation this simulation emphasizes punishing the non-punishers -- is that as successful as rewarding the punishers? I&#39;m also interested in investigating some of the further works where Fehr and Fischbacher are among the co-authors, such as this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/science/Altruistic_Punishment.pdf&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; using MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging) that shows that our brain&#39;s pleasure systems are activated when we altruistically punish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure that the findings of this simulation are not the only reason why there might be a dip in group satisfaction at group sizes around 15, such as I observed. However, it does offer some interesting insights into group size thresholds, both for the threshold at 15 and for threshold of non-survival groups which I&#39;ve identified as being significantly less then the Dunbar mean of 150. It also shows that for large groups we need to offer not only moderation, but meta-moderation capabilities that involve all the participants in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary this research offers me another widget for my social software toolbox: in any group process look for the commons, allow participants to participate in identifing defectors; determine what the costs are for such identification (which may be as simple as requiring some attention or charging for such punishment); and encourage participation in the common good by punishing those who do not participate in seeking out defectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
For role based community blogging, check out http://go.webassistant.com/wa
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Garsett Larosse&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-22T21:09:33-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-22T21:09:33-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You may be onto something. The Dunbar number was referred to in the Tipping Point and in some places plays a role in tribal-forming. But for smaller activities the number 15 seems ideal, eg, for a classroom or workshop. If there&#39;s under 10 or 12, regardless of the room size people want to bail out because there doesn&#39;t seem to be &#34;enough&#34; people. Much over 15 and the group dynamic must change to lecture style as if there were 50 or 100 people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.pagehalffull.com/humanyms/&#34;&gt;Pearl&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-23T12:16:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-23T12:16:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Association Football (&#34;soccer&#34;) and cricket teams are 11 strong and are organised by a single player, the captain.  Rugby Union sides are 15 strong, and the organising job is split: the forwards are led by a &#34;pack leader&#34; who is subject to the team captain.  Any significance?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;dearieme&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-30T03:16:15-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-30T03:16:15-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
A superb blog Chris, but just a few errata on the post.
First the simulation in Fehr,et al is a multi-person prisoner&#39;s dilemma--a public goods game--which is identical to the game in the &#34;research on altruistic punishment&#34; link which I think is a great introduction to the literature.
Second, the prisoner&#39;s dilemma is not a zero-sum game although often times mis-attributed as such. In zero-sum games, the total payoff in each possible outcome must be the same; thus, your gain must be my loss. The tragedy of the prisoner&#39;s dilemma is simply that cooperate is not a good strategy for either player.
Third, I think the sentence with the &#34;research on altruistic punishment&#34; link should be &#34;... cooperation flourishes EVEN if there is a cost to punishing defectors.&#34; The later part of the sentence is incorrect. However, the result is still paradoxical as under the notion of rationality one would not expect anyone to incur the cost of punishing another without any personal profit.
Finally, although this research seems to be one capable of addressing organizational size, it is actually quite incapable of that feat. The number 16 on the graph is really a coincidence of circumstances see the graph in http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/anthro/faculty/boyd/SecondOrderFreeRidePublished.pdf for the impact of parameter values on the model. Actually, coincidence is not quite correct; it was a deliberate selection by the researchers. This literature is designed to unshackle economics from the rational agent paradigm not to address optimal organizational size.
I will try to see if there are more pertinent experimental research addressing the Dunbar number question and post them, but I&#39;m somewhat doubtful as the experimental design is still too limited to study such a complex phenomenon. I had thought to try to run such an experiment myself a year ago, but abandoned the idea. I think an econometric analysis of the online games data is probably the most promising course.
--an apologetic economist
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;chinteliu&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-07T03:45:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-07T03:45:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;is the supposed cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable social relationships: the kind of relationships that go with knowing who each person is and how each person relates socially to every other person. Proponents assert that group sizes larger than this generally require more restricted rules, laws, and enforced policies and regulations to maintain a stable cohesion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.edivergent.com&#34;&gt;Busby seo challenge&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-07-26T23:03:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-07-26T23:03:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>