<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ranking on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/ranking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ranking on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2006 23:37:09 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/ranking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2006 23:37:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.7em;&#34;&gt;by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This is the third in a series of articles on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt;, co-written by my collegue &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline&#34;&gt;Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt;. It will be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_179.phtml&#34;&gt;jointly posted&lt;/a&gt; in Shannon&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT.shtml&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities&lt;/a&gt; online games column at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our first article on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt; we outlined a number of different types of choice systems, among them voting, polling, rating, and ranking. Since then we&#39;ve been spending some time expanding upon the systems, with the goal being to create both a lexicon of and a dialogue about systems for collective choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we&#39;re going to dig more into &lt;em&gt;comparison ranking systems&lt;/em&gt;, by focusing on &lt;em&gt;competitive&lt;/em&gt; rankings and looking more in depth at ELO Chess Ranking System and the other systems that we briefly mentioned previously. Our goal is to explicate these systems, to better address their flaws, to begin detailing the purposes of ranking systems, and to show how those purposes are critical in the design of ranking systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;subjective_vs_objective&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Subjective vs. Objective Rankings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our original article we discussed &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;rating systems&lt;/a&gt; as being largely subjective and ranking systems as being objective, but the situation isn&#39;t nearly as simple as that. In truth, there&#39;s a clear spectrum of ratings and rankings with varying amounts of subjectivity and objectivity in each collective choice system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcsfootball.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Bcs_1&#34; title=&#34;Bcs_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/bcs_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.officialworldgolfranking.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/golfrankings_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Golfrankings_1&#34; alt=&#34;Golfrankings_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowl_Championship_Series&#34;&gt;Bowl Championship Series&lt;/a&gt; (BCS) for college football is a good example of a ranking system that explicitly allows a subjective component. It involves a complex mathematical formula that includes things like win/loss ratios, but also sportswriters&#39; and coaches&#39; ratings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, public opinion continues to show that people don&#39;t necessarily like seeing true ranking systems having subjective components, because they expect them to be &amp;quot;fair&amp;quot;. The BCS formula has come under attack several times in the last few years precisely due to its subjective basis. Cal Berkeley was one of several teams denied a bowl position in 2004 when many felt that they were worthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atptennis.com/en/players/raceleaderboard/rank_definitions.asp&#34;&gt;APL tennis rankings&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_rankings&#34;&gt;official world golf rankings&lt;/a&gt; also have a subjective component, but it is much more subtle. Each tournament is worth a certain number of points, and the allocation of those points is relatively arbitrary, based upon the &amp;quot;prestige&amp;quot; of each tournament and the quality of players who have traditionally played in it. The subjectivism isn&#39;t quite as near to the surface as that of the college bowls, but it&#39;s still something that can have a notable, and perhaps unwarranted, effect upon the final results.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;algorithmic_rankings&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Algorithmic Rankings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kosteniuk.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; title=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wcsrating_2.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This brings us back to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELO_rating_system&#34;&gt;ELO system&lt;/a&gt;, a ranking system originally designed for chess which is fairly well-known and well-understood. As we said in our overview article, &amp;quot;[ELO] builds a simple distribution of player ratings around a norm (typically 1500 points), then awards or deducts points based upon wins and losses, with the total sum of all points in the system staying constant. Players are then ranked according to their comparative scores.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big difference between this and the previously discussed systems is that it&#39;s almost entirely objective; in fact it uses a statistical basis to create an underlying mathematical model for rankings, rather than allowing human subjectivity to get in the way.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest formulation for an ELO rating looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span size=&#34;+2&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&#39; = R + K * (S - E)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&#39;&lt;/code&gt; is the new rating&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is the old rating&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; is a maximum value for increase or decrease of rating (16 or 32 for ELO)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; is the score for a game&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt; is the expected score for a game&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the trick is in figuring out what the (&lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;)xpected score of a game is. ELO uses the following formulas for players A and B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;E(A) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [R(B) - R(A)] / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;E(B) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [R(A) - R(B)] / 400 ) ]&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a good model because, using the two formulas, it means that a great player gains little from beating an average player, but an average player gains a lot from beating a great player. Take the following example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;R(A) = 1900&lt;br /&gt;R(B) = 1500&lt;br /&gt;
E(A) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [1500 - 1900] / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( -400 / 400) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ -4 / 4 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ -1 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / 1 + .1&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = .91&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 91%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;E(B) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [1900 - 1500] / 400) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( 400 / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ 1 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / 11&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = .09&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 9%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player A is expected to score .91 in an average game, which is to say he should win 91% of the time, and will be punished accordingly if he loses to player B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * (0 - .91)&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 - 29.12&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1871&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely a win nets him very little:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * (1 - .91)&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * .09&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 2.88&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1903&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELO is almost entirely mathematical. Players can gain or lose different amounts of points based upon playing different players, but this is all part of the formula. The only slightly subjective element is the definition of &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; -- how much a player can win or lose from a particular game. The most widely used ELO systems for Chess break &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; down into two values: 16 for masters and 32 for everyone else. So there is a subjective decision that masters should vary their score less frequently than other players. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a very minor element in an otherwise objective system, but as we&#39;ll see, more recent systems by Days of Wonder and Microsoft first reduce, then eliminate even this subjectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;days_of_wonder&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations of a Theme: Days of Wonder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daysofwonder.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Dowlogo_1&#34; title=&#34;Dowlogo_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/dowlogo_1.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
ELO is probably the most used ranking system in the world. You can find it in use for Go, &lt;em&gt;Tantrix&lt;/em&gt;, and many other games. Days of Wonder, producers of &lt;em&gt;Gang of Four&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ticket to Ride&lt;/em&gt;, and many other games use a variant of the system which they describe on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gangoffour.com/index.php?t=content&amp;amp;sub=ranking&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They identify three core problems with ELO: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New players can take a long time to ascend or descend to their correct levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highly ranked players can be hesitant to play with provisional players whose ranking might be much more uncertain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no allowances for games with more than two players.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Days of Wonder resolved the first problem by creating a new formula for provisional players, allowing them to rise and fall in the rankings much more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely when playing against provisional players, regular players can only lose a maximum of &lt;code&gt;K*n/20&lt;/code&gt; points, where n is the number of games that the provisional player has played--rather than the normal maximum loss of &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;. For example, playing someone who has just played one game, can only result in a loss of 1/20th of the regular &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; value, and so it really doesn&#39;t matter if the provisional player&#39;s ranking is wildly out of whack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these new formulas are set up to converge toward a normal ELO formula as a provisional player&#39;s number of games approaches 20 (making them a normal player at Days of Wonder).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It should be pointed out that using the number &amp;quot;20&amp;quot; to define a provisional player, and making a player less provisional in clean 5% steps, inevitably offers yet another small, subjective element into this mathematical formula; as we&#39;ll see momentarily Microsoft has more recently incorporated the idea of provisional uncertainty into their core mathematical model, much as the whole ELO system originally turned subjective win and loss statistics into tighter mathematics.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/wonder/TT/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ttrskotosrankings.png&#34; title=&#34;Ttrskotosrankings&#34; alt=&#34;Ttrskotosrankings&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, to resolve the situation of multiple players, Days of Wonder considers each game to be a set of duels, as described here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
There are 4 players in a &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gang of Four game. Let&#39;s name A the winning player, B the second one, C the third one and D the last one. We consider that there were 6 duels: A won against B, C and D. B won against C and D. C won against D. We compute independently the new scores for each duel, and then we average the values for each player&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a fairly elegant answer that not only rewards or penalizes all players separately, but also encourages playing for second place, or even third, if first isn&#39;t possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been continued discussions of the Days of Wonder ELO variant in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daysofwonder.com/index.php?t=forums&#34;&gt;their forums&lt;/a&gt;, and the questions raised there are common to many different ranking systems. Some players wanted unranked games, while others thought that having unranked games would discourage people from playing good competitors &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; in unranked games.&amp;nbsp; There has also been a lot of discussion regarding &lt;em&gt;Ticket to Ride&lt;/em&gt;, a strategy game that supports 2-5 people, and whether the ELO variant system discourages multiperson play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various lessons learned at Days of Wonder underline two basic ideas about rankings. First, even with a well-studied system like ELO, there&#39;s still a lot to understand, and, second, any ranking system needs to reflect the specifics of what it&#39;s ranking -- and what its purpose is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;xbox_360_live&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations on a Theme: XBox 360 Live&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/default.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskillxbox360&#34; title=&#34;Trueskillxbox360&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/trueskillxbox360.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An even more recent large-scale ranking system is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.microsoft.com/displayArticle.aspx?id=1361&#34;&gt;TrueSkill&lt;/a&gt; system developed by Microsoft for use with the XBox 360. It appears to be an expanded variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://math.bu.edu/people/mg/glicko/glicko.doc/glicko.html&#34;&gt;glicko&lt;/a&gt; ranking system used by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freechess.org/&#34;&gt;free internet chess server&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the problems identified by Microsoft were the same as those already noted by Days of Wonder and others, including: the uncertainty of provisional ratings and the need to rank players in multiplayer games. However, the TrueSkill system notably expands both issues. Ranking uncertainty is now defined as a mathematical concept and the rankings now support not just multiple players, but also multiple teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/trueskill.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=430,height=324,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskill&#34; title=&#34;Trueskill&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/trueskill.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;TrueSkill explicitly includes two values in any ranking: a skill level and an uncertainty level. The first, like the more common ELO ranking, tells how good a player is. The second states how sure that ranking is. The uncertainty rating is effectively a margin of error, similar to those we saw in &lt;em&gt;polling systems&lt;/em&gt;. If a first-time player has a skill rating of 25 with an uncertainty rating of 8.3 that means that his skill is probably somewhere in the range of 16.7 to 33.3, a pretty wide range, but then this is a totally untested player. According to benchmarks that Microsoft produced, 99.99% of actual skill levels were within 3x of the uncertainty rating, and 100% were within 4x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of TrueSkill&#39;s innovations are built around this model of uncertainty. All players win or lose skill points, based upon how many players they beat or lose to, and they also decrease their uncertainty rating as they play more games. However, uncertainty is decreased more for players toward the middle of a pack within a game than those around the edges (because on the edges the players could actually be much better or much worse than it is possible to see from a specific game). In addition, TrueSkill is only a zero-sum ranking system for players at the exact same level of uncertainty. The more uncertainty that an opponent possesses, the smaller the weighting of any gain or loss (much like the simpler system that Days of Wonder uses, which bases weightings of games against provisional players as &lt;code&gt;n/20&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall TrueSkill is a somewhat complex system that is described more fully at Microsoft&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/Details.aspx#How_to_Update_Skills&#34;&gt;web site&lt;/a&gt;. Some of their expansions had already been considered by others, but still their system is notably innovative in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expanding a competitive ranking system to include concepts of teams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incorporating the uncertainty of ratings further into the core mathematical model, rather than using a somewhat more subjective model such as that described by Days of Wonder for provisional players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/RankCalculator.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/trueskillcalculator_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Trueskillcalculator_1&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskillcalculator_1&#34; class=&#34;image-full&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The TrueSkill calculations are a bit complex. In general, that&#39;s not a problem for a computer-based ranking model because you can have a computer doing all the computations, and players only need to understand the results. However the two-part ranking system used by TrueSkill, which notes both skill level and uncertainty, does offer a potential problem on this latter point. &lt;em&gt;Can players understand it?&lt;/em&gt; In general, the concept of uncertainty will not be understood by people other that statisticians, thus raising a real user-interface question with the TrueSkill system -- and the exact sort of thing that designers of new ranking systems will need to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;a_tale_in_the_desert&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations on a Theme: A Tale in the Desert&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atid.com&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;A_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1&#34; title=&#34;A_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/a_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The online game, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atitd.com&#34;&gt;A Tale in the Desert&lt;/a&gt;, identified a different problem with the ELO system: &lt;em&gt;cheating&lt;/em&gt;. This is a uniquely Internet-based problem, because there users can create fake accounts, then defeat those accounts to win points. This can also be done more subtly, by having multiple additional accounts build up the rating of that fake account before the fake account is defeated. So a totally new ranking system, called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.atitd.net/tale1/EGenesis_Ranking_System&#34;&gt;eGenesis Ranking System&lt;/a&gt;, was created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each player is ranked through a 256-bit vector, half of which is initially set to 0 and half of which is set to 1 (therefore creating an average ranking of 128). Whenever a match occurs between players a hash function based on the players&#39; names mathematically selects 32 of those bits, 8 of which are then randomly selected. Among those bits, any 1s in the loser&#39;s vector which correspond to 0s in the winner&#39;s vector are &amp;quot;transferred&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple design corresponds in some ways to ELO&#39;s more complex formula. A good player will have more 1s and thus more to lose, and he will lose correspondingly more to a poor player who has more 0s in his vector. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the system also prevents the collusion earlier noted. Statistically, a single player will only ever gain 8 ranking points from another new player, since out of the 32 bit hash only eight of those will, on average, be in the correct 0-1 configuration. Expanding a group of players expands the number of points that can potentially be gained, but within real limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wowsocialmap_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Wowsocialmap_1&#34; alt=&#34;Wowsocialmap_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In fact, the eGenesis system prevents cheating by measuring the size of social networks, then limiting the number of ranking points that can be earned within a social network. It&#39;s not necessarily the only way to measure social network size, but its methodology points toward social software as an interesting area for additional study of ranking systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with XBox&#39;s TrueSkill, the eGenesis algorithms are overall fairly sophisticated and confusing, perhaps more so than TrueSkill itself. However, unlike TrueSkill the output is very simple: a skill number between 0 and 255. The intricacies are hidden by the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Competitive Ranking Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, as we mentioned when discussing Days of Wonder, any ranking system has to be measured by what it&#39;s trying to do and how well it does that. ELO and similar numerical, long-term ranking systems, are most likely trying to achieve one of three goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;heirarchy&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hierarchy:&lt;/strong&gt; Players are divided into hierarchies of success, giving players goals to constantly strive for and ways to measure their success (or failure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;matching&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matching:&lt;/strong&gt; Players can play with other players at their same skill level, rather than having to play beginners or experts who are much better than they are. This generally increases everyone&#39;s enjoyment. For computer games, the complexity of a matching system can be largely moderated by the computer, thus ensuring better competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;handicapping&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handicapping:&lt;/strong&gt; If players do play against others of different skill levels, the better players can be handicapped in automatic, appropriate ways for the game in question, again increasing the fairness of games and everyone&#39;s enjoyment. For instance, someone ranked 3-kyu in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28board_game%29&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; playing a less experienced 7-kyu player would give him a starting &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_handicap&#34;&gt;4 stone advantage&lt;/a&gt; to make for better competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ELO system may be a good matching system, which allows players to easily find other players of their same skill level and play against them. However it doesn&#39;t provide any way to handicap players, nor would the ELO method necessarily be a good one to analyze handicaps (and conversely a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_handicap&#34;&gt;golf handicap&lt;/a&gt; might not do a good job of finding like players nor measuring players&#39; ability in a hierarchy). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently the XBox system has stated that it&#39;s explicitly for matchmaking, with the goal being to always try and match up players at nearly the same skill level. It&#39;s also used for hierarchy (or &amp;quot;leaderboards&amp;quot; as it&#39;s described in the TrueSkill docs), but that&#39;s clearly a subsidiary purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these systems would be ineffective for measuring a winner in a live event, which is a very different goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tourney:&lt;/strong&gt; A single player is listed as an absolute winner, the &amp;quot;King of the Hill&amp;quot;. Often, second, third, and fourth place winners are measured too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the systems we&#39;ve discussed thus far may not be useful for measuring privileges, yet another goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threshold:&lt;/strong&gt; The best ranks of players can be given special privileges, including the ability to create games and form tournaments. Alternatively, they can be given privileges totally outside the game, again giving them something extra to strive for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each of these additional goals we may need to consider very different ranking systems, not just variations of ELO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;tourneys&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Different Themes: Tourneys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.kumc.edu/itc/staff/rknight/tourneys.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Tournament_1&#34; title=&#34;Tournament_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/tournament_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
There are a number of well-known tournament types which can be used to create a &amp;quot;King of the Hill&amp;quot; ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-elimination_tournament&#34;&gt;single-elimination tournament,&lt;/a&gt; where the winner of each competition moves on to compete with other winners, until there is only one. However, this style of tournament is quite cut-throat and is not suited very well to events where the competition may result in a draw, or where chance is a notable factor in the competition. It also has a very subjective factor in the initial &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-elimination_tournament#Seeding&#34;&gt;seeding&lt;/a&gt; of the rounds. The single-elimination tournament also does not rank the losers. However, by having the losers compete with each other in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swiss_system_tournament&#34;&gt;Swiss-style tournament&lt;/a&gt;, the relative strengths of the players can be ranked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jsoo.home.mindspring.com/articles/formats/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/pseudodoubleelimination_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Pseudodoubleelimination_1&#34; alt=&#34;Pseudodoubleelimination_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An improvement is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double-elimination&#34;&gt;double-elimination tournament&lt;/a&gt; which is now one of the best known tournament systems in sports. Players compete in series of two-player matches, and a player has to lose twice before he&#39;s eliminated. This is done through a system of winner and loser brackets, wherein people drop from the winners&#39; brackets to the losers&#39; brackets when they lose once, and drop out altogether when they lose twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem with standard double-elimination is that there are unusual situations where a significantly inferior player can still make it to the final round, or the last player to remain undefeated can lose only once and still be eliminated. These can be addressed through variants such as face-off (requiring the last two remaining competitors to compete &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; if the undefeated team is defeated for the first time in the finals) or by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jsoo.home.mindspring.com/articles/formats/&#34;&gt;reconfiguring the loser&#39;s brackets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wscgames.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wsc_1&#34; title=&#34;Wsc_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wsc_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Round-robin_tournament&#34;&gt;Round-robin tournaments&lt;/a&gt;, such as official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wscgames.com/2005/build/standing/1/topten.html&#34;&gt;Scrabble Tournaments&lt;/a&gt; involve every player playing a set number of games (24 in the 2005 World Scrabble Championship), facing opponents with similar win-lose records. They then ultimately rank players by their win-lose ratios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of these sorts of tournament over an ELO-style ranking is that they&#39;re easily understandable and seem fair. In addition, they measure ranking in a much more topical manner: how well someone is playing during a singular instant, rather than over a longer career. As a result they work much better for a live tournament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;thresholds&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Different Themes: Thresholds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we discussed in our original article on Collective Choice, thresholds are ranking barriers above which members get a special ability--or alternatively levels below which members lose a special ability. They can also act as another goal for a ranking system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usgo.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/gosmall.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Gosmall&#34; alt=&#34;Gosmall&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In the game of Go there are both &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_ranks_and_ratings#Pro_and_amateur_ranks&#34;&gt;amateur&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_ranks_and_ratings#Professional_strength&#34;&gt;professional&lt;/a&gt; players. Although they aren&#39;t technically in the same &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cns.nyu.edu/~mechner/go/kyu.html&#34;&gt;hierarchy of rankings&lt;/a&gt;, the highest Go amateur ranking&amp;nbsp; (7 dan) is approximately equal to the lowest Go professional ranking (1 dan), forming a de facto threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/uscf_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Uscf_1&#34; alt=&#34;Uscf_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Likewise the United States Chess Federation uses their ELO rankings to denote &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Chess Masters&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone who achieves 2200 UCSF is given a National Master threshold ranking and anyone who maintains it for 300 games is given a Life Master threshold ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/acblopt2_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Acblopt2_1&#34; alt=&#34;Acblopt2_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/&#34;&gt;American Contract Bridge Association&lt;/a&gt; uses a threshold system where you have to win a certain number of tournaments and thus earn &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/about/honorTitles.html&#34;&gt;masterpoints&lt;/a&gt; in order achieve official rankings such as &amp;quot;section master&amp;quot;. Furthermore, players may earn different &amp;quot;colors&amp;quot; of masterpoints depending the difficulty of the tournament, and some ranks require that you earn at least some specific colored masterpoints in order to meet the requirements for the next threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These thresholds are fairly explicitly based on other hierarchical ranking systems, but this doesn&#39;t need to be the case. Since determining the purpose of a ranking system is often the first step in designing it, as we delve further into the area of thresholds we may well find that systems specifically dedicated toward measuring thresholds are more likely to do so well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our next article we&#39;ll consider among other things the Avogadro reputation system, which manages thresholds in such a way as to prevent cheating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s actually a lot of variety in ranking systems, and even though we&#39;d like them to be totally objective, various subjective elements often creep into these systems. In addition, there&#39;s a lot of variety in what ranking systems can do. For competitive systems, hierarchy, privilege, matching, and handicapping are some of the top purposes of ranking. Determining what a ranking system is going to do is a necessary first step in designing the system, as different systems will accomplish various goals to a better or worse degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELO, in several variants, is the best studied and most used competitive ranking system. It works particularly well as a matching system. However, even ELO has flaws in it, among them: issues with new player rankings; its core two-player basis; its lack of provisions for teams; a few minor subjective elements; and problems with cheaters. New systems continue to be rolled out on the Internet to resolve these issues, and overall, it&#39;s an area of interesting new study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tournament systems and threshold systems offer a few good examples of competitive ranking systems with very different purposes, underlying the need to understand what you&#39;re doing before you do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking systems also lay very near yet another type of Collective Choice: reputation systems. We briefly addressed reputation systems when talking about threshold systems and will return to this in our next article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;A data point on ELO cheating for you: Yahoo! Games uses ELO rankings for several their two-player games. Before recent abuse mitigation changes, some people used robot to accumulate scores in excess of 6,000,000 points. The abuse-the-ranking game had become a totally seperate competition.
For now, Yahoo! has capped the ELO scores at 3,000 (I think.) This removed most of the cheating incentive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fudco.com/habitat&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-05T13:46:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-05T13:46:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;In the slashdot discussion of this blog entry http://games.slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=173988&amp;threshold=0&amp;mode=flat   there was an interesting link to beatpaths.com, which is sort of a tourney system for when you can&#39;t complete a full set of round-robin or double-elimination competitions, as what happens in NFL during the fall season.
What is also interesting to me is that it introduces a goal for ranking systems that I&#39;d not thought of before -- prediction. The purpose of the beatpath systems is actually focused on predicting the outcome the next set of the weekend games.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-14T14:31:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-14T14:31:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;No mention of Glicko and Glicko2?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://swaits.com/&#34;&gt;Stephen Waits&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-15T08:57:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-15T08:57:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;There&#39;s a ranking scheme that Mark Newman from the U of Michigan did for college football, which Yahoo Search turned up a pointer to here:
http://www.sciencenews.org/articles/20051112/mathtrek.asp
quoting:
Physicists Juyong Park and M.E.J. Newman aimed for a ranking system that&#39;s fast and easily understood by fans (in contrast to the cumbersome, opaque BCS formula). They based their ranking method on the notion that, if A beats B, and B beats C, then A also beats C, even if it may not actually play C. Hence, the method counts both direct wins by beating a team and indirect wins by beating a team that beat another team.
(end quote)
You end up with a directed graph of teams as nodes and games as edges, and compute a function of that graph that is related to a centrality metric.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://vielmetti.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Edward Vielmetti&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-02T22:18:39-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-02T22:18:39-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This article is a great survey of the subject!  I&#39;m working on the PvP ranking system for another game with some unique problems, because the teams in a PvP match can be of disparate size and widely differing power levels, which are then balanced so that wildly mismatched teams (ignoring relative rank at PvP for the moment) are actually reasonably matched.
It starts here: http://ncanson.livejournal.com/3938.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ncanson.livejournal.com/&#34;&gt;Matthew Weigel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-01-31T09:55:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-01-31T09:55:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems for Collective Choice</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2005 16:03:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.7em;&#34;&gt;by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline&#34;&gt;[Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt; is a friend and colleague of mine at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;, an online game company. Over the last few years we&#39;ve had many discussions about how decisions are made, and how our society collectively makes choices. The origin of these discussions have varied from &amp;quot;what makes this board game work?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how can we give our players more control of our online games?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how do we make decisions in our company?&amp;quot;, and of course &amp;quot;how did we collectively make such a mess of decision making in America?&amp;quot;. This article, and some followup articles, summarize our thoughts on these topics, and will be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_178.phtml&#34;&gt;jointly posted&lt;/a&gt; in Shannon&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT.shtml&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities&lt;/a&gt; online games column at Skotos.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Peoplearoundthesun&#34; title=&#34;Peoplearoundthesun&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/peoplearoundthesun.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt; Collective choice systems have been around for a long time. Since at least the birth of democracy in ancient Greece people have made joint decisions about important issues, and since at least the knightly tournaments of the late Middle Age people have competed to be ranked against their peers. Today Western culture especially values diversity of input when implementing any type of choice, believing that wide input from a variety of people provides the fairest result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet expands this long history of collective choice. However, as we bring collective choice systems onto the Internet, quantifying and programming them, we discover the need to be more analytical and more methodical in the techniques used. Thus we&#39;re beginning to learn that we don&#39;t know nearly as much about these collective choice systems as we should. There is a need to analyze and study them further, to understand their strengths and weaknesses, and to evaluate their social impact. Fortunately, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/10/tracing_the_evo.html&#34;&gt;social software&lt;/a&gt; and online games on the Internet provides the perfect &lt;em&gt;petri dish&lt;/em&gt; for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before any analysis can occur, however, there is a need for a categorization of systems and a definition of terms. That is the purpose of this article: to lay out at least some of the ways in which collective choices can be made, to organize them, to define them, and to briefly consider them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, there seem to be three methods of collective choice, divided by the intended result: &lt;em&gt;selection&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;opinion&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;comparison&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;selection_systems&#34;&gt;Selection Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selection systems allow for the purposeful choice between multiple items. There are many types of selection systems, but two in particular, &lt;em&gt;representative systems&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;deliberative systems&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;consensus systems&lt;/em&gt; are worth noting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=369,height=393,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/19thamend.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;159&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/19thamend.jpg&#34; title=&#34;19thamend&#34; alt=&#34;19thamend&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;representative_systems&#34;&gt;Representative Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a representative system, individuals cast a ballot for someone who will represent their interests. They&#39;re by definition &lt;em&gt;voting systems&lt;/em&gt; and the heart of any &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republicanism&#34;&gt;Republican&lt;/a&gt; system of government. When you&#39;re voting for a president, prime minister, senator, congressman, director, or board member, that&#39;s representative voting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most representative voting a winner is selected by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality&#34;&gt;plurality&lt;/a&gt;, meaning the winner had more votes than any other candidate. This works well in a simple two-member election, but begins to fall apart if there are multiple candidates, because similar candidates can steal votes from each other, and thus allow a candidate with less popular ideas to be elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest solution is to require a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majority&#34;&gt;majority&lt;/a&gt; victory, meaning that one winner must have at least 50% of the votes. Some places in the United States use this system for their representative elections, holding a first election, eliminating all but the two biggest vote-getters, then holding a new election between these two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_election&#34;&gt;primary-based election system&lt;/a&gt;, wherein all like-minded candidates compete against each other before participating in the real election. This requires buy-in from all like-minded candidates, however, and recent U.S. elections with third-party candidates like Ralph Nader and Ross Perot show the flaws in a voluntary primary system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many other types of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voting_systems&#34;&gt;voting systems&lt;/a&gt; are possible, most of which allow voters to select multiple candidates at the same time. These systems then eliminate the lowest ranked candidates and give their votes to others based upon those voter selections. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/irv.gif&#34; title=&#34;Irv&#34; alt=&#34;Irv&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRV&#34;&gt;Instant Runoff Voting&lt;/a&gt;, or IRV, is a fairly commonly used multiple candidate system (though not necessarily the best one). It&#39;s technically a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_Transferable_Vote&#34;&gt;single transferable vote&lt;/a&gt; preferential voting system. Wikipedia describes the process like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Each voter ranks at least one candidate in order of preference.&lt;br /&gt; ...&lt;br /&gt; First choices are tallied. If no candidate has the support of a majority of voters, the candidate with the least support is eliminated. A second round of counting takes place, with the votes of supporters of the eliminated candidate now counting for their second choice candidate. After a candidate is eliminated, he or she may not receive any more votes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This process of counting and eliminating is repeated until one candidate has over half the votes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s simple to understand, but also flawed. That&#39;s because every voting system ultimately has &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow&#39;s_impossibility_theorem&#34;&gt;flaw&lt;/a&gt; in it, as is evidenced by the fact that given the same conditions the different systems will often declare different winners. Different systems may also allow voters to &amp;quot;game&amp;quot; the system in different ways. This is often called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tactical_voting&#34;&gt;tactical voting&lt;/a&gt; or strategic voting. Similar to analyzing various &amp;quot;attacks&amp;quot; when studying a cryptosystem, looking at which tactical voting approaches each voting system is vulnerable to helps you evaluate the voting systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, one type of tactical voting that can be used against an Instant Runoff Vote is the push-over strategy, which Wikipedia describes as this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Push-over is a type of strategic voting in which a voter ranks a perceived weak alternative higher, but not in the hopes of getting it elected. This primarily occurs in runoff voting when a voter already believes that his favored candidate will make it to the next round - the voter then ranks an unpreferred, but easily beatable, candidate higher so that his preferred candidate can win later. A United States analogy would be voters of one party crossing over to vote in the other party&#39;s primary to nominate a candidate who will be easy for their favorite to beat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in an IRV election between Bush, Gore, and Nader, Democrats might rank Nader over Bush. The hope would be that this would give Nader enough votes to keep him from being eliminated, thus knocking Bush out instead in the first round. Afterward the Republican Bush votes transfer to the less progressive Gore, rather than the fringe Nader, allowing Gore to beat the &amp;quot;pushover&amp;quot; Nader when they couldn&#39;t have faced Bush in a straight-up fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There several different tactical voting &amp;quot;attacks&amp;quot; against various representative voting systems. One of the technically better multiple-candidate voting methods is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condorcet_method&#34;&gt;condorcet method&lt;/a&gt; for voting. It&#39;s immune to most tactical voting strategies and more people would consider its result &amp;quot;correct&amp;quot;, but unfortunately it is much harder on the voters, who have to rank every single candidate. Maybe if we can create a better Internet user-interface to condorcet voting we can make this more sophisticated representative voting system more broadly available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;deliberative_systems&#34;&gt;Deliberative Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a deliberative system, individuals directly make a decision, rather than selecting a representative to do so. Deliberative systems do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have to include voting, and the subcategory of &lt;em&gt;consensus systems&lt;/em&gt; described below technically don&#39;t, however most modern deliberative sytems do. A deliberative system is the heart of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DEMOCRACY&#34;&gt;true democracy&lt;/a&gt;. Traditionally it&#39;s been relatively unfeasible because voters were not expected to be educated enough to make governmental decisions and because they didn&#39;t have the time or capability to regularly decide on issues. The spread of the Internet alleviates at least the latter problem, since millions of people can now simultaneously decide on any issue if they so desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States the best known deliberative system is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Initiative&#34;&gt;initiative&lt;/a&gt; system found in some states, including California. It allows for issues to be put directly before the voters through the submission of sufficient signatures, and then allows the voters to pass or fail those issues, based on either &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality&#34;&gt;plurality&lt;/a&gt; (most votes), &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majority&#34;&gt;majority&lt;/a&gt; (at least 50% of votes), or else &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supermajority&#34;&gt;super majority&lt;/a&gt; (some percentage of votes in excess of 51%). In California, for example, 66% approval is required for new tax initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/constitution_signing.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=540,height=350,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;129&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Constitution_signing&#34; title=&#34;Constitution_signing&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/constitution_signing.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The United States constitution defines a large and very complex deliberative system. It creates three bodies of government to support deliberation and voting, and uses a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checks_and_Balances#Checks_and_balances&#34;&gt;checks and balances&lt;/a&gt; systems in order to allow different branches to have different effects upon a vote. The main voting is done by the legislature, which requires two &lt;em&gt;pluralities&lt;/em&gt; from two different groups of people to pass a vote. Then the executive branch has a singular opportunity to veto legislature, which then requires a &lt;em&gt;super majority&lt;/em&gt; (here, 66%) to override that veto. Once a law is established, the judicial department may by &lt;em&gt;plurality&lt;/em&gt; vote to declare that legislation unconstitutional, but that may be overcome by an even greater &lt;em&gt;super majority&lt;/em&gt; (typically, 66% of each legislature + 75% of the state governments) who want to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Constitution#Provisions_for_amendment&#34;&gt;amend the constitution&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constitution also shows how deliberation can span beyond simple voting because of the fact that it includes specific rules for how to debate, when debate can be closed, etc. In today&#39;s very fractured congress, however, it&#39;s unclear if individuals ever are actually swayed by deliberations in the floor of the legislature, or if they&#39;ve already decided to follow their party lines or their specific interests, long before they entered the Capitol buildings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smaller example of a true deliberative system, based on guiding discussions as much as holding votes, is found in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertsrules.org/&#34;&gt;Robert&#39;s Rules of Order&lt;/a&gt;, a guide for conducting meetings. These rules detail explicit methods not just for voting, but also for the deliberation and discussion surrounding the voting. Various &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;minority&lt;/em&gt; votes can be taken to allow for certain actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because deciding directly upon ideas rather than just voting for representatives can have a greater effect upon a community, the deliberative systems may need to be more complex to avoid abuse, as evidenced by the complexities of the U.S. Government and Robert&#39;s Rule of Order. However, these very complexities can make these systems more prone to purposeful gaming. The benefits and deficits of more complex deliberative systems have not yet been fully studied, nor have there been as much analysis of &amp;quot;attacks&amp;quot; against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/consensus_1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;141&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/consensus_1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Consensus_1&#34; alt=&#34;Consensus_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;consensus_systems&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;consensus_systems&#34;&gt;Consensus Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In consensus systems people jointly come to a consensus as a group through group interactions. This sort of decision making theoretically avoids the &amp;quot;tyranny of the majority&amp;quot; and likewise can produce more informed decision making. It&#39;s a variant of the broader &lt;em&gt;deliberative systems&lt;/em&gt;, but one with more group and less individual power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of consensual selection is cabinet government as laid out under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster_system&#34;&gt;Westminster System&lt;/a&gt;. Wikipedia describes it as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; Members of the Cabinet are collectively seen as responsible for government policy. All Cabinet decisions are made by consensus, a vote is never taken in a Cabinet meeting. All ministers, whether senior and in the Cabinet, or junior ministers, must support the policy of the government publicly regardless of any private reservations. If a minister does not agree with a decision he, or she, can resign from the government; as did several British ministers over the 2003 Invasion of Iraq. This means that in the Westminster system of government the cabinet always collectively decides all decisions and all ministers are responsible for arguing in favour of any decision made by the cabinet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_decision-making#Quaker-based_consensus&#34;&gt;Quaker-based consensus&lt;/a&gt; offers a similar example. Herein a facilitator helps to identify disagreements and agreements to move a discussion forward until an end result is embraced by all individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final note, it&#39;s important to differentiate consensus from coercion. The end result of unanimity isn&#39;t the sole definition of a consensus system, nor is it entirely required. What is required is a more open and thoughtful selection process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;opinion_systems&#34;&gt;Opinion Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Poll&#34; title=&#34;Poll&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/poll.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;Opinion systems are a clear subsidiary category to selection systems. An opinion system&#39;s main use is as a decision indicator, to show how people will decide or did decide in a representative system, a deliberative system, or both. Current opinion systems tend to be oriented toward actual votes, as opposed to more freeform selection systems (though the &lt;em&gt;delphic polling system&lt;/em&gt; shows a more freeform version of the category itself). Opinion systems tend to be push-based (meaning people are asked for their opinions rather than actively offering them), but this isn&#39;t required. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All opinion systems tend to have the same general problem, which is figuring out how to use scientific means to determine the actual results of a decision. This means massaging respondent numbers to offset categories of people more or less likely to vote to try and generate the actual results. For example, one 1998 poll showed that 62% of Republicans were absolutely certain they were going to vote, while only 51% of Independents could say the same. This means that every Republican voter a poll contacted in that year might have been weighted about 1.2x over every Independent contacted. Of course the actual calculations are much more complex than that, since they tend to depend upon traditional voter turnout and lots of analysis, but the core idea is sound, which is that every polled individual should &lt;u&gt;not&lt;/u&gt; be considered equal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All opinion system results tend to be rated with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margin_of_error&#34;&gt;margins of error&lt;/a&gt;. The margin of error is a percent spread which the poll is expected to be within, 90-99% of the time (depending on how conservative of a confidence rating is given). If a poll shows that a politician is expected to take 48% of the vote, for example, and the margin of error is 4%, that means he is expected to take 44-52% of the vote with 90-99% surety. Margins of error are typically given much greater importance in the modern media than they should, as they&#39;re calculated solely based upon the total number of respondents to a poll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two general categories of opinion systems: &lt;em&gt;pre-voting (subjective) polling systems&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;post-voting (objective) polling systems&lt;/em&gt;. A different type of opinion system, &lt;em&gt;delphic polling&lt;/em&gt;, which could apply to either pre- or post-voting systems is also covered. Polling systems not directly related to selection systems are covered later, as &lt;em&gt;subjective rating systems&lt;/em&gt;, since they tend to have issues very different from other polling systems, as their goal isn&#39;t to try and match the &amp;quot;true&amp;quot; number of an actual vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;pre-voting_polling_systems&#34;&gt;Pre-voting Polling Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; These are polls made before a vote is cast. They&#39;re often called &amp;quot;opinion polls&amp;quot; and tend to be conducted via phone. They try and isolate &amp;quot;likely voters&amp;quot; and determine how they will vote. This question of voter likelihood is one of the first issues with a pre-voting system, because there&#39;s no guarantee that the polled people will actually later vote. Likewise, pre-voting systems have to accommodate &amp;quot;undecided voters&amp;quot; and the fact that no voter has ever truly made up their mind until they cast their final ballot. Unlike post-voting polling systems, pre-voting systems also have considerable more possibility for bias (which is not accounted for by margins of error), based upon how questions are asked, in what order, and with what additional text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Exitpoll&#34; title=&#34;Exitpoll&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/exitpoll.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;post-voting_polling_systems&#34;&gt;Post-voting Polling Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; These are polls taken after a vote is cast. They&#39;re typically called &amp;quot;exit polls&amp;quot;, as most are conducted as people are leaving a &amp;quot;polling&amp;quot; station (where they cast a vote). One would expect these to be much more reliable than pre-voting polls, but as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004_U.S._presidential_election_controversy_and_irregularities#Exit_polls&#34;&gt;2004 U.S. Presidential Election&lt;/a&gt; showed, exit polls can be wildly inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems with post-voting polling systems, shared with pre-voting systems, is that the results must be manipulated to make sure that respondents to the poll match the percentages of those constituencies in the overall populations. For example, in the 2004 exit polls it appears that women were initially overrepresented in exit polls, and because of increased black turnout it appears that blacks were underrepresented in the exit polls. It can easily be seen how either of these misrepresentations could cause notable changes in an exit poll result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When conducted &amp;amp; matched correctly, exit polls are supposed to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004_U.S._presidential_election_controversy%2C_exit_polls#Reliability_of_Exit_Polls&#34;&gt;quite reliable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/delphiamphitheatre.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=458,height=317,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;138&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Delphiamphitheatre&#34; title=&#34;Delphiamphitheatre&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/delphiamphitheatre.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;delphic_polling_systems&#34;&gt;Delphic Polling Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; An interesting polling method applicable to all sorts of opinion systems is the &amp;quot;delphi poll&amp;quot;. This is a specific method of polling which is &lt;em&gt;iterative&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;anonymous&lt;/em&gt; and which supports &lt;em&gt;confidence ratings&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;feedback&lt;/em&gt;. The general idea is that people are polled on a question using not just binary responses, but a full confidence rating (e.g., you would state that you are 60% sure that Bush would be elected, rather than stating that you think Bush would be elected). After polls are collected, the anonymous results--or at least a summary of those results--are shared with the participants, who then poll again. This iterative process continues until a consistent answer is settled upon. By incorporating feedback into the polling process there&#39;s the possibility for greatly increased reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways delphic polling systems can be seen as an analogy to &lt;em&gt;consensus systems&lt;/em&gt;, since both involve more iterative processes that eventually result in a more commonly-held decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;comparison_systems&#34;&gt;Comparison Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparison systems allow individual items to be measured up against each other. There are three general categories: &lt;em&gt;comparison ranking systems&lt;/em&gt;, which are largely objective and which typically rank people; and &lt;em&gt;comparison rating systems&lt;/em&gt;, which more often mix subjective and objective opinions, and which more frequently rate things; and &lt;em&gt;reputation rating systems&lt;/em&gt;, which again tend to rank people, but also have a subject and objective mix. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;ranking_systems&#34;&gt;Comparison Ranking Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a ranking system, items in a hierarchy (most frequently people) rise or fall based upon specific, objective, and well-known rules. This is the heart of most multiplayer competitive systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=500,height=336,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/chess.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;134&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/chess.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Chess&#34; alt=&#34;Chess&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELO_rating_system&#34;&gt;ELO System&lt;/a&gt; is an example of a ranking system used for two-player games, and is used by the U.S. Chess Federation. Days of Wonder uses a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gangoffour.com/index.php?t=content&amp;amp;sub=ranking&#34;&gt;multiplayer variant of the ELO system&lt;/a&gt; for their online games. Each system builds a simple distribution of player ratings around a norm (typically 1500 points), then awards or deducts points based upon wins and losses, with the total sum of all points in the system staying constant. Players are then ranked according to their comparative scores. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are flaws in ranking systems like ELO. For example, two players could collude, with one purposefully throwing games so that his opponent could increase his ranking. Alternatively if a player gets a few lucky victories against good opponents, his rating might temporarily skyrocket above its normative value. However, these tend to be well-known and well-researched problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are numerous other ranking systems which are used for competitions, from double-elimination seeded tournaments (e.g., a tennis tournament) to ranked comparisons based upon win-loss ratios (e.g., baseball standings). Objective rankings are also (less commonly) used to rank items, such as a ranking of cars based upon safety ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/usmc_enlisted_rank_structure.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=476,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;148&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Usmc_enlisted_rank_structure&#34; title=&#34;Usmc_enlisted_rank_structure&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/usmc_enlisted_rank_structure.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most ranking systems create a hierarchy of positive rankings (e.g., &amp;quot;best chess players ever&amp;quot;). However, a hierarchy of negative rankings may also most be used, most commonly based on a negative criteria (e.g., &amp;quot;biggest Player Killers (PKers)&amp;quot;). In addition, either direction of ranking can use threshold systems to mark positive or negative rankings that meet a certain criteria. A positive threshold might be a &amp;quot;Grand Master&amp;quot; ranking threshold for anyone with a Chess rating of 2700, while a negative threshold might be a &amp;quot;Player Killer&amp;quot; ranking threshold, for with sufficient &amp;quot;accidental&amp;quot; PKs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking systems are somewhat removed from the other collective choice systems listed here, since there&#39;s isn&#39;t a collaborative decision, only a collective result. However their problems &amp;amp; results remain closely related to the more collective rating and reputation systems, hence their inclusion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=373,height=239,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/stars_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/images/stars_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Stars_1&#34; alt=&#34;Stars_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;rating_systems&#34;&gt;Rating Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a rating system, the value of individual items (most frequently goods) rise or fall based upon the largely subjective judgment of individual users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.netflix.com&#34;&gt;Netflix&lt;/a&gt; are two examples of stores which provide subjective rating systems. Individual users rate items from 1 to 5 stars, then an average user rating is calculated. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boardgamegeek.com&#34;&gt;BoardGameGeek&lt;/a&gt; offers a slightly different example because it not only lets users rate individual items, but also ranks items against each other based upon those ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flaws in these systems are similar to those in ranking systems: low numbers of ratings producing bad rankings, and individual users purposefully biasing ratings. Some mathematical methods may be used to smooth out these issues, among them &lt;em&gt;bayesian averages&lt;/em&gt;, which give ratings weight based upon total number of ratings for an item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stock Market offers an example of a different sort of rating system, because there&#39;s theoretically some objective basis to it. In a perfect Stock Market system, stock prices are based upon a solid cost analysis, such as a multiplier on yearly revenues or profits. However, as the Internet bubble of the late 1990s conclusively showed, there&#39;s also a high irrational component to stock purchases: thus subjective and objective views are combined in the rating (cost) of a stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;reputation_systems&#34;&gt;Reputation Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, reputation systems are very similar to ranking systems: items in a hierarchy (most frequently people) rise or fall based upon specific and well-known rules. However, unlike true ranking systems, reputation systems instead base their rules for rise and fall upon other user feedback. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of a reputation system is ultimately to create a trust metric that often allows different users access to different powers. We&#39;ll be covering reputation systems a bit more thoroughly in a couple of weeks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of ways to measure the collective choices of a large group of people. We&#39;ve outline nine here: representative, deliberative, and consensus selection systems; ranking, rating, and reputation comparison systems; and three varieties of opinion systems. When developing social software it is important to understand the difference between these broad categories of systems and to use lessons already learned from the appropriate category in your own social software designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34;&gt;2006-01: Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You seemed to leave out consensus methods such as the Quakers and facilitated decision making processes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.imaginal.nl&#34;&gt;Jon Jenkins&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-02T00:08:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-02T00:08:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;My intent was more to outline the broad categories of collective choice, then to give all the possible examples within each category. Both consensus methods and facilitated decision making processes fall under the &#34;deliberation systems&#34; category.
It is my hope in future articles to dig deeper into each broad category and show more examples of types. Next week hopefully will be comparison rating systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-02T00:39:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-02T00:39:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You should take a look at Jeff Vails&#39; writings on rhizome networks as counter weights to hierchical power structures. http://www.jeffvail.net/2005/08/rhizome-communication-and-our-one-time.html
There&#39;s a connection between your ideas and his that I can&#39;t quite articulate because my mind is focussed elsewhere at the moment. But I shall return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://karavans.typepad.com/&#34;&gt;peter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-07T17:17:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-07T17:17:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve made some changes to this blog entry, adding consensus systems under deliberation systems, added reputation systems as a type of opinion system, simplifying some of the category names, and added some links.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-08T13:13:09-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-08T13:13:09-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is an excellent summary, but I feel like I want a comparison table of some kind.
Would &#34;information futures market&#34; or the like be a Delphic system? It sure seems more like a consensus measuring device to me.
One of the most interesting things about all of these systems is the side effects they have on the decisions made. Binary Votes polorize options. Information Futures Markets encourage results manipulation (by design!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fudco.com/habitat&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-08T14:24:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-08T14:24:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is a wonderful overview.  Thank you for putting it together!
I&#39;d like to suggest one small correction to the description of Condorcet voting, which says &#34;it is much harder on the voters, who have to rank every single candidate&#34;.  In a Condorcet system, the voters don&#39;t have to rank every candidate; they can rank as many or as few as they want (just like IRV), and they can even rank candidates equally (unlike IRV).  The Wikipedia article entitled &#34;Condorcet method&#34; describes this.
Regarding a comparison of these systems, i&#39;ve tried to illustrate the behaviour of plurality, approval, IRV, and Condorcet elections at http://zesty.ca/voting/ , and i hope you will find my method and results interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://wolog.net/&#34;&gt;Ping&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-14T01:33:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-14T01:33:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The problem of choice is outline very well in the book &#39;The Paradox of Choice&#39; by Bary Schwartz.  It provides a great description of some of the other challenges of multi-party elections. I found it very interesting when it got into the psychology of choice regret, and alternative choices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.como.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Randal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-14T08:48:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-14T08:48:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I agree this is a very interesting article!  I notice an (intentional?) lack of coverage of most of the dominant and mature decision-making institutions in our society: markets in general (and specifically institutions such as exchanges -- mentioned briefly -- auctions, fixed-price retail stores vs. haggling bazaars, and so on), risk sharing institutions (e.g. insurance), hierarchical organizations based on the employer-employee and boss-subordinate relationships, the judiciary based on written law, opinion, and precedent, and so on.  Of course, it would be very ambitious to tackle these, but it would at least be interesting to try to categorize them according to your taxonomy.  Perhaps they are so complex they often fall into multiple categories.
The systems you describe abstract a vast amount of diffuse and often tacit information pertinent to a decision into a numerical result. Most economists (particularly Austrian school) would argue that at least on a large scale prices generated by auctions and exchanges generally do this better than other collective decision making systems.  On the other hand, many systems for collective choice don&#39;t work via an abstract numerical intermediary (e.g. the opinion and precedent system of the judiciary).
I suggest that the most important factor in these institutions is the costs involved in eliciting diffuse knowledge and lossily compressing it into a decision which is hopefully nevertheless a reasonably accurate reflection of that diffuse information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://unenumerated.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;nick szabo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-15T11:49:05-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-15T11:49:05-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;At least part of the reason why I didn&#39;t strongly highlight markets is that the definition of &#34;collective choice&#34;, at least as far as how many academics use it, is all the methods that groups make decisions EXCEPT markets. For instance, from http://www.bsos.umd.edu/umccc/ &#34;models of individual rational choice behavior to study non-market social phenomena&#34;.
However, another definition is http://www.artsci.wustl.edu/~polisci/calvert/PolSci505/ &#34;social choice theory and noncooperative game theory&#34;, and I might say that markets fall into a subset of noncooperative game theory.
Personally I&#39;m not sure why most academics exclude markets, thus I do briefly mention the Stock Market as a subcategory of comparison system. I hope to mention them more in other future articles, in particular, prediction markets as a subcategory of Polling Systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-15T12:20:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-15T12:20:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Will you cover, in a future post the forced choice vote? I&#39;d welcome learning about more ways that a group can discuss alternatives (online or in person) then either vote in a priority way (first choice, second choice, etc.)
and/ or choose to vote in a first round for &#34;x&#34; number of options then limit the conversation to those options, then perhaps do a forced choice vote.
In other words what are some hybrid methods that you
(amazing) Christopher might craft that combine:
A. Thoughtful conversation to hear all ideas/opinions -
without the downsides of :
 being prolonged to the point it pains participants
and/or
 being dominated by one or two &#34;strong&#34; or verbose personalities
.....with
B. Stages of voting closure that enable all participants
to see &#39;we&#39; are moving to the top choice(s) of the group
- another fan of life with alacrity
p.s. In addition to the aforementioned, brilliant, The Paradox of Choice, read Smart Choices by Howard Raiffa
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typekey.com/kareanderson/&#34;&gt;Kare&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-12-30T13:37:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-12-30T13:37:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>