<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Itunes on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/itunes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Itunes on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 08:49:14 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/itunes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using 5-Star Rating Systems</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 08:49:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt; I discuss ratings scales of various sorts, from eBay&#39;s 3-point scale to RPGnet&#39;s double 5-point scale, and BoardGame Geek&#39;s 10-point scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=373,height=239,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/stars_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/stars_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Stars_1&#34; alt=&#34;Stars_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the various ratings scales, 5-point scales are probably the most common on the Internet. You can find them not just in my own RPGnet, but also on Amazon, Netflix, and iTunes, as well as many other sites and services. Unfortunately 5-point rating scales also face many challenges in their use, and different studies suggest different flaws with this particular methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sloan.ucr.edu/category/working-papers/product-reviews/&#34;&gt;one study&lt;/a&gt; using Amazon data has shown that many &lt;em&gt;undetailed&lt;/em&gt; ratings (where the rater isn&#39;t required to add any additional information other than the rating they select) show a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bimodal_distribution&#34;&gt;bimodal distribution&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; In other words the distribution of ratings tends to cluster around two different numbers (e.g., 1 and 5) rather than offering a normal distribution where the ratings cluster around a single height (e.g., 3). Thus the median of these ratings is not an accurate reflection of product quality, but instead is a statement of conflicting opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;our own study&lt;/a&gt; using RPGnet data has shown that many &lt;em&gt;detailed&lt;/em&gt; ratings (where the rater does add additional information, in this case a full review) offer normal distributions, however it is biased toward the high end of the scale. On RPGnet, for example, we discovered that 90% of this 5-point rating system was 3 or higher with an average around 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://360.yahoo.com/profile-9lciejI3aafX1stHPoIRNmkmv4EowQ--&#34;&gt;Randy Farmer&lt;/a&gt; of Yahoo suggests that this scale limitation is particularly troublesome for fan-based ratings, such as those found on episodic TV sites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Only the fans of a show evaluate the episodes, and being fans, will never rate an episode one or two stars, ever. I&#39;ve seen this attempted over and over on the net with the same results every time: Each episode of a show is 4-stars +/- .5 stars. This goes all the way back to the Babylon-5 website, probably the first source for this kind of data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And indeed, the TV episode &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tv.com/babylon-5/tko/episode/25148/summary.html?tag=ep_list;title;14&#34;&gt;TKO&lt;/a&gt;, from &lt;em&gt;Babylon 5&lt;/em&gt;&#39;s first season, is considered an entirely atrocious episode by even the fans. Yet it has a 6.1 of 10 &amp;quot;Fair&amp;quot; rating on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tv.com&#34;&gt;tv.com&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus even when a bimodal distribution is not a problem, on a 5-point scale the upward bias often results in only 2 or 3 meaningful data points. This is problematic because it minimizes differentiation. In many cases, a 5-star rating system where most of the ratings are either 3 or 4 is actually no better then just a thumbs-up/thumbs-down rating system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, given that 5-point scales are probably here to stay, we are forced to make the best use of them we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we need to provide raters with &lt;em&gt;incentives&lt;/em&gt;, so that they provide meaningful ratings. We&#39;ve already seen that this can be done by requesting detailed ratings: when a person takes the time to write text, and knows that his name will be attached to it, he generally does a better job in his rating. There are other possible incentives techniques as well, such as RPGnet&#39;s new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_191.phtml&#34;&gt;XP System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we need to provide means for a 5-point scale to become more meaningful by encouraging raters to use not just the top half of the scale, but the bottom half as well. One method to accomplish this is to make ratings &lt;em&gt;distinct&lt;/em&gt; -- as I briefly mentioned in my previous article on this topic -- and encourage standards so that an &amp;quot;average&amp;quot; rating is 2 or 3, not 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of how to accomplish both of these goals with already existing 5-point rating scales, I&#39;ve detailed my own experiences with using ratings on two popular services -- iTunes and Amazon. By providing myself with incentives and making my use of ratings very distinctive, I have created more meaningful and useful output for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Music Ratings - iTunes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple&#39;s iTunes software offers you the ability to rate individual songs with a 0-5 Star rating. If you use iTunes with an iPod, you can change the rating of a song on your iPod and the change will be reflected in your iTunes database the next time you sync your iPod. The &amp;quot;Shuffle Songs&amp;quot; feature available on more modern iPods has an option to have songs with higher ratings be played more often. A very powerful feature, Smart Playlists, can dynamically create sophisticated playlists based on ratings. All of this makes rating music on iTunes very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Shannon and I wrote our Rating Systems article, I examined the ratings in my iTunes catalog. Using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://girtby.net/archives/2005/11/03/itunes-library-preening/&#34;&gt;Alastair&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; fabulous XLST &lt;a href=&#34;http://girtby.net/offerings/itunes-ratings-stats/&#34;&gt;iTunes rating statistics tool&lt;/a&gt;, I discovered that the ratings I created in iTunes clearly were biased overly high, matching the pattern we&#39;d described. I had far too many songs rated with 4 Stars, and almost nothing rated 1 or 2. This made my ratings less useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&#34;6&#34;&gt;Here are some statistics from your iTunes Library: 4172 tracks, 412 (10%) rated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;Cumulative % of Rated&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;% of rated&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Actual&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Target&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Shortfall&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 5 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;112&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-22&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 4 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;183&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-57&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 3 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-44&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 2 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 1 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So over the last few months I&#39;ve completely revamped my iTunes ratings. Since I can&#39;t change the user interface, I&#39;ve changed my behavior. I&#39;m also taking advantage of two other fields: &amp;quot;checked&amp;quot; which I use to give more distinctiveness to my ratings, and &amp;quot;play count&amp;quot; which shows whether or not I&#39;ve listened to something through to the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the criteria I used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 5 - Exemplars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_5_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_5_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_5_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Only my most favorite songs are rated 5. They have to meet the following criteria: they make me feel good or excite me no matter how often I listen to them, I can typically listen to them often without getting tired of them, and they are the best of their particular genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 4 - Great &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_4_checked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_4_checked&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_4_checked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; There is only a small difference between a song that is rated 4 and 5 in my ratings -- typically it doesn&#39;t excite me or make me smile quite as much, or it isn&#39;t necessarily an exemplar of its genre. However, I still can typically listen to them often without getting tired of them. Items that are rated 4 and 5 are ones that I carry on my iPod Shuffle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 4 - Great (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_4_unchecked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_4_unchecked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_4_unchecked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; There are a few songs that I do consider to be great, but that I only want to play when I&#39;m in the mood for them, or I want to only play in a specific order, or they &amp;quot;don&#39;t play well&amp;quot; with other music. For instance I love the song &amp;quot;The Highwayman&amp;quot; by Loreena McKennitt, however, it is over 10 minutes long and I just don&#39;t want to hear that type of song unless I&#39;m in the mood for it. Other examples are the 12 songs that make up Mussorgsky&#39;s &amp;quot;Pictures at an Exhibition&amp;quot;&amp;nbsp; -- I want them played in order when I do play them, and I really don&#39;t want them played in the middle of my other songs. Unfortunately, iTunes does not let you select only unchecked items, so I don&#39;t have a Smart Playlist for these; instead I keep them in a regular playlist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 3 - Good &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_3_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_3_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_3_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are songs I like. Typically I can play them regularly but not too often. Songs rated 3-5 go on my iPod Nano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 3 - Good (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_3_unchecked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_3_unchecked&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_3_unchecked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; There is a lot of music that I think is Good, but I don&#39;t want to play all the time. I have a large catalog of sound tracks from movies. All but a few of those tracks are in this category. Again, iTunes does not let you select only unchecked items in a Smart Playlist, so I have several regular playlists for these items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 2 - Ok &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_2_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_2_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_2_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; I have very diverse musical tastes, starting with jazz, various ethnic and world music, and also including quite a bit of pop, rap, R&amp;amp;B, punk, and metal that I enjoy. I don&#39;t enjoy them all the time -- but I do like them to pop up every once in a while for variety. So I rate these 2 and leave them checked. I have an old 40GB iPod that I take on long trips, and it stores everything I have that is checked and rated 2-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 2 - Ok (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_2_unchecked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_2_unchecked&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_2_unchecked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Some songs are OK, but I really have to be in the mood specifically for that song. Listening to Jimmy Buffet&#39;s &amp;quot;Margaritaville&amp;quot; can be a guilty pleasure on a lazy summer day at the beach, but it isn&#39;t something I want to regularly listen to. I have a number of special playlists for songs rated like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 1 - Don&#39;t Like &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_1_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_1_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_1_checked&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are the songs that I don&#39;t like. They&#39;re just not my style. Many are still quality music, they just doesn&#39;t work for me. I do keep most of these for completeness -- it might just be one or two songs on the album, and I want to keep the album complete. Or I keep it in case my tastes change. But in general, once something is rate 1 Star, I&#39;ll probably never listen to it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rated 1 - Trash (Unchecked) &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_1_unchecked&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_1_unchecked&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_1_unchecked.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are songs that not only do I not like, they just are not good music. I don&#39;t like most rap music, but I can tell that most are still quality. Some are junk -- these I rate 1 and uncheck, and are candidates for deletion the next time I purge my collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unrated &amp;amp; Listened &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_0_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; /&gt;, playcount &amp;gt; 0:&lt;/strong&gt; If I&#39;ve listened to something through to the end, but haven&#39;t rated it yet, it shows up in this Smart Playlist. Periodically I check this Smart Playlist, sort by playcount, and try to rate everything that I&#39;ve listened to more then once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unrated &amp;amp; Unlistened &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/myrating_0_checked.png&#34; title=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; alt=&#34;Myrating_0_checked&#34; /&gt;, play count=0:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the default when a new song is added to my library. So any song that is unrated, checked, and has a play count of 0 shows up in my &amp;quot;Unrated &amp;amp; Unlistened&amp;quot; Smart Playlist. When I&#39;m in the mood for variety, I go through this playlist and rate songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modifying my rating system in this way has caused my average rating for music to change from around 4 to somewhere between 2 and 3. It will probably, over time, become closer to 2 as I rate more of my collection. This gives me a lot of distinctiveness so that I can create Smart Playlists that work well for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&#34;6&#34;&gt;Here are some statistics from your iTunes Library: 6519 tracks, 726 (11%) rated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&#34;3&#34;&gt;Cumulative % of Rated&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;% of rated&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Actual&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Target&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Shortfall&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 5 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 4 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;144&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-15&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 3 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;211&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 2 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;270&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks rated 1 stars:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously rating a large music collection can become a chore -- you don&#39;t want to spend your limited music listening time always fine tuning your ratings. So I have some approaches that make it easier for me to rate my music with less effort:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, I sorted my catalog by my old ratings, and modified everything down by 1, Starting with everything rated 2 becoming 1, 3 becoming 2, etc. This gave me a good base to start with&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/exemplar_smart_playlist.png&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=512,height=216,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;84&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Exemplar_smart_playlist&#34; title=&#34;Exemplar_smart_playlist&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/exemplar_smart_playlist.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Next I created Smart Playlists for each rating, i.e. &amp;quot;Rating 5 - Exemplar&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;Match only checked songs&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Live updating&amp;quot; checked. I then added &amp;quot;Play Count&amp;quot; as a column to my view, and sorted by it. This gave me the songs that I played the most and least, and I adjusted some songs up and down accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist.png&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=512,height=241,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;94&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist&#34; title=&#34;Plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/plays_well_with_others_smart_playlist.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Then I created a new Smart Playlist that simply plays songs rated 3 to 5, limiting the list to the first 100 GB selected by random (i.e. everything random), and saved this Smart Playlist as &amp;quot;Plays Well With Others&amp;quot;. I play this on occasion in the background, and when I hear something that jars me I know something isn&#39;t rated right. Thus without a lot of effort I can change ratings for songs that no longer fit their rating, or uncheck items where the rating was appropriate but it &amp;quot;didn&#39;t play well with others&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I try to be aware when I&#39;m using my iPod of what a songs rating is, and change it if it seems wrong. The next time I sync the iPod my ratings will be adjusted in my iTunes catalog.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/play_count.png&#34; title=&#34;Play_count&#34; alt=&#34;Play_count&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;I also try to be aware of Play Count -- this number only goes up if you play a song to the end. So even if I&#39;m not able to take a look at the rating (for instance when I&#39;m in a car), I can at least forward to the next song. Periodically I review the play counts for songs that I&#39;ve rated and consider moving them up and down accordingly. Of course, this means that I have to be careful and not let the iPod keep running when I&#39;m not listening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tip for those of you that do put a lot of effort into your iTunes ratings: I&#39;ve learned the hard way that unlike most song information, the rating is &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; stored in the song itself, so if your iTunes database gets corrupted, or you move your music to another server, you&#39;ll lose all your ratings. One way to avoid this is to periodically backup your ratings into a field that is stored in the song itself. I personally use the &amp;quot;Grouping&amp;quot; field as it is rarely used, select all songs with the same rating and click on &amp;quot;Get Info&amp;quot;, and change the Grouping field to &amp;quot;My Rating: 5 Stars&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only have 11% of my collection rated so far, but using this system I&#39;m finding it a lot easier to manage my ratings. I&#39;m already getting many benefits from it -- I&#39;m playing my music more often, my iPods typically have the music I want on them, and various music discovery services can use my ratings to help me identify new music I might enjoy. This provides the &lt;em&gt;incentive&lt;/em&gt; to keep me entering meaningful ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Book Ratings - Amazon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon also uses a 5-Star rating system, and your ratings can be used by Amazon to help you find books that you might like. Though I like to support my local bookstores, it is this feature that brings me back to Amazon time and again. Whenever I browse through Amazon and see a book I&#39;ve already read I try to take the time to update my rating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon has a number of different tools to assist you in your ratings. If you are an Amazon customer, you can go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/yourstore/iyr/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;collection=owned&#34;&gt;Improve Your Recommendations: Edit Items You Own&lt;/a&gt; and see all the books that you&#39;ve purchased and quickly rate them with a nice AJAX interface. You can also review items that you&#39;ve already rated, whether or not you own them, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/yourstore/iyr/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;collection=rated&#34;&gt;Improve Your Recommendations: Edit Items You&#39;ve Rated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=509,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/amazon_your_media_library.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;159&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/amazon_your_media_library.png&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_your_media_library&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_your_media_library&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Amazon has also recently added a very nice web service called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/library/&#34;&gt;Your Media Library&lt;/a&gt; that can be used to help manage your media library of books, music, and dvds. I personally only have used it to manage my books and dvds, as I find rating albums useless -- it is songs that I prefer to rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After browsing through my ratings to date, I discovered the same flaws I found iTunes -- my ratings typically were too high; most were a 4. This is particularly encouraged by the popup when your cursor is over the Stars &amp;quot;1 - I hate it, 2 - I don&#39;t like it, 3 - It&#39;s Ok, 4 - I like it, and 5 - I love it&amp;quot;. I suspect if I use the same trick that I use for iTunes of making a rating of 2 Stars mean &amp;quot;Ok&amp;quot; I could potentially cause the recommendation engine to be less effective (though it could possibly make it better, I don&#39;t know). So I am being much more brutal with my ratings and pushing many more down to 3, so that my ratings of 4 and 5 have more meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/amazon_5_star.png&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_5_star&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_5_star&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These have to be the exemplars -- the best books I&#39;ve ever read, would be glad to read again, would be proud to show off on my best bookshelf, and will buy extra copies to give to friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_4_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_4_star&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/amazon_4_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These have to be really good books -- most of them I&#39;m willing to read again and I promote them by offering to loan them to my more discriminating friends. Although I may keep them on my bookshelf I&#39;d rather give them to a friend then sell them at a used book store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_3_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_3_star&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/amazon_3_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; These are books are decent books, and I do share them with my voracious reader friends. But I don&#39;t push them and I&#39;m much more likely to sell them at a used bookstore then keep them on my shelf. This is the rating that I significantly underused previously, and I&#39;m finding that the key discriminator for me so far is how much I feel like recommending this to friends who are more discriminating readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_2_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_2_star&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/amazon_2_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; This rating is where the Amazon rating system fails the most -- these are suppost to be books that &amp;quot;I don&#39;t like&amp;quot;, however, most of the time I don&#39;t buy books that I probably wouldn&#39;t like, much less read them, so I have very few in this category. However, I&#39;ve decided this category is for books that are just not quite good enough, or are slightly disappointing. Not bad, or disliked, but just somewhat disappointing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 Stars &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Amazon_1_star&#34; title=&#34;Amazon_1_star&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/amazon_1_star.png&#34; /&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; This is where I put the books that I don&#39;t like, or worse, I hate. Not many here, but I&#39;m willing to risk more then many people are so I have some. Also books go here that just don&#39;t fit my interest, like romance novels that get recommended to me because I like some crossover fantasy-romance authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I started more accurately rating my books at Amazon, I&#39;ve found that their suggestions for other books to read to be more accurate. Thus I am getting value from rating these books, and I have &lt;em&gt;incentive&lt;/em&gt; to continue to make the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering an incentive for people to rate is important for ratings of all sorts, with both individual gain and status recognition being powerful motivators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the easiest technique for making a 5-point rating scale more useful is to make it &amp;quot;distinct&amp;quot;. If a user has a more specific meaning for each rating, ratings will slowly settle toward a truer average, and thus more of each rating scale will be used. We&#39;ve also tried this technique recently on RPGnet, with our new &lt;a href=&#34;http://index.rpg.net/&#34;&gt;Gaming Index&lt;/a&gt;; and thus far our new 10-point scale -- which has distinct meanings for each number -- is averaging &lt;a href=&#34;http://index.rpg.net/browse.phtml?count=50&amp;amp;type=Best&amp;amp;productCategory=Entries&#34;&gt;7.27&lt;/a&gt;. That&#39;s still a fair amount above the real average of 5.5, but at least it&#39;s below the 8+ rating that our old double 5-point scale resulted in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often you, as a consumer of rating systems, will be making use of rating scales designed by others, rather than those you&#39;re designing yourself. For those cases it often makes sense to design your own rules for what each number means, and to do so in such a way that your median is the average of the scale, rather than toward one of the extremes. When you do, even if you&#39;re using a tight 5-point scale you&#39;ll end up with enough differentiation for it to actually be more meaningful than a thumbs up or a thumbs down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34;&gt;2006-01: Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;See
http://web.archive.org/web/20010207224515/http://people.delphi.com/mike100000/p5summary.html#summary (or click my name below) for a summary of all the votes for the B5 Series.
Averaging all episodes you get a mean score of 8.19 with a standard deviation of 0.84 - a *very* narrow range.
Context and Motivation matter more than scale in getting reusable scores out of rating systems. As I like to tell the folks here at Yahoo! – the person creating the rating has to get something out of the transaction other than just altruism.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20010207224515/http://people.delphi.com/mike100000/p5summary.html#summary&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-08-11T09:49:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-08-11T09:49:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I thought the issue, like Randy Farmer suggests, was that only positive discrete scales always tend to their maximum.  The problem then in rating systems, like you mentioned I think earlier, is that readers have to interpret what the real norm and limits are.  Even if every rating is in the upper quartile.  You may want to check out what I did in Playerep (http://www.playerep.com), where the rating system is based on election but not a fixed scale (always norming to zero without influence).   FWIW. Thanks.
Adam
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://tidehorion.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Adam MacDonald&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-08-11T10:21:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-08-11T10:21:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I like your classification scheme for iTunes. I&#39;m going to have to work on adapting my scale (which is definitely showing signs of skewing towards the high end).
One thing, though. You mention that you can&#39;t create smart playlists to show unchecked songs. It&#39;s true that you can&#39;t do it with only one playlist, but you can do so with 2:
#1) Any playlist (for example, let&#39;s say your smart playlist for 4 star, checked songs, so you have it set (I assume) for My Rating = 4, Match Only Checked Songs = checked)
#2) Use these criteria:  My Rating = 4, Playlist Is Not &lt;playlist #1&gt;. Leave match only checked songs unchecked, and enable live updating and you have a smart playlist that shows you your unchecked 4-star songs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Andy Tinkham&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-08-16T13:55:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-08-16T13:55:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
&gt;&gt;Unfortunately, iTunes does not let you select only unchecked items, so I don&#39;t have a Smart Playlist for these; instead I keep them in a regular playlist.
You can:
Make a smart playlist called &#39;Checked&#39; with a rule that is always true (e.g. artist does not contain (leave the field emtpy), or bitrate &gt; 0). Create a smart playlist called &#39;Unchecked&#39; with the rule: &#39;Playlist is not Checked&#39;. There you have all your unchecked files.
From there you can make smart ones that use this Unchecked playlist.
I like your rating system. I have 40% on a 3star now, and around 25% for 2 and 4 stars. I might scale it down a little bit more.
hmm, after typing this I read the comments and see Adam McDonald already mentioned something similar about the unchecked items. I&#39;ll leave it here anyway...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Tino&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-10-16T11:52:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-10-16T11:52:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Christopher, I think some, if not all, of the issues with the 5-point rating system could be addressed with a better UI. For example, displaying a normal distribution curve skewed by accumulated rating to nudge raters away from the extremes. Of course, this doesn&#39;t work well if sample size is too small which usually happens on the far end of the long tail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/&#34;&gt;Don Park&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-12-17T18:25:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-12-17T18:25:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Thanks for writing this article. I found another view on 5 point music rating other than my own informational.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Jonathan&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-06T00:33:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-06T00:33:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple, AirVideo, and Immersive vs Ambient Media</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/05/airvideo_and_im.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2005 12:25:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/05/airvideo_and_im.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reading on &lt;a href=&#34;http://slashdot.org/&#34;&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt; a discussion about &lt;a href=&#34;http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/05/10/0235212&#34;&gt;iTune 4.8&lt;/a&gt; and its new capability to purchase videos from the iTunes Music Store, when I read two things that just made me say &amp;quot;duh&amp;quot; with their obviousness, yet I&#39;d never thought of them before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these &amp;quot;duh&amp;quot; moments were inspired by the comments by an anonymous Apple engineer with the handle &lt;a href=&#34;http://slashdot.org/~As%20Seen%20On%20TV&#34;&gt;As Seen on TV&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everybody&#39;s wrong about the video iPod thing. A video iPod would be a dumb idea for lots of reasons, some technical, some psychological. If you want to know where we&#39;re going with video playback, look not to the iPod but to its considerably less famous little brother, AirPort Express.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;He didn&#39;t explain himself further, but I grokked it immediately. The current &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/airportexpress/&#34;&gt;Airport Express&lt;/a&gt; already offers digital output of audio in a feature called &amp;quot;AirTunes&amp;quot;. It isn&#39;t much of a stretch to believe that they could add the capability to offer video. If they added a dedicated H.264/MPEG4 decoder chip to the Airport Express, you could just plug in an HD-capable monitor and offer internet delivery of video and movies. The bandwidth wouldn&#39;t be an issue, as you are talking only 2 Mbps for the most popular HD compressed format, and even the full resolution 1080i compressed only requires 8-9 Mbps -- all of which will fit amply the bandwidth available to 802.11g. Thus &amp;quot;AirVideo&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;As Seen on TV&amp;quot; continues with more insights on Apple&#39;s strategy:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And the iPod is not repeat not gonna say it one more time not meant to be a video-playback device. It’s not even remotely designed for it. The iPod has a tiny hard drive that’s designed for embedded applications, and a 32 MB (I think it is) RAM buffer cache that’s optimized for dealing with song-sized chunks of data. That’s about 4 MB. Even a half hour of HD content is gonna be half a gigabyte. There’s basically no way for the iPod to play that without constantly keeping the hard drive running, and that will burn out the drive very quickly. Seriously, under constant use, the iPod hard drives’ life spans are measured in tens of hours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(How can we do photos, then? Easy. Photos are even smaller than songs. And unlike video, people often do want to carry photos around with them. Keep reading.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember when I said the problem was part technology and part psychology? People like to listen to music while they do other things: Ride on the train, exercise, shop. People like to multi-task with their music.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video, whether short-form like TV or long-form like movies, isn’t like that. Video is an immersive experience. You sit down and you watch it, and you don’t do anything else until it’s over. That’s a totally different interaction model than music.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So there’s basically zero reason for video to be portable. You’re not going to carry it around with you. You’re going to watch it at home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exceptions? Sure. But Apple isn’t a company that makes a habit of marketing to the exceptions. We shoot for a pretty clearly defined target market and let the exceptions buy their gadgets somewhere else. Chiefly because there aren’t nearly enough exceptions out there to make it worth going after, financially speaking. We’d never be able to recover what we invest in R&amp;amp;D and design by selling a few hundred thousand units. We have to sell millions of units per quarter, otherwise the business plan just doesn’t work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This all made sense, but it this comment that brought it home: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All you have to do is pay attention to the way people interact with their media. The difference between immersive media and ambient media jump out at you immediately.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d guess never really understood intuitively the concept that there are really two major media types: ambient and immersive. Now that I understand it, it seems obvious. I just never internalized the difference. Yes, sometimes TV is an ambient media, sometimes music is immersive, but only rarely. As I think about it more it makes me wonder about other types of ambient vs immersive media, such as games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll close with more last quote from &amp;quot;As Seen on TV&amp;quot;: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I know you’re going to say I’m being a dick here, but I’m going to give you the pure, unvarnished truth: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neither Apple’s management nor Apple’s shareholders give a shit about what the “alpha geeks” think. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I know, I know. It’s harsh. But it’s absolutely true. See, the “alpha geeks” are not our market. We don’t sell to them. The “alpha geeks” are defined by one key characteristic: they’re irrational. Now, I’m not trying to insult you. I mean it literally. Geeks are not rational. They base their purchasing decisions on things that, from a rational point of view, just don’t make any sense. Things like politics, lack “openness,” like “customizability.” Things that just don’t add up in the cost-benefit analysis. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That’s fine. That’s totally legitimate. But it’s not our business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We sell products to people who want them to work. We don’t sell products to people who want to take them apart. There are other companies that do that. We don’t seek to dominate them or to put them out of business. We don’t see them as competition at all, because the kinds of people who buy our products would never buy a motherboard. They’d never buy Linux. Never in a million years. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there some overlap? Sure. We love the fact that some prominent hard-core geeks use Macs. But we’re not going to abandon our business plan to woo them. We’re not going to turn our backs on the vast and untapped market for next-generation content delivery services, a market which we basically created, in order to please some Internet message board guys. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Again, I’m sorry for sounding so harsh here. I don’t mean to be rude. I’m just not going to sugar-coat it for you. You do your thing, whatever makes you happy. We’ll do ours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Very well put. I&#39;d never thought about it that way before - but it makes a lot of sense. Wireless video.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.newathens.org&#34;&gt;Trevor&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T20:20:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T20:20:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
the ambient and immersive stuff is very similar, if not the same as, some of mcluhan&#39;s theories on media
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T20:33:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T20:33:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Simpsons Did It!
...errr... I mean... Sony. x2 read...
exhibit A) The Location Free Television - http://www.sonystyle.com/is-bin/INTERSHOP.enfinity/eCS/Store/en/-/USD/SY_DisplayProductInformation-Start?ProductSKU=LFX5&amp;Dept=tvvideo&amp;CategoryName=tv_LocationFreeTVs
exhibit B) Media Roomlink - Which was an older product as well.. http://www.sonystyle.com/is-bin/INTERSHOP.enfinity/eCS/Store/en/-/USD/SY_DisplayProductInformation-Start?CategoryName=acc_PCAccessories_roomlink&amp;ProductSKU=VGPMR100U&amp;INT=sstyle-cpu_accessories-catpfeature-VGPMR100U
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.existence2.com/&#34;&gt;Dranore&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T20:47:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T20:47:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The &#34;ambient vs immersive&#34; stuff is not new - it was what Steve Jobs called &#34;background vs foreground activity&#34;, a point he made when called to comment on the possibility of video iPods, about a year ago or so.
(That said, this is an important and useful rule.)
As for this paragraph:
&#34;And the iPod is not repeat not gonna say it one more time not meant to be a video-playback device. It’s not even remotely designed for it. The iPod has a tiny hard drive that’s designed for embedded applications, and a 32 MB (I think it is) RAM buffer cache that’s optimized for dealing with song-sized chunks of data. That’s about 4 MB. Even a half hour of HD content is gonna be half a gigabyte. There’s basically no way for the iPod to play that without constantly keeping the hard drive running, and that will burn out the drive very quickly. Seriously, under constant use, the iPod hard drives’ life spans are measured in tens of hours.&#34;
Disclosures:
1. I couldn&#39;t care less about a video iPod at the moment
2. I don&#39;t think these have a chance of success as it is
But, that said, why&#39;s he mentioning HD along with the iPod? Do I *have* to view the videos on my iPod in my HD format? What&#39;s wrong with compressed/lossy formats?
Do you *have* to listen to your tunes in uncompressed (WAV/AIFF) format when using your iPod?
Sure, we won&#39;t achieve tiny filesizes when compressing video, but we won&#39;t be near HD-territory either.
If you take this under consideration, this argument of his carries much less weight.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://kostas.yoink.com/&#34;&gt;Konstantinos&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T21:18:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T21:18:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve not purchased one, but now I&#39;m quite curious about the level of movie immersiveness when using the Sony PSP http://www.us.playstation.com/psp.aspx -- Sony is reportedly going to be offering 70+ movies for the PSP. If the experience is sufficiently immersive, then maybe that is the form factor for a &#34;video iPod&#34;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-10T23:00:16-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-10T23:00:16-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
ok, let´s put two and two together then. see here:
http://www.macobserver.com/article/2005/05/10.18.shtml
and then you know: instead of vidpod, think vidpad. this also explains why the first h.264 videos (consider them test videos) are being run through itunes (not iphoto) - it&#39;s well integrated with airport...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Philip R&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T00:01:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T00:01:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You don&#39;t have to watch videos on your videom iPod in HD, but files compressed down to iPod file size (&lt; 10Mb) are going to be really, really crappy for any non-trivial piece.
I watched an iTMS video in small size and frankly, it was a chore.
One thing interested me:
&#34;We sell products to people who want them to work.&#34;
Hm. Apple certainly sells iPods to people who want them to work. I reckon there&#39;s a large percentage of Mac owners who are power users, as compared to Wintel PCs and iPods (even ignoring the business space - we&#39;re just talking consumers here).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://pauldwaite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Small Paul&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T02:29:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T02:29:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Apple also tends to put images of products its pushing in the itunes installer, and this revision happened to feature airport express, at least for me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Gnubardt&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T12:59:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T12:59:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It&#39;s pretty obvious that regardless of what they call it Apple will offer a portable video player at SOME point in the future.
Do people want to watch video content on the go?  Other technology companies sure think so.  Even cell phones are starting to be able to display low-res video.  Sprint just launched a new campaign for NBC to go, etc.
And now the PSP brings high-quality video on the go in a small package.
I watch videos on my Palm Tungsten more than I do on my laptop due to its portability.  I can compress PVRed video from the night before while I&#39;m in the shower and watch the shows on my Palm while I&#39;m on the train.  I&#39;d love to have something that was a little more robust in terms of video decompression (i.e. with a dedicated hardware GPU that could decompress Divx on the fly) and Palm&#39;s new &#34;Lifedrive&#34; 4Gb model will work pretty well for my needs, I think, but a 100Gb video iPod would be even better if they could dedicate hardware to video encoding/decoding.
HD is still years away from a portable because the small screen resolutions are still pretty low.  The PSP seems about the best portable video has to offer at this time, but there are other portable media center devices that also work well.
And the sales of those little portable DVD players with screens are through the roof.
So Apple can&#39;t be blind to the fact that people do want video on the go.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://jough.com&#34;&gt;Jough Dempsey&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T13:10:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T13:10:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Portable video has a mass appeal and not just to alpha geeks, but the ambient/immersive distinction does make sense.
Would also be nice if it had better games them pong!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://timewarp-tshirts.com&#34;&gt;Timewarp&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-11T23:18:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-11T23:18:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Whether Apple will choose to go there in the near future, I don&#39;t know, but as for this statement:
&#34;You sit down and you watch it, and you don’t do anything else until it’s over. That’s a totally different interaction model than music.&#34;
I think this is a little short sited, all told.
The reason we have that model is that we&#39;ve never had portable video devices. There are already ways to extract information from our environments with digital cameras [1], why should we assume there will be no new applications of portable video?
[1] http://www.hpl.hp.com/news/2004/apr-jun/beyond_film.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ruphus.com/blog&#34;&gt;Patrick Hall&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-12T20:34:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-12T20:34:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I hope this blog does not mind I &#39;ve a put an extended post at http://blog.startup.gr/blog/_archives/2005/9/10/1214941.html
which can serve as a comment on this post.
Have a look
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.startup.gr&#34;&gt;startup&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-09-10T04:30:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-09-10T04:30:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/05/airvideo_and_im.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>