<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>orkut on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/orkut/</link>
    <description>Recent content in orkut on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2004 02:00:51 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/orkut/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Four Kinds of Privacy</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2004 02:00:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been thinking about the nature of privacy a lot lately.
I&#39;ve long been associated with issues of preserving privacy. I helped with anti-Clipper Chip activism in the early 90s and supported various efforts to free cryptography such as PGP and other tools built with RSAREF from export control. However, my efforts in these areas wasn&#39;t really focused on privacy -- instead my focus was on issues of trust.
I&#39;ve always tried to be precise here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Advice to Social Networking Services</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2004 11:39:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</guid>
      <description>I have now had CEOs of three different social networks send me emails asking me to compare Orkut to their service. I&#39;ve not had a chance to dig deeply into good answers for each specific one, but I did have some general advice that I wanted to offer given my recent experiences with Orkut.com, and my evaluation and followup on various social networking services in December.
Privacy First, be extremely careful about privacy issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 17:12:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/confirmed_email.html</guid>
      <description>Another Orkut user and I have confirmed a privacy hole in Orkut whenever you send a message to someone via Orkut.
For instance, whenever I send a message to anyone in the system that is forwarded by email, in the message headers it will read:
 From: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;member@orkut.com&amp;gt; Reply-To: &#34;Christopher Allen&#34; &amp;lt;christophera@alacritymanagement.com; When someone reads the message in their email software, the &#34;From:&#34; line will be my name but the fake email of &amp;lt;member@orkut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Followup on Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 13:21:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/02/followup_on_ork.html</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve read of emails, Orkut messages, and blog postings since my post yesterday, so I thought I would share some with you.
There have been a number of good posts, as well as user comments at Danah Boyd&#39;s blog Apophenia.
Danah Boyd writes Correcting Marc Canter&#39;s Perception of My Views
Marc - i don&#39;t believe that users should take these relationships more seriously; i believe that YOU should. Users will do whatever they damn well please, and i think that we should learn from them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insecurity at Orkut</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2004 13:58:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</guid>
      <description>Like many others, I&#39;ve been paying attention to Orkut in the last couple of weeks. I&#39;ve answered more requests to be &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut then I have of any of the other half-dozen Social Networking Services I&#39;ve tried, and I&#39;ve looking at other people&#39;s friends to see if I know anyone. I&#39;ve yet to ask someone to join Orkut that wasn&#39;t already a member, and I&#39;ve been careful to not have anyone as a &amp;quot;friend&amp;quot; that I didn&#39;t know reasonably well and I thought knew me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
