<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Friends on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/friends/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Friends on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2005 15:05:50 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/friends/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2005 15:05:50 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/ryzeblogtribefriends.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=579,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;181&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Ryzeblogtribefriends&#34; title=&#34;Ryzeblogtribefriends&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/ryzeblogtribefriends.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who now has over 171 professional &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot; in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;LinkedIn Profile&lt;/a&gt;, 198 &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=2789681602836776519&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt;, many more non-intersecting friends and acquaintances on&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cluster.tribe.net/tribe/servlet/template/pub,pcard,PeopleCard.vm?personid=ce34093a-3c72-4954-b52f-3d6bc51884af&#34;&gt;Tribe.Net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/users/christophera_/&#34;&gt;LiveJournal&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://socialsoftware.weblogsinc.com/sns-meta-list/&#34;&gt;other social networking services&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a plethora of correspondents that I only interact with via email, I am trying reconcile a mismatch between my connections and my own &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venture Capitalist &lt;a href=&#34;http://sapventures.typepad.com/main/2004/02/quality_or_quan.html&#34;&gt;Jeff Nolan&lt;/a&gt; relates similar concerns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
&amp;quot;It strikes me that the social networking theory holds that the more volume you have, the bigger your network will become by introducing degrees of separation roughly along the lines of Metcalfe&#39;s Law. I disagree, human networks do not grow in value by multiplying, but rather by reduction. For me, it&#39;s the quality of relationships that enhances my professional and personal life, not the sheer numbers.&amp;quot;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately social networking services -- be it LinkedIn, Tribe.Net, Orkut, or LiveJournal -- are making the problem worse, not solving it. Any engineer or information theorist can tell you that a system that only has amplifiers will be out of balance, and that you need attenuators in the system as well. Our current breed of social networking services have focused on amplifying our contacts not only because it serves us, but because it serves them. The more contacts that you make, the more people they potentially have in their service. However, in the long run this is unsustainable -- a social networking service also has to be useful -- merely amplifying your contacts isn&#39;t enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the problem becomes not just one unique to me, where my friends network is overextended, but rather one that&#39;s endemic to the current generation of social networking services. In order to solve it we need to look at the traditional cultural answers to the problem, compare them to technical solutions, both current and to-be-invented, and then see how a new generation of social networking services can be designed that molds the two ideas together into a more cohesive whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offer here the beginning of that discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Cultural Strategies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of overextended social networks are not new with the Internet generation. Many professions require maintaining a large base of relationships and have done so for hundreds of years, among them: politicians, salespeople, public company CEOs, and even professions that you might not think of requiring these skills such as family doctors. The Dunbar Number of 150 may be a kind of species-wide average limit, it is not an individual limit -- thus my guess is that people with an innate talent for maintaining more relationships are attracted to these professions. But even with innate talent those who follow these professions can be overwhelmed, and each have found different cultural strategies for managing larger numbers of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Spending More Time:&lt;/strong&gt; Some people just spend a lot more time keeping up with their connections. Politicians and salespeople are classic examples of professions that require significant schmoozing time in order to keep trusted connections together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does someone like a member of the US House of Representatives manage their relationships? In no way can they even come close to having a relationship with all the 645,952 people they represent. They would, however, at least have to keep up at some level with the other 435 House members, their own staff, key members of the staff of other House members, as well as key politicians and contacts back home. From what I&#39;ve read, successful politicians spend most of their days just meeting with people, and have staff dedicated to &amp;quot;tickling&amp;quot; -- keeping track of constituents, schedules, issues, etc. and reminding the politician before each meeting of the essentials they need to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of this strategy is twofold -- the time spent managing relationships can&#39;t be spent elsewhere, and the quantity of relationships lowers the quality of those relationships. For instance, my experience with most politicians and many salesperson is that I will be forgotten as soon as I leave the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Changing the Standard:&lt;/strong&gt; There are different cultural standards in each profession as to what is an acceptable relationship. Thus some people chooose a profession that manages relationships in different ways. Doctors are a good example of socializers who fit into this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your family doctor has a similar problem to that of politicians -- too many people to keep track of. Yet a good family practitioner can see you and look beyond just today&#39;s symptoms. Thus because of an ongoing relationship with you he can be a better doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way the doctor does this is through cultural and professional limits. Because of the authority, status and title granted to doctors, patients tend to defer to them. There is not an expectation that the relationship is equal. This allows the doctor to have a &#39;shallower&#39; relationship with the patient that is still acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, even this level of serial, shallow socialization can be excessive for many people. A Radiologist acquaintance of mine told me the reason why she ended up in her specialty was that she just couldn&#39;t handle the ongoing patient relationships required by other specialities -- instead, she now looks at one set of images at a time, performs a diagnosis, and doesn&#39;t have to retain any relationship to move on to the next patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also problems with changing your socialization standards. Unless it is culturally understood, or your standard is reciprocated by others, it can make you appear shallow and not trustworthy. I&#39;ve seen this when someone moves from one profession to another, say a salesperson to a manager -- styles of relationships that were acceptable among salesperson and between salespeople and customers are not quite as acceptable as those between managers and their staff. Another example is when someone moves from the East Coast to the West Coast, where the usefulness of casual alumni connections is significantly less valued, but those casual connections are unable to understand the change in standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Prioritization:&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps a more common cultural strategy for managing excessive relationships is prioritization. I could prioritize my relationships and focus only on the 100+ or so that might be the most useful to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two problems with prioritizing. First, analyses of social networks show that it is often the weak and most unrelated links that can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/context/1333462/0&#34;&gt;the most important&lt;/a&gt;. Thus any attempt to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triage&#34;&gt;triage&lt;/a&gt; may cut off some of these weak ties because I thought that the links might not be &amp;quot;useful&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, how do you tell someone &amp;quot;I&#39;m sorry, but I&#39;m overly Dunbarred, so I have removed you from my list.&amp;quot; Rejection is painful (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csudh.edu/dearhabermas/mripain01.htm&#34;&gt;MRI brain studies&lt;/a&gt; have actually shown), so I risk offending people forever by excluding them today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Technological Solutions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great hopes of social networking services is to improve the ways that we interact with other people, particularly those that we know at a distance -- the &amp;quot;weak links&amp;quot;. Right now, these services are part of the problem because they offer out-of-balance social systems. However, they can also be part of the solution; science-fiction writers and social software designers alike are starting to look at these issues and offer new solutions that would not have been possible before the advent of widespread software communication systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technological Solution - Augmentation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/geodesica.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Geodesica&#34; alt=&#34;Geodesica&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;I recently read in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0441012698/qid=1107286515/sr=8-1/ref=skotos_20/102-0974708-1794504?v=glance&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;n=507846&#34;&gt;Geodesica: Ascent&lt;/a&gt;, a new science fiction novel by Sean Williams and Shane Dix, a futurist example of augmentation as a method of maintaining extended social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0441012698/qid=1107286515/sr=8-1/ref=skotos_20/102-0974708-1794504?v=glance&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;n=507846&#34;&gt;Geodesica: Ascent&lt;/a&gt; the protagonist, &amp;quot;Melilah&amp;quot; is a politician in the distant future. She has her own problems with the Dunbar Number, and solves it with her own personalized social networking service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two things she had learned from her political career were that society depended on interpersonal relationship networks, and that everything could turn on a simple misidentification. In her fifties she had set about ensuring that her memory remained in good working order in order to avoid the latter. Anthropologists had known since the twentieth century that people were born with a ceiling on their social groups. Once Melilah exceeded the Dunbar and Hill number of 150, and rapidly acquiring still more associates, it became progressively harder to keep track of everyone she had to know. As she passed her hundredth birthday, it became only worse. Some of her contemporaries option for cortical grafts and other memory prosthetics. She, motivated by a gut-level -- some would say irrational -- desire to keep her body as free of technology as possible, opted for other means.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She had found that using a name once every two months was enough to keep her memory fresh. Any longer than that between reminders, and the associations faded, rendering recall unreliable. So she programmed a complete list of her occasional acquaintances and enemies into a database and programmed it to cycle through them ever sixty days, shuffling the order each time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A hundred years on, she was still in the habit of skimming fifty or so names a day, just to keep on the ball. By flicking through the images, voice files, place names, and more obtuse clues, she felt confident of recognizing any of the several thousand people more or less likely to interact with her at any point in the near future. The list had grown and shrunk down over the years, and many people had dropped off it entirely because of death or distance. Sometimes she added names to the list only to be surprised that they had been on it once before, decades ago, and she had forgotten them completely. That only reinforced the need for the list and the effort to keep it fresh in her mind.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure that the Dunbar Number problem is solely one of &amp;quot;recognition&amp;quot;, as illustrated by Williams and Dix. However, I think this is a great example of seeing how a traditional cultural solution to network overextension (namely, &amp;quot;Spending More Time&amp;quot;) can be better applied by Social Software. In this example Melilah&#39;s software automates the &amp;quot;ticklers&amp;quot; that politicians use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/photos/uncategorized/spokekeepintouchsettings.gif&#34; title=&#34;Spokekeepintouchsettings&#34; alt=&#34;Spokekeepintouchsettings&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;Already at least one social networking service has adopted a somewhat similar idea.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://center.spoke.com/person/personalProfileTab.spoke?id=[serverID=center,ID=4877427]&#34;&gt;Spoke&lt;/a&gt; has a &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; setting. The Spoke client software will watch your Outlook mailbox and addressbook to see how often you contact various people, and if you don&#39;t email them or modify your address book entry for them periodically, will remind you that you should contact them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve never used Spoke&#39;s &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; feature -- largely for privacy reasons (I was &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html&#34;&gt;stung by a Zero Degrees&lt;/a&gt; Outlook extension), but also because Spoke seemed to be oriented toward salespeople and thus emphasized growing the network. My problem is not growing my network, but managing the network I already have more effectively. But I may have to take another look at Spoke. So, it doesn&#39;t quite offer the same solution that Melilah used in the far-future, but it&#39;s still a start upon that path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions and Questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not certain that Spoke&#39;s &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; feature, or Melilah&#39;s social recognition reminder service are the full solution to the &amp;quot;Dunbar Triage&amp;quot; problem. However, they do at least offer a few examples of people looking at the problems, and how social software can help solve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;ve outlined here there are at least three traditional methods&amp;nbsp; that we&#39;ve used to manage Dunbar Triage prior to advent of social networking services: spending more time, changing standards, and prioritization. The technological solutions that I&#39;ve offered up as an example concentrates upon the first of those cultural solutions, but it is by no means a conclusive statement on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could next-generation social networking services improve upon the ideas of changing standards or prioritization? Could simple categorization help improve expectations for attention levels that various associates receive from you? Are there ways that social networking services, acting as an intermediary, could better manage disappointment-inducing events, such as a decision to spend less attention on an associate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More so, could social software offer solutions that aren&#39;t even being considered right now? For example, many Cyberpunk novels have suggested the ideas of avatars that can collect information for you on the &#39;net while your attention is elsewhere. Could these avatars likewise maintain more distant social networks for you, without your full attention? Would that function even be desirable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some solutions are not technological -- what new skills and changes to practices, etiquette and ethics are required for our ever expanding network of relationships? Or as &lt;a href=&#34;http://alevin.com/weblog/&#34;&gt;Adina&lt;/a&gt; asks: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Who will offer us a 21st century, internet-augmented take on Dale Carnegie and Emily Post?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any problem in the developing technical world, the first step is to define the problem and to consider possible solutions. Here&#39;s the start: social networks can become too large, and many social networking services are causing the problem rather than solving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s your solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000219.html&#34; alt=&#34;gapingvoid blog, by hugh&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/zzzmkghilkj38.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Too Many Friends, by hugh, from gapingvoid blog&#34; alt=&#34;Too Many Friends, by hugh, from gapingvoid blog&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;(comic illustration from the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000219.html&#34;&gt;gapingvoid&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000823.html&#34;&gt;hugh&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think the politicians and sales people use another strategy - they pretend that they keep up with the connections, but in fact they don&#39;t.
That&#39;s why they have the people to keep them informed about people they are going to meet. They don&#39;t remember the people but they use techniques to impress them that they do. And that is why we don&#39;t like them.
YASNS let us all switch into the politician networking mode.
For some time I have beed thinking that Huminity which bases the networking on IM buddy lists is a step in the direction of making SNS more balanced, since it bases the networking on the most scarce Internet resource - user attention.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://zby.aster.net.pl&#34;&gt;Zbigniew Lukasiak&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T03:21:13-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T03:21:13-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Nice post. A few random thoughts:
This seems analogous to what happens when people move from rural communities with relatively sparse social options to the city.
Another prioritization scheme is to emphasize face to face relationships, or to distinguish between real-time and non-realtime relationships. These are not always appropriate filters, but because getting f2f or talking realtime requires a special effort, I&#39;ve found these approaches can help me gauge whether a relationship is maintainable.
The older system of etiquette, which separated personal from professional relationships, is another approach, though when I hear the words &#34;I don&#39;t do business with friends,&#34; it means someone neither a friend nor a business associate.
Perhaps there are some other frames for looking at this, e.g. time management or attention management, or as another instance of the Tyranny of Choice.  Approaching the problem as one of more choice in who we pick to be our friends and associates, or as one of more demand on us from others also colors our choice of solutions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.archival.tv&#34;&gt;Jeff Ubois&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T12:03:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T12:03:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;One way of putting the brakes on endlessly expanding contact lists is to have the SNS site charge per contact. If you really need more than 100 contacts then you&#39;d pay for them, but if not then when you&#39;ve got another 1 person you want to add to your list you&#39;d consider dropping one off your current list. It might work better with per-contact charges, so you&#39;re not forced into making a decision when you hit the package borders (101, 201, etc)
Not only does it counter the pack-rat mentality, but it also provides a business model.
Another idea I had was if the SNS would provide me with a continuous feed of updates and changes in the profiles of my contacts - I occasionally notice that some contact of mine has changed jobs, but more likely I wouldn&#39;t notice. The list of contacts just sit there, passive. This feedback would provide two forces: (1) the memory refreshing effect, and (2) the opportunity to drop those contacts that are moving into areas I don&#39;t care for.
A third idea: I&#39;d like it if the SNS I use (LinkedIn) allowed me to attach some notes or tags to each contact in my list ... I have a few there where I have to think really hard just how I happen to know them. Right now it seems that every SNS I look at lets me make connections, but every connection is bland and generic. The system is relying on me remembering why I know that person, when instead it could remember it for me.
When it comes time to triage, I&#39;d really like it if the SNS would provide a simple network map for me. Show me my immediate contacts, any connections they have amongst themselves, and my second circle contacts (anonymised if necessary). This way at least I can see that Person X is a gatekeeper to a whole different community from all my other contacts, and so should reconsider dropping them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://IAwiki.net/&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T18:44:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T18:44:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid has the right idea... but his number of 100 is still too high.
His last paragraph is golden.  When I first joined RYZE  in 2002 [ no longer an active member] I mapped out my 1 and 2 step network there.  In the diagram linked below I am the green node, my immediate neighbors are in blue and my two step contacts are in grey.
The network map reveals why Eric&#39;s 100 number is too high...
http://www.orgnet.com/RYZE2a.gif
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orgnet.com&#34;&gt;Valdis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T10:02:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T10:02:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This, and the earlier article on Dunbar numbers are interesting reading.  I&#39;m not sure whether the Dunbar number applies in all cases.
In some discussion on SNs recently, I theorised that if we analysed Social Networks that there would be people who maintained relationships in Groups, i.e meshes where everyone knows everyone.  Bridging between groups occurs because of multiple membership, i.e. person X knows all the parents in their kids soccer club, AND all the people at the office.  Dunbars number, and the theories around it, seem to apply here, i.e. to the social-grooming required in GROUPS.
There would also be people who maintain relationships, between a lot of people who mostly do NOT know each other. We used to call these people Networkers, and typically they are the people you call when you want to know who to talk to about some topic where you have no personal connections.  I&#39;m not sure whether the Dunbar number applies to those people&#39;s connections, probably the power-law applies better, i.e. they can maintain progressively more distant connections with progressively more people.
Anecdotal, if you randomly pick people in for example Orkut then you&#39;ll see the same names turn up as intermediates in many cases. This is not necessarily because those people have large numbers of Orkut friends, but because their Orkut friends are dispersed over a range of sub-groups.
I don&#39;t think that any of the SN tools do a good job of managing these kinds of relationships yet, in particular the lack of interworking between them causes problems as different Groups tend to belong to different SN systems, so the bridges are often not evident. Also the relative strength of a connection doesn&#39;t seem to drive the ranking of possible connections, i.e. I&#39;m just as likely to be presented with a potential introduction through a person with a weak connection to the target, than through someone with a strong connection.
- Mitra
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.mitra.biz/blog&#34;&gt;Mitra&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T15:40:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T15:40:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;On tactic that comes to mind is the automated equivalent of an 18th/19th century butler, who mediated social interaction at a time when the intrusive, in-person visit was one of only two ways to make social contact.
The butler has broad and nuanced knowledged of the circumstances in which the Lady is to be acknowledged to be IN.
Today&#39;s online presence indicators are flat; they tell everyone the same message; that one is working, or eating ice cream in front of the television.
A butler would understand whether one is working or not, and would put through different connections at different hours.
A butler would understand the understand the nuances of one&#39;s social circle, and admit some people automatically, allowing others to wait, and requiring still others to leave a message.
We also need the 18th/19th century interface to the Butler, the calling card, which conveys by its printed message and accompanying whether the caller is a longlost relative whom the butler may not remember; a recommendation from a reputable source; a specific message about the urgency of the visit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/weblog&#34;&gt;Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-06T08:42:20-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-06T08:42:20-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think that the key to defeating the Dunbar number is to a) establish a real relationship to begin with and b) massage that relationship at least once per year.
I find that if I&#39;ve built a meaningful relationship with someone, based on some shared experiences, simply getting in touch with someone once a year on their birthday is enough to keep the relationship alive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://chrisyeh.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Chris Yeh&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T06:25:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T06:25:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You&#39;ve got to distinguish between &#34;friends&#34; and everything else - the relationships that range across acquaintance, association, colleague and just plain &#34;potentially useful.&#34; Why treat them all with the same UI? Why not invite your true friends to share a more intimate online relationship and keep the rest in the &#34;relationship parking lot&#34; of an Orkut? Yeah, I know that friends are often useful, too, but they deserve better than to share the same utilitarian role as that guy you met at SXSW last year.
I&#39;ll invite my real friends into my Grouper hangout, but I&#39;m not a Congressional Rep, so I don&#39;t need to be responsible to hundreds of familiar names. I&#39;ve got plenty of other things to do with my time, which I believe is the case with most of us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.socialchemy.com&#34;&gt;Cliff Figallo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T15:53:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T15:53:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi, Crhis. Three years&#39; ago Adrian Scott asked this question too, and it led to his founding Ryze...
from: http://www.edge.org/q2002/q_scott.html
Edge.org&#39;s Question Page of 2002 - by Adrian Scott.
******
&#34;How do we scale up the number of quality human relationships one person can sustain by many orders of magnitude? In an increasingly connected world, how does one person interact with a hundred thousand, a million or even a billion people?&#34;
Our one fixed resource is time — human attention. As we become increasingly networked in the technological sense, we also become more networked in the social sense.
As our social networks scale up, we move more and more of our interactions to the technological sphere. We can have many more telephone interactions than we can have hand-written letter interactions. When we move from telephone to e mail, the number of interactions between people goes up even more dramatically.
Then we pair our e-mail interactions with a personal Web site, and we start moving our personalities into the technology net, as a way of automating and scaling up the number of relationships even further.
We end up with personal CRM systems to handle our increased interaction load, and then add interfaces from our technology net to our human forms. These interfaces will develop from current-day Palm Pilots and Blackberry&#39;s to heads-up display style interfaces in glasses and eventually retinal and neuronal interfaces.
&#34;Hi Jerry, Ahh.., we met back in 1989, May 14th at 7pm, and since then we&#39;ve exchanged 187 e-mails and 39 phone calls. I hope your cousin&#39;s daughter Gina had a wonderful graduation yesterday.&#34;
The whole range of interactions becomes organized. Introductions from one person to another, and rating systems become automated.
Currently many people run into barriers as their personal networks approach the range of thousands of people. Soon they will move to the tens of thousands, to the millions and beyond.
With these trends, the friction costs of personal introductions go down, and consequently the value of quality measurement and gatekeeping go up dramatically. As the depth of knowledge in a relationship increases, the threshold point at which you &#39;really know someone&#39; increases also. It&#39;s an arms race of intimacy.
Adrian Scott is founder of Ryze, a business networking community. He is a founding investor in Napster, got his Ph.D. in nonlinear optimization at age 20, and has sung with Placido Domingo and performed with the NYC Ballet.
*****
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://dijest.com/dontblog/&#34;&gt;Phil Wolff&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T20:12:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T20:12:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
An Avatar? Maybe that&#39;s what I&#39;m doing. I look at life as a whole. Coincidences (for lack of a non-cliched word) are road signs helping us determine a direction of movement (not necessarily in the physical realm).
I&#39;m working on a software module which links coincidental interaction within Nature and published human consciousness. Currently I&#39;m modeling Climate Change.
For my software to ultimately work within a social network, a persons daily life of data would be connected via an identifier - and freely available. Too, an aspect of human momentum would need to change dramatically - we would trust that life is a whole and not something to be mastered, assimilated, conquered. We would need to move to a much less mechanical decentralized world. And our user base would need to be decreased.
Which coincidentally, Climate Change is forcing upon us. And it&#39;s ramping up.
Google, with all the tools I need (email, blog, webpages, and soon a social network site) seemed like a potential opportunity. They never responded to my email :)
My profile is lost within LinkedIn...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;michael white&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-20T10:05:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-20T10:05:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Learning by Subtraction
The human brain has on half the number of synapses at age six as it had at age two. It learns by subtraction. So do computer based neural nets.
This principle could well be applied to organizations to increase the size of the Dunbar number that could work effectively without drowning in bureaucracy.
Consider three ways to bring order in a human organization. The chain of command, community spirit and marketplace choice.
The chain of command tends to keep demanding ever more connections. You must get permission from all these people before taking action. The free intraprise systems we set up (See The Intelligent Organization by Gifford &amp; Elizabeth Pinchot and link at the end of this post) allow people to connect and disconnect at the end of each contract at will. Teams contract with line officers and each other to get the work done, much like a virtual organization except that key competencies and trade secrets remain in the organization.
Relationships that create value are maintained; those that consume value are terminated by either party. This provides a powerful advantage over the innane connections that are often maintained in highly time consuming ways in a bureaucracy.
The force of community also has a self-organizing quality that allows people to volunteer for what has juice and walk away from relationships that consume purpose and meaning. Community is a necessary balance to free enterprise or free intraprise. Both should be used in place of the chain of command in many of the situations where the chain of command is used today.
http://www.pinchot.com/MainPages/BooksArticles/InnovationIntraprenuring/FreeIntraprise.html
http://www.pinchot.com/MainPages/BooksArticles/OtherArticles/GiftEconomy.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.bgiedu.org&#34;&gt;Gifford Pinchot&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-23T22:43:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-23T22:43:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Adina: Getting in touch once a year may keep a relationship alive, but only just. This begs the question, what do you want from your relationships? What do you value them for? What is the point in keeping a relationship on drip-feed attention when putting so little in precludes the possibility of growth, of enrichment, of greater intimacy, of learning something, of sharing the experience of life in some way.
Perhaps what we&#39;ll see, with or without the help of clever internet applications, is a polarisation: a small circle of close friends, a very wide circle of friendly acquaintances (whether social, professional, shared interest, discussion group, blog reader, etc, by origin), and an almost infinite range of potential one-off contacts. Along the lines Chris Reh is suggesting, I think.
I&#39;m not sure I need to know which of my friendly acquaintances are in touch with one another. Better just to get on and live, and concentrate on putting something into those relationships, the better to get something out of them.
Or have I missed the point?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://thiswayplease.com/extra.html&#34;&gt;Fred&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-30T21:48:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-30T21:48:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Fred, is there someone in your household who sends birthday cards and holiday cards? These are traditional tools for staying minimally in touch. They don&#39;t maintain intimacy, but they do keep an open door, so that it&#39;s easier to keep the benefits of weak ties, and regain contact when the time is right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/weblog&#34;&gt;Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-09T13:26:17-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-09T13:26:17-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I just had a minor realization: when we speak of &#34;dropping&#34; someone from our personal network, are we really doing that? The fact is, they are very probably connected to other people we do know, and so what we are really doing is *delegating* the intimate relationship to someone we also know. Being able to see a map of my local network would help a lot in deciding whether to cut someone loose or not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://IAwiki.net/&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-07-30T01:53:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-07-30T01:53:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Advice to Social Networking Services</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2004 11:39:47 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have now had CEOs of three different social networks send me emails asking me to compare Orkut to their service. I&#39;ve not had a chance to dig deeply into good answers for each specific one, but I did have some general advice that I wanted to offer given my &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34;&gt;recent experiences with Orkut.com&lt;/a&gt;, and my &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html&#34;&gt;evaluation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2003/12/followup_to_eva.html&#34;&gt;followup&lt;/a&gt; on various social networking services in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Privacy&lt;/h4&gt;
First, be extremely careful about privacy issues. For some of you outside the US, you may not know about what has been going on in the area of identity theft, but it has become a significant problem. I am not a privacy fanatic, but I am concerned that social networking services encourage people to reveal too much information too broadly, and that this will be someday be taken advantage of by identity thieves. For instance, many services ask for birthday and reveal it to everyone. You can ask for the birthday, but don&#39;t display it -- give the person&#39;s age, or birth month, but don&#39;t give the full info. I personally am particularly wary of billing address, billing zip code, birthday, and potential common security questions like name of pet, mother&#39;s maiden name, etc. These are in addition to the obvious targets of identity theft like SSN, full name, and account numbers.
&lt;p&gt;Orkut&#39;s interface for selectively allowing some fields to be visible &#34;only to myself&#34;, &#34;to friends&#34;, or to &#34;friends of friends&#34; is nice, but I wish it was for all fields. I also think every field by default should be set to &#34;only to myself&#34;. In fact, all security parameters should default to reveal the least information, and have the tightest limits -- allow the user to open selectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are going to support all different kinds of social networks (dating, friendships, activities, business) consider finding ways to make sure that those people who are not using the service for dating are not asked for that info, and don&#39;t see it for others who are dating. People who are only using it for dating shouldn&#39;t see business info. If someone is using a service for all types of relationships, allow people to selectively set what they reveal to each group, say two columns of &#34;only to connections who are dating&#34; or &#34;only to business connections&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never reveal someone&#39;s email address or other critical information without them knowing about it. In particular there are issues with emails sent among members. The only safe way is to do redirection through your site (although that will cost you bandwidth.) But if you can&#39;t do that, then just tell people &#34;your email will be revealed if you do this&#34; -- that is enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard on your TOS and Privacy terms. Don&#39;t let your lawyers rule you here too much -- find some way to get your principles out there and still cover yourself against problems. Make all the personal information that people give you be their information -- they are only leasing it to you temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make it easy for someone to quit the system. Maybe offer to them to export their information in case they want to rejoin later, and give them an opportunity to send a last message to any connections they may have. Be friendly at all times, and as the market shakes out they may come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Connections &amp; Invites&lt;/h4&gt;
If possible, find some other way to call the connections between people &#34;friends&#34; -- maybe even use a unique trademarkable term. There is some power in the emotions behind the word friends that helps with the virus-like nature of social networking software, but I think in the long term it is a bad idea. LinkedIn and Spoke use the word connections which sounds too mechanical, but I think it is better then &#34;friends&#34;.
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t encourage the &#34;how many friends do my friends have&#34; game. It sets up bad behaviors, and as you grow you don&#39;t want to have barriers of entry to new people who feel that they can&#39;t compete in that game. This means don&#39;t sort friends or groups etc. by the number of friends they have by default -- it can be an option, but just not be default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t encourage people to by default upload their address book. Have that feature be off of some optional utility page. Have the default option for it to just scan for people that are already members of your system and to forget the rest -- that is effectively what I do with systems that ask for address book information, and they make it hard for me to do so. Don&#39;t store people&#39;s address information for them unless you can sync them with people&#39;s personal contact books -- save that for version 2.0, not 1.0 beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t focus on people contacting new people that are not already their connections. It is not the number of connections, but the quality. Instead, focus on helping people with their weak connections. It is &#39;reconnection&#39; that is the most powerful feature of these social network services, not new connections. You can also help with &#34;triage&#34; -- how do I maximize the value of my existing weak connections with the least effort?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow people to opt-out with a custom message. What this means is that if someone sends an email to someone who has opted out, they will get something like. &#34;Thanks for inviting me to Orkut -- I&#39;ve decided for now not to join, but you can find me on Tribe.&#34; However, keep a list of people who have tried to connect to that opted-out user, and if that user does change their mind later, it will make it easier for them to have an initial list of friends that may already be on the service. Yes, I know that this risks sending people to other services, but there are so many now that you can get good buzz by doing the right thing, and recovering those people later when they have confidence in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to have better methods of handling invites from unknowns without saying no. For instance &#34;I&#39;m not sure I know you, have I forgotten?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related, don&#39;t fill out default text for invitations and other request forms -- force people to put something personal into the request, don&#39;t allow it to be blank. Never do what Orkut does and not give the opportunity to offer text when you invite someone who is already on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid anything beyond friends of friends as a primary part of your service. It bugs me that I see by default 3 degrees away in many services -- 2 degrees should be max by default, as that is the level that real referral can work. 3 degrees is too far for users to trust (though it can be optional for some purposes, or useful internally.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=6080f857- 4784-4679-8e41-c6881ed933ce&#34;&gt;Friendship Circle&lt;/a&gt; may also be a good idea, though perhaps how you classify people should be private. You may mark someone as being &#34;family&#34; &#34;intimate&#34; or &#34;acquaintance&#34; or &#34;business&#34;, or whatever, however, no one else should see that; they should just see &#34;connection&#34; unless they have named you, and you in turn should not say that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Profiles&lt;/h4&gt;
Find some better way then simple lists to do profiles. Someone&#39;s profile needs to express the richness of who they are -- it also needs to change and grow and flow over time, so make it easy for people to annotate and grow over time. Consider asking for only a few things at first, not make the process of filling out the profile feel daunting, then after each login prompt them to add one small thing that is useful based on how they used the service recently. For instance &#34;You have joined the AnyoneButBush2004 group -- do you want to enter information to share with others about your political interests?&#34;.
&lt;p&gt;Right now lots of people are experimenting on their blog sidebars how best to profile themselves -- learn from them. Look at hundreds of examples, look for patterns beyond the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow people to have multiple affiliations, whether they be work or play. I&#39;m a bad edge case personally, with too many hats to name, but almost everyone I know has at least two professional hats &#34;Sysadmin by day, Writer by night&#34;, &#34;Laywer on weekdays, Carpenter on weekends&#34; , as well as several affiliation hats &#34;Bay Area Costumer Guild president, member of League of Women Voters&#34;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now LinkedIn has the best looking professional profile, but it is still hard for some people to use. I like LinkedIn&#39;s use of multiple professional affiliations, however, I wish I could mark some as major or minor; for instance, there is a big difference between being an Advisor to MG Taylor and being CEO of Consensus. It also doesn&#39;t handle professional associations and lesser affiliations, much less non-professional affiliations and interests. Also, being able to arbitrarily order them would be nice, LinkedIn does it by date which can make for some confusing emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reputation &amp; Endorsements&lt;/h4&gt;
Be very careful of the design of rating systems and reputation systems. They are extremely difficult to design well, as they too often can be gamed, or fall into reciprocity such that they are meaningless. My personal advice is just don&#39;t do it at first -- save it for a 2.0 version of the product, not 1.0 beta. If you are going to do it now, really study it -- there is a lot of good academic research on issues of reputation. It can be hard to slog through but it is worth it. Offer a grant to Danah&#39;s school for them to do research for you on the topic.
&lt;p&gt;Endorsements are a best way of doing reputation for now. They is also is imperfect and vulnerable to reciprocity games, however, as least you can see if two people are playing that game just by looking at the endorser and endorsee. If you find too much reciprocity you can basically ignore both players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow endorsements at a more granular level. For instance, if you are offering dating and professional information, segregate the endorsements. Even more ideally, do like LinkedIn and allow endorsements of relatively small things in a profile, for instance &#34;I really enjoy Chris&#39; blog&#34; against the blog profile item, and &#34;I like what Chris says about the environment&#34; against my affiliation with a group. Consider allowing endorsements of groups: &#34;Of the three groups here on Wiki, I find this one fits me the best&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can afford it, consider hiring a game designer from the online game industry who understands behavior incentives in online games. If you can&#39;t, study it. Part of the reason why EverQuest is the largest MMPORG is because it incentivizes certain kinds of social behaviors. In fact, it could be considered to be a type of social network service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Launch &amp; Support&lt;/h4&gt;
Be careful with your beta launch -- a culture for a community forms in the first few weeks, and our experience from online games is that the nature of this culture can make or break a project. Find ways to encourage the kinds of behaviors you want, and discourage those that you don&#39;t.
&lt;p&gt;Be very careful of labeling people who are gaming your product in ways you don&#39;t like. Being in Orkut&#39;s &#39;jail&#39; is almost becoming a badge of honor. There is no reason why people who invite too many friends to join, submit too many posts to forums, or sends too many messages to friends of friends, should be put under the same label as those people who put child pornography up on your system and thus you&#39;ve banned them. Instead, slow down the overly active people, just say in advance &#34;If you invite this number of people, you may not invite more people for 24 hours, do you want to continue?&#34;, or &#34;If you invite this person, you must wait an hour before inviting another.&#34;, etc. Also, if you do lock people out of a feature, don&#39;t lock them out of all features, just the one that they are over-using. If someone gets locked out of lots of features at the same time, then they should be looked at for possibly banning, but not if they are doing just one thing -- you want to encourage their enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you give feedback to anyone that tries to be helpful, for instance in reporting a bug. Ideally public reports should be encouraged public (as this encourages other people to be helpful) but even private reports should be encouraged, and as promptly as possible including &#34;Thanks for taking time to write up this, we are logged this problem and hope to get to it as soon as we can given limited resources.&#34; Find other ways to give feedback, such as a weekly report, or a group developers blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create multiple stages for your beta, for instance &#34;profile features beta&#34;, &#34;group features beta&#34;, &#34;scaling beta&#34;, &#34;load beta&#34;, etc. Tell people in your beta what you want to hear about and not hear at each stage. As each stage ends, find some way to publically thank those who made the biggest difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set up a bug tracking system like TypePad has (like Bugzilla but hugely simpler to use). From help menu at the top you can click to post a new report, see all open reports, or see all closed reports. Every help page can have at the bottom to open a report on that topic. If anything goes wrong there (404, various system error messages, etc) you should give you an opportunity to open a report. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Features&lt;/h4&gt;
Figure out how to use RSS everywhere for input and output -- if Orkut or Tribe&#39;s group features supported RSS feeds, they could be very powerful competition to the hugely funded Friendster. Figure out how to use trackbacks with your system, and make them simpler for users. Make group bookmarks and other lists available as OPML. I&#39;m not a huge fan of FOAF yet, but figure out how to use it anyhow (and maybe vCards) until something better comes along, if nothing else but allow someone to import it and export it.
&lt;p&gt;My personal take is that if you can combine a substantial number of these &lt;br /&gt;
features, you could have a great product that gives the others a run for the &lt;br /&gt;
money:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Offering intentional groups (like Tribe and Orkut) is essential. It is Friendster&#39;s and LinkedIn&#39;s weakest link.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eVite/Meetup style invitations for both private functions (come to my birthday party), friend functions (anyone near 00301 want to have lunch Thursday?) and groups (Let&#39;s all meet for dinner next week to discuss this).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to import via RSS the recent items from my blog to my profile page&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional blogging-style home pages (FunChain &amp; Live Journal) for those who don&#39;t already have blogs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended family support as an explicit type of group, grandmother, mother, child in college&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Couples can be a form of a group also&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better ways to organize groups of groups&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better support for user-optional presence &#34;There are members of this group who are reading it right now who have said that they are available online to members to this group, 3 via Skype, 12 via AIM&#34;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.docuverse.com/blog/donpark/EntryViewPage.aspx?guid=94333937-ecd8-4d08-994d-7f4c96c523dd&#34;&gt;Permachat&lt;/a&gt; at a group level is an interesting idea. I hate that I can&#39;t see chat text before the point I logged in&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of group management support, for instance:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;ability to have multiple admins (eGroups, Live Journal)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group moderation (Slashdot, Kuro5hin, Advogato, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional group shared links (eGroups)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional group shared calendar (eGroups)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polling inside groups (no one that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invitation or approval of entry by different methods, such as by vote, by 1 reference from existing member, etc. (none that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to merge groups (none that I know of) &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wiki-style areas available for groups (no one that I know of)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine all the above with good innovative RSS and optionally Atom (FunChain, SocialText)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports the various blog submission APIs for blogs, wiki, and groups (none that I know of)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a great job for those who don&#39;t use RSS and those APIs to use email instead, including email submission (you can mail pages to a SocialText wiki)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to be federated, i.e. I could still use my existing blog (you just mirror it), RSS aggregation, my FOAF file could be synced, you sync with my addressbook at Yahoo, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Business Models&lt;/h4&gt;
Business models for social networking services is going to be one of the biggest issues. Even those social networking sites with lots of money behind them are going to have difficulty because there are so many.
&lt;p&gt;The paid subscriber model is probably dead until some of the VC funded startups go out of business. Advertising can be a good model, but be careful not to make it obtrusive -- remember, Google has made good money with very simple ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t have VC funding, find ways to co-opt partners -- build from the beginning support for Google AdSense and Adwords, Amazon APIs, etc. If you are small, consider federating with another company. Figure out what you can do to differentiate yourself from both your competitors and partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t be evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Me&lt;/h4&gt;
I am interested in getting more professionally involved with social software. I think we are still in Apple II days of social software -- we see the promise of things to come, but we are still typing in ALL CAPS. Given the overfunding in this field, my own ability to start a company as an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alacrityventures.com&#34;&gt;angel investor&lt;/a&gt; is insufficient, so I&#39;m looking to partner with others. I&#39;ve been involved with online communities, groupware, collaboration, and security for over 20 years. If you are interested in an executive in this area, see my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;profile on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Some notes:
a) On privacy -- the list of people who tried to reach you is two-edged,
you may want to point that out, because it gathers my list of friends,
and somebody else might come and get it, but it is pretty useful.
b) All these ideas and many others are good, and I have my own lists
of useful features,  but there&#39;s some huge feature creep and it will
be tough for the people doing this software to cherry pick.
c) I have notes in the orkut forum (I presume you posted this there)
about dealing with people you don&#39;t remember.  It doesn&#39;t work to force
me to send them a note saying &#34;where do I know you from?&#34; because if
you forgot them it&#39;s still embarassing.   You need to establish a principle
in advance that people doing an invite include where they know you from.
Unless they are intimate friends.
d) On dating/non-dating, I agree that we don&#39;t want to see that our
business associate is in an open marriage.  However I am not sure the
moded UI (you are either in biz mode or dating mode) will fly.  I had
big plans for such modes, on backburner for now.
A better idea would be to only show you dating info on people who are
potential dates.   Ie. if you are an M seeking F, you only see dating
info of F seeking Ms.  People want the serendipity of knowing, &#34;Oh, that
women I met at the conference is single and looking?&#34;
Best of all it doesn&#39;t require new UI.
The other big thing with Orkut is going to be the FoF spam.  The mail
volume must be limited some way.  We&#39;ve got many thousands of FoF it
seems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ideas.4brad.com&#34;&gt;Brad Templeton&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-03T14:24:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-03T14:24:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Good advice overall.  You might want to take a fast look at how phpbb does polls (re your &#34;polling inside groups&#34; note).  It&#39;s integrated into the comment posting interface so you can very quickly turn any entry into a poll, with a few simple options.
I&#39;d also be interested in seeing your comments on pay vs. free membership options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://web.media.mit.edu/~wex/&#34;&gt;Alan Wexelblat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-04T07:40:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-04T07:40:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Fantastic post, Christopher.  I&#39;ll never again claim you only flog Orkut; you&#39;re very fair and constructive with your observations, too!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ifindkarma.typepad.com/relax/&#34;&gt;Adam Rifkin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-07T13:38:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-07T13:38:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What do you think about the political applications of friendster-like sites?  Think how it helps solve the problems associated with the ghetto email petitions of the past, and how it could create a non-intrusive, viral fundraising medium.  Do you agree with me?
Given the multiple kinds of ways that people want to use social software (e.g., business networking, dating, politics), will there be specific sites for each kind of activity or will there be some sharing model?
Anyway, we&#39;re thinking about leveraging this trend and it would be helpful to get your thoughts as we consider build vs. partnering, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.e-thePeople.org&#34;&gt;Michael Weiksner&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-09T14:54:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-09T14:54:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;FriendBlend is another new social networking site you might want to take a look at - it combines match-making with blogs, moblogs, online photo sharing and a lot of the group features such as polling and quizes that you mention. Great post!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.friendblend.com&#34;&gt;David Jenness&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-20T18:04:23-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-20T18:04:23-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;another cool site to check out is for College &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.collegester.com&#34;&gt; Social Networking&lt;/a&gt; is http://www.collegester.com . Also a hip site for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lloydbankster.com&#34;&gt;Lloyd Banks&lt;/a&gt; is worth peaking at..... I&#39;ve seen the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bestnetsoftware.com&#34;&gt;Social Networking Software&lt;/a&gt; for sell at http://www.bestnetsoftware.com for those interested in starting their own social networking site or community!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.collegester.com&#34;&gt;Social Networking&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-09T07:42:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-09T07:42:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;my friend http://www.ryanleslie.com is planning a social networking site for musicians
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.tcgss.org&#34;&gt;ricky&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-21T10:50:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-21T10:50:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
http://www.egrupos.com/
is virtually unknown in the US but becoming very popular in Spain and Latin America, and they&#39;re becoming a trend-setter, integrating email groups (a la YahooGroup but perhaps even more customizable), social networking tools and online auctions. A weird combination that however it seems to be working ok so far.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Pepe B.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-15T12:01:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-15T12:01:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is kind of a neat personals site that&#39;s looking to add in social network functionality. Email through the site if you&#39;re interested in partnerships.
http://www.itsjustcoffee.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.itsjustcoffee.com&#34;&gt;ItsJustCoffee&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-12-03T16:48:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-12-03T16:48:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi...I put up a site dedicated to the social networking niche of gated online communities at
http://www.gatedonlinecommunities.com
Any comments on the subject are appreciated!
Thanks Marc
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.gatedonlinecommunities.com&#34;&gt;Marc L GatedOnlineCommunities.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-10-24T14:24:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-10-24T14:24:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Eerst Europa Doelstellingen: De Ci2i Verzekering (Ci2i) zal het nummer een gebrandmerkte pan Europese commoditized online verzekeringsmakelaar door 2010 zijn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.firsteuropa.nl&#34;&gt;Alice Mike&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-12-03T22:37:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-12-03T22:37:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for posting this your section about privacy is very useful. There are some issues regarding privacy and social networking sites that have not been addressed properly and may cause the downfall of social networking sites such as stalkers and identity fraudsters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://scribblesheet.co.uk/article/can_i_have_my_life_back_please&#34;&gt;Vince&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-27T14:15:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-27T14:15:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/02/my_advice_to_so.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insecurity at Orkut</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2004 13:58:38 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like many others, I&#39;ve been paying attention to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=2789681602836776519&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt; in the last couple of weeks. I&#39;ve answered more requests to be &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on Orkut then I have of any of the other half-dozen Social Networking Services I&#39;ve tried, and I&#39;ve looking at other people&#39;s friends to see if I know anyone. I&#39;ve yet to ask someone to join Orkut that wasn&#39;t already a member, and I&#39;ve been careful to not have anyone as a &amp;quot;friend&amp;quot; that I didn&#39;t know reasonably well and I thought knew me. Currently I have 68 Orkut &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot;, many more then I have on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, which I&#39;ve been using for several months and have 50 &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this activity on Orkut, I&#39;ve been reading a lot of blogs about other people&#39;s experiences on Orkut. In particular, I&#39;ve found Danah Boyd&#39;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/&#34;&gt;Apophenia&lt;/a&gt; a great source for thought on social networking services, so I&#39;ve got it near the top of my RSS aggregator. I&#39;d just read her rant &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/venting_my_contempt_for_orkut.html&#34;&gt;venting my contempt for Orkut&lt;/a&gt; when I saw a follow up post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/orkut_pissyness_round_2.html&#34;&gt;orkut pissyness round 2&lt;/a&gt; where I read:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wanna see a big phat privacy hole on Orkut? Go to messages. Click compose. Click &amp;quot;friends and friends of friends.&amp;quot; Click next. Copy &amp;amp; paste all of your friends and their friends&#39; email addresses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tested this out, and discovered she was correct, when I clicked &amp;quot;friends of friends&amp;quot; I got a long web page of names and email address. So I sent to this list I&#39;d generated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A serious security hole? Yep.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just was shown 1137 friend and friends of friends email address, including your email address. As reported by Zephoria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/01/30/orkut_pissyness_round_2.htm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got a lot of replies back like &amp;quot;What did you expect?&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;That is why I don&#39;t use my main email for Orkut&amp;quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got a reply from Orkut Buyukkokten via email:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Could you please send an email to your friends and friends of friends to tell them that there is no security hole?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked very hard to ensure that the privacy of our members is not compromised in any way. I don&#39;t want our members to get the wrong impression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would greatly appreaciate it if you could pass the following message to you friends (:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll only see the e-mail addresses of people who chose to share them with you: if you mark your email address as not to be shared with friends and friends of friends, they won&#39;t be able to get your address this way. If you look at the list of people it&#39;s addressed to, you&#39;ll see that some are listed without addresses (unless you&#39;ve got very permissive friends).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat abashed, I checked, and since the last time I&#39;d sent an email, the interface changed. I discovered that only 356 of 1137 of my friends of friends were actually allowing their email to be shown, and the rest now showed a &amp;quot;lock&amp;quot; icon next to their name. Of course, the first 100 or so on that list coincidentally allowed their emails to be shown, so I had assumed incorrectly that all had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I sent Orkut&#39;s reply out to my &amp;quot;friends of friends&amp;quot; and added links to my blog and this comment:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m still quite uncomfortable with privacy issues of Orkut.com at this time. I&#39;ve had to reveal more information then I&#39;m comfortable, and the software is too lax in letting me see other people&#39;s info, for instance &amp;quot;relationship status&amp;quot; when I&#39;ve marked myself as not interested in that. Maybe Orkut is just trying to be too much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sent an email back to Orkut saying that I&#39;d sent this email, then continued to get a lot of replies to my original email, and I discovered that I was now in Orkut &amp;quot;jail&amp;quot;. This meant that I could not send messages, could not add friends or groups, etc. No reason was given for why I was in jail. The only reason why I&#39;d seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.it/0100198/2004/01/29.html#a2216&#34;&gt;other people in jail&lt;/a&gt; was because they had added too many friends too fast. I had only 50+ friends at the time, so I knew that wasn&#39;t the reason. I could only assume the worse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m out of Orkut &amp;quot;jail&amp;quot; this morning, but I still don&#39;t have any explanation of why. I continued to get replies both in support of my concerns:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tend to agree with you. I&#39;ve learned more information than I expected about people. Also it&#39;s been a little odd to see people I know professionally on orkut, since I first conceptualized it as a social-friends service. (Then again, I&#39;ve found professors on Friendster, which is much more explicitly social, so perhaps I&#39;d better just accept that these people have lives.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think that Orkut&#39;s attempt to be all things to all people has helped it take off. I feel easier asking professional contacts to join orkut than I would for Friendster. It seems like less of a big deal to add someone to your orkut list rather than on another more focused service, as there is a level of plausible deniability as to intention. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as comments like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t want to be too harsh, but if perhaps you, and Danah, and Cory don&#39;t want to play then really no one is forcing you to play. But whining about things that you don&#39;t like is just, well, unseemly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took a break to think on why I responded so negatively when Orkut has the appearance of doing something wrong (first, the &#39;security hole&#39; that was a feature, and secondly the &#39;jail&#39;). Then it came to me:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&#39;m insecure about orkut.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the definitions of &#39;insecure&#39; are &lt;em&gt;not firm or firmly fixed; likely to fail or give way; lacking self-confidence or assurance; not safe from attack; lacking in security or safety; not financially safe or secure;&lt;/em&gt;. The one that fits me the best is &amp;quot;lacking self-confidence or assurance&amp;quot;. Why do I feel this way about Orkut?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess my insecurity started out at the very beginning. As it is in beta, you can&#39;t join Orkut, you have to be invited. This made the place seem &#39;exclusive&#39; and thus possibly safer. Yet right off it asks you some fairly personal questions: What is your relationship style? What is your sexual orientation? Who are you living with? What are your politics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I find out by looking at other people&#39;s information that this is all completely public. It isn&#39;t limited to just friends, or friends of friends, but instead is prominent. In fact, other then your name and how many &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; you have, your relationship style is the most prominent thing listed. Do I really want to know that my business acquaintance that I see only at technical conferences 2 or 3 times a year is in an open marriage? Or divorced? Or gay?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live in the Bay Area and I&#39;ve seen it all, and consider myself open and try to be consciously non-prejudiced. That&#39;s not to say that I&#39;m comfortable when I&#39;m hit on by another man, but for that matter, I&#39;m not that comfortable when I&#39;m hit on by a woman. The point is that I don&#39;t think about someone&#39;s sexual and personal choices when I interact with them. I don&#39;t care if you are gay, into S&amp;amp;M, or any other radical lifestyle. I don&#39;t care if your straight, chaste, and christian. What I do care about is your relationship to me -- if you feel that it is important to your identity to let me know, well that is between us. But I&#39;m not going to pry. I once had a male employee in my office that wore a dress to work -- I still don&#39;t know if he is gay or not. It didn&#39;t matter to me and he didn&#39;t tell me -- what mattered was that he was good employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This started my &#39;insecurity&#39; about Orkut. Later I read that you couldn&#39;t delete your pictures or profiles. This worried me. Then I read that the system was down because of a XML hack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Orkut came back after the hack, a new feature was added, fans and ratings. This made me yet even more uncomfortable. Did I really want to have to not say I was a fan of someone that said they were a fan of me? Wasn&#39;t endorsing someone a far better signifier of fan? What does Trustworthy mean? Cool? I refused to enter anything for Sexy. I worried if someone could see my ratings, or reverse socially engineer it, or hack it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus these insecurities of mine led me to think the worst and to post too quickly about the &amp;quot;Friends of Friends Security Hole&amp;quot; and still feel uncomfortable about why I was put in &amp;quot;jail&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I&#39;ve had no abuses of me by Orkut -- I&#39;ve had only two people ask me to be friends that I don&#39;t know, and so far I&#39;ve not been told that someone is my fan whom I&#39;m not willing to honestly say that I&#39;m a fan back. I&#39;ve even found some old friends that I&#39;d lost track of, which is exactly why I still &amp;quot;play&amp;quot; and not leave Orkut. I do believe that there may be something useful in these social network services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet I feel that my old blog entry &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2003/12/evaluating_soci.html&#34;&gt;Evaluating Social Network Services&lt;/a&gt; that concluded with my take on &lt;strong&gt;The Perfect Social Network Service&lt;/strong&gt; is still quite on track:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My ideal service would have the multiple professional affiliation features of LinkedIn, but also allow me to show non-professional affiliations. It would allow me to form intentional communities like Tribes.Net, but would also let me do a Wiki in addition to a message board. It would have meeting/party invite services like eVite, and blogging features like LiveJournal. It would have an endorsement system like LinkedIn integrated not only with professional endorsements, but personal endorsements as well, and you could even endorse intentional communities. It would let me better map and control my network, giving different friends different privileges. It would handle the release of my personal information like Ryze, but less clunky.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d add to that list that I&#39;d like to have more control over my information, in particular, relationship information. That I&#39;d like to see more &amp;quot;progressive disclosure&amp;quot; where there was more granularity of what was revealed at public, friends of friends, friends, fans, fans who I&#39;ve endorsed, etc. Finally, I&#39;d really not like to see things that are not applicable to me, such as relationship information of other people when I&#39;m not looking for relationships, or professional information of others if I&#39;m only using Orkut for dating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Update: another Orkut user and I found a different privacy hole when sending emails -- see &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/02/confirmed_email.html&#34;&gt;Confirmed Email Privacy Hole at Orkut&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The only reason why I&#39;d seen other people in jail was because they had added too many friends too fast.
There is no basis in this assumption other than, maybe, a little hubris. The constant repetition of this unfounded claim speaks volumes about the research and professionalism of those perpetuating it. Marc, at least, had a question mark after that sentence.
Fact is, some people have been &#34;jail&#34;-ed for violating the Orkut TOS, namely the posting of images of children or nude photography. One person I know of has been suspended for posting copyrighted images. Now, one may think that the limitations are overly stupid and should be changed, but as it stands a look at Marc&#39;s profile shows, that he has been most likely suspended for the images of his children. I think is is safer to assume, he has been &#34;jailed&#34; for violating the TOS, than for having too many &#34;friends&#34;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.netwarriors.org&#34;&gt;Jonas M Luster&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T14:25:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T14:25:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hmm, nothing in the message said anything about TOS. In fact, I later received an email from Orkut saying &#34;Your account was blocked by the system automatically. The block is temporary. Your account should be fine now. I apologize for the inconvenience.&#34;
I still don&#39;t know why I was in &#34;jail&#34; last night, and in fact, now I&#39;m in &#34;jail&#34; again late today, so I can only assume that it is because I sent another email to &#34;friends of friends&#34; as that is the only common event between last night and today.
If they use the &#34;jail&#34; for TOS as well as for slowing down people like Marc and I, then I think that is a big mistake to use the same name for both purposes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T14:33:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T14:33:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What is your proof for the &#34;slowing down&#34; of Marc?
His assertions aside, Marc is by far not the most prolific linker, and has not been adding friends as fast as some others, who are neither in Jail nor suspended. Other, much less prolific linkers, have been suspended, all of which share the fact that their actions (the posting of children pics) violated an admittedly stupid TOS provision. At this point, it&#39;s Marc&#39;s assumption (&#34;they don&#39;t like me, because I link a lot of people&#34;) against a trend in suspensions that is closely related to what images have been posted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.netwarriors.org&#34;&gt;Jonas M Luster&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T14:48:16-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T14:48:16-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I too am concerned about a lot of things regarding Orkut, and working on a post of my own about it. But, just to contribute to this, I&#39;ve sent two messages to friends of friends and haven&#39;t been in Jail or anything yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.seanbonner.com&#34;&gt;sean bonner&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T15:26:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T15:26:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Later I find out by looking at other people&#39;s information that this is all completely public. It isn&#39;t limited to just friends, or friends of friends, but instead is prominent. In fact, other then your name and how many &#34;friends&#34; you have, your relationship style is the most prominent thing listed.
That I&#39;d like to see more &#34;progressive disclosure&#34; where there was more granularity of what was revealed at public, friends of friends, friends, fans, fans who I&#39;ve endorsed, etc.&lt;/i&gt;
There&#39;s quite a bit of granularity already, since launch, which you continue to ignore. Every one of your hypothetically incomfortable tidbits of information are filterable by social distance, that is, yourself, friends, friends of friends, everyone. And I can only expect that you will be able to filter by karma/fan, since that would be one of the only primary benefits to the end user of the karma system.
I&#39;m not sure what you mean by &#34;XML hole&#34;. Perhaps you meant XSS? To my knowledge, the precise reasoning for Orkut&#39;s shutdown has not been revealed, but judging by what I&#39;ve noticed has changed, it seems like they took it down to remove the ability of users to broadcast messages to the everyone on the site. The reply-to-all button is gone, and you can no longer send a message to a saved search.
I can think of more applicable (and offensive) words for the orkut-bashing chicken-littles than &#34;unseemly&#34;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://aramchek.net&#34;&gt;dreww&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T18:25:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T18:25:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I don&#39;t like that it&#39;s not easy to opt out. I&#39;ve already had to delete a flame from my &#34;scrapbook&#34; and I could see how this could turn ugly quickly. Without an opt-out I don&#39;t see how I have any way of getting out of there quickly if there&#39;s a problem. Maybe what they need is a way for me to put myself in jail for a period of time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://peaceandlove.com/&#34;&gt;Trash Averse&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-01-31T22:31:52-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-01-31T22:31:52-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve joined a few social networks, revealing things about myself that I don&#39;t mind if everyone reads.  Things I don&#39;t want &#39;everyone&#39; to know, I don&#39;t add to these networks.
I also choose my communities/tribes/groups knowing everyone will be able to see my interests, and have avoided joining some I considered interesting but don&#39;t want linked to my profile.
I use disposable email addresses for social groups; when weaknesses are found, I&#39;m not disturbed by it.  I think others might be though, because they might reveal more about themselves that what I did.  I&#39;ve changed my settings to not expose my address to everyone (I think, there&#39;s a lot of places to check).
I think it&#39;s good that weaknesses are exposed, even publicly.  Not picking on any particular network, but if a person found a weakness in it, and reported it to them, there&#39;s a chance it would be missed/overlooked/ignored.
Perhaps there are some that would take a reported weakness about their network very seriously, probably not as many though.
So by making the weaknesses public, I think it puts a fire under the developers to patch the hole.  Would Orkut&#39;s hole have been patched as quickly as it was if the persons that found the hole had reported it to them instead of publicly?  Maybe, maybe not.
If a network does take immediate measures to patch holes as soon as they&#39;re reported, I&#39;d think it would be nice to give them advance notification before going public with the breach.  But I&#39;m pessimistic about this, and think it probably takes threat of bad publicity to get some networks to patch.
Keep up the good works; your blog is very interesting, and I&#39;ve subbed your RSS in my Bloglines.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://shreela.f2o.org&#34;&gt;Sherri&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-16T05:44:11-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-16T05:44:11-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I also felt insecure about Orkut, I went to jail maybe because of too many friends in short time (281), but I did not receive any explanation, do not know when the jail will be open and do not know why and when it could be closed again.
http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=13086236090759842440
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ecuaderno.com&#34;&gt;Jose Luis Orihuela&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-16T13:29:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-16T13:29:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Regarding your perfect vision of a social networking service:  I guess one could say there maybe other features that someone else might like and visa versa.  So, maybe the perfect service would allow you to pick and choose from a menu of features and services.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;bardia&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-02-24T16:46:35-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-02-24T16:46:35-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
hey...invite me to orkut...ive been trying to find someone whos a member so thell invite me...but ur the onlyone i know
thanx!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;CamilA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-02T16:24:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-02T16:24:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I realize this is kind of late to respond... But Every bit of information other than your name is pretty much optional. You only have to tell Orkut what you want to tell it, and the visibility of what you tell it is controllable by defining when strangers/friends/etc can see... I&#39;m thinking part of your paranoia is a misunderstanding of how the system works.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;CbiMerrow&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-06T10:22:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-06T10:22:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I got put in Orkut jail! Here&#39;s why. I had created a community for those critical of the Macintosh and the mac zealots all ganged up and marked me as bogus user! I sent a fed-ex to Orkut demanding he remove from his system all of the Mac users who abused the &#34;bogus user&#34; button. So far, no reply
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Reuven&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-05-18T21:59:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-05-18T21:59:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
please, i just want to know what the word orkut means, etimological or eletronic one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Antonio Carlos&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-26T23:40:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-26T23:40:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Al I have to say to is that if you are so unconfortable with Orkut, just get out, and don&#39;t be a part of the communite. I&#39;m not trying to defend orkut or something, but I&#39;ve found a lot o friends that i&#39;ve not seen for many years and that is the power of orkut.. find or be together friends
I guess that make you unconfortable too... if you don&#39;t like don&#39;t try to finish with a whole ideia, that in my point of view is very good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Marcelo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-25T11:19:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-25T11:19:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Al I have to say to is that if you are so unconfortable with Orkut, just get out, and don&#39;t be a part of the communite. I&#39;m not trying to defend orkut or something, but I&#39;ve found a lot o friends that i&#39;ve not seen for many years and that is the power of orkut.. find or be together friends
I guess that make you unconfortable too... if you don&#39;t like don&#39;t try to finish with a whole ideia, that in my point of view is very good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Marcelo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-25T11:19:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-25T11:19:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
There are other reasons to be in jail. Some people say that people that &#34;spam&#34; a lot go to jail.
There are a link under the photo of any person that anyone can click. That link says report as bougus.
But I realy don´t know...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Marcelo Vergara&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-27T15:26:34-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-27T15:26:34-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
plz make me a member of orkut.com  plz.....
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;maliya&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-08-05T07:25:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-08-05T07:25:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Hi... I&#39;d like to ask how Orkut works...
Do i need to be invited to use Orkut??
thanks ... bye ...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;rafael&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-01T14:32:47-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-01T14:32:47-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Hi again :) ... People really go to jail because of orkut?!!?
They&#39;r real life is destroyed because a fucking idiot computer program???
if this is true......
Orkut users are a bunch of dumb people who riscs they&#39;r freedom at this idiot program of &#34;&#34;FRIENDS&#34;&#34;
thanks.... bye ....
sorry if i offended someone...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;rafael&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-01T14:36:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-01T14:36:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
well i dont know if u had experienced this but i found a different hole. i browsed throught friends and friends of friends and went to community search added a community and when i went to create one i found out that somebody in india is owner of it. i hit the home button and here i was at the home page of that indian guy. with all access from changing his profile to terminate his account.
well if i got there somebody can get to mine.
ANZ
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;amyn&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-06T13:30:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-06T13:30:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I have been playing around with Orkut a lot in the last 24 hours. One thing I don&#39;t understand about these Social Networking Platforms is why they ask for useless information and why they don&#39;t ask for the interesting things.
Example: Orkut gives me five large textareas to explain things like what I have learned from my past relationships. It lets me give Karma-Points to Phil Wolff if I think he is sexy. It lets me upload photos of my cat.
But it does not ask me if I have ever met Phil in person. (I have.) It does not ask me for how long I have known him. It does not distuinguish between &#34;friend&#34; and &#34;acquaintance&#34;.
It asks &#34;Is xxx your friend?&#34; and I am supposed to give a &#34;thumbs-up&#34; or a &#34;thumbs-down&#34;. (And if I say &#34;no&#34; I cannot even add an explanation to that. I hope I haven&#39;t hurt anybody.)
I don&#39;t get it. It would be so easy to gather this information and it would be so valuable. A simple &#34;have met in person&#34;-flag or something like &#34;How often have you met X?&#34; - &#34;never - once - several times - often - meet regularly&#34; would do it and give so much more depth to the network.
What is it that I am missing? Why is Orkut not gathering more data about the relationships of its members? (Like most of the information it could be optional - I bet many people would share it.) Please enlighten me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.edgenericpills.com&#34;&gt;Robin Smith&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-09T20:07:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-09T20:07:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
hi
i wnt to become a member of orkut
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;nasir&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-15T14:44:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-15T14:44:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i came across lifewithalacrity a while ago [6:20 pm GMT, Nov 18, 2004] while i was searching for answers regarding &#39;identity theft&#39; on orkut after suffering a harrowing experince on that social networking site. i&#39;ve been a member of Orkut for no more than 2 months now. i&#39;m a journalist and work for a satellite tv channel in Pakistan. i have so far added 16 friends to my freind&#39;s list on Orkut who r either journalists, or celebrated singers, or tv actors/actresses in my country. this is the first ever social networking forum i&#39;ve joined primarily becuase i have always had security concerns regarding privacy on other forums and because it was in affiliation with Google, offering a degree of reliability. throughout the time i have been a member of Orkut, i have sufferd loging and access problems on the site. there were times i culd not log into my account at all, or access my messages or access my friends. logging out was especially a major hassle becuase 8 out of 10 times i culdn&#39;t log out at the end of a session because when i tried to log out i got a messgae saying that the page i was trying to access was no longer available. i&#39;d try a couple of times and then close the browser window which was always a source of concern becuase i use cablenet connection and remain apprehensive of leaving my account open and vulnerable on the network server if i dont log out. i duly reported all of this to the orket team via emails but all they ever sent me were automated replies telling me that due to the rapid expansion of Orkut these problems wuld come up especially since the software was beta. Today however i got a real shock when i logged into my account at about 1:15 pm GMT. There were horrible messages sent from account to all my freinds [scribbled on their scrapbooks mostly], messages like &#39;hey guys i am gay&#39; and &#39;you suck!&#39;. my user name and password to my account are known only to me. i dont knwo how someone got access to my account and sent these messages to all my freinds and made posts in my name on the communities i am a member of.
my first instinct was to remove my account altogether from orkut. but then i thought that this was precisly what the malicious act was meant to do, to intimidate me ne and annoy me.
but i am seriously not sure what i should do to ensure my id is not stolen again. any suggestions?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;tahir&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-11-18T10:55:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-11-18T10:55:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;please ask me to orkut
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://us.f524.mail.yahoo.com/ym/login?.rand=bkhibvtb9dj1d&#34;&gt;mohamad&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-09T19:07:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-09T19:07:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Well dear, yet I have not been invited by any one to join orkut. Can you help me to join orkut.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Abbas&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-18T04:45:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-18T04:45:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;i can not go in orkut site cus of proxy how can i passed it iam living in iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com&#34;&gt;mani&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-31T01:06:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-31T01:06:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;hi mani,
Access http://www.openproxies.com
[]&#39;s
Weber Ress
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://weber.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Weber Ress&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-01-31T07:37:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-01-31T07:37:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
give me ID in orkut
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;snopy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-04T04:04:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-04T04:04:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i can not go in orkut site cus of proxy how can i passed it iam living in iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;sara&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-13T12:25:28-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-13T12:25:28-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
i can not go in orkut site cus of proxy how can i passed it iam living in iran
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;neda&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-21T07:45:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-21T07:45:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Some guy named Junaid from Karachi, Pakistan put up my cell no. on orkut in the call girls&#39; list. I have been receiving countless phone calls from guys asking me how much i charge. This is pathetic because i don&#39;t even know any Junaid and i had never heard of this site till some guy called and told me that my cell no. was on display and so was my name under the call girl list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Maheen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-23T05:09:00-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-23T05:09:00-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/01/insecurity_at_o.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>