<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Collaboration on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/collaboration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Collaboration on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 01:13:10 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/collaboration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Shared Language and Shared Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 01:13:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://worldatuningfork.com/John/medusaosxPDF.pdf#page=203&#34; style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Poem: Language&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577a68d970b &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577a68d970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px;&#34; title=&#34;Poem: Language&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We live in a world of conversation, of language; all full of words. Mastery of language requires learning the meanings of thousands of words. The average native English language speaker uses in the realm of 12,000 to 20,000 words, whereas a college graduate would use 20-25,000 words. Shakespeare actively used more then 30,000 words, and his vocabulary was estimated to be over 66,000 words. Yet there are, at the very least, a quarter of a million distinct English words, excluding inflections, and words from technical and regional vocabularies. The Oxford English dictionary defines more then 600,000 words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But mastery of words is not enough to allow effective conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is because words themselves don&amp;#39;t have meaning; the meaning is provided by the people who use them. Meaning is in the mind, not in the words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words also require context, outside of which they may have different meanings. For instance, consider the word &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot;. To a banker or CPA &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot; is a property held by someone to manage for someone else&amp;#39;s benefit. To a cryptographer it is the confidence in a future outcome based on probabilistic mathematics and past experience. Finally, to the lay person &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot; is about honesty. &amp;quot;Spin&amp;quot; is another example of a word that changes with context; to a weaver it is the production of thread, to a physicist it is a property of elemental particles, to an athlete it is a type of exercise class, and to a politician or public relations professional it is a way to tell a story to sway pubic opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Creating a Shared Language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Life With Alacrity Wordle&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b-320pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Life With Alacrity Wordle&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Every time a new group of people meet together — whether in a team, in a marketplace, or in a community — one of the first activities they must do together is create a shared language. They do this in order to communicate more effectively together, to put a context on the words that they have in common, to construct a shared understanding in their minds based both on available information and their individual diversity of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t forget that the linguistic root of communication is the Latin verb&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.18:3557.lewshort&#34; title=&#34;Latin definition of commūnĭco&#34;&gt;commūnĭco&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;&amp;#0160;— which doesn&amp;#39;t mean &amp;quot;to communicate&amp;quot; but instead means &amp;quot;to share something with someone, to take or receive a part of, to partake, to participate in&amp;quot;. Thus the creation of a shared language takes us to the roots of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without taking the time time to create shared language, groups have a difficult time forging mutual trust. Without a shared language there will be no clarity on mutual goals — whether it involves working together, transacting a trade, or creating something. Without a shared language commitments can be hard to make, and if misunderstood can lead to disagreements. These group formation phases — trust building, goal clarification, and commitment — are essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the art of creating a shared language together is not taught. Some individuals and groups do it intuitively while others will just let it evolve naturally over time. However, some facilitators have learned that one of the best ways to help a group form a shared language is by having the group create together a shared artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Using Shared Artifacts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shared artifact is the creation of an object or shared space that is created collaboratively. It allows the individuals participating to ask the questions: &amp;quot;Is this what you mean when you are talking about this? I use these words, so suppose we change it to this? Is that what you mean? Does this reflect our new shared understanding?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;WatsonCrick&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c-120pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px;&#34; title=&#34;WatsonCrick&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Napkin-idea-original-concept-300x293&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c-120wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Examples of shared artifacts include Watson &amp;amp; Crick&amp;#39;s Tinker-Toy DNA model. Each scientist would work on the model separately, then use grad students to carry the model around to his partner to express certain ideas. Both Compaq Computer and Southwest Airlines were reportedly established after their founders wrote their ideas down together on a table napkin, another shared artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these examples show an important factor in shared artifacts — if the shared artifact is not constrained then it will be too large or complex for the group to reach some measure of completion. Finishing the shared artifact really helps establish trust and the connections between the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shared artifact is also useful because flooding someone with information and terms gives no assurance that the recipient has gained knowledge of the subject. Instead, the act of creation confirms to both parties that the knowledge was successfully assimilated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage to creating a shared artifact is that it isolates any problems to the task at hand. Often there are differences in status, purpose, or perspective that can get in the way of group formation, but a focus on a common task of the creation of a neutral shared artifact allows those issues to come later as the participants develop the trust and shared language required to talk about those tough issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best facilitators know what kinds of shared artifacts work best for different groups under different circumstances. Sometimes a shared artifact is just a model of a process drawn on a white wall. Often it is a creation of a mission statement or joint objectives. I personally like taking old mind maps and trying to recreate them anew with more recent knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Future of Shared Language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of shared language is changing in the 21st century. The conjoined social networks in the blogosphere — via Facebook, Twitter, or the attendee-focused Unconference — cause new terminology and new language to form ever faster. I&amp;#39;ve personally seen words like &amp;quot;retweet&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;attribution&amp;quot; gain important contextual meaning within my social networks. As with any shared language, newcomers have difficulty discovering their meanings only by osmosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tagging is another means by which shared language is rapidly expanding. Certain words are gaining context through common use at Delicious.com, Technorati, Flickr, and other tag-enabled web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a certain extent, all of these new shared languages are built upon shared artifacts. Twitter, Facebook, Delicious.com and others sites each create constraints on how language is shared and with whom. However, there is little purposeful social design being applied to these new shared languages. Though there may be shared artifacts, they are not purposefully facilitated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will these increasingly organic shared languages prove better than more purposefully created ones or worse? Is social language facilitation the next big thing in social network? Or is there just not enough space for it within the tightly constrained social artifacts of the internet? These are questions that we as social software technologists need to address as the future of the internet increasingly becomes the present of our social groupings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I learned the concept of Shared Language in 1990 from Michael Schrage&amp;#39;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Shared-Minds-New-Technologies-Collaboration/dp/0394565878&#34;&gt;Shared Minds: The New Technologies of Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. It is out of print, but there is a new edition retitled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/No-More-Teams-Mastering-Collaboration/dp/0385476035/&#34;&gt;No More Teams!: Mastering the Dynamics of Creative Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. The use of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com/mgtaylor/glasbead/modexpl.htm&#34;&gt;modeling language&lt;/a&gt; to facilitate group formation I learned from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.matttaylor.com&#34;&gt;Matt Taylor&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/worthyprojects&#34;&gt;@worthyprojects&lt;/a&gt;) of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com/&#34;&gt;MG Taylor Corporation&lt;/a&gt;, though the use of the term shared artifacts and approach is my own. I make passing reference to the early stages of team formation (&amp;quot;trust building&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;goal clarification&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;commitment&amp;quot;) which come from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grove.com/site/ourwk_gm_tp.html&#34;&gt;Drexler/Sibbet Team Peformance Model&lt;/a&gt;. The poem is by excerpt of a larger work by &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldatuningfork.com/John/&#34;&gt;John Campion&lt;/a&gt; and is reprinted with permission — the work reflects the poet&amp;#39;s Ecotropic concerns and are part of his third
book-length poem Medusa. Look at the work under the Medusa Project link. The table napkin photo is from an excellent post on &lt;a href=&#34;http://createtheconditions.com/?p=304&#34;&gt;The Idea Napkin&lt;/a&gt; by Morry Potoka and is also reprinted with permission. The Watson-Crick photo is public domain, and the Life With Alacrity graphic was produced using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordle.net/&#34;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;m wondering whether the creation of such language is adding to an intellectual, generational and cultural divisiveness that is already prevalent in our society. Can we design tools that serve as bridges? Using the web for social change is a powerful concept, particularly if we can broaden the audience. This is a fascinating topic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Julie  Mihalisin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-09-21T10:45:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-09-21T10:45:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve not really thought of Shared Language in the context of divisiveness — Shared Language tends to be a function of small groups. Thus I more think of the divisiveness is coming from the fact that Shared Language typically evolves naturally in a small group, but fails to evolve naturally in larger groups. Possibly a better understanding of how Shared Language and tools to facilitate it like Shared Artifacts function will make it easier for larger groups to grow a Shared Language together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-09-21T14:06:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-09-21T14:06:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Shared artifacts are also known as models; the best form of understanding of business that I have found yet is when you develop simulators with practitioners. The quality of the the output is only surpassed by the shared understanding created through healthy challenge to the way things actually work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Dave Carter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-05-05T04:15:41-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-05-05T04:15:41-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SynchroEdit: Simultaneous Editing for the Web</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2005 16:04:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the last several months I&#39;ve been working on a new open source project that I&#39;ve been calling &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit&lt;/a&gt;. SynchroEdit is a browser-based simultaneous multiuser editor, useful for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.it.bton.ac.uk/staff/rng/teaching/notes/CSCWgroupware.html&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/synchroeditmac.png&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=493,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;262&#34; height=&#34;202&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Synchroeditmac&#34; title=&#34;Synchroeditmac&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/synchroeditmac.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The basic concept is that it allows multiple users to WYSIWYG edit a single web-based document, all at exactly the same time. SynchroEdit continuously synchronizes all changes so that users always see the same version. They can also see each others&#39; changes as they type, see where each user is currently editing, and see each others&#39; changes by color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SynchroEdit is a tool for &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration, either &amp;quot;same-time, different-place&amp;quot;, as in teleconference calls, or &amp;quot;same-time, same-place&amp;quot;, during a meeting or a conference. If you&#39;ve ever used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/&#34;&gt;SubEthaEdit&lt;/a&gt; on Mac OS X, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moonedit.com&#34;&gt;MoonEdit&lt;/a&gt; for Windows or Linux, or the cross-platform &lt;a href=&#34;http://gobby.0x539.de/&#34;&gt;Gobby&lt;/a&gt;, this is a similar experience. The difference is that unlike those tools you are not limited to just plain text -- character styles (bold, italic, etc.) and paragraph styles (rulers, headers, blockquotes, etc) are synchronized as well. And of course, it all works inside your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SynchroEdit is inspired by my frustration with the lack of an easily accessible cross-platform simultaneous editor. Many times when I&#39;ve been on the phone with a colleague discussing a draft blog entry, or demonstrating some code, or on a teleconference call with others to discuss a proposal or a standard, or at a conference taking notes with others, I&#39;ve wanted to have this tool. The rare occasions that we all have been on the same platform and have been able to use an existing tool have demonstrated to me the value of having a good simultaneous editor. Having SynchroEdit available will make it easier for people to have these positive collaborative experiences.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a long history with &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration tools -- back in 1988 I was briefly executive producer at Broderbund for a same-time groupware product called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/search?q=cache:1cDDTqwlqGoJ:www.the-scientist.com/yr1988/jul/software_p22_880725.html+%2Bbroderbund+%2B%22for+comment%22+groupware&#34;&gt;For Comment&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, the success of the Nintendo game console forced Broderbund to drop all of their non-consumer product efforts. In the early 90&#39;s I worked on several different &amp;quot;same-time same-place&amp;quot; groupware tools for live meetings. Most recently, my game company &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net&#34;&gt;Skotos Tech&lt;/a&gt;, created several browser-based &amp;quot;enhanced chat&amp;quot; clients for playing in MUSH-like storytelling games, which are also &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally believe that that this capability should be a fundamental feature of the web, sort of the obvious extension of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee&#34;&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/4132752.stm&#34;&gt;vision&lt;/a&gt; of the editable web. Thus my desire to offer this tool as open source, allowing anyone to add this capability to their own software (unlike proprietary editor services such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotlive.com&#34;&gt;JotLive&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.writely.com/&#34;&gt;Writely&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge with offering SynchroEdit as open source is finding a business model -- unlike an application like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/&#34;&gt;SubEthaEdit&lt;/a&gt; or a service like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jotlive.com&#34;&gt;JotLive&lt;/a&gt;, it is difficult to get revenues from individual users. Instead, we ask for contributions from companies that might find the tool useful, we offer consulting to customize it for specific purposes, and we give these companies public credit for their contributions to the common good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first company to step up to the plate is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.socialtext.com&#34;&gt;SocialText&lt;/a&gt;, an enterprise wiki company. Clearly, being able to offer this capability to their customers will give them added value, and they already have a history of using open source with their support of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kwiki.org/&#34;&gt;Kwiki&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wikiwyg.net/&#34;&gt;Wikiwyg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second supporter is venture capitalist and blogger &lt;a href=&#34;http://joi.ito.com/&#34;&gt;Joichi Ito&lt;/a&gt;. He is is particularly well known for his own experiments with &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; collaboration. He runs a continuous #joiito IRC chat room, active 24 hours a day with hundreds of his friends. He also has done many live &amp;quot;same-time&amp;quot; experiments with chat backchannel during his talks at various conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to to financial support of SocialText and Joichi Ito, I have some offers of help from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bgiedu.org&#34;&gt;Bainbridge Graduate Institute&lt;/a&gt;, who plan to use it in its socially responsible and environmentally sustainable MBA program, and we&#39;ve also taken advantage of some code developed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of SynchroEdit is being led by Kalle Alm, a young Swedish coder I met when he was creating an online game at Skotos. Skotos has long had the vision of having games created by its members, and Kalle Alm was the first member to create a game completely from scratch using Skotos&#39; tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking more financial contributions so that we can accelerate development. Currently SynchroEdit only works in Mozilla/Firefox, and I anticipate that making it work with Internet Explorer may be quite difficult, so we&#39;ll need more partners to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/christopher_allen_web2point1_brainjam.png&#34; title=&#34;Christopher_allen_web2point1_brainjam&#34; alt=&#34;Christopher_allen_web2point1_brainjam&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;I did a demo of last year&#39;s open source project, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.EditThisPage.net&#34;&gt;EditThisPage&lt;/a&gt;, and of the SynchroEdit alpha at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.web2point1.org/&#34;&gt;Web 2.1 BrainJam&lt;/a&gt; last week; there are two videos available from Enric Teller&#39;s vBlog: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cirne.com/vlog/2005/10/10/web-21-a-brainjam-christopher-allen-presentation/&#34;&gt;Presentation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cirne.com/vlog/2005/10/10/web-21-a-brainjam-christopher-allen-qa/&#34;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in learning more, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;SynchroEdit website&lt;/a&gt;. We have additional information on the program, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.synchroedit.com&#34;&gt;developers wiki&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a sandbox that you can play in to demonstrate SynchroEdit in use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;m curious about what ways you think this could be useful as a teaching aid? Have you looked into particular implementations or studied existing case studies?
(I have studied this a fair amount and I don&#39;t think there are existing case studies, especially in the classroom, which is why I ask.. I&#39;m looking at ways in which chatrooms could be incorporated into classroom environments as a backchannel)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;yardi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-16T11:00:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-16T11:00:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/10/for_the_last_se.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:38:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my post about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; I offered some evidence on the levels of satisfaction of various group sizes based on some empirical data from online games. There I was able to show that even though the Dunbar Number might predict a mean group size of 150 for humans, that in fact for non-survival oriented groups the mean was significantly less, probably between 60 to 90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/groupsatisfaction.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=436,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;272&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Groupsatisfaction&#34; title=&#34;Groupsatisfaction&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/groupsatisfaction.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I also offered a second hypothesis, that there is a dip in satisfaction level of groups at around the size of 15. Unfortunately, I could only offer anecdotal evidence that this threshold existed. My personal belief was that this dip was caused by not enough &amp;quot;attention&amp;quot; being given to everyone and that group gatherings of this size risk becoming too noisy, too boring, too long, or some combination thereof. Yet groups of this size are not large enough to allow for different perspectives (i.e. insufficient &lt;a href=&#34;http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/REQVAR.html&#34;&gt;requisite variety&lt;/a&gt;) or for other group processes to come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading through the current (12 March) issue of &lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt;, and found an interesting table in the article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=mg18524901.600&#34;&gt;Charity Begins at Homo Sapiens&lt;/a&gt;. It stood out to me as it showed a dip approaching zero average cooperation for group sizes of 16 -- almost precisely same place that my hypothesis predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging further, I found the original source for this table was published in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; back in October 2003, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/papers/NatureOfHumanAltruism.pdf&#34;&gt;The Nature of Human Altruism&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/&#34;&gt;Ernst Fehr&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fischbacher/&#34;&gt;Urs Fischbacher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=495,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;309&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/images/nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1&#34; alt=&#34;Nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What the chart shows is actually not empirical data from human experiments, but instead data from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_theory&#34;&gt;game theory&lt;/a&gt; simulation of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&#34;&gt;prisoner&#39;s dilemma&lt;/a&gt;. This is the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-sum&#34;&gt;zero-sum game&lt;/a&gt; where if you cooperate, the joint payoff of the players is higher. However, in zero-sum games there is also incentive for the players to cheat by defecting and thus taking less risk. Robert Axelrod showed in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0465021212/102-0974708-1794504&#34;&gt;The Evolution of Cooperation&lt;/a&gt; back in 1985 that in spite of the statistical best individual strategy being that of defection, cooperation inevitably evolves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fehr and Fischbacher, in their &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; article, took this idea a bit further by creating 100 independent simulations with group sizes ranging from 2 to 512, and then executing each simulation 1,000 to 2,000 times. Each generation of the &amp;quot;players&amp;quot; was allowed to evolve different strategies of cooperation vs defection, the classic successful strategy being &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tit_for_tat&#34;&gt;Tit for Tat&lt;/a&gt;. They would then evaluate the percentage of players who had cooperative strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If punishment of defections was ruled out, they discovered that over the 1,000+ generations of the simulation that the rate of cooperation quickly crashes, such that at the group size of 8 a little over 50% cooperation evolved, and for groups that are larger than 16 none cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next they added to the simulation &amp;quot;&lt;a name=&#34;altruistic_punishment&#34;&gt;Altruistic Punishment&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. This is the ability for players to punish those who did not cooperate -- however, such punishment is at some cost to the punisher. Earlier game theory &lt;a href=&#34;http://ideas.repec.org/cgi-bin/get_doc.pl?urn=RePEc:wpa:wuwpmi:0305006&amp;amp;url=http://econwpa.wustl.edu:8089/eps/mic/papers/0305/0305006.pdf&#34;&gt;research on altruistic punishment&lt;/a&gt; has shown that cooperation flourishes if there is some price for punishing defectors -- if you allow punishment at no cost then cheating strategies emerge. This earlier research determined that allowing individuals to punish at some cost that yields them no material gain will paradoxically result in an average gain for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding altruistic punishment to the simulation increased the amount of cooperation that evolved, such that groups with the size of 32 would have 50% cooperation. But even this had limits; at the group size of 128 no cooperation would evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if they added to the simulation the ability to punish those who did not participate in punishing (i.e. didn&#39;t pay the cost to punish defectors), then the percentage of cooperation that evolved was never less then 60%, and in fact got better as groups got larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very interesting result. To explain it in different terms, if you have a system that depends on sharing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons&#34;&gt;commons&lt;/a&gt; and there are no process or trust metrics, a group as small as 16 may find themselves not cooperating very effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of commons can be as simple as how much speaking time participants in a meeting share. The time that each participant uses during the meeting can be considered the shared &amp;quot;commons&amp;quot;. If there are no enforced rules, with a group size of 16 there will inevitably be someone who will abuse the time and speak more than their share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some simple rules (some type of process to partition time more fairly), or through some trust metrics (punish those who abuse the commons), larger groups can gain value from cooperating, but even these groups have limits. As long as there is some effort required to punish those who abuse the process, eventually the price for that effort becomes too high, and no one is willing to punish any longer. You see this in moderated discussion groups, where the guardians of the common good have to spend too much time moderating, given the number of people that wish to participate. Moderated newsgroups and early versions of SlashDot moderation had this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting observation from this simulation is that for larger groups, you needed to have a system to punish those who did not participate in punishing -- or to put it another way, get everyone involved with the process, not just a few. I think that this explains something that I&#39;ve always wondered about SlashDot&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usemod.com/cgi-bin/mb.pl?MetaModeration&#34;&gt;meta-moderation&lt;/a&gt; system -- with this feature you grade those who have moderated, and if someone abuses it they will no longer be able to moderate. What I suspect, given these results, is that if you don&#39;t participate in the meta-moderation system, you have less a chance of being able to moderate; thus SlashDot has a system that punishes those who are not involved in participating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have some questions based on this simulation -- I would like to see results with more granularity then powers of 2. I&#39;d also like to know the percentage of players participating in punishment -- I suspect that you&#39;ll find a very small number of &amp;quot;moderators&amp;quot; are required in the middle graph, even when cooperation evolves successfully. I&#39;m curious as to how many moderators are required to participate in punishing the non-punishers for cooperation to evolve in the third scenario. Also, in meta-moderation this simulation emphasizes punishing the non-punishers -- is that as successful as rewarding the punishers? I&#39;m also interested in investigating some of the further works where Fehr and Fischbacher are among the co-authors, such as this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/science/Altruistic_Punishment.pdf&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; using MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging) that shows that our brain&#39;s pleasure systems are activated when we altruistically punish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure that the findings of this simulation are not the only reason why there might be a dip in group satisfaction at group sizes around 15, such as I observed. However, it does offer some interesting insights into group size thresholds, both for the threshold at 15 and for threshold of non-survival groups which I&#39;ve identified as being significantly less then the Dunbar mean of 150. It also shows that for large groups we need to offer not only moderation, but meta-moderation capabilities that involve all the participants in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary this research offers me another widget for my social software toolbox: in any group process look for the commons, allow participants to participate in identifing defectors; determine what the costs are for such identification (which may be as simple as requiring some attention or charging for such punishment); and encourage participation in the common good by punishing those who do not participate in seeking out defectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
For role based community blogging, check out http://go.webassistant.com/wa
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Garsett Larosse&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-22T21:09:33-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-22T21:09:33-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You may be onto something. The Dunbar number was referred to in the Tipping Point and in some places plays a role in tribal-forming. But for smaller activities the number 15 seems ideal, eg, for a classroom or workshop. If there&#39;s under 10 or 12, regardless of the room size people want to bail out because there doesn&#39;t seem to be &#34;enough&#34; people. Much over 15 and the group dynamic must change to lecture style as if there were 50 or 100 people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.pagehalffull.com/humanyms/&#34;&gt;Pearl&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-23T12:16:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-23T12:16:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Association Football (&#34;soccer&#34;) and cricket teams are 11 strong and are organised by a single player, the captain.  Rugby Union sides are 15 strong, and the organising job is split: the forwards are led by a &#34;pack leader&#34; who is subject to the team captain.  Any significance?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;dearieme&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-30T03:16:15-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-30T03:16:15-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
A superb blog Chris, but just a few errata on the post.
First the simulation in Fehr,et al is a multi-person prisoner&#39;s dilemma--a public goods game--which is identical to the game in the &#34;research on altruistic punishment&#34; link which I think is a great introduction to the literature.
Second, the prisoner&#39;s dilemma is not a zero-sum game although often times mis-attributed as such. In zero-sum games, the total payoff in each possible outcome must be the same; thus, your gain must be my loss. The tragedy of the prisoner&#39;s dilemma is simply that cooperate is not a good strategy for either player.
Third, I think the sentence with the &#34;research on altruistic punishment&#34; link should be &#34;... cooperation flourishes EVEN if there is a cost to punishing defectors.&#34; The later part of the sentence is incorrect. However, the result is still paradoxical as under the notion of rationality one would not expect anyone to incur the cost of punishing another without any personal profit.
Finally, although this research seems to be one capable of addressing organizational size, it is actually quite incapable of that feat. The number 16 on the graph is really a coincidence of circumstances see the graph in http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/anthro/faculty/boyd/SecondOrderFreeRidePublished.pdf for the impact of parameter values on the model. Actually, coincidence is not quite correct; it was a deliberate selection by the researchers. This literature is designed to unshackle economics from the rational agent paradigm not to address optimal organizational size.
I will try to see if there are more pertinent experimental research addressing the Dunbar number question and post them, but I&#39;m somewhat doubtful as the experimental design is still too limited to study such a complex phenomenon. I had thought to try to run such an experiment myself a year ago, but abandoned the idea. I think an econometric analysis of the online games data is probably the most promising course.
--an apologetic economist
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;chinteliu&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-07T03:45:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-07T03:45:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;is the supposed cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable social relationships: the kind of relationships that go with knowing who each person is and how each person relates socially to every other person. Proponents assert that group sizes larger than this generally require more restricted rules, laws, and enforced policies and regulations to maintain a stable cohesion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.edivergent.com&#34;&gt;Busby seo challenge&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-07-26T23:03:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-07-26T23:03:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2004 16:56:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A number of my posts have been about integrating different domains of knowledge in order to better understand how human behavior should be incorporated in the design of social software. I found &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;The Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; in sociology, and both &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/04/four_kinds_of_p.html&#34;&gt;Four Kinds of Privacy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt; come from my work in the cryptography field. The topic of this post comes from the field of architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to provide for &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt;, you need to establish what is known as an &#34;Intimacy Gradient&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of Intimacy Gradient comes from architect Christopher Alexander, in his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/&#34;&gt;A Pattern Language: Towns, Buildings, Construction. (Oxford University Press, 1977)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/ptn127.html&#34;&gt;Pattern #127 - Intimacy Gradient:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conflict:&lt;/b&gt; Unless the spaces in a building are arranged in a sequence which corresponds to their degrees of privateness, the visits made by strangers, friends, guests, clients, family, will always be a little awkward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Resolution:&lt;/b&gt; Lay out the spaces of a building so that they create a sequence which begins with the entrance and the most public parts of the building, then leads into the slightly more private areas, and finally to the most private domains.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In architecture there are always some areas of the house or building that are more public -- the entry, the living room, the atrium, etc., and areas that are more private such as bathrooms, bedrooms, and offices. In a good design there is some marker of change between these different areas -- it might be a difference in ceiling height, a stairway leading to a different floor, or a narrow entrance. As an example, in the classical Japanese tea house, you have to bow low before entering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to respect the Intimacy Gradient results in uncomfortable buildings. &lt;a href=&#34;http://munnecke.com/gehry.htm&#34;&gt;Tom Munnecke&lt;/a&gt; reported about a Frank Gehry building at Case Western Reserve University:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; I asked many of the graduate students how they felt about their new environment. &#34;Horrible,&#34; said one. &#34;Like living in a refrigerator&#34; said another. &#34;We used to have comfortable offices and gathering places, and had the most wonderful conversations. Now everything is so sterile, and the acoustics so bad, that we can&#39;t do anything together. I have to go outside if I want any privacy.&#34;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Intimacy Gradient is also used in other media. As I noted in my review of &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/01/seven_fingers_o.html&#34;&gt;Seven Fingers of the Hand Circus&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;When we arrived, we were led down the side of the theatre and all of a sudden I noticed that it looked like we were all being led backstage. We curve around and all of a sudden see an entrance -- maybe 5 foot tall requiring most of us to duck. We duck through and to our surprise, we are have walked through a fridgerator, and we are on the stage!
&lt;p&gt;One of the 7 players welcomes us, and another offers random people a glass of tea as we walk across the stage to our seats. The stage is set like a city loft, with a tv, some couches, a bed, a bathtub and shower, a kitchen, and of course the fridgerator we entered through. On the stage, and chatting to members of the audience are the 7 cast members, all wearing comfortable looking white shorts or athletic and white t-shirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience arrives over 30 minutes and the 7 players act as if we are guests of their loft, serving some of us tea, chatting, sweeping the floor, etc.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entering through the refrigerator door raised the intimacy of the experience for the audience of that circus. Thus in spite of it being produced in a large auditorium it felt as up-close and personal as did the much smaller &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/circus_contrapt.html&#34;&gt;Circus Contraption&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Intimacy Gradient exists in movies as well -- anywhere you see a scene taking place in a public space that transitions down through smaller and tighter shots ultimately to a closeup of a face it is much more intimate then just cutting to the closeup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In social software design, there also needs to be an Intimacy Gradient. One of the problems with Wikis is that there is often very little transition between public and intimate, and doing so can be quite jarring. SocialText, a Wiki service vendor, is aware of this problem and is &lt;a href=&#34;http://alevin.com/weblog/archives/001393.html&#34;&gt;&#34;seeking to add more layers to the &#39;intimacy gradient&#39;, without recreating the highly structured collaboration tools that exist today&#34;&lt;/a&gt;. Ross Mayfield outlines &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.corante.com/many/archives/2004/08/12/collaboration_cases_and_spaces.php&#34;&gt;this possible future Intimacy Gradient for SocialText&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The broadest tier is a guest space, available to all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second tier is a knowledgebase, accessible to all employees and contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third tier is product development, for employees and contractors bound by a confidentiality agreement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fourth tier is for the core management team to share confidential financial and HR information.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These thoughts from an earlier post by &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Ross&lt;/a&gt; are also thoughtful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;He is right that groupthink is avoided by a social network structure that allows a dynamic and diverse periphery to provide new ideas, but the core of the network needs to be tightly bound to be able to take action.
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s the main point of Building Sustainable Communities through Network Building by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orgnet.com&#34;&gt;Valdis Krebs&lt;/a&gt; and June Holley. When studying a &lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0114726/categories/socialNetworks/2003/01/07.html&#34;&gt;community over time&lt;/a&gt;, they suggest a vibrant community is made up of four stages: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Scattered Clusters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single Hub-and-Spoke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-Hub Small-World Network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Core/Periphery&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal core/periphery structure affords a densely linked core and a dynamic periphery. One pattern for social software that supports this is an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jacana.org.uk/pattern/P127.htm&#34;&gt;intimacy gradient&lt;/a&gt; (privacy/openness), to allow the core some privacy for backchannelling. But this requires ridiculously easy group forming, as the more hardened the space the more hard-nosed its occupants become.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just a problem for Wiki. There is an excellent paper on the web called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ai.mit.edu/~konrad/docs/IJMMS-patterns-junestrand-keijer-tollmar.pdf&#34;&gt;Design Patterns for Private and Public Digital Spaces in the Home Environment&lt;/a&gt; where they explore how people used VNC (video-mediated communications, or more colloquially video-chat). They state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The earlier &#34;public&#34; character of a traditional farmer&#39;s house or bourgeois flat (in Sweden) has disappeared with the modern housing planning. Instead, distinguishing the public from the private has become central during the industrial age, with the dwelling as an exclusively private place. Now, with the transition to an information society, it seems as if the concept of public space in the private dwelling has to be reconsidered, which also means that the borders between the private and the public at home have to be opened up.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to provide for an Intimacy Gradient in social software is clear; however, the techniques for showing the transitions between the gradients are not. For instance, in the original Netscape Communicator, when you connected with a secure SSL connection, the border around the edge of the window would turn blue, and a solid blue key would show up. However, most people didn&#39;t notice this change and no current browser does this; even the little locked icon at the bottom of Internet Explorer and often isn&#39;t visible if you have the status bar turned off or if you are using frames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ming.tv/flemming2.php/__show_article/_a000010-001289.htm&#34;&gt;Flemming Funch&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redtailcanyon.com/items/278391.aspx&#34;&gt;mirror&lt;/a&gt;) notes part of the difficulty is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;As long as a certain chat room or Wiki page is accessible directly with a deep link, it is going to be very hard to make it feel more intimate than any other place I can reach with similar ease. So a hierarchical structure of links doesn&#39;t do it. On the web you can&#39;t force people to accept your hierarchy if it is all just links.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the solution might come from the architecture world as well -- here are some other Patterns by Christopher Alexander (see the link for Alexander&#39;s resolutions for each):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/ptn31.html&#34;&gt;Pattern #31 - Promenade:&lt;/a&gt; Each subculture needs a center for its public life: a place where you can go to see people, and to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/ptn61.html&#34;&gt;Pattern #61 - Small Public Squares:&lt;/a&gt; A town needs public squares; they are the largest, most public rooms, that a town has. but when they are too large, they look and feel deserted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/ptn69.html&#34;&gt;Pattern #69 - Public Outdoor Room:&lt;/a&gt; There are very few spots along the streets of modern towns and neighborhoods where people can hang out, comfortably, for hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/ptn142.html&#34;&gt;Pattern #42 - Sequence of Sitting Spaces:&lt;/a&gt; Every corner of a building is a potential sitting space. But each sitting space has different needs for comfort and enclosure according to its position in the intimacy gradient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downlode.org/etext/patterns/ptn147.html&#34;&gt;Pattern #147 - Communal Eating&#34;:&lt;/a&gt; Without communal eating, no human group can hold together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other lessons for social software from the architecture world are the concepts of &#34;refuge and prospect&#34;, the &#34;savanna theory&#34;, and &#34;defensible space&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Refuge and prospect&lt;/i&gt; come from the landscape architect &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.landscaperesearch.org.uk/extra31/refuge.htm&#34;&gt;Jay Appleton&lt;/a&gt;. Prospect is a place where we can see others, and refuge is a place were we can retreat and conceal ourselves. A specific prediction of his theory is that people prefer the edges of a space more then the middle. Often prospect and refuge are in conflict, as a prospect tends to be expansive and bright whereas a refuge is small and dark, but there are cases where they are combined in one place; this is why we value private homes with a spectacular view so much, and why we pay so much to stay at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.djc.com/news/ae/11127729.html&#34;&gt;scenic retreats&lt;/a&gt;. So what are the edges of our social spaces? Are there ways that we can signal either prospect and refuge?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;savanna theory&lt;/i&gt; comes from a hypothesis by &lt;a href=&#34;http://notes.utk.edu/bio/greenberg.nsf/0/f60081ef35fba95c85256e6e006a2a77?OpenDocument&#34;&gt;Richard Coss and Gordon Orians&lt;/a&gt; that we should be most comfortable with those landscapes where humans spent most of their evolutionary past. Thus supposedly the ideal landscape design has the same proportionality of trees, grass, and brush as the African savanna; parks and golf clubs are shown as evidence of this theory. An alternate to this theory is that we desire a certain amount of &lt;a href=&#34;http://evolution.anthro.univie.ac.at/institutes/urbanethology/student/html/erich/synekpro.html&#34;&gt;visual complexity&lt;/a&gt;. Either theory raises this question: what are the evolutionary markers regarding groups that our human ancestors needed? This question fits well with my thoughts regarding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;defensible space&lt;/i&gt; concept comes from the idea that anonymous spaces lead to problems because of vandalism, incivility, and crime, and to eliminate those problems requires the residents to mark their &#34;territories&#34; and &#34;take possession&#34; of their areas. We have similar problems in the online world. So maybe the answer is similar -- allow more ways for groups of people to mark up and take possession of their own virtual spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of links that integrate these ideas in architecture that you might find useful:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wbdg.org/design/resource.php?cn=0&amp;rp=181&#34;&gt;Psychosocial Value of Space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edcmag.com/CDA/ArticleInformation/features/BNP__Features__Item/0,4120,22486,00.html&#34;&gt;Building Biophilia: Connecting People to Nature in Building Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ceae.colorado.edu/~amadei/CVEN4838/BioInspire.1_%2001.15.03.htm&#34;&gt;Bio-Inspired Design: What Can We Learn from Nature?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://evolution.anthro.univie.ac.at/institutes/urbanethology/archi/archi.html&#34;&gt;Evolutionary Architecture: A Field Course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.the-scientist.com/yr2001/nov/opin_011126.html&#34;&gt;Why We Say It With Flowers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contemporary.ab.ca/ke/content/pdf/evolutionary_psychology.pdf&#34;&gt;Evolutionary Psychology and Workplace Design (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are still breaking ground and exploring new ideas in the world of social software. However, there are already extant fields of study which may give us insight into this new venue. Architecture is one of them. By better understanding ideas of intimacy gradients, pattern language, refuge and prospect, savannas, and defensible spaces, we may gain new understandings of how to build social environments which are attractive and enjoyable to more people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Tried to post this elsewhere and failed. Sorry if it&#39;s duplication.
If a person loading a page has an identity or role (one could have many of these for different purposes) then the system serving the page could show different sets of links based on the &#34;privacy level&#34;. Of course, one could show entirely different sets of links to different people. This du(multi?)plicity would also reflect the method commonly employed in social manipulation, i.e. saying different things to different people based on one&#39;s view of them.
As it stands, this suggests that the person providing the link sets owns the server, which is often not the case.  Alternatively, it suggests that one is happy to trust a service provider with one&#39;s most intimate secrets.  I suspect neither needs to be the case if cryptography is used.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://example.com&#34;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-09-20T02:05:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-09-20T02:05:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
The fridge door speaks to another one of the Pattern Language patterns -- that a doorway should truly be a noticable, transforming experience. That is, a clear indicator that you have gone from &#34;there&#34; to &#34;here.&#34; Off-topic, I know. But interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Charlie&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-08T13:04:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-08T13:04:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for the great summary and roundup of key concepts, theories and techniques from architecture and urban planning that can be applied to social software design.  I&#39;m also a big fan of these fields and I think we can stand to have a lot more cross-pollination between the worlds of software, and of space/place design.
As for how to simulate intimacy gradients, and more basic, &#34;hardwired&#34; ways that we behave in spaces and places, in the online world (or how to symbolize or substitute for them), I wonder:  Why don&#39;t we cheat more often?
People use our software in spaces and places, after all.  Instead of trying to -simulate- the physical, real-world intimacy mechanisms that we&#39;ve evolved to use, why not just -use- those physical mechanisms and context cues that already exist?  Why not design software that&#39;s aware of the very different places we move through?  Why not design software and devices tied to places?  That&#39;s what we&#39;re trying to do in a few very specific ways with PlaceSite.com, but there&#39;s so much more that can be done here.
Sean
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.cheesebikini.com&#34;&gt;Sean Savage&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-07-05T22:04:01-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-07-05T22:04:01-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progressive Trust</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/progressive_tru.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2004 23:42:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/08/progressive_tru.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I believe that as we evolve social software to better serve our needs and the needs of the groups that we are involved in, we need to figure out how to apply an understanding of how human groups behave and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One useful concept I use I call &#34;Progressive Trust&#34;. The basic idea is to model how trust works in the real world, between real people, rather then solely relying on mathematical or cryptographic trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how I typically explain progressive trust when I meet someone in-person at a conference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are now spending your most precious resource, that most unrenewable commodity -- time, in order to listen and understand what I have to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you do so? Because by the act of us being here in this common space, at this conference, you have found a very simple credential from me--that I&#39;m willing to spend time here in a place that you are interested in as well. In turn, I&#39;m willing to spend more time chatting with you for the same reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we continue to chat, and not move on to other people to discuss with? Because as we chat we are exchanging a number of credentials -- people we know in common, common interests, meaningful ideas, etc. We may also present credentials typically issued by others, like our business cards, or explain our relationship to the host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our unspoken agreement to continue discussion evolves, we typically will unconsciously check to see if others are listening, and adapt our conversation thereafter. If the discussion becomes more personal or serious, we will often find ourselves moving to a more private portion of the room. As our discussions become deeper, we may begin to speak of things that hint at a mutual respect for confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also early on we&#39;ll begin to scope out the nature of our time together. Is it only professional, or a potential friendship? Even intimate relationships go through this phase -- are we with someone who wants to date? Is is possible that a future date lead to something more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we agree to meet later to discuss more, before we meet again we may go authenticate some of the credentials given us. We&#39;ll not authenticate all of them, only enough to substantiate the level of assurance that we need for the risk we are taking (which may only be the future loss due to wasted time, but even that is a form of risk.) This authentication can consist simply of confirming information given, or it can be as complex as asking for an endorsement from a mutual colleague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our collaboration grows, we will find ourselves seeking more and more credentials, endorsements, etc., but they will not be enough. The next level of trust can only be established by experience of commitment -- for instance do we call back when we said we would? These tests typically start with small things, and then grow to larger things. At some point this may ultimately grow to form simple verbal contracts; over time richer, deeper social contracts are agreed upon that might not be written down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately we may bring in third parties to witness, and thus possibly enforce our mutual obligations, whether it is just having a mutual colleague view our handshake or friends see us kiss, or whether it is having a legal, signed document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point our mutual interests may be so large that we decide not just to collaborate, but to share assets, whether through a partnership, a corporation, or a marriage. Before this is complete there will be more credentials and authentication of those credentials (talk to former employees, engage in credit checks, visit each others&#39; families, take blood tests), endorsements, and less risky tests of the full contract (signing a term sheet, or a marriage engagement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the way human trust works. It also very similar to the way that groups work -- a corporation will collaborate with another corporation in the same way, starting with small trust, going on to tests, and leading ultimately up to partnerships and mergers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer trust rarely works the way that human trust does. It starts with mathematical proofs--that such and such a mathematical algorithm is extremely difficult, thus something built on it must also be difficult. These are then built on top of each other until a system is created. It often seeks a level of &#34;perfect trust&#34; that is rarely required by human trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why I chose to back the then nascent SSL (Secure Sockets Layer) Standard back in 1992-3, was that I felt that it much better mapped to the progressive trust model, and thus to human trust, then did its competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the SET standard was backed by all the major players--Visa, Mastercard, Microsoft, etc. However, it not only required strong mutual authentication, but it also require multiple authentications. HTTPS was backed by RSA, required digital signatures, preferably by both parties. SSL was not necessarily a clear winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But SSL starts out very simple--first it just connects two parties, then it establishes simple confidentiality between them. If one party wants more confidentiality, they can upgrade to a stronger algorithm. Then one party can request a credential from the other, or both can. Either party has the option to request authentication of those credentials. Ultimately you could use SSL to come close to the level trust that SET tried to establish, but SSL isn&#39;t generally used that way because the market decided that only one party needed to send a credential--the merchant. SSL also proved to be more flexible then for use just with web pages or credit cards -- now it is used for things like securing email, creating VPNs, and playing online games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus progressive trust is a useful conceptual model for understanding how trust might be built using online tools. Look at the tools that you are using now -- do they support various levels of trust, and a natural path between them? Or is trust more binary -- someone is only trusted, or not trusted. Are there implicit levels of progressive trust that are part of the culture of your group that might not embodied in the software itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progressive trust also maps well to an user-interface design technique called &lt;a href=&#34;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?ProgressiveDisclosure&#34;&gt;Progressive Disclosure&lt;/a&gt;. It sequences information and actions across several different windows in order not overwhelm the user. You disclose basic information and choices first, then revealing progressively more complex information and choices. Thus you help the user manage the complexity of the application. Navigating group interactions and culture is also complex, thus progressive trust allows you to hide some of initial complexity of the trust model behind your tools, and thus lower barriers of entry to your software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Ash Maurya&#39;s thought provoking Venn diagram in &#34;Beyond Social Networking&#34; (see http://www.wiredjournal.com/archives/000008.html) lists a number of modes or contexts that enable trust buildig in a relationship.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.skmurphy.com/&#34;&gt;Sean Murphy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-08-20T00:42:48-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-08-20T00:42:48-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Very cogent post, Christopher.  I think you&#39;ve hit upon what makes blogs so useful and novel in the computing world.  I wrote a response in my own blog:
http://frassle.rura.org/christopherAllenGets
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://frassle.rura.org/Directory/index?feed=1&#34;&gt;Shimon Rura&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-08-26T08:39:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-08-26T08:39:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Yet Sophisticated Group Page Editing</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2004 14:58:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been leading the design of a new Open Source collaboration tool called &lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index.php&#34;&gt;EditThisPagePHP&lt;a&gt;, which started &lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2003/12/editthispagephp.html&#34;&gt;six months ago&lt;/a&gt; and now is in beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal with EditThisPagePHP attempt to come close to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scripting.com/&#34;&gt;Dave Winer&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://davenet.scripting.com/discuss/msgReader$641?mode=topic&#34;&gt;visionary statement&lt;/a&gt; back in May of 1999:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;When I&#39;m writing for the web, and I&#39;m browsing my own site, every bit of text that I create has a button that says Edit This Page when I view it. When I click the button, a new page opens with the text in an HTML textarea. I edit. Click on Submit. The original page displays with the change. Three easy steps. The essential element is that *every* bit of text has this button. There can be no exceptions.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the fundamental level, EditThisPagePHP basically just let you remotely edit a single page. There are many situations where existing Wiki or Blog software is too complicated, or imposes too much structure. EditThisPagePHP lets you have total control over the HTML -- you can use sophisticated CSS layouts, or very simple HTML -- the software does not get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet in spite of this simplicity, EditThisPagePHP also uses ideas drawn from various Wiki, Blog, and CMS (content management system) technologies. Like Wikis, it supports an edit-this-page button, page history, page diffs, and can email users when pages change. Like Blogs, it supports optional user comments, trackbacks (both send and receive), and delivers two RSS feeds -- one for the current version of the page, and one with diffs. Like a CMS, it supports multiple roles, by default a reader, an editor, and a super-editor -- each with different privileges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally plan to use it for standards documents, lists, game rules, and home pages for various groups I collaborate with. I expect that others will use it anytime a group of people want to maintain a publicly accessible page together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some screenshots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/editpage.png&#34; title=&#34;Edit Page&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/tn_editpage.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; alt=&#34;Edit Page&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/history.png&#34; title=&#34;View History&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/tn_history.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; alt=&#34;View History&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/diffs.png&#34; title=&#34;Page Diffs&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/tn_diffs.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; alt=&#34;Page Diffs&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/trackbacks_comments.png&#34; title=&#34;Trackbacks and Comments&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/tn_trackbacks_comments.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; alt=&#34;Trackbacks and Comments&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/auth_msg.png&#34; title=&#34;Edit Authorization Message&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/index-images/tn_auth_msg.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; alt=&#34;Edit Authorization Message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Technical Details:&lt;/b&gt; EditThisPagePHP is written solely in PHP, and it currently works with PHP 4 and 5, and does not require SQL. Every revision makes a backup of itself, so no data can be lost. PHP is not allowed in the HTML text itself, to minimize security risks. Only two files are required: the core PHP script (editthispage.php) and a data file for your page. The core file can support as many pages as desired. The current version is &lt;a href=&#34;http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/editthispagephp/editthispage-0.5b2.zip?download&#34;&gt;0.5b2&lt;/a&gt;, is licensed under a BSD-style license, and there is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/demo_05b2/index.php&#34;&gt;working sandbox demo&lt;/a&gt; available to play with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future goals are to support more technical features, without losing the elegance and simplicity of the implementation. This may include limited Wiki TextFormatting or a simple WYSIWYG editor, HTML-tidy, some user-interface enhancements, etc. A complete list is available on our &lt;a href=&#34;http://editthispagephp.sourceforge.net/home/wishlist.php&#34;&gt;wishlist&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;m amused at the talk of prior art and 1999 visions, the very first web client (1990) had EditThisPage built in - the browser was the editor. The same approach is still taken by browsers like Amaya.
http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/WorldWideWeb.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://dannyayers.com&#34;&gt;Danny&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-02T05:23:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-02T05:23:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;m amused at the talk of prior art and 1999 visions, the very first web client (1990) had EditThisPage built in - the browser was the editor. The same approach is still taken by browsers like Amaya.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;alex&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-06T10:59:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-06T10:59:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2004/05/simple_yet_soph.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>