<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/voting/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/voting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dyads &amp; Triads — The Smallest Teams</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:16:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(by Christopher Allen with Elyn Andersson and Shannon Appelcline)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.BGI.edu&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;BGIedu Logo&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;100&#34; src=&#34;http://www.bgi.edu/files/BGI-Logomark-CMYK.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; width=&#34;100&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Two years ago, the Bainbridge Graduate Institute (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.BGI.edu&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Bainbridge Graduate Institute&#34;&gt;www.BGI.edu&lt;/a&gt;) faculty gathered to radically reinvent their sustainable business curriculum for the next decade. Our goal was not only to update course content, but also to significantly update how the material was taught. We wished to make our teaching process (our pedagogy) more interactive and also more effective for students graduating into a 21st-century work environment, where people increasingly work in teams-both online and offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a specialist in group interactions, I was asked by the faculty whether formal graduate student study groups (called &amp;quot;Study Buddies&amp;quot;) should consist of two people or of three. I did not have an easy answer to this question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My expertise with group dynamics comes from professional experience as an entrepreneur and from considerable experience both building online communities and helping others to do the same. Through these processes, I&amp;#39;ve seen how groups of people act differently at different sizes. As I discussed in my previous blog post on Group Thresholds [&lt;a href=&#34;#Allen&#34;&gt;Allen&lt;/a&gt;], there are pros and cons associated with different group sizes. However, the smallest group that I spoke of in that article was the &amp;#39;working team size&amp;#39;, which is a group of four to nine members (but ideally about seven). I didn&amp;#39;t talk about groups consisting of less than four members-specifically dyads (a group of two people) and triads (a group of three people)-and that was what the BGIedu faculty was now interested in learning more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first inclination when considering BGIedu&amp;#39;s request was to say that triads would be the best size for study groups, but I wasn&amp;#39;t sure. I knew from my past research on group size that a dyad has a significantly different behavior than any other small groups. However, I wasn&amp;#39;t certain if triads should also be considered on their own, or if they were just the low end of one of those &amp;#39;work teams&amp;#39;, which I&amp;#39;d always thought of as containing four to nine members. Triads were a hole in my research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to dig deeper into this question by engaging my teaching assistant Elyn Andersson and my writing partner Shannon Appelcline to help me investigate further. This post is the fruit of our research and our discussions about dyads and triads. We hope it might help you decide whether a dyad or a triad is the better team size for groups that you are working in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;choosing&#34; name=&#34;choosing&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Choosing between Dyads and Triads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c3859329f970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pythagorian Dyad - Public Domain&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c3859329f970b&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c3859329f970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Pythagorian Dyad - Public Domain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Before I share with you the details of our investigation, I want to be clear that dyads, triads, and small &amp;#39;working team&amp;#39; groups can all be effective. Any challenge faced by groups of these sizes can be overcome by a good process, teamwork, training, or just positive energy. However, my thesis is that certain sizes of groups are better for certain purposes-and when a group size is selected appropriately it will require less energy and thus be more likely to be productive when the inevitable group challenges occur. When choosing among a dyad, a triad, or a working team, the important thing to focus on is thus the intent in forming the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the groups being considered by BGIedu, the faculty felt that the students taking the new curriculum needed three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More formal support for studying (i.e. not ad hoc study teams);&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of emotional support in that support structure; and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A system where the members of a study group would help each other to keep their commitments to study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last requirement - that members of these study teams would be accountable to each other without one student just taking up the slack of another - was the toughest one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, working teams of 4-9 people were too large for our purposes. Teams this size are rarely intimate enough to support the needs of individuals. In addition, research shows that they are poor at supporting accountability. That&amp;#39;s because working teams of 4-9 are very vulnerable to social loafing (i.e., slackers)-except when the tasks assigned to these working teams are highly independent (i.e. an entrepreneurial team that has different members focused on different topics, such as management, development, operations, marketing and sales) or when they require high diversity. An upcoming blog will cover this topic in more depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c38593410970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pythagorian Triad - Public Domain&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c38593410970b&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c38593410970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Pythagorian Triad - Public Domain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Removing working teams left the question of dyad vs. triad - which our research would show were both very different from working teams. Triads ultimately fit BGIedu&amp;#39;s particular need better. That was primarily due to advantages of accountability and cohesion, combined with some emotional support. However, some simple numerical properties of triads also prove useful: they have elemental diversity because they&amp;#39;re up to 50% more diverse than dyads; and if someone misses a team meeting the other two-thirds of the team can still benefit. For all of these reasons, my recommendation to the BGIedu faculty was that these formal study teams be formed in triads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dyads, however, are quite appropriate for a variety of other purposes, and should not be dismissed. I&amp;#39;ll be talking of some of their advantages before proceeding on to the lessons learned about triads themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;dyad&#34; name=&#34;dyad&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Dyad&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has had experience with dyads. The first social experience of anyone&amp;#39;s life is a dyadic relationship - that between a mother and her unborn child. This parent-child relationship continues once the child is born. Overall, dyads are the most common social group; they are seen everywhere, in personal, academic and business relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/94611163@N00/683866337/&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Great Guitar Duo — Photo by Tom706 CC-BY-NC-ND&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1108/683866337_4dd654b650_n.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;To decide if a dyad is the best group size for your needs, it is again important to focus on the purpose of the group. A number of interesting characteristics of dyads - some benefits and some limitations - make them unique from triads and other larger group sizes, among them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotional Support&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commitment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoned Agreement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power Inequality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Group Accountability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;emotional_support&#34; name=&#34;emotional_support&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Emotional Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been some academic studies [&lt;a href=&#34;#Taylor&#34;&gt;Taylor&lt;/a&gt;] that suggest that it&amp;#39;s easier to be open and share within dyads. The research has shown that people feel safer about revealing personal and intimate information in a dyad than they do when a third person is added to the group. As a result, disclosure rates increase when people are put into dyads as compared to triads. Furthermore, adding a third person to a group causes its members to be more socially conscious, making it harder for members to listen to the conversation and at the same time be aware of their own thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together it&amp;#39;s this trust level (allowing for disclosure) and this focus level (allowing for better listening) that make dyads much stronger for emotional support than triads or larger teams. If the intent of a group is to have an intimate and fully open space, or if the work of the group is emotional in nature, this might make dyads a better choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though dyads are clearly more effective for providing emotional support, triads can still offer that as well under the right conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;commitment&#34; name=&#34;commitment&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Commitment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This intimacy and confidentiality of a dyad helps its members to build strong team dynamics relatively quickly. The two individuals not only will have formed a trust bond more easily than three or more individuals could, but they generally will have a better ratio of time to performance outcomes compared to groups of larger sizes, in part because less time is spent maintaining the team relationship itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a triad or larger group, the group would need to put effort towards team work over task work and thus less time is put towards performing the task. In other words, more resources would be spent on relating to a teammate than on finishing a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;reasoned_agreement&#34; name=&#34;reasoned_agreement&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Reasoned Agreement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most unique element of dyads is that they are the only group size in which one voice is paired against another voice equally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you were in dyad in which you did not agree on an issue? Most likely, you and the other individual spent some considerable time trying to convince the other of your reasons, and the outcome was one of two things: you either both stuck with your opinion and walked away, or one of you changed your mind after hearing the other&amp;#39;s ideas and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because members can&amp;#39;t &amp;#39;vote&amp;#39;, a dyad is either in agreement or disagreement, which forces a longer deliberation for tasks when consensus is required. There are times when you want a small group to deliberate deeply, and dyads are ideal for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;power_inequality&#34; name=&#34;power_inequality&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Power Inequality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though dyads have several advantages, they can also bring with them a few additional problems - one of which is a power inequality of knowledge that would be detrimental within some teams. For some tasks, this could offset the benefits of having a more intimate small group. For my BGIedu groups, I was concerned that it might prevent some students from benefiting academically from the study exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic has been addressed in a study &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160289604000972&#34;&gt;[&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#Day&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Day&#34;&gt;Day&lt;/a&gt;] that compared homogeneous teams that were entirely high-ability or low-ability to heterogeneous dyads of mixed abilities. The study found that while high-ability people tested better individually after learning the material in a dyad with another high-ability team mate, low-ability people did not gain much benefit from studying in a dyad with a high-ability team member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was somewhat surprising. A student with more knowledge of a subject should be able to mentor a student with less knowledge, therefore creating a true dyad study partner. However, this study showed that this was not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study also argued against another common conception. One might assume that two high-ability team members could learn more together, when they could bounce ideas off of each other, than they could alone. However, this was again not the case: high-ability individuals performed better after learning alone than after learning with another high-ability team member! Only homogeneous low-ability teammates performed better after being in a dyad than alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study pushed me toward triads for study teams at BGIedu, as dyads would not be large enough to guarantee high performance outcomes; the teams would always consist of one higher performing student and one lower performing student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;group_accountability&#34; name=&#34;group_accountability&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Group Accountability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another disadvantage of dyads shows up in the area of accountability. The simplest version of this issue can be shown in this question: if one teammate says she did the majority of the work, while the other teammate says the work was shared 50/50, who was correct? A tougher question: if they both say that the work was shared 50/50, how is a third party able to determine if this actually was true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elyn, my teaching assistant, interned in a high school in Seattle while working towards her Master&amp;#39;s in Teaching. Her experiences highlight this problem. In today&amp;#39;s educational model, collaborative learning is highly valued, and Elyn worked to incorporate in-class group work into many of her lessons. When assessing the students&amp;#39; group projects, however, she found that it was difficult to determine if the students shared the work equitably or if some of the students rode on the hard work of their partners. In some cases, Elyn doubted that the work was split equally. In particular, she found that if she let the students choose their own partners, the students were more likely to say that &amp;#39;both&amp;#39; did the work, rather than tell the teacher their friend slacked off on the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent study [&lt;a href=&#34;#Alkaslassy&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Alkaslassy&lt;/a&gt;]&amp;#0160;supports Elyn&amp;#39;s experience. In it, students working on a paired group assignment were asked to allocate the percent of work done between the pair. 86% of the students assigned equal credit between the two individuals in the group. At a surface level, one could presume that each party performed half the work and was honest in their assignment of credit. However, Elyn and I believe that in some dyadic relationships, friendship can become an overriding factor and that in those situations, students are more likely to allocate equal credit because of this friendship, not because of true equity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the psychological field, this relates to a well-known cognitive bias called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egocentric_bias&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia: Egocentric Bias&#34;&gt;egocentric bias&lt;/a&gt;, where an individual will claim more responsibility for group action then an independent observer would credit them. Although this is most often discussed for larger groups, in dyads a member might rate their own efforts as being half of the effort when in fact is it is less. Thus in academic group projects, it can sometimes be more effective to have the students rate their peer rather than themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though group accountability can be a disadvantage for dyads, it improves when you have triads, thanks in part to a triad&amp;#39;s inability to devolve. This, as it turns out, would be another comparative advantage that helped me choose triads over dyads for BGIedu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;triads&#34; name=&#34;triads&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Triads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/yaketyyakyak/5991422366/in/photostream/&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Fernando&amp;#39;s Kitchen, Cambridge 30-07-11 —&amp;#0160;Photo by Dave Catchpole CC-BY&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6123/5991422366_6301a83c43_n.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;There are a number of interesting characteristics of triads that make them different from dyads and also from small &amp;#39;working team&amp;#39; groups. I&amp;#39;ll talk about three of them in this article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inability to Devolve&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elemental Diversity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;inability_to_devolve&#34; name=&#34;inability_to_devolve&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Inability to Devolve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have experienced what happens when a party gets too busy or too noisy - the size of the conversation groups get smaller. If you are having an informal dinner for seven, sometimes the conversation will include the entire table. However while people are eating the conversation will typically devolve into smaller groups: four people at one end of the table will being having one conversation, while the remaining three will be talking at the end other. Sometimes one person will be left out of any conversation, but studies show that with small groups this is less likely to happen. We have a natural tendency not to want to exclude or reject individuals unjustly, so such a singleton will usually find a place in one conversation or another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working teams also have this natural tendency to devolve when confronted with external challenges (of which noise is one of the simpler ones) or internal challenges (such as differences of opinion), only reuniting when those challenges are resolved. A team of six can devolve gracefully a number of different ways: a three and a three; a four and a two; or three groups of two. Teams of five can devolve into teams of two and three. A team of four can devolve into two teams of two. In all of these cases the devolution does not exclude any individual&amp;#39;s voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a triad can not devolve without excluding someone. Triads thus have a lot of subtle pressure to try to keep the group together, so that no individual is explicitly rejected - except for a good reason. This leads to more accountability for the individuals in the group, compared to teams of two where the dyadic nature of the group can override liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;voting&#34; name=&#34;voting&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Unconscious Voting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dyad&amp;#39;s inability to vote was an advantage of that group size, and thus issues that require deeper deliberation are often better with dyads. However, you sometimes don&amp;#39;t want as much deliberation. You want fast action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that we unconsciously gauge each others&amp;#39; opinions in a small group very quickly, and even more so with a triad. This means that a triad seems to be able to come to at least some decision very fast. There are many cases where this can be very useful - if that is the intent of your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an personal example, I saw a presentation in the early 1990s from the Apple Human Interface Group (HIG) about their survey of how users colored &amp;quot;folders&amp;quot; on the Macintosh. The result was that there was little commonality - everyone colored folders differently for different reasons. Afterward, I met with the team and suggested that that if they instead asked teams of three to decide how to color code folders that they used together, then the results from all the different teams would have much more commonality. This suggestion ended up getting me a consulting job with Apple HIG, and shows how a triad can quickly create successful performance outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Triads are not the only group size that can vote easily - all odd size groups can - but I believe the voting of a triad to be fundamentally different because the voting can be so unconscious and informal that the members are not even aware of it. This can be useful, but it can also cause problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was just starting my business, I was doing a lot of work with a company formed by two partners who had a 50/50 stock split in their company. Theirs was a good partnership; they had very different but complementary skills and worked well and profitably together. As a fellow entrepreneur, I was a peer to both them, and we were developing a new product line together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when I worked with them on this product line, I saw that I&amp;#39;d changed their very successful dyad to a triad, and I thus became a tiebreaker in many of their business decisions - including business decisions on issues that had nothing to do with our joint product. This was caused by a shift in power: one partner might ask me a question about marketing rather than asking his partner (who knew marketing), and then it would become our opinion against the remaining partner&amp;#39;s. Conversely, I found the marketing partner asking me to side with him on development questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this quite troubling; a more manipulative person could have controlled or broken that relationship by always breaking the ties in their own favor. In our case, we never shipped the product line and went our separate ways. I couldn&amp;#39;t help but think it might have been because my unofficial &amp;quot;vote&amp;quot; was causing problems in their partnership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When getting a result is the purpose of a team, a triad is better than a dyad as it allows for this voting to take place. As I mentioned to BGIedu, a triad can have a two-to-one vote, allowing a better chance at task accomplishment. Task accomplishment is also achieved because triads stay on topic better than dyads due of this voting ratio: if one member of a dyad decides to go off topic, it is easy for the other to follow his or her lead. In a a triad, two out of the three members would need to &amp;#39;agree&amp;#39; to follow an unrelated discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;elemental_diversity&#34; name=&#34;elemental_diversity&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Elemental Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final advantage of triads when compared to dyads is that the knowledge base of the group is larger. I saw this issue clearly in my recent Social Web for Social Change class at BGIedu, where I changed the team size from two to three, and immediately saw a growth in elemental diversity that benefited the groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this class, I have the students participate in an exercise on personal branding. I originally had the students pair up in teams of two, effectively giving each student a &amp;#39;branding buddy&amp;#39; to help them form their personal brand and to give and receive feedback. In the last year, however, I decided to change this dyad to a triad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, these groups followed the same methods I used for dyads: one person would self-brand themselves to a second person in the group, who would then echo back what they thought they heard the first person say, using their own words. However, it is difficult for two people to really hear the similarities and differences between what they said and what they heard. The third person thus became a neutral sounding board who told both individuals that spoke what they said. Together, all three could figure out the similarities and differences between the statements. After consensus is reached, all three students switch roles. I call this the Echo Exercise, and it shows how triads can be beneficial at times when the natural characteristics of dyads don&amp;#39;t lead to optimum results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;finalnotes&#34; name=&#34;finalnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Final Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Triple-Spiral-Symbol-filled.svg&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Tripal Spiral —&amp;#0160;from Wikimedia Commons, Public Domain&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c2/Triple-Spiral-Symbol-filled.svg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; width=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;As it happens, this article was created by a triad. It wasn&amp;#39;t purposeful, nor was it meant to show off the findings of this article. Instead, the triad evolved naturally because it proved the best group size for writing this piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came up with the initial concept for the article and wrote out the problem and introduction. Elyn then did considerable research and wrote up a rough draft of her findings. To that point, we were a committed dyad, working together in an organic way. However, we also had an article that felt like it was in two parts. That&amp;#39;s when I had Shannon join us. He reorganized the article, unified its voice, and produced a final draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it wasn&amp;#39;t purposeful, you can see the advantages of triads just from this example. Most notably, our triad made great use of elemental diversity. Though I held the core ideas and concepts for the article, Elyn provided the research expertise and Shannon provided the editorial expertise that were required to complete it. Voting also came into the equation (in the unconscious way that it tends to in triads) when Shannon effectively &amp;quot;broke the tie&amp;quot; of two different writing styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, this triad has fallen apart. It&amp;#39;s something that was created for a specific project and with all of our other tasks, we didn&amp;#39;t have room for it going forward. Teams breaking apart is natural. Sometimes it happens under normal conditions (as was the case with this triad), and sometimes it happens as a result of unhealthy conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not give BGIedu any advice at the time about the termination of a team, although it will eventually come up: some teams will end badly, and members of these groups may leave with an impression that a triad is a bad group size, even though the size did not lead the group to ending in an unhealthy way. Perhaps the groups should be counseled, or perhaps the members should jump right back on the triad horse ... but that&amp;#39;s a topic for another article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, I&amp;#39;d like to open the conversation up to you. Have you had experiences in either dyads or triads that you would like to share? Were you one of the BGIedu students in a Study Buddy triad? Did the experiences match the studies shown here or did you have an experience that differed? We invite your comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reference:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Allen&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Allen, Christopher (2008) &lt;em&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part One: Group Thresholds&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#0160;Life With Alacrity (blog) (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;/2008/09/group-threshold.html&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Alkaslassy&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Alkaslassy, E. (2011)&lt;em&gt; How often do students working in two-person teams report that work was shared equitably?&lt;/em&gt; Assessment &amp;amp; Evaluation in Higher Education, 36. 367-375. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02602930903428700#preview&#34;&gt;(http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02602930903428700#preview&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Baer&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Baer, M. (2010) &lt;em&gt;The Strength-of-Weak-Ties Perspective on Creativity: A comprehensive Examination and Extension.&lt;/em&gt; Journal of Applied Psychology, 95 592-601. &lt;a href=&#34;http://apps.olin.wustl.edu/workingpapers/pdf/2010-02-008.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://apps.olin.wustl.edu/workingpapers/pdf/2010-02-008.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Basden&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Basden, B.H., Basden, D.R., Henry, S. (2000) &lt;em&gt;Costs and Benefits of Collaborative Remembering&lt;/em&gt;. Applied Cognitive Psychology, 1. 497-507. &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://124.42.15.59/ck/2011-03/165/030/165/530/Research%20ArticleCosts%20and%20benefits%20of%20collaborative%20remembering.pdf&#34;&gt;(ftp://124.42.15.59/ck/2011-03/165/030/165/530/Research%20ArticleCosts%20and%20benefits%20of%20collaborative%20remembering.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Bertucci&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Bertucci, A., Conte, S., Johnson, D.W., Johnson, R.T. (2010) &lt;em&gt;The Impact of Size of Cooperative Group on Achievement, Social Support and Self-Esteem&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of General Psychology, 137(2), 256-272. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20718226&#34;&gt;(http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20718226_&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Blaskovich&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Blaskovich, J.L. (2008) &lt;em&gt;Exploring the Effect of Distance: An Experimental Investigation of Virtual Collaboration, Social Loafing and Group Decisions&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Information Systems, 22 27-46. &lt;a href=&#34;http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;amp;id=JINFE3000022000001000027000001&amp;amp;idtype=cvips&amp;amp;gifs=yes&amp;amp;ref=no&#34;&gt;(http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;amp;id=JINFE3000022000001000027000001&amp;amp;idtype=cvips&amp;amp;gifs=yes&amp;amp;ref=no)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Day&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day, E.A., Arthur, W., Bell, S.T., Edwards, B.D., Bennett, W., Mendoza, J.L., &amp;amp; Tubre, T.C. (2005). &lt;em&gt;Ability -based pairing strategies in the team-based training of a complex skill; Does the intelligence of your training partner matter?&lt;/em&gt; Intelligence, 33, 39-65. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160289604000972&#34;&gt;(http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160289604000972)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;De_Cremer&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;De Cremer, D., Leonardelli, G. J. (2003). &lt;em&gt;Cooperation in Social Dilemmas and the Need to Belong: The Moderating Effect of Group Size&lt;/em&gt;. Group Dynamics: Theory, Research and Practice, 2, 168-174 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rotman.utoronto.ca/geoffrey.leonardelli/2003GD.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://www.rotman.utoronto.ca/geoffrey.leonardelli/2003GD.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Laughlin&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Laughlin, P.R., Hatch, E.C., Silver, J.S., Boh, L. (2006) &lt;em&gt;Groups perform better than the best individuals on letters-to-numbers problems: effects of group size&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 4. 644-651. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agileadvice.com/archives/Research%20on%20Group%20Effectiveness%20vs%20Individuals.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://www.agileadvice.com/archives/Research%20on%20Group%20Effectiveness%20vs%20Individuals.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Markam&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Markam, S.E., Dansereau, F. Jr., Alutto, J.A. (1982) &lt;em&gt;Group size and Absenteeism Rates: A Longitudinal Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Academy of Management Journal, 25 921-927. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/pss/256108&#34;&gt;(http://www.jstor.org/pss/256108)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Seibold&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Seibold, D., Kang, P., Gailliard, B., Jahn, J.. &lt;em&gt;Communication that Damages Teamwork: The Dark Side of Teams&lt;/em&gt;. Conference Papers - International Communication Association; 2008 Annual Meeting. 1-32. &lt;a href=&#34;http://citation.allacademic.com//meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/2/3/0/5/1/pages230513/p230513-2.php&#34;&gt;(http://citation.allacademic.com//meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/2/3/0/5/1/pages230513/p230513-2.php)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Smith&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Smith, S. and Haythorn, W.W. (1972) &lt;em&gt;Effects of Compatibility, Crowding, Group Size, and leadership seniority on stress, anxiety hostility and annoyance in isolated groups&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 22, 67-79 &lt;a href=&#34;http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;amp;id=1972-24882-001&#34;&gt;(http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;amp;id=1972-24882-001)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Taylor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Taylor, R. B. De Soto, C.B., Lieb, R., &lt;em&gt;Sharing Secrets: Disclosure and Discretion in Dyads and Triads&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 37, 1196-1203. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbtaylor.net/pub_jpsp_1979.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://www.rbtaylor.net/pub_jpsp_1979.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I just discovered your site, and I&#39;m really enjoying your posts.
I am an Organizational Leadership student through Fort Hays State University, and this is a fascinating topic.
I can definitely see the point of the disadvantage of voting. Dyads are forced to use consensus decision-making, unless the power differential is so wide that unilateral decisions are made by the dyad&#39;s autocrat.
Consensus, of course, can take a little longer, but being the default for the Dyad, it makes disagreements automatically covert into brainstorming sessions to find solutions that satisfy both parties. Often, these solutions will be creative and superior to either original idea.
Triads, by virtue of the odd number, CAN employ democracy to make decisions, but the question is-- SHOULD they? A Triad can still opt to employ consensus. If it chooses democracy, it can speed decisions, but there is no requirement for democracy to govern the Triad&#39;s decisions. If they opt for consensus, they can once more engage in creative problem-solving that satisfies all parties.
A consensus-based Triad has all the other advantages of a Triad, without the down-side.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Kevin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2014-11-05T12:19:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2014-11-05T12:19:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems for Collective Choice</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2005 16:03:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.7em;&#34;&gt;by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline&#34;&gt;[Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt; is a friend and colleague of mine at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;, an online game company. Over the last few years we&#39;ve had many discussions about how decisions are made, and how our society collectively makes choices. The origin of these discussions have varied from &amp;quot;what makes this board game work?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how can we give our players more control of our online games?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how do we make decisions in our company?&amp;quot;, and of course &amp;quot;how did we collectively make such a mess of decision making in America?&amp;quot;. This article, and some followup articles, summarize our thoughts on these topics, and will be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_178.phtml&#34;&gt;jointly posted&lt;/a&gt; in Shannon&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT.shtml&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities&lt;/a&gt; online games column at Skotos.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Peoplearoundthesun&#34; title=&#34;Peoplearoundthesun&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/peoplearoundthesun.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt; Collective choice systems have been around for a long time. Since at least the birth of democracy in ancient Greece people have made joint decisions about important issues, and since at least the knightly tournaments of the late Middle Age people have competed to be ranked against their peers. Today Western culture especially values diversity of input when implementing any type of choice, believing that wide input from a variety of people provides the fairest result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet expands this long history of collective choice. However, as we bring collective choice systems onto the Internet, quantifying and programming them, we discover the need to be more analytical and more methodical in the techniques used. Thus we&#39;re beginning to learn that we don&#39;t know nearly as much about these collective choice systems as we should. There is a need to analyze and study them further, to understand their strengths and weaknesses, and to evaluate their social impact. Fortunately, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/10/tracing_the_evo.html&#34;&gt;social software&lt;/a&gt; and online games on the Internet provides the perfect &lt;em&gt;petri dish&lt;/em&gt; for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before any analysis can occur, however, there is a need for a categorization of systems and a definition of terms. That is the purpose of this article: to lay out at least some of the ways in which collective choices can be made, to organize them, to define them, and to briefly consider them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, there seem to be three methods of collective choice, divided by the intended result: &lt;em&gt;selection&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;opinion&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;comparison&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;selection_systems&#34;&gt;Selection Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selection systems allow for the purposeful choice between multiple items. There are many types of selection systems, but two in particular, &lt;em&gt;representative systems&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;deliberative systems&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;consensus systems&lt;/em&gt; are worth noting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=369,height=393,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/19thamend.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;159&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/19thamend.jpg&#34; title=&#34;19thamend&#34; alt=&#34;19thamend&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;representative_systems&#34;&gt;Representative Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a representative system, individuals cast a ballot for someone who will represent their interests. They&#39;re by definition &lt;em&gt;voting systems&lt;/em&gt; and the heart of any &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republicanism&#34;&gt;Republican&lt;/a&gt; system of government. When you&#39;re voting for a president, prime minister, senator, congressman, director, or board member, that&#39;s representative voting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most representative voting a winner is selected by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality&#34;&gt;plurality&lt;/a&gt;, meaning the winner had more votes than any other candidate. This works well in a simple two-member election, but begins to fall apart if there are multiple candidates, because similar candidates can steal votes from each other, and thus allow a candidate with less popular ideas to be elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest solution is to require a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majority&#34;&gt;majority&lt;/a&gt; victory, meaning that one winner must have at least 50% of the votes. Some places in the United States use this system for their representative elections, holding a first election, eliminating all but the two biggest vote-getters, then holding a new election between these two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_election&#34;&gt;primary-based election system&lt;/a&gt;, wherein all like-minded candidates compete against each other before participating in the real election. This requires buy-in from all like-minded candidates, however, and recent U.S. elections with third-party candidates like Ralph Nader and Ross Perot show the flaws in a voluntary primary system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many other types of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voting_systems&#34;&gt;voting systems&lt;/a&gt; are possible, most of which allow voters to select multiple candidates at the same time. These systems then eliminate the lowest ranked candidates and give their votes to others based upon those voter selections. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/irv.gif&#34; title=&#34;Irv&#34; alt=&#34;Irv&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRV&#34;&gt;Instant Runoff Voting&lt;/a&gt;, or IRV, is a fairly commonly used multiple candidate system (though not necessarily the best one). It&#39;s technically a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_Transferable_Vote&#34;&gt;single transferable vote&lt;/a&gt; preferential voting system. Wikipedia describes the process like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Each voter ranks at least one candidate in order of preference.&lt;br /&gt; ...&lt;br /&gt; First choices are tallied. If no candidate has the support of a majority of voters, the candidate with the least support is eliminated. A second round of counting takes place, with the votes of supporters of the eliminated candidate now counting for their second choice candidate. After a candidate is eliminated, he or she may not receive any more votes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This process of counting and eliminating is repeated until one candidate has over half the votes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s simple to understand, but also flawed. That&#39;s because every voting system ultimately has &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow&#39;s_impossibility_theorem&#34;&gt;flaw&lt;/a&gt; in it, as is evidenced by the fact that given the same conditions the different systems will often declare different winners. Different systems may also allow voters to &amp;quot;game&amp;quot; the system in different ways. This is often called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tactical_voting&#34;&gt;tactical voting&lt;/a&gt; or strategic voting. Similar to analyzing various &amp;quot;attacks&amp;quot; when studying a cryptosystem, looking at which tactical voting approaches each voting system is vulnerable to helps you evaluate the voting systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, one type of tactical voting that can be used against an Instant Runoff Vote is the push-over strategy, which Wikipedia describes as this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Push-over is a type of strategic voting in which a voter ranks a perceived weak alternative higher, but not in the hopes of getting it elected. This primarily occurs in runoff voting when a voter already believes that his favored candidate will make it to the next round - the voter then ranks an unpreferred, but easily beatable, candidate higher so that his preferred candidate can win later. A United States analogy would be voters of one party crossing over to vote in the other party&#39;s primary to nominate a candidate who will be easy for their favorite to beat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in an IRV election between Bush, Gore, and Nader, Democrats might rank Nader over Bush. The hope would be that this would give Nader enough votes to keep him from being eliminated, thus knocking Bush out instead in the first round. Afterward the Republican Bush votes transfer to the less progressive Gore, rather than the fringe Nader, allowing Gore to beat the &amp;quot;pushover&amp;quot; Nader when they couldn&#39;t have faced Bush in a straight-up fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There several different tactical voting &amp;quot;attacks&amp;quot; against various representative voting systems. One of the technically better multiple-candidate voting methods is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condorcet_method&#34;&gt;condorcet method&lt;/a&gt; for voting. It&#39;s immune to most tactical voting strategies and more people would consider its result &amp;quot;correct&amp;quot;, but unfortunately it is much harder on the voters, who have to rank every single candidate. Maybe if we can create a better Internet user-interface to condorcet voting we can make this more sophisticated representative voting system more broadly available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;deliberative_systems&#34;&gt;Deliberative Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a deliberative system, individuals directly make a decision, rather than selecting a representative to do so. Deliberative systems do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have to include voting, and the subcategory of &lt;em&gt;consensus systems&lt;/em&gt; described below technically don&#39;t, however most modern deliberative sytems do. A deliberative system is the heart of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DEMOCRACY&#34;&gt;true democracy&lt;/a&gt;. Traditionally it&#39;s been relatively unfeasible because voters were not expected to be educated enough to make governmental decisions and because they didn&#39;t have the time or capability to regularly decide on issues. The spread of the Internet alleviates at least the latter problem, since millions of people can now simultaneously decide on any issue if they so desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States the best known deliberative system is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Initiative&#34;&gt;initiative&lt;/a&gt; system found in some states, including California. It allows for issues to be put directly before the voters through the submission of sufficient signatures, and then allows the voters to pass or fail those issues, based on either &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality&#34;&gt;plurality&lt;/a&gt; (most votes), &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majority&#34;&gt;majority&lt;/a&gt; (at least 50% of votes), or else &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supermajority&#34;&gt;super majority&lt;/a&gt; (some percentage of votes in excess of 51%). In California, for example, 66% approval is required for new tax initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/constitution_signing.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=540,height=350,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;129&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Constitution_signing&#34; title=&#34;Constitution_signing&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/constitution_signing.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The United States constitution defines a large and very complex deliberative system. It creates three bodies of government to support deliberation and voting, and uses a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checks_and_Balances#Checks_and_balances&#34;&gt;checks and balances&lt;/a&gt; systems in order to allow different branches to have different effects upon a vote. The main voting is done by the legislature, which requires two &lt;em&gt;pluralities&lt;/em&gt; from two different groups of people to pass a vote. Then the executive branch has a singular opportunity to veto legislature, which then requires a &lt;em&gt;super majority&lt;/em&gt; (here, 66%) to override that veto. Once a law is established, the judicial department may by &lt;em&gt;plurality&lt;/em&gt; vote to declare that legislation unconstitutional, but that may be overcome by an even greater &lt;em&gt;super majority&lt;/em&gt; (typically, 66% of each legislature + 75% of the state governments) who want to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Constitution#Provisions_for_amendment&#34;&gt;amend the constitution&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constitution also shows how deliberation can span beyond simple voting because of the fact that it includes specific rules for how to debate, when debate can be closed, etc. In today&#39;s very fractured congress, however, it&#39;s unclear if individuals ever are actually swayed by deliberations in the floor of the legislature, or if they&#39;ve already decided to follow their party lines or their specific interests, long before they entered the Capitol buildings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smaller example of a true deliberative system, based on guiding discussions as much as holding votes, is found in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertsrules.org/&#34;&gt;Robert&#39;s Rules of Order&lt;/a&gt;, a guide for conducting meetings. These rules detail explicit methods not just for voting, but also for the deliberation and discussion surrounding the voting. Various &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;minority&lt;/em&gt; votes can be taken to allow for certain actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because deciding directly upon ideas rather than just voting for representatives can have a greater effect upon a community, the deliberative systems may need to be more complex to avoid abuse, as evidenced by the complexities of the U.S. Government and Robert&#39;s Rule of Order. However, these very complexities can make these systems more prone to purposeful gaming. The benefits and deficits of more complex deliberative systems have not yet been fully studied, nor have there been as much analysis of &amp;quot;attacks&amp;quot; against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/consensus_1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;141&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/consensus_1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Consensus_1&#34; alt=&#34;Consensus_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;consensus_systems&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;consensus_systems&#34;&gt;Consensus Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In consensus systems people jointly come to a consensus as a group through group interactions. This sort of decision making theoretically avoids the &amp;quot;tyranny of the majority&amp;quot; and likewise can produce more informed decision making. It&#39;s a variant of the broader &lt;em&gt;deliberative systems&lt;/em&gt;, but one with more group and less individual power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of consensual selection is cabinet government as laid out under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster_system&#34;&gt;Westminster System&lt;/a&gt;. Wikipedia describes it as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; Members of the Cabinet are collectively seen as responsible for government policy. All Cabinet decisions are made by consensus, a vote is never taken in a Cabinet meeting. All ministers, whether senior and in the Cabinet, or junior ministers, must support the policy of the government publicly regardless of any private reservations. If a minister does not agree with a decision he, or she, can resign from the government; as did several British ministers over the 2003 Invasion of Iraq. This means that in the Westminster system of government the cabinet always collectively decides all decisions and all ministers are responsible for arguing in favour of any decision made by the cabinet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_decision-making#Quaker-based_consensus&#34;&gt;Quaker-based consensus&lt;/a&gt; offers a similar example. Herein a facilitator helps to identify disagreements and agreements to move a discussion forward until an end result is embraced by all individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final note, it&#39;s important to differentiate consensus from coercion. The end result of unanimity isn&#39;t the sole definition of a consensus system, nor is it entirely required. What is required is a more open and thoughtful selection process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;opinion_systems&#34;&gt;Opinion Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Poll&#34; title=&#34;Poll&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/poll.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;Opinion systems are a clear subsidiary category to selection systems. An opinion system&#39;s main use is as a decision indicator, to show how people will decide or did decide in a representative system, a deliberative system, or both. Current opinion systems tend to be oriented toward actual votes, as opposed to more freeform selection systems (though the &lt;em&gt;delphic polling system&lt;/em&gt; shows a more freeform version of the category itself). Opinion systems tend to be push-based (meaning people are asked for their opinions rather than actively offering them), but this isn&#39;t required. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All opinion systems tend to have the same general problem, which is figuring out how to use scientific means to determine the actual results of a decision. This means massaging respondent numbers to offset categories of people more or less likely to vote to try and generate the actual results. For example, one 1998 poll showed that 62% of Republicans were absolutely certain they were going to vote, while only 51% of Independents could say the same. This means that every Republican voter a poll contacted in that year might have been weighted about 1.2x over every Independent contacted. Of course the actual calculations are much more complex than that, since they tend to depend upon traditional voter turnout and lots of analysis, but the core idea is sound, which is that every polled individual should &lt;u&gt;not&lt;/u&gt; be considered equal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All opinion system results tend to be rated with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margin_of_error&#34;&gt;margins of error&lt;/a&gt;. The margin of error is a percent spread which the poll is expected to be within, 90-99% of the time (depending on how conservative of a confidence rating is given). If a poll shows that a politician is expected to take 48% of the vote, for example, and the margin of error is 4%, that means he is expected to take 44-52% of the vote with 90-99% surety. Margins of error are typically given much greater importance in the modern media than they should, as they&#39;re calculated solely based upon the total number of respondents to a poll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two general categories of opinion systems: &lt;em&gt;pre-voting (subjective) polling systems&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;post-voting (objective) polling systems&lt;/em&gt;. A different type of opinion system, &lt;em&gt;delphic polling&lt;/em&gt;, which could apply to either pre- or post-voting systems is also covered. Polling systems not directly related to selection systems are covered later, as &lt;em&gt;subjective rating systems&lt;/em&gt;, since they tend to have issues very different from other polling systems, as their goal isn&#39;t to try and match the &amp;quot;true&amp;quot; number of an actual vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;pre-voting_polling_systems&#34;&gt;Pre-voting Polling Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; These are polls made before a vote is cast. They&#39;re often called &amp;quot;opinion polls&amp;quot; and tend to be conducted via phone. They try and isolate &amp;quot;likely voters&amp;quot; and determine how they will vote. This question of voter likelihood is one of the first issues with a pre-voting system, because there&#39;s no guarantee that the polled people will actually later vote. Likewise, pre-voting systems have to accommodate &amp;quot;undecided voters&amp;quot; and the fact that no voter has ever truly made up their mind until they cast their final ballot. Unlike post-voting polling systems, pre-voting systems also have considerable more possibility for bias (which is not accounted for by margins of error), based upon how questions are asked, in what order, and with what additional text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Exitpoll&#34; title=&#34;Exitpoll&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/exitpoll.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;post-voting_polling_systems&#34;&gt;Post-voting Polling Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; These are polls taken after a vote is cast. They&#39;re typically called &amp;quot;exit polls&amp;quot;, as most are conducted as people are leaving a &amp;quot;polling&amp;quot; station (where they cast a vote). One would expect these to be much more reliable than pre-voting polls, but as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004_U.S._presidential_election_controversy_and_irregularities#Exit_polls&#34;&gt;2004 U.S. Presidential Election&lt;/a&gt; showed, exit polls can be wildly inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems with post-voting polling systems, shared with pre-voting systems, is that the results must be manipulated to make sure that respondents to the poll match the percentages of those constituencies in the overall populations. For example, in the 2004 exit polls it appears that women were initially overrepresented in exit polls, and because of increased black turnout it appears that blacks were underrepresented in the exit polls. It can easily be seen how either of these misrepresentations could cause notable changes in an exit poll result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When conducted &amp;amp; matched correctly, exit polls are supposed to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004_U.S._presidential_election_controversy%2C_exit_polls#Reliability_of_Exit_Polls&#34;&gt;quite reliable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/delphiamphitheatre.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=458,height=317,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;138&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Delphiamphitheatre&#34; title=&#34;Delphiamphitheatre&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/delphiamphitheatre.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;delphic_polling_systems&#34;&gt;Delphic Polling Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; An interesting polling method applicable to all sorts of opinion systems is the &amp;quot;delphi poll&amp;quot;. This is a specific method of polling which is &lt;em&gt;iterative&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;anonymous&lt;/em&gt; and which supports &lt;em&gt;confidence ratings&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;feedback&lt;/em&gt;. The general idea is that people are polled on a question using not just binary responses, but a full confidence rating (e.g., you would state that you are 60% sure that Bush would be elected, rather than stating that you think Bush would be elected). After polls are collected, the anonymous results--or at least a summary of those results--are shared with the participants, who then poll again. This iterative process continues until a consistent answer is settled upon. By incorporating feedback into the polling process there&#39;s the possibility for greatly increased reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways delphic polling systems can be seen as an analogy to &lt;em&gt;consensus systems&lt;/em&gt;, since both involve more iterative processes that eventually result in a more commonly-held decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;comparison_systems&#34;&gt;Comparison Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparison systems allow individual items to be measured up against each other. There are three general categories: &lt;em&gt;comparison ranking systems&lt;/em&gt;, which are largely objective and which typically rank people; and &lt;em&gt;comparison rating systems&lt;/em&gt;, which more often mix subjective and objective opinions, and which more frequently rate things; and &lt;em&gt;reputation rating systems&lt;/em&gt;, which again tend to rank people, but also have a subject and objective mix. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;ranking_systems&#34;&gt;Comparison Ranking Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a ranking system, items in a hierarchy (most frequently people) rise or fall based upon specific, objective, and well-known rules. This is the heart of most multiplayer competitive systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=500,height=336,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/chess.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;134&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/chess.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Chess&#34; alt=&#34;Chess&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELO_rating_system&#34;&gt;ELO System&lt;/a&gt; is an example of a ranking system used for two-player games, and is used by the U.S. Chess Federation. Days of Wonder uses a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gangoffour.com/index.php?t=content&amp;amp;sub=ranking&#34;&gt;multiplayer variant of the ELO system&lt;/a&gt; for their online games. Each system builds a simple distribution of player ratings around a norm (typically 1500 points), then awards or deducts points based upon wins and losses, with the total sum of all points in the system staying constant. Players are then ranked according to their comparative scores. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are flaws in ranking systems like ELO. For example, two players could collude, with one purposefully throwing games so that his opponent could increase his ranking. Alternatively if a player gets a few lucky victories against good opponents, his rating might temporarily skyrocket above its normative value. However, these tend to be well-known and well-researched problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are numerous other ranking systems which are used for competitions, from double-elimination seeded tournaments (e.g., a tennis tournament) to ranked comparisons based upon win-loss ratios (e.g., baseball standings). Objective rankings are also (less commonly) used to rank items, such as a ranking of cars based upon safety ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/usmc_enlisted_rank_structure.jpg&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=476,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;148&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Usmc_enlisted_rank_structure&#34; title=&#34;Usmc_enlisted_rank_structure&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/usmc_enlisted_rank_structure.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 5px 5px 0px 0px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most ranking systems create a hierarchy of positive rankings (e.g., &amp;quot;best chess players ever&amp;quot;). However, a hierarchy of negative rankings may also most be used, most commonly based on a negative criteria (e.g., &amp;quot;biggest Player Killers (PKers)&amp;quot;). In addition, either direction of ranking can use threshold systems to mark positive or negative rankings that meet a certain criteria. A positive threshold might be a &amp;quot;Grand Master&amp;quot; ranking threshold for anyone with a Chess rating of 2700, while a negative threshold might be a &amp;quot;Player Killer&amp;quot; ranking threshold, for with sufficient &amp;quot;accidental&amp;quot; PKs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking systems are somewhat removed from the other collective choice systems listed here, since there&#39;s isn&#39;t a collaborative decision, only a collective result. However their problems &amp;amp; results remain closely related to the more collective rating and reputation systems, hence their inclusion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=373,height=239,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/stars_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;128&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/stars_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Stars_1&#34; alt=&#34;Stars_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;rating_systems&#34;&gt;Rating Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In a rating system, the value of individual items (most frequently goods) rise or fall based upon the largely subjective judgment of individual users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.netflix.com&#34;&gt;Netflix&lt;/a&gt; are two examples of stores which provide subjective rating systems. Individual users rate items from 1 to 5 stars, then an average user rating is calculated. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boardgamegeek.com&#34;&gt;BoardGameGeek&lt;/a&gt; offers a slightly different example because it not only lets users rate individual items, but also ranks items against each other based upon those ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flaws in these systems are similar to those in ranking systems: low numbers of ratings producing bad rankings, and individual users purposefully biasing ratings. Some mathematical methods may be used to smooth out these issues, among them &lt;em&gt;bayesian averages&lt;/em&gt;, which give ratings weight based upon total number of ratings for an item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stock Market offers an example of a different sort of rating system, because there&#39;s theoretically some objective basis to it. In a perfect Stock Market system, stock prices are based upon a solid cost analysis, such as a multiplier on yearly revenues or profits. However, as the Internet bubble of the late 1990s conclusively showed, there&#39;s also a high irrational component to stock purchases: thus subjective and objective views are combined in the rating (cost) of a stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;reputation_systems&#34;&gt;Reputation Systems:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, reputation systems are very similar to ranking systems: items in a hierarchy (most frequently people) rise or fall based upon specific and well-known rules. However, unlike true ranking systems, reputation systems instead base their rules for rise and fall upon other user feedback. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of a reputation system is ultimately to create a trust metric that often allows different users access to different powers. We&#39;ll be covering reputation systems a bit more thoroughly in a couple of weeks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of ways to measure the collective choices of a large group of people. We&#39;ve outline nine here: representative, deliberative, and consensus selection systems; ranking, rating, and reputation comparison systems; and three varieties of opinion systems. When developing social software it is important to understand the difference between these broad categories of systems and to use lessons already learned from the appropriate category in your own social software designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34;&gt;2006-01: Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You seemed to leave out consensus methods such as the Quakers and facilitated decision making processes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.imaginal.nl&#34;&gt;Jon Jenkins&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-02T00:08:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-02T00:08:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;My intent was more to outline the broad categories of collective choice, then to give all the possible examples within each category. Both consensus methods and facilitated decision making processes fall under the &#34;deliberation systems&#34; category.
It is my hope in future articles to dig deeper into each broad category and show more examples of types. Next week hopefully will be comparison rating systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-02T00:39:54-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-02T00:39:54-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You should take a look at Jeff Vails&#39; writings on rhizome networks as counter weights to hierchical power structures. http://www.jeffvail.net/2005/08/rhizome-communication-and-our-one-time.html
There&#39;s a connection between your ideas and his that I can&#39;t quite articulate because my mind is focussed elsewhere at the moment. But I shall return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://karavans.typepad.com/&#34;&gt;peter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-07T17:17:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-07T17:17:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve made some changes to this blog entry, adding consensus systems under deliberation systems, added reputation systems as a type of opinion system, simplifying some of the category names, and added some links.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-08T13:13:09-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-08T13:13:09-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is an excellent summary, but I feel like I want a comparison table of some kind.
Would &#34;information futures market&#34; or the like be a Delphic system? It sure seems more like a consensus measuring device to me.
One of the most interesting things about all of these systems is the side effects they have on the decisions made. Binary Votes polorize options. Information Futures Markets encourage results manipulation (by design!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fudco.com/habitat&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-08T14:24:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-08T14:24:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This is a wonderful overview.  Thank you for putting it together!
I&#39;d like to suggest one small correction to the description of Condorcet voting, which says &#34;it is much harder on the voters, who have to rank every single candidate&#34;.  In a Condorcet system, the voters don&#39;t have to rank every candidate; they can rank as many or as few as they want (just like IRV), and they can even rank candidates equally (unlike IRV).  The Wikipedia article entitled &#34;Condorcet method&#34; describes this.
Regarding a comparison of these systems, i&#39;ve tried to illustrate the behaviour of plurality, approval, IRV, and Condorcet elections at http://zesty.ca/voting/ , and i hope you will find my method and results interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://wolog.net/&#34;&gt;Ping&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-14T01:33:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-14T01:33:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The problem of choice is outline very well in the book &#39;The Paradox of Choice&#39; by Bary Schwartz.  It provides a great description of some of the other challenges of multi-party elections. I found it very interesting when it got into the psychology of choice regret, and alternative choices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.como.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Randal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-14T08:48:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-14T08:48:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I agree this is a very interesting article!  I notice an (intentional?) lack of coverage of most of the dominant and mature decision-making institutions in our society: markets in general (and specifically institutions such as exchanges -- mentioned briefly -- auctions, fixed-price retail stores vs. haggling bazaars, and so on), risk sharing institutions (e.g. insurance), hierarchical organizations based on the employer-employee and boss-subordinate relationships, the judiciary based on written law, opinion, and precedent, and so on.  Of course, it would be very ambitious to tackle these, but it would at least be interesting to try to categorize them according to your taxonomy.  Perhaps they are so complex they often fall into multiple categories.
The systems you describe abstract a vast amount of diffuse and often tacit information pertinent to a decision into a numerical result. Most economists (particularly Austrian school) would argue that at least on a large scale prices generated by auctions and exchanges generally do this better than other collective decision making systems.  On the other hand, many systems for collective choice don&#39;t work via an abstract numerical intermediary (e.g. the opinion and precedent system of the judiciary).
I suggest that the most important factor in these institutions is the costs involved in eliciting diffuse knowledge and lossily compressing it into a decision which is hopefully nevertheless a reasonably accurate reflection of that diffuse information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://unenumerated.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;nick szabo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-15T11:49:05-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-15T11:49:05-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;At least part of the reason why I didn&#39;t strongly highlight markets is that the definition of &#34;collective choice&#34;, at least as far as how many academics use it, is all the methods that groups make decisions EXCEPT markets. For instance, from http://www.bsos.umd.edu/umccc/ &#34;models of individual rational choice behavior to study non-market social phenomena&#34;.
However, another definition is http://www.artsci.wustl.edu/~polisci/calvert/PolSci505/ &#34;social choice theory and noncooperative game theory&#34;, and I might say that markets fall into a subset of noncooperative game theory.
Personally I&#39;m not sure why most academics exclude markets, thus I do briefly mention the Stock Market as a subcategory of comparison system. I hope to mention them more in other future articles, in particular, prediction markets as a subcategory of Polling Systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-12-15T12:20:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-12-15T12:20:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Will you cover, in a future post the forced choice vote? I&#39;d welcome learning about more ways that a group can discuss alternatives (online or in person) then either vote in a priority way (first choice, second choice, etc.)
and/ or choose to vote in a first round for &#34;x&#34; number of options then limit the conversation to those options, then perhaps do a forced choice vote.
In other words what are some hybrid methods that you
(amazing) Christopher might craft that combine:
A. Thoughtful conversation to hear all ideas/opinions -
without the downsides of :
• being prolonged to the point it pains participants
and/or
• being dominated by one or two &#34;strong&#34; or verbose personalities
.....with
B. Stages of voting closure that enable all participants
to see &#39;we&#39; are moving to the top choice(s) of the group
- another fan of life with alacrity
p.s. In addition to the aforementioned, brilliant, The Paradox of Choice, read Smart Choices by Howard Raiffa
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typekey.com/kareanderson/&#34;&gt;Kare&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-12-30T13:37:36-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-12-30T13:37:36-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>