<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Network on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/social-network/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Network on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/tags/social-network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing your Social Graph with Google&#43; [Google Plus]</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563798/&#34; title=&#34;Trust Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Trust Circle&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3230/3055563798_5355b9b99c_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With Google+ almost two weeks into its test phase, conversation about this new social network service seems to be going in circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because Circles is the Google+ feature that users are generating the most buzz about. It’s Google’s answer to the problem of organizing your social graph online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_graph&#34;&gt;social graph&lt;/a&gt; it’s a map of everyone you know and how they are related to you. Social graphs are tricky; as you try to define them you’ll inevitably run into some complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete Pachal, news director of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387808,00.asp&#34;&gt;@PCMag&lt;/a&gt; comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;“People want things easy, and Google Circles isn’t easy. It puts the burden on users to take the time to think about each and every contact and put them in a specific bucket. To use the feature effectively, users will certainly have to create new Circles, and that requires even more thought. After using Google+ for a few minutes last night, I was often unsure which Circles to put certain people in and, more to the point, which to leave them out of. And what if you create a new Circle that should include some of the people in other Circles you already have?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circles are lists that you’ve created by grouping people together and giving them a name. They’re important in Google+ because when you post you must explicitly say which “Circles” you wish to share with. Posting to a limited list of people is a big change from existing social networks such as Facebook, where posts are sent to all mutual friends by default, or Twitter, where posts are public. This change forces you to think more deeply about your social graph and who should see each item you post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BwvygI2xKGM&#34; width=&#34;560&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yourinitialsetofcircles&#34;&gt;Your Initial Set of Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google+ will present you with 4 suggested set of Circles: Friends, Family, Acquaintances, and Following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d image-full&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-800wi&#34; title=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Google+ also defines five special Circles: Two are only for reading: &amp;quot;Stream&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; and &amp;quot;Incoming&amp;quot; which is are posts that are shared to you by people not in your Circles. Then are three special Circles managed by Google only for posting: &amp;quot;Your Circles&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; “Extended” which is everyone in your Circles plus the people in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; Circles; and “Public” which is &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few find this default set to be sufficient. As a result, most Google+ users are soon creating new Circles, moving people around, renaming Circles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sound reasons for people finding the default Circles limiting. Sociological research shows that everyone has a number of concentric personal circles (see my blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt; for more details). These circles are sometimes called “ego-centric” social graphs as the individual is located in the center. This sort of graph is the model I used when I began reorganizing my own Google+ Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out using Support (for my Support Circle), Close (for my Sympathy Circle), Trusted (for my Trust Circle), and Colleagues (for my Emotional Circle), but that didn’t work for very long. I’ve since been experimenting with a number of different ways to organize my Circles. I wanted an initial set that would offer useful early advice for using Google+ but would still be applicable for when expanded to hundreds of people. (I now have over 600 people in my Circles.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One insight I’ve had is to avoid the word ‘friends’, which has been corrupted to almost meaninglessness in recent years. So instead I use terminology like Peers for my trust circle and Kith for the combination of my support and sympathy circles. (Kith may be familiar to you from the phrase “kith and kin”. The root of kith means “to know”, thus it’s those people that you know very well and that know you very well.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that sub-Circles exist within Circles. Using a ‘general ledger’ system of naming Circles with numbers—which I’ll demonstrate in a moment—helps me keep these Circles and sub-Circles in order and allows me to easily add new Circles when I need to. Hopefully Google+ will in the future introduce features that allow us to order Circles as we please, but until then this numbering system works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Google+ has also shown me that some Circles are for reading and other Circles are for posting. I’ll talk a little more about this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has only been a week, but by combining these insights to organize my Circles I’ve improved my ease of use and become better able to manage my time while using Google+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my recommended initial list of Circles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 ME&lt;/strong&gt; - a simple Circle with just yourself in it, for saving posts, for drafts, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.0 KIN&lt;/strong&gt; - your family &amp;amp; extended family&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt; 2.0 KITH&lt;/strong&gt; - your best friends, your confidants (i.e. those with whom one shares a secret or private matter, trusting them not to repeat it to others)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.0 PEERS&lt;/strong&gt; - your trusted colleagues, those who you work closely with, your collaborators&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.0 LOCAL&lt;/strong&gt; - your neighbors, parents of your children&amp;#39;s friends, people you&amp;#39;d invite to a party&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.0&lt;/strong&gt; {various groups &amp;amp; interests}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;/strong&gt; - people you know, but that you don&amp;#39;t know well or that don’t know you well&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;/strong&gt; - people who follow you on Google+, who you may or may not know&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;/strong&gt; - people whose posts you read, but who don&amp;#39;t necessarily read your posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 9.0 SPECIAL&lt;/strong&gt; - useful for special lists &amp;amp; exceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expandingcircles&#34;&gt;Expanding Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people will find my default set of ~10 Circles to be very useful, and need only add a few more. However, the design of this set is to allow for much greater expansion should you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like those “personal circles” that I wrote about previously, most of the Circles above are ego-centric: they’re fundamentally centered on your own personal social graph. This isn’t the only potential type of Circle, however. Socio-centric Circles aren’t centered on you, though they still have some sort of membership boundaries, while info-centric Circles are based on topics instead of being based on relationships. These socio-centric and info-centric Circles will support many relationships better than ego-centric Circles do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone seems to write a lot about a particular topic, I put him or her into an appropriate info-centric Circle. My own info-centric Circles thus include people who post about topics like iOS Development, the Social Web, Sustainability/Green, and Entrepreneuring. If a number of people are all part of a group or all come from a certain geographical area then I put them together in a socio-centric circle. After creating the Circles, I put the ones that were geographic into 4.0 of my ledger, then placed the others in 5.0. (I tried separating out groups and interests, and found that didn’t work, so now I keep them together.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now have over 600 people in my Google Plus+ social graph. All together my Circles now look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 Read Later&lt;br /&gt; 0.1 Drafts&lt;br /&gt; 0.2 Book Project&lt;br /&gt; 0.3 iPad Project&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 1.0 ALL KIN&lt;br /&gt; 1.1 Immediate Family&lt;br /&gt; 1.2 Extended Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 2.0 ALL KITH&lt;br /&gt; 2.1 Close Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.2 Old But Distant Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.3 Distant Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 3.0 ALL PEERS&lt;br /&gt; 3.2 Collaborators&lt;br /&gt; 3.3 Current Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt; 3.4 Former Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 4.0 ALL LOCAL&lt;br /&gt; 4.1 Local Kith, Kin &amp;amp; Peers&lt;br /&gt; 4.2 Local Berkeley&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Seattle&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Portland&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 5.0 ALL GROUPS &amp;amp; INTERESTS&lt;br /&gt; 5.1 Entrepreneurs&lt;br /&gt; 5.2 Apple &amp;amp; iOS&lt;br /&gt; 5.3 - iOSDevCamp&lt;br /&gt; 5.4 Green &amp;amp; Sustainability&lt;br /&gt; 5.5 - BGIedu&lt;br /&gt; 5.6 Social Web&lt;br /&gt; 5.7 - Jerry’s Kids&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;br /&gt; 6.1 Familiar Strangers&lt;br /&gt; 6.2 Friendly Strangers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;br /&gt; 7.1 Core Audience&lt;br /&gt; 7.2 Commented or Shared My Posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;br /&gt; 8.2 Pundits&lt;br /&gt; 8.3 Celebrities&lt;br /&gt; 8.4 Noisy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 9.0 ALL&lt;br /&gt; 9.1 Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy&lt;br /&gt; 9.2 Read Daily&lt;br /&gt; 9.3 Read Weekly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future blog post I’ll share my ongoing experience with using this approach to Circles, but this example shows how easy it is to separate and add Circles as your interests change and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;managingyourcircles&#34;&gt;Managing Your Circles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, enjoy social networks in large part because we get to interact with people. Managing your Circles is thus about more than just understanding your social graph. It also allows you to manage your time effectively when you read and share with other people on Google+. Here is my approach for how to manage the time you spend reading, sharing, and managing your social graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforreading&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Reading&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it useful to think about Circles that are explicitly for reading as different from Circles intended for sharing. I have a few of these read-only Circles. Thus, my “Pundits” Circle contains people that share a lot and for whom I don’t always want to read everything. My “Read Daily” Circle is conversely for people for whom I want to read everything they post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also found Circles helpful for close collaborators. It’s easy in Google+ to have a conversation with someone directly by simply typing their name as +&amp;lt;name&amp;gt; into the share field of posts. However, I find these direct posts get lost over time. To resolve this problem, create a Circle dedicated to just the two of you: a dyad. I have a number of people that I’m collaborating with closely and I use these small Circles to both keep track of our mutual posts and to see what they are thinking about at the moment. Examples of this kind of two-person Circle include my “Book Project” and “iPad Project”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofreadingcircles&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Reading Circles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day I look first at my “ALL KIN”, “ALL KITH” and and “ALL PEER” Circles to see what is going on with my support, sympathy and trust cliques. Then I’ll read my “Read Daily” Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading these daily basics (which I try to keep to a limited number), I’ll typically pick an interest, a geography, or a group, depending on what I’m doing that day. (My personal time-management style is to only follow one interest per day, e.g. if I am working on my iPad app then I’m not reading Social Web posts.) If I’m preparing a blog post and want to see what my audience is thinking I might review “Core Audience”, or “FOLLOWS ME”. If I’m traveling I might read one of my non-local Circles such as “Seattle”. If I’m doing ‘weak-signal research’ I might start with “ALL INTERESTS”, but if I’m particularly tolerant of noise I might read “Familiar Strangers”, “FOLLOWS ME”, “Everyone but Pundits &amp;amp; Strangers”, “Pundits”, or even “ALL”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;postingtocircles&#34;&gt;Posting to Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the important reasons for creating Circles in the first place is so that you can share with groups of people. I’ve developed some strategies for this as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforposting:&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Posting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it useful to create a Circle that only contains yourself. I have two of these — “Read Later”, and “Drafts”. If I’m reading and I see something interesting but don’t have time for it immediately, I’ll share it with my “Read Later” Circle so that I can quickly go back to it. Similarly, if I need to do some more research before writing and sharing, I’ll share my immediate thoughts in “Drafts”. As new features are added to Google+ these Circles will hopefully become obsolete, but they are useful for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofprivateposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Private Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sharing, you want to ask yourself if this is ‘private’ post, a ‘quasi-public’ post or a ‘public’ post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My private posts tend to go “KIN”, “KITH”, a dyad project, or one of the sub-Circles of PEER depending on their context. Some posts that are of only geographic interest (say a party, or local event) will be shared privately to the appropriate local Circle. If you are using my ledger system of using numbers in Circle names, these are the lower numbers—5.0 and below are Circles where I’m more sensitive about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once shared, these more personal posts will be labeled as “Limited” instead of using the “Public” label that allows anyone to see them. If a recipient tries to share a “Limited” post, a box will pop up reminding the person: “This post was originally shared with a limited audience – remember to be thoughtful about who you share it with”. Unlike Facebook or Twitter, one purpose of Circles on Google+ is to determine who gets what information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it may be easy to create Circles to segregate those with whom you wish to share private information, the recipients of your posts have no such limitations and could share outward beyond your intent (though they will be warned if they try to, as noted above). To enable further privacy you can disable resharing of these personal posts made to your Circles. To do so, share your post to a non-public Circle, then you select the arrow in the upper-right-hand corner where you can edit, delete or disable the post, and click on the final option, “Disable Reshare”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another privacy issue: by clicking the grey “Limited” label, a message’s recipient can see all others you shared the post with. This could potentially result in privacy problems, as the reader could discover who is in one of your Circles. There are ways of eliminating this by going into your Privacy account settings, which I will cover in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofquasi-publicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Quasi-Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call posts “quasi-public” when they’re of narrow interest to a specific group or a topic that isn’t really relevant to other members of my audience. I find these quasi-public posts happen the most for my more esoteric interests—for instance, when I’m sharing a complex iPhone development article that is really only interesting to a narrow group of my contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Google Reader, I typically wouldn’t share these articles at all because there were so many of my contacts that wouldn’t be interested in them and it would only be noise to them. Ditto with Twitter. I found that sometimes people would stop following me after a conference I attended because I posted regularly and the conference was not of interest to them. This could be quite frustrating at times. Though these posts were not private by any means, I only wanted to share them with a specific group, such as an iPhone group. Now with Circles, I can share this information easily with my “Apple &amp;amp; iOS” Circle. I find that this feature is what makes Google+’s Circles so potentially powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I might offer much of this more esoteric information as “quasi-public” posts to a specific group or interest, I’ll probably offer the best of them to the “Public”. Sometimes that is what it means to be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maven&#34;&gt;Maven&lt;/a&gt;—you share across social network boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofpublicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing a post to your “Your Circles” is effectively public, as is sharing to “Extended Circles”. Ask yourself if there is really some reason why you don’t want to make a post totally “Public” so that it is searchable by those who are not members of Google+. If there is some reason, consider sharing to your “ALL” Circle or some other more limited circle instead, as you’ll have more control and can turn off resharing or commenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;managingyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;Managing Your Social Graph&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining your Circles can take away from the time you can spend on reading and sharing. I’ve come up with the following strategy to limit the time I spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, I have some basic rules for which Circles to place people in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone is following me, I add them to “FOLLOWS ME” and an appropriate other Circle. If I vaguely recognize a follower’s name or face, I put them in “Familiar Strangers”. If I don’t recognize them at all but they look interesting, I add them to “Friendly Strangers”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone has +1’ed, commented, or mentioned me in a post, I add them to “Core Audience” and the appropriate sub-Circle. I will also make sure that the other Circles they are in are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I discover while I’m reading that someone is too noisy for the Circle I selected, I’ll move them to a more appropriate Circle—or place them in the “Noisy” Circle or even block them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Your Social Graph&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition I review a few of my Circles every day. I do so by going to “Manage Circles”, then selecting “People in your Circles” and sorting by last name. I choose that letter of the alphabet that corresponds to the day of the month and hover my mouse over each name. (For example, I look at names starting with “L” on July 12th, as “L” is the 12th letter.) Google+ highlights the Circles that each person is in. If they’re in the wrong Circle, I move them. I might even click on some people and review their profile so that I can see who they are—or (if I already know them) see what they are up to lately, update my address book, and maybe send them a brief email. At the end of the month (on the 27th through the 31st) I review my overall Circles lists. This way, over the course of each month I briefly review my entire social network, without spending too much time on it. (I try to spend 10 minutes or so a day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Periodically (right now weekly, but hopefully eventually monthly) I do some larger scale management of my Circles. Learning how to do this the first time is a pain, but once you know how it only takes a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to “Manage Circles” and select “People Who Have Added You”. I sort that list by “Not Yet in Circles”, “Select All” and add the people revealed to “FOLLOWS ME”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then do the same with all of my Circles to update my “ALL” Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I copy my “ALL” circle to “Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy” and remove any Pundits, Celebrities or Noisy people from that Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When managing your Circles, remember the motto “Perfection is the Enemy of the Good”. You are the only one that sees who is in which Circle, and you can place people in multiple Circles. So your Circles don’t have to be perfect, just good enough. If you share a lot of private posts, concentrate on making sure that those more personal Circles are more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these approaches, you should find Circle management quick, and you won’t get mired down in Circle management for hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish I had this organization when I started on Google+ two weeks ago. By using some of these techniques from the beginning I would have made my life a lot easier. Over the next month I now have to go back and re-organize people and re-Circle them. I hope sharing these tips will make your use of Google+ simpler from the start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I expect that Google will be adding new features to make Google+ easier. For instance I’m hoping for #hashtags (the ability to tag posts into topic categories), favorites (the ability to tag posts into a persistent archive, hopefully with an option tag), ordering Circles, concentric Circles, and better integration with Google Reader. (I share my favorite blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/reader/shared/ChristopherA&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; at &amp;#0160;and my best of best articles and posts in &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ChristopherA/favorites&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Twitter Favorites&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;or &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/christophera&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Delicious&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any new online feature, people are finding out new things and coming up with new ideas every day. So what are &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; methods for organizing your Circles and social graph?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to follow me on Google+, I’m at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/about&#34;&gt;+Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#39;d like to comment using Google+, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/posts/2eYjBB2CpNm&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;public comment thread&lt;/a&gt; about this post.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you would like to subscribe to my Google+ posts in Google Reader, use my &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;feed://plusfeed.appspot.com/113059510043663667610&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlusFeed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts from my blog related to this post:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some recent high signal-to-noise blog posts on Google+ and/or managing your Circles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107631581023945167601/about&#34;&gt;+Matt Stratton&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattstratton.com/tech-tips/how-i-set-up-my-circles-in-google-plus&#34;&gt;How I Set Up My Circles in Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113551191017950459231/about&#34;&gt;+Anson Alex&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ansonalex.com/tutorials/managing-circles-in-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Guide to Working with Circles in Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/101746196094367799224/about&#34;&gt;+Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/?p=2616&#34;&gt;The promise of Google+ for organizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104681313125038107957/about&#34;&gt;+Sterling Ledet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.weteachthecoolstuff.com/2011/07/09/a-thought-on-circles-privacy-vs-relevance/&#34;&gt;A Thought on Google+ Circles – Privacy vs. Relevance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/118432652629200965858/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Dave Pollard&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtosavetheworld.ca/2011/07/11/google-plus-on-communities-circles-friendship-and-love/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google+: On Communities, Circles, Friendship and Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethkanter.org/np-google/&#34;&gt;Are You Going To Adopt Google+ for Professional Learning/Networking? Why or Why Not?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104181568670836761473/about&#34;&gt;+Damon Morda&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brandedclever.com/five-steps-to-configuring-privacy-on-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Five Steps to Configuring Privacy on Google Plus (+)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some quality recent public Google+ posts regarding Google+ or managing your Circles (be sure to look over the comments):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/about/&#34;&gt;+Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/posts/ghn6Bu6tsmM&#34;&gt;My tips for newer users of Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/1SdhSBqwAmA&#34;&gt;Where circles can go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/D9bRJCmjJRV&#34;&gt;Sharing Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/XHvCRURHidx&#34;&gt;Is Google plus public or private?It’s neither, and both!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/posts/DV8QxNzTxaF&#34;&gt;Insightful Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/about&#34;&gt;+Craig Kanalley&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/posts/52dmpNDbWtp&#34;&gt;Tips &amp;amp; Thoughts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/about/&#34;&gt;+Paul Goode&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/posts/W9CaNrwku3x&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Sketch on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on related to this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;personal circles&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the of personal limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;familiar strangers&lt;/a&gt; - those people you recognize by face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustration by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;, Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/102320045646237908121/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Elyn Andersson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;for their assistance with this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I really like the idea of using circles for social time management. One big problem I have with networks is that I feel committed (obligated?) to a certain, indistinct, level of communication - particularly with those people that social media has now kept me in &#39;contact&#39; with, and whom in the old days I would have lost touch with. The end result is always a big time defecit and multiple layers of guilt. The idea of being able to apply some kind of equitable rationing/priority to circles may be a bit geeky... but it&#39;s preferable to non-specific angst  ;0)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/grimbold&#34;&gt;Grimbold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I like your ideas; I&#39;ve also been trying to play about with the circles &amp; work out something that works for me.
How, however, do you manage to add people to them, when you have quite so many (looking at the second list with the 1.3 etc) - I can only see 1.5 rows of circles! (OK, I know you can add someone by right clicking &amp; going for the add to circle, but that&#39;s fiddly if you&#39;re block adding them!)
I&#39;ve also got in the (equivalent of the) me circle my &#39;other&#39; G+ account, that I&#39;ve been using to see the effect of things like extended circles. Which I do find useful.
Would be nice, if, at some point, rather than having &#39;stream&#39; it was possible to see in a single stream all the updates from a set of circles, rather than 1 or all. (Unless that&#39;s something I&#39;ve yet to find!)
(That, and I want boolean logic for them, so I can have everyone who is in both a &amp; b, but not a or b!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/emmadw&#34;&gt;Emmadw&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Shared Language and Shared Artifacts</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 01:13:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://worldatuningfork.com/John/medusaosxPDF.pdf#page=203&#34; style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Poem: Language&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577a68d970b &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577a68d970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px;&#34; title=&#34;Poem: Language&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We live in a world of conversation, of language; all full of words. Mastery of language requires learning the meanings of thousands of words. The average native English language speaker uses in the realm of 12,000 to 20,000 words, whereas a college graduate would use 20-25,000 words. Shakespeare actively used more then 30,000 words, and his vocabulary was estimated to be over 66,000 words. Yet there are, at the very least, a quarter of a million distinct English words, excluding inflections, and words from technical and regional vocabularies. The Oxford English dictionary defines more then 600,000 words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But mastery of words is not enough to allow effective conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is because words themselves don&amp;#39;t have meaning; the meaning is provided by the people who use them. Meaning is in the mind, not in the words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words also require context, outside of which they may have different meanings. For instance, consider the word &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot;. To a banker or CPA &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot; is a property held by someone to manage for someone else&amp;#39;s benefit. To a cryptographer it is the confidence in a future outcome based on probabilistic mathematics and past experience. Finally, to the lay person &amp;quot;trust&amp;quot; is about honesty. &amp;quot;Spin&amp;quot; is another example of a word that changes with context; to a weaver it is the production of thread, to a physicist it is a property of elemental particles, to an athlete it is a type of exercise class, and to a politician or public relations professional it is a way to tell a story to sway pubic opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Creating a Shared Language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Life With Alacrity Wordle&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a577c005970b-320pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Life With Alacrity Wordle&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Every time a new group of people meet together — whether in a team, in a marketplace, or in a community — one of the first activities they must do together is create a shared language. They do this in order to communicate more effectively together, to put a context on the words that they have in common, to construct a shared understanding in their minds based both on available information and their individual diversity of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t forget that the linguistic root of communication is the Latin verb&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.18:3557.lewshort&#34; title=&#34;Latin definition of commūnĭco&#34;&gt;commūnĭco&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;&amp;#0160;— which doesn&amp;#39;t mean &amp;quot;to communicate&amp;quot; but instead means &amp;quot;to share something with someone, to take or receive a part of, to partake, to participate in&amp;quot;. Thus the creation of a shared language takes us to the roots of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without taking the time time to create shared language, groups have a difficult time forging mutual trust. Without a shared language there will be no clarity on mutual goals — whether it involves working together, transacting a trade, or creating something. Without a shared language commitments can be hard to make, and if misunderstood can lead to disagreements. These group formation phases — trust building, goal clarification, and commitment — are essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the art of creating a shared language together is not taught. Some individuals and groups do it intuitively while others will just let it evolve naturally over time. However, some facilitators have learned that one of the best ways to help a group form a shared language is by having the group create together a shared artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Using Shared Artifacts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shared artifact is the creation of an object or shared space that is created collaboratively. It allows the individuals participating to ask the questions: &amp;quot;Is this what you mean when you are talking about this? I use these words, so suppose we change it to this? Is that what you mean? Does this reflect our new shared understanding?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;WatsonCrick&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce5085970c-120pi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px;&#34; title=&#34;WatsonCrick&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Napkin-idea-original-concept-300x293&#34; class=&#34;at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c &#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef0120a5ce82e4970c-120wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Examples of shared artifacts include Watson &amp;amp; Crick&amp;#39;s Tinker-Toy DNA model. Each scientist would work on the model separately, then use grad students to carry the model around to his partner to express certain ideas. Both Compaq Computer and Southwest Airlines were reportedly established after their founders wrote their ideas down together on a table napkin, another shared artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these examples show an important factor in shared artifacts — if the shared artifact is not constrained then it will be too large or complex for the group to reach some measure of completion. Finishing the shared artifact really helps establish trust and the connections between the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shared artifact is also useful because flooding someone with information and terms gives no assurance that the recipient has gained knowledge of the subject. Instead, the act of creation confirms to both parties that the knowledge was successfully assimilated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage to creating a shared artifact is that it isolates any problems to the task at hand. Often there are differences in status, purpose, or perspective that can get in the way of group formation, but a focus on a common task of the creation of a neutral shared artifact allows those issues to come later as the participants develop the trust and shared language required to talk about those tough issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best facilitators know what kinds of shared artifacts work best for different groups under different circumstances. Sometimes a shared artifact is just a model of a process drawn on a white wall. Often it is a creation of a mission statement or joint objectives. I personally like taking old mind maps and trying to recreate them anew with more recent knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Future of Shared Language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of shared language is changing in the 21st century. The conjoined social networks in the blogosphere — via Facebook, Twitter, or the attendee-focused Unconference — cause new terminology and new language to form ever faster. I&amp;#39;ve personally seen words like &amp;quot;retweet&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;attribution&amp;quot; gain important contextual meaning within my social networks. As with any shared language, newcomers have difficulty discovering their meanings only by osmosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tagging is another means by which shared language is rapidly expanding. Certain words are gaining context through common use at Delicious.com, Technorati, Flickr, and other tag-enabled web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a certain extent, all of these new shared languages are built upon shared artifacts. Twitter, Facebook, Delicious.com and others sites each create constraints on how language is shared and with whom. However, there is little purposeful social design being applied to these new shared languages. Though there may be shared artifacts, they are not purposefully facilitated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will these increasingly organic shared languages prove better than more purposefully created ones or worse? Is social language facilitation the next big thing in social network? Or is there just not enough space for it within the tightly constrained social artifacts of the internet? These are questions that we as social software technologists need to address as the future of the internet increasingly becomes the present of our social groupings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I learned the concept of Shared Language in 1990 from Michael Schrage&amp;#39;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Shared-Minds-New-Technologies-Collaboration/dp/0394565878&#34;&gt;Shared Minds: The New Technologies of Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. It is out of print, but there is a new edition retitled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/No-More-Teams-Mastering-Collaboration/dp/0385476035/&#34;&gt;No More Teams!: Mastering the Dynamics of Creative Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. The use of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com/mgtaylor/glasbead/modexpl.htm&#34;&gt;modeling language&lt;/a&gt; to facilitate group formation I learned from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.matttaylor.com&#34;&gt;Matt Taylor&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/worthyprojects&#34;&gt;@worthyprojects&lt;/a&gt;) of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mgtaylor.com/&#34;&gt;MG Taylor Corporation&lt;/a&gt;, though the use of the term shared artifacts and approach is my own. I make passing reference to the early stages of team formation (&amp;quot;trust building&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;goal clarification&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;commitment&amp;quot;) which come from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grove.com/site/ourwk_gm_tp.html&#34;&gt;Drexler/Sibbet Team Peformance Model&lt;/a&gt;. The poem is by excerpt of a larger work by &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldatuningfork.com/John/&#34;&gt;John Campion&lt;/a&gt; and is reprinted with permission — the work reflects the poet&amp;#39;s Ecotropic concerns and are part of his third
book-length poem Medusa. Look at the work under the Medusa Project link. The table napkin photo is from an excellent post on &lt;a href=&#34;http://createtheconditions.com/?p=304&#34;&gt;The Idea Napkin&lt;/a&gt; by Morry Potoka and is also reprinted with permission. The Watson-Crick photo is public domain, and the Life With Alacrity graphic was produced using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordle.net/&#34;&gt;Wordle&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;m wondering whether the creation of such language is adding to an intellectual, generational and cultural divisiveness that is already prevalent in our society. Can we design tools that serve as bridges? Using the web for social change is a powerful concept, particularly if we can broaden the audience. This is a fascinating topic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Julie  Mihalisin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-09-21T10:45:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-09-21T10:45:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;ve not really thought of Shared Language in the context of divisiveness — Shared Language tends to be a function of small groups. Thus I more think of the divisiveness is coming from the fact that Shared Language typically evolves naturally in a small group, but fails to evolve naturally in larger groups. Possibly a better understanding of how Shared Language and tools to facilitate it like Shared Artifacts function will make it easier for larger groups to grow a Shared Language together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-09-21T14:06:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-09-21T14:06:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Shared artifacts are also known as models; the best form of understanding of business that I have found yet is when you develop simulators with practitioners. The quality of the the output is only surpassed by the shared understanding created through healthy challenge to the way things actually work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Dave Carter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-05-05T04:15:41-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-05-05T04:15:41-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2009/09/creating-shared-language-and-shared-artiifacts.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Seoul for the Social Web</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2008/06/in-seoul-for-th.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2008 01:18:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2008/06/in-seoul-for-th.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/2610236112/&#34; title=&#34;Downtown Seoul, South Korea, from Hotel Window by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3067/2610236112_a59ce2f7b5_m.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; alt=&#34;Downtown Seoul, South Korea, from Hotel Window&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I&#39;m in Seoul, South Korea this week for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.globalforumactionlearning.com/&#34;&gt;13th Global Forum on Business Driven Action Learning and Executive Development&lt;/a&gt;, where I&#39;m presenting on the topic of the how to get involved with the Social Web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My presentation is an offshoot of an odd sideline of mine, executive blog and social web coaching. Basically, many times over the last couple of years I&#39;ve been asked by colleagues and friends to help them with the social web. I&#39;ve always been honored to spend the time to teach them how to blog, better manage the noise of the web by using a feed reader, how to participate in social networks, and how to improve their personal brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, the social network of their peers is now asking me to help them to do the same for them. So I&#39;ve been doing this more and more over the last year on a consulting basis as their social networks appear to be saying saying that I have a lot to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve twice now been out to Cincinnati where I&#39;ve been working with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/pub/5/3a9/480&#34;&gt;Drew Boyd&lt;/a&gt; at Johnson &amp; Johnson, where I&#39;ve been coaching him on his blog and personal brand. He has been blogging now for almost six months at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.innovationinpractice.com/&#34;&gt;Innovation in Practice&lt;/a&gt; with some success. Now he is referring me to other executives at Johnson &amp; Johnson who need similar coaching, or need strategic advice on how to deal with specific social web initiatives within Johnson &amp; Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently, Drew has asked me to join him in Seoul to speak at the Global Forum, which is a worldwide gathering of executive trainers. There I am presenting a synopsis of what I teach, and how they can begin to learn how to teach their staff how to do the same. My trip has been sponsored by Johnson &amp; Johnson, so it has been a lot of fun to be here. I get to both dive into deep discussions of methodologies for teaching inside business, as well as learn about the Korean and other international business cultures and how they are different from the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the evenings I&#39;ve had a chance to wander the streets of downtown Seoul. It is very different then wandering though streets in Europe, not only because of the different culture and language, but also because all of the signs are in Hangul, the korean character set. Very few signs use the roman alphabet, so it is often very difficult to figure out what is what without walking in. Like Japan, there are some signs in English to represent a brand or a style, but not many. Even China has more signs in English then Korean&#39;s do -- the last time I was there I was surprised by how almost every important sign was in both Chinese and English, so much so I was beginning to learn Chinese language characters just by association! Despite the language problems everyone is nice and it feels safe to wander in these neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I return on Monday, and I&#39;ll make a copy of my final presentation available here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2008/06/in-seoul-for-th.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems</title>
      <link>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2006 23:37:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.7em;&#34;&gt;by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This is the third in a series of articles on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt;, co-written by my collegue &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline&#34;&gt;Shannon Appelcline&lt;/a&gt;. It will be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_179.phtml&#34;&gt;jointly posted&lt;/a&gt; in Shannon&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT.shtml&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities&lt;/a&gt; online games column at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our first article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;collective choice&lt;/a&gt; we outlined a number of different types of choice systems, among them voting, polling, rating, and ranking. Since then we&#39;ve been spending some time expanding upon the systems, with the goal being to create both a lexicon of and a dialogue about systems for collective choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time we&#39;re going to dig more into &lt;em&gt;comparison ranking systems&lt;/em&gt;, by focusing on &lt;em&gt;competitive&lt;/em&gt; rankings and looking more in depth at ELO Chess Ranking System and the other systems that we briefly mentioned previously. Our goal is to explicate these systems, to better address their flaws, to begin detailing the purposes of ranking systems, and to show how those purposes are critical in the design of ranking systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;subjective_vs_objective&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Subjective vs. Objective Rankings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our original article we discussed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;rating systems&lt;/a&gt; as being largely subjective and ranking systems as being objective, but the situation isn&#39;t nearly as simple as that. In truth, there&#39;s a clear spectrum of ratings and rankings with varying amounts of subjectivity and objectivity in each collective choice system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcsfootball.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Bcs_1&#34; title=&#34;Bcs_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/bcs_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.officialworldgolfranking.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/golfrankings_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Golfrankings_1&#34; alt=&#34;Golfrankings_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowl_Championship_Series&#34;&gt;Bowl Championship Series&lt;/a&gt; (BCS) for college football is a good example of a ranking system that explicitly allows a subjective component. It involves a complex mathematical formula that includes things like win/loss ratios, but also sportswriters&#39; and coaches&#39; ratings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, public opinion continues to show that people don&#39;t necessarily like seeing true ranking systems having subjective components, because they expect them to be &amp;quot;fair&amp;quot;. The BCS formula has come under attack several times in the last few years precisely due to its subjective basis. Cal Berkeley was one of several teams denied a bowl position in 2004 when many felt that they were worthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atptennis.com/en/players/raceleaderboard/rank_definitions.asp&#34;&gt;APL tennis rankings&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_rankings&#34;&gt;official world golf rankings&lt;/a&gt; also have a subjective component, but it is much more subtle. Each tournament is worth a certain number of points, and the allocation of those points is relatively arbitrary, based upon the &amp;quot;prestige&amp;quot; of each tournament and the quality of players who have traditionally played in it. The subjectivism isn&#39;t quite as near to the surface as that of the college bowls, but it&#39;s still something that can have a notable, and perhaps unwarranted, effect upon the final results.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;algorithmic_rankings&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Algorithmic Rankings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kosteniuk.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; title=&#34;Wcsrating_2&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wcsrating_2.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This brings us back to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELO_rating_system&#34;&gt;ELO system&lt;/a&gt;, a ranking system originally designed for chess which is fairly well-known and well-understood. As we said in our overview article, &amp;quot;[ELO] builds a simple distribution of player ratings around a norm (typically 1500 points), then awards or deducts points based upon wins and losses, with the total sum of all points in the system staying constant. Players are then ranked according to their comparative scores.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big difference between this and the previously discussed systems is that it&#39;s almost entirely objective; in fact it uses a statistical basis to create an underlying mathematical model for rankings, rather than allowing human subjectivity to get in the way.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest formulation for an ELO rating looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span size=&#34;+2&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&#39; = R + K * (S - E)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&#39;&lt;/code&gt; is the new rating&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is the old rating&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; is a maximum value for increase or decrease of rating (16 or 32 for ELO)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; is the score for a game&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt; is the expected score for a game&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the trick is in figuring out what the (&lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;)xpected score of a game is. ELO uses the following formulas for players A and B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;E(A) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [R(B) - R(A)] / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;E(B) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [R(A) - R(B)] / 400 ) ]&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a good model because, using the two formulas, it means that a great player gains little from beating an average player, but an average player gains a lot from beating a great player. Take the following example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;R(A) = 1900&lt;br /&gt;R(B) = 1500&lt;br /&gt;
E(A) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [1500 - 1900] / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( -400 / 400) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ -4 / 4 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ -1 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / 1 + .1&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = .91&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 91%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;E(B) = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( [1900 - 1500] / 400) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ ( 400 / 400 ) ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / [ 1 + 10 ^ 1 ]&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 1 / 11&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = .09&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; = 9%&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player A is expected to score .91 in an average game, which is to say he should win 91% of the time, and will be punished accordingly if he loses to player B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;pre&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * (0 - .91)&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 - 29.12&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1871&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely a win nets him very little:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * (1 - .91)&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 32 * .09&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1900 + 2.88&lt;br /&gt;R&#39; = 1903&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELO is almost entirely mathematical. Players can gain or lose different amounts of points based upon playing different players, but this is all part of the formula. The only slightly subjective element is the definition of &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; -- how much a player can win or lose from a particular game. The most widely used ELO systems for Chess break &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; down into two values: 16 for masters and 32 for everyone else. So there is a subjective decision that masters should vary their score less frequently than other players. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a very minor element in an otherwise objective system, but as we&#39;ll see, more recent systems by Days of Wonder and Microsoft first reduce, then eliminate even this subjectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;days_of_wonder&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations of a Theme: Days of Wonder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daysofwonder.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Dowlogo_1&#34; title=&#34;Dowlogo_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/dowlogo_1.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
ELO is probably the most used ranking system in the world. You can find it in use for Go, &lt;em&gt;Tantrix&lt;/em&gt;, and many other games. Days of Wonder, producers of &lt;em&gt;Gang of Four&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ticket to Ride&lt;/em&gt;, and many other games use a variant of the system which they describe on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gangoffour.com/index.php?t=content&amp;amp;sub=ranking&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They identify three core problems with ELO: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New players can take a long time to ascend or descend to their correct levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highly ranked players can be hesitant to play with provisional players whose ranking might be much more uncertain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no allowances for games with more than two players.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Days of Wonder resolved the first problem by creating a new formula for provisional players, allowing them to rise and fall in the rankings much more quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely when playing against provisional players, regular players can only lose a maximum of &lt;code&gt;K*n/20&lt;/code&gt; points, where n is the number of games that the provisional player has played--rather than the normal maximum loss of &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;. For example, playing someone who has just played one game, can only result in a loss of 1/20th of the regular &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; value, and so it really doesn&#39;t matter if the provisional player&#39;s ranking is wildly out of whack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these new formulas are set up to converge toward a normal ELO formula as a provisional player&#39;s number of games approaches 20 (making them a normal player at Days of Wonder).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It should be pointed out that using the number &amp;quot;20&amp;quot; to define a provisional player, and making a player less provisional in clean 5% steps, inevitably offers yet another small, subjective element into this mathematical formula; as we&#39;ll see momentarily Microsoft has more recently incorporated the idea of provisional uncertainty into their core mathematical model, much as the whole ELO system originally turned subjective win and loss statistics into tighter mathematics.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/wonder/TT/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/ttrskotosrankings.png&#34; title=&#34;Ttrskotosrankings&#34; alt=&#34;Ttrskotosrankings&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, to resolve the situation of multiple players, Days of Wonder considers each game to be a set of duels, as described here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
There are 4 players in a &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gang of Four game. Let&#39;s name A the winning player, B the second one, C the third one and D the last one. We consider that there were 6 duels: A won against B, C and D. B won against C and D. C won against D. We compute independently the new scores for each duel, and then we average the values for each player&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a fairly elegant answer that not only rewards or penalizes all players separately, but also encourages playing for second place, or even third, if first isn&#39;t possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been continued discussions of the Days of Wonder ELO variant in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daysofwonder.com/index.php?t=forums&#34;&gt;their forums&lt;/a&gt;, and the questions raised there are common to many different ranking systems. Some players wanted unranked games, while others thought that having unranked games would discourage people from playing good competitors &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; in unranked games.&amp;nbsp; There has also been a lot of discussion regarding &lt;em&gt;Ticket to Ride&lt;/em&gt;, a strategy game that supports 2-5 people, and whether the ELO variant system discourages multiperson play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various lessons learned at Days of Wonder underline two basic ideas about rankings. First, even with a well-studied system like ELO, there&#39;s still a lot to understand, and, second, any ranking system needs to reflect the specifics of what it&#39;s ranking -- and what its purpose is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;xbox_360_live&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations on a Theme: XBox 360 Live&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/default.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskillxbox360&#34; title=&#34;Trueskillxbox360&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/trueskillxbox360.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An even more recent large-scale ranking system is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.microsoft.com/displayArticle.aspx?id=1361&#34;&gt;TrueSkill&lt;/a&gt; system developed by Microsoft for use with the XBox 360. It appears to be an expanded variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://math.bu.edu/people/mg/glicko/glicko.doc/glicko.html&#34;&gt;glicko&lt;/a&gt; ranking system used by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freechess.org/&#34;&gt;free internet chess server&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the problems identified by Microsoft were the same as those already noted by Days of Wonder and others, including: the uncertainty of provisional ratings and the need to rank players in multiplayer games. However, the TrueSkill system notably expands both issues. Ranking uncertainty is now defined as a mathematical concept and the rankings now support not just multiple players, but also multiple teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/trueskill.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=430,height=324,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskill&#34; title=&#34;Trueskill&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/images/trueskill.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;TrueSkill explicitly includes two values in any ranking: a skill level and an uncertainty level. The first, like the more common ELO ranking, tells how good a player is. The second states how sure that ranking is. The uncertainty rating is effectively a margin of error, similar to those we saw in &lt;em&gt;polling systems&lt;/em&gt;. If a first-time player has a skill rating of 25 with an uncertainty rating of 8.3 that means that his skill is probably somewhere in the range of 16.7 to 33.3, a pretty wide range, but then this is a totally untested player. According to benchmarks that Microsoft produced, 99.99% of actual skill levels were within 3x of the uncertainty rating, and 100% were within 4x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of TrueSkill&#39;s innovations are built around this model of uncertainty. All players win or lose skill points, based upon how many players they beat or lose to, and they also decrease their uncertainty rating as they play more games. However, uncertainty is decreased more for players toward the middle of a pack within a game than those around the edges (because on the edges the players could actually be much better or much worse than it is possible to see from a specific game). In addition, TrueSkill is only a zero-sum ranking system for players at the exact same level of uncertainty. The more uncertainty that an opponent possesses, the smaller the weighting of any gain or loss (much like the simpler system that Days of Wonder uses, which bases weightings of games against provisional players as &lt;code&gt;n/20&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall TrueSkill is a somewhat complex system that is described more fully at Microsoft&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/Details.aspx#How_to_Update_Skills&#34;&gt;web site&lt;/a&gt;. Some of their expansions had already been considered by others, but still their system is notably innovative in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expanding a competitive ranking system to include concepts of teams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incorporating the uncertainty of ratings further into the core mathematical model, rather than using a somewhat more subjective model such as that described by Days of Wonder for provisional players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.microsoft.com/mlp/trueskill/RankCalculator.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/trueskillcalculator_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Trueskillcalculator_1&#34; alt=&#34;Trueskillcalculator_1&#34; class=&#34;image-full&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The TrueSkill calculations are a bit complex. In general, that&#39;s not a problem for a computer-based ranking model because you can have a computer doing all the computations, and players only need to understand the results. However the two-part ranking system used by TrueSkill, which notes both skill level and uncertainty, does offer a potential problem on this latter point. &lt;em&gt;Can players understand it?&lt;/em&gt; In general, the concept of uncertainty will not be understood by people other that statisticians, thus raising a real user-interface question with the TrueSkill system -- and the exact sort of thing that designers of new ranking systems will need to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;a_tale_in_the_desert&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Variations on a Theme: A Tale in the Desert&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atid.com&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;A_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1&#34; title=&#34;A_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/a_tale_in_the_desert_logo_1.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The online game, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atitd.com&#34;&gt;A Tale in the Desert&lt;/a&gt;, identified a different problem with the ELO system: &lt;em&gt;cheating&lt;/em&gt;. This is a uniquely Internet-based problem, because there users can create fake accounts, then defeat those accounts to win points. This can also be done more subtly, by having multiple additional accounts build up the rating of that fake account before the fake account is defeated. So a totally new ranking system, called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.atitd.net/tale1/EGenesis_Ranking_System&#34;&gt;eGenesis Ranking System&lt;/a&gt;, was created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each player is ranked through a 256-bit vector, half of which is initially set to 0 and half of which is set to 1 (therefore creating an average ranking of 128). Whenever a match occurs between players a hash function based on the players&#39; names mathematically selects 32 of those bits, 8 of which are then randomly selected. Among those bits, any 1s in the loser&#39;s vector which correspond to 0s in the winner&#39;s vector are &amp;quot;transferred&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple design corresponds in some ways to ELO&#39;s more complex formula. A good player will have more 1s and thus more to lose, and he will lose correspondingly more to a poor player who has more 0s in his vector. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the system also prevents the collusion earlier noted. Statistically, a single player will only ever gain 8 ranking points from another new player, since out of the 32 bit hash only eight of those will, on average, be in the correct 0-1 configuration. Expanding a group of players expands the number of points that can potentially be gained, but within real limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wowsocialmap_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Wowsocialmap_1&#34; alt=&#34;Wowsocialmap_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In fact, the eGenesis system prevents cheating by measuring the size of social networks, then limiting the number of ranking points that can be earned within a social network. It&#39;s not necessarily the only way to measure social network size, but its methodology points toward social software as an interesting area for additional study of ranking systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with XBox&#39;s TrueSkill, the eGenesis algorithms are overall fairly sophisticated and confusing, perhaps more so than TrueSkill itself. However, unlike TrueSkill the output is very simple: a skill number between 0 and 255. The intricacies are hidden by the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Competitive Ranking Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, as we mentioned when discussing Days of Wonder, any ranking system has to be measured by what it&#39;s trying to do and how well it does that. ELO and similar numerical, long-term ranking systems, are most likely trying to achieve one of three goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;heirarchy&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hierarchy:&lt;/strong&gt; Players are divided into hierarchies of success, giving players goals to constantly strive for and ways to measure their success (or failure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;matching&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matching:&lt;/strong&gt; Players can play with other players at their same skill level, rather than having to play beginners or experts who are much better than they are. This generally increases everyone&#39;s enjoyment. For computer games, the complexity of a matching system can be largely moderated by the computer, thus ensuring better competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;handicapping&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handicapping:&lt;/strong&gt; If players do play against others of different skill levels, the better players can be handicapped in automatic, appropriate ways for the game in question, again increasing the fairness of games and everyone&#39;s enjoyment. For instance, someone ranked 3-kyu in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28board_game%29&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; playing a less experienced 7-kyu player would give him a starting &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_handicap&#34;&gt;4 stone advantage&lt;/a&gt; to make for better competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ELO system may be a good matching system, which allows players to easily find other players of their same skill level and play against them. However it doesn&#39;t provide any way to handicap players, nor would the ELO method necessarily be a good one to analyze handicaps (and conversely a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golf_handicap&#34;&gt;golf handicap&lt;/a&gt; might not do a good job of finding like players nor measuring players&#39; ability in a hierarchy). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently the XBox system has stated that it&#39;s explicitly for matchmaking, with the goal being to always try and match up players at nearly the same skill level. It&#39;s also used for hierarchy (or &amp;quot;leaderboards&amp;quot; as it&#39;s described in the TrueSkill docs), but that&#39;s clearly a subsidiary purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these systems would be ineffective for measuring a winner in a live event, which is a very different goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tourney:&lt;/strong&gt; A single player is listed as an absolute winner, the &amp;quot;King of the Hill&amp;quot;. Often, second, third, and fourth place winners are measured too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the systems we&#39;ve discussed thus far may not be useful for measuring privileges, yet another goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threshold:&lt;/strong&gt; The best ranks of players can be given special privileges, including the ability to create games and form tournaments. Alternatively, they can be given privileges totally outside the game, again giving them something extra to strive for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each of these additional goals we may need to consider very different ranking systems, not just variations of ELO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;tourneys&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Different Themes: Tourneys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.kumc.edu/itc/staff/rknight/tourneys.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Tournament_1&#34; title=&#34;Tournament_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/tournament_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
There are a number of well-known tournament types which can be used to create a &amp;quot;King of the Hill&amp;quot; ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-elimination_tournament&#34;&gt;single-elimination tournament,&lt;/a&gt; where the winner of each competition moves on to compete with other winners, until there is only one. However, this style of tournament is quite cut-throat and is not suited very well to events where the competition may result in a draw, or where chance is a notable factor in the competition. It also has a very subjective factor in the initial &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-elimination_tournament#Seeding&#34;&gt;seeding&lt;/a&gt; of the rounds. The single-elimination tournament also does not rank the losers. However, by having the losers compete with each other in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swiss_system_tournament&#34;&gt;Swiss-style tournament&lt;/a&gt;, the relative strengths of the players can be ranked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jsoo.home.mindspring.com/articles/formats/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/pseudodoubleelimination_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Pseudodoubleelimination_1&#34; alt=&#34;Pseudodoubleelimination_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An improvement is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double-elimination&#34;&gt;double-elimination tournament&lt;/a&gt; which is now one of the best known tournament systems in sports. Players compete in series of two-player matches, and a player has to lose twice before he&#39;s eliminated. This is done through a system of winner and loser brackets, wherein people drop from the winners&#39; brackets to the losers&#39; brackets when they lose once, and drop out altogether when they lose twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem with standard double-elimination is that there are unusual situations where a significantly inferior player can still make it to the final round, or the last player to remain undefeated can lose only once and still be eliminated. These can be addressed through variants such as face-off (requiring the last two remaining competitors to compete &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; if the undefeated team is defeated for the first time in the finals) or by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jsoo.home.mindspring.com/articles/formats/&#34;&gt;reconfiguring the loser&#39;s brackets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wscgames.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Wsc_1&#34; title=&#34;Wsc_1&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/wsc_1.png&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Round-robin_tournament&#34;&gt;Round-robin tournaments&lt;/a&gt;, such as official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wscgames.com/2005/build/standing/1/topten.html&#34;&gt;Scrabble Tournaments&lt;/a&gt; involve every player playing a set number of games (24 in the 2005 World Scrabble Championship), facing opponents with similar win-lose records. They then ultimately rank players by their win-lose ratios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of these sorts of tournament over an ELO-style ranking is that they&#39;re easily understandable and seem fair. In addition, they measure ranking in a much more topical manner: how well someone is playing during a singular instant, rather than over a longer career. As a result they work much better for a live tournament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;thresholds&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Different Themes: Thresholds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we discussed in our original article on Collective Choice, thresholds are ranking barriers above which members get a special ability--or alternatively levels below which members lose a special ability. They can also act as another goal for a ranking system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usgo.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/gosmall.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Gosmall&#34; alt=&#34;Gosmall&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In the game of Go there are both &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_ranks_and_ratings#Pro_and_amateur_ranks&#34;&gt;amateur&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_ranks_and_ratings#Professional_strength&#34;&gt;professional&lt;/a&gt; players. Although they aren&#39;t technically in the same &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cns.nyu.edu/~mechner/go/kyu.html&#34;&gt;hierarchy of rankings&lt;/a&gt;, the highest Go amateur ranking&amp;nbsp; (7 dan) is approximately equal to the lowest Go professional ranking (1 dan), forming a de facto threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/uscf_1.png&#34; title=&#34;Uscf_1&#34; alt=&#34;Uscf_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Likewise the United States Chess Federation uses their ELO rankings to denote &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Chess Masters&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone who achieves 2200 UCSF is given a National Master threshold ranking and anyone who maintains it for 300 games is given a Life Master threshold ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/photos/uncategorized/acblopt2_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Acblopt2_1&#34; alt=&#34;Acblopt2_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/&#34;&gt;American Contract Bridge Association&lt;/a&gt; uses a threshold system where you have to win a certain number of tournaments and thus earn &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acbl.org/about/honorTitles.html&#34;&gt;masterpoints&lt;/a&gt; in order achieve official rankings such as &amp;quot;section master&amp;quot;. Furthermore, players may earn different &amp;quot;colors&amp;quot; of masterpoints depending the difficulty of the tournament, and some ranks require that you earn at least some specific colored masterpoints in order to meet the requirements for the next threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These thresholds are fairly explicitly based on other hierarchical ranking systems, but this doesn&#39;t need to be the case. Since determining the purpose of a ranking system is often the first step in designing it, as we delve further into the area of thresholds we may well find that systems specifically dedicated toward measuring thresholds are more likely to do so well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our next article we&#39;ll consider among other things the Avogadro reputation system, which manages thresholds in such a way as to prevent cheating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s actually a lot of variety in ranking systems, and even though we&#39;d like them to be totally objective, various subjective elements often creep into these systems. In addition, there&#39;s a lot of variety in what ranking systems can do. For competitive systems, hierarchy, privilege, matching, and handicapping are some of the top purposes of ranking. Determining what a ranking system is going to do is a necessary first step in designing the system, as different systems will accomplish various goals to a better or worse degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ELO, in several variants, is the best studied and most used competitive ranking system. It works particularly well as a matching system. However, even ELO has flaws in it, among them: issues with new player rankings; its core two-player basis; its lack of provisions for teams; a few minor subjective elements; and problems with cheaters. New systems continue to be rolled out on the Internet to resolve these issues, and overall, it&#39;s an area of interesting new study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tournament systems and threshold systems offer a few good examples of competitive ranking systems with very different purposes, underlying the need to understand what you&#39;re doing before you do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking systems also lay very near yet another type of Collective Choice: reputation systems. We briefly addressed reputation systems when talking about threshold systems and will return to this in our next article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related articles from this blog:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Systems for Collective Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2005-12: Collective Choice: Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html&#34;&gt;2006-08: Using 5-Star Rating Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html&#34;&gt;2007-01: Experimenting with Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles from Shannon Appelcline&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/show-column.phtml?colname=TTnT_&#34;&gt;Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities:&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_192.phtml&#34;&gt;#192: Managing User Creativity, Part One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_193.phtml&#34;&gt;#193: Managing User Creativity, Part Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_196.phtml&#34;&gt;#196: Collective Choice: Ratings, Who Do You Trust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/articles/TTnT_/TTnT_198.phtml&#34;&gt;#198: Collective Choice: More Thoughts About Ratings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;A data point on ELO cheating for you: Yahoo! Games uses ELO rankings for several their two-player games. Before recent abuse mitigation changes, some people used robot to accumulate scores in excess of 6,000,000 points. The abuse-the-ranking game had become a totally seperate competition.
For now, Yahoo! has capped the ELO scores at 3,000 (I think.) This removed most of the cheating incentive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.fudco.com/habitat&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-05T13:46:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-05T13:46:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;In the slashdot discussion of this blog entry http://games.slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=173988&amp;threshold=0&amp;mode=flat   there was an interesting link to beatpaths.com, which is sort of a tourney system for when you can&#39;t complete a full set of round-robin or double-elimination competitions, as what happens in NFL during the fall season.
What is also interesting to me is that it introduces a goal for ranking systems that I&#39;d not thought of before -- prediction. The purpose of the beatpath systems is actually focused on predicting the outcome the next set of the weekend games.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-14T14:31:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-14T14:31:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;No mention of Glicko and Glicko2?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://swaits.com/&#34;&gt;Stephen Waits&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-01-15T08:57:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-01-15T08:57:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;There&#39;s a ranking scheme that Mark Newman from the U of Michigan did for college football, which Yahoo Search turned up a pointer to here:
http://www.sciencenews.org/articles/20051112/mathtrek.asp
quoting:
Physicists Juyong Park and M.E.J. Newman aimed for a ranking system that&#39;s fast and easily understood by fans (in contrast to the cumbersome, opaque BCS formula). They based their ranking method on the notion that, if A beats B, and B beats C, then A also beats C, even if it may not actually play C. Hence, the method counts both direct wins by beating a team and indirect wins by beating a team that beat another team.
(end quote)
You end up with a directed graph of teams as nodes and games as edges, and compute a function of that graph that is related to a centrality metric.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://vielmetti.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Edward Vielmetti&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-02-02T22:18:39-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-02-02T22:18:39-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This article is a great survey of the subject!  I&#39;m working on the PvP ranking system for another game with some unique problems, because the teams in a PvP match can be of disparate size and widely differing power levels, which are then balanced so that wildly mismatched teams (ignoring relative rank at PvP for the moment) are actually reasonably matched.
It starts here: http://ncanson.livejournal.com/3938.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ncanson.livejournal.com/&#34;&gt;Matthew Weigel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-01-31T09:55:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-01-31T09:55:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lifewithalacrity.github.io/previous/2006/01/ranking_systems.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34;&gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>