<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>collective choice on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/collective-choice/</link>
    <description>Recent content in collective choice on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 22:38:15 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/collective-choice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Experimenting with Ratings</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 22:38:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2007/01/collective_choi.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[This is the fourth in a series of articles on collective choice, co-written by my collegue Shannon Appelcline. It will be jointly posted in Shannon&#39;s Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities online games column at Skotos.]
Last year in Collective Choice: Rating Systems we took a careful look at eBay and other websites that collect ratings, and used those systems as examples to highlight a number of theories about how to make rating systems more useful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ratings: Who Do You Trust?</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2006 16:28:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/09/ratings_who_do_.html</guid>
      <description>My colleague, Shannon Appelcline, has been working on a game rating system for RPGnet. This has resulted in real-world application of the principles for designing rating systems which we&#39;ve previously discussed in our Collective Choice articles. Shannon&#39;s newest article, Ratings, Who Do You Trust? offers a look at weighting ratings based on reliability.
On the RPGnet Gaming Index we&#39;ve put this all together to form a tree of weighted ratings that answer the question, who do you trust?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using 5-Star Rating Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 08:49:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/using_5star_rat.html</guid>
      <description>In Collective Choice: Rating Systems I discuss ratings scales of various sorts, from eBay&#39;s 3-point scale to RPGnet&#39;s double 5-point scale, and BoardGame Geek&#39;s 10-point scale.

Of the various ratings scales, 5-point scales are probably the most common on the Internet. You can find them not just in my own RPGnet, but also on Amazon, Netflix, and iTunes, as well as many other sites and services. Unfortunately 5-point rating scales also face many challenges in their use, and different studies suggest different flaws with this particular methodology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Competitive Ranking Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2006 23:37:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/01/ranking_systems.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[This is the third in a series of articles on collective choice, co-written by my collegue Shannon Appelcline. It will be jointly posted in Shannon&#39;s Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities online games column at Skotos.]
In our first article on collective choice we outlined a number of different types of choice systems, among them voting, polling, rating, and ranking. Since then we&#39;ve been spending some time expanding upon the systems, with the goal being to create both a lexicon of and a dialogue about systems for collective choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Choice: Rating Systems</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2005 17:58:34 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/collective_choi.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[This is the second of a series of articles on collective choice, co-written by my collegue Shannon Appelcline. It will be jointly posted in Shannon&#39;s Trials, Triumphs &amp;amp; Trivialities online games column at Skotos.]
In our previous article we talked about the many systems available for collective choice. There are selection systems, which are primarily centered on voting and deliberation, opinion systems, which represent how voting could occur, and finally comparison systems, which rank or rate different people or things in a simple, comparative manner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems for Collective Choice</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2005 16:03:26 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/12/systems_for_col.html</guid>
      <description>by Christopher Allen &amp;amp; Shannon Appelcline
[Shannon Appelcline is a friend and colleague of mine at Skotos, an online game company. Over the last few years we&#39;ve had many discussions about how decisions are made, and how our society collectively makes choices. The origin of these discussions have varied from &amp;quot;what makes this board game work?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how can we give our players more control of our online games?&amp;quot;, to &amp;quot;how do we make decisions in our company?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
