<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community By The Numbers on Life With Alacrity</title>
    <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/community-by-the-numbers/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community By The Numbers on Life With Alacrity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/tags/community-by-the-numbers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>“Look Up” Your Strong Ties, Connect to Your Weak Ties</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/05/look-up-your-strong-ties-connect-to-your-weak-ties.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 12:02:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2014/05/look-up-your-strong-ties-connect-to-your-weak-ties.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;fb-root&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;script id=&#34;facebook-jssdk&#34; src=&#34;//connect.facebook.net/en_US/all.js#xfbml=1&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;fb-post&#34; data-href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/ChristopherRayAllen/posts/10152397235185540&#34; data-width=&#34;600&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;fb-xfbml-parse-ignore&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/ChristopherRayAllen/posts/10152397235185540&#34;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/ChristopherRayAllen&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2014/05/look-up-your-strong-ties-connect-to-your-weak-ties.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dyads &amp; Triads — The Smallest Teams</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 14:16:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(by Christopher Allen with Elyn Andersson and Shannon Appelcline)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.BGI.edu&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;BGIedu Logo&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;100&#34; src=&#34;http://www.bgi.edu/files/BGI-Logomark-CMYK.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; width=&#34;100&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Two years ago, the Bainbridge Graduate Institute (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.BGI.edu&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Bainbridge Graduate Institute&#34;&gt;www.BGI.edu&lt;/a&gt;) faculty gathered to radically reinvent their sustainable business curriculum for the next decade. Our goal was not only to update course content, but also to significantly update how the material was taught. We wished to make our teaching process (our pedagogy) more interactive and also more effective for students graduating into a 21st-century work environment, where people increasingly work in teams-both online and offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a specialist in group interactions, I was asked by the faculty whether formal graduate student study groups (called &amp;quot;Study Buddies&amp;quot;) should consist of two people or of three. I did not have an easy answer to this question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My expertise with group dynamics comes from professional experience as an entrepreneur and from considerable experience both building online communities and helping others to do the same. Through these processes, I&amp;#39;ve seen how groups of people act differently at different sizes. As I discussed in my previous blog post on Group Thresholds [&lt;a href=&#34;#Allen&#34;&gt;Allen&lt;/a&gt;], there are pros and cons associated with different group sizes. However, the smallest group that I spoke of in that article was the &amp;#39;working team size&amp;#39;, which is a group of four to nine members (but ideally about seven). I didn&amp;#39;t talk about groups consisting of less than four members-specifically dyads (a group of two people) and triads (a group of three people)-and that was what the BGIedu faculty was now interested in learning more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first inclination when considering BGIedu&amp;#39;s request was to say that triads would be the best size for study groups, but I wasn&amp;#39;t sure. I knew from my past research on group size that a dyad has a significantly different behavior than any other small groups. However, I wasn&amp;#39;t certain if triads should also be considered on their own, or if they were just the low end of one of those &amp;#39;work teams&amp;#39;, which I&amp;#39;d always thought of as containing four to nine members. Triads were a hole in my research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to dig deeper into this question by engaging my teaching assistant Elyn Andersson and my writing partner Shannon Appelcline to help me investigate further. This post is the fruit of our research and our discussions about dyads and triads. We hope it might help you decide whether a dyad or a triad is the better team size for groups that you are working in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;choosing&#34; name=&#34;choosing&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Choosing between Dyads and Triads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c3859329f970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pythagorian Dyad - Public Domain&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c3859329f970b&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c3859329f970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Pythagorian Dyad - Public Domain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Before I share with you the details of our investigation, I want to be clear that dyads, triads, and small &amp;#39;working team&amp;#39; groups can all be effective. Any challenge faced by groups of these sizes can be overcome by a good process, teamwork, training, or just positive energy. However, my thesis is that certain sizes of groups are better for certain purposes-and when a group size is selected appropriately it will require less energy and thus be more likely to be productive when the inevitable group challenges occur. When choosing among a dyad, a triad, or a working team, the important thing to focus on is thus the intent in forming the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the groups being considered by BGIedu, the faculty felt that the students taking the new curriculum needed three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More formal support for studying (i.e. not ad hoc study teams);&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of emotional support in that support structure; and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A system where the members of a study group would help each other to keep their commitments to study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last requirement - that members of these study teams would be accountable to each other without one student just taking up the slack of another - was the toughest one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, working teams of 4-9 people were too large for our purposes. Teams this size are rarely intimate enough to support the needs of individuals. In addition, research shows that they are poor at supporting accountability. That&amp;#39;s because working teams of 4-9 are very vulnerable to social loafing (i.e., slackers)-except when the tasks assigned to these working teams are highly independent (i.e. an entrepreneurial team that has different members focused on different topics, such as management, development, operations, marketing and sales) or when they require high diversity. An upcoming blog will cover this topic in more depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c38593410970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pythagorian Triad - Public Domain&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c38593410970b&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef017c38593410970b-800wi&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; title=&#34;Pythagorian Triad - Public Domain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Removing working teams left the question of dyad vs. triad - which our research would show were both very different from working teams. Triads ultimately fit BGIedu&amp;#39;s particular need better. That was primarily due to advantages of accountability and cohesion, combined with some emotional support. However, some simple numerical properties of triads also prove useful: they have elemental diversity because they&amp;#39;re up to 50% more diverse than dyads; and if someone misses a team meeting the other two-thirds of the team can still benefit. For all of these reasons, my recommendation to the BGIedu faculty was that these formal study teams be formed in triads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dyads, however, are quite appropriate for a variety of other purposes, and should not be dismissed. I&amp;#39;ll be talking of some of their advantages before proceeding on to the lessons learned about triads themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;dyad&#34; name=&#34;dyad&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Dyad&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has had experience with dyads. The first social experience of anyone&amp;#39;s life is a dyadic relationship - that between a mother and her unborn child. This parent-child relationship continues once the child is born. Overall, dyads are the most common social group; they are seen everywhere, in personal, academic and business relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/94611163@N00/683866337/&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Great Guitar Duo — Photo by Tom706 CC-BY-NC-ND&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1108/683866337_4dd654b650_n.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;To decide if a dyad is the best group size for your needs, it is again important to focus on the purpose of the group. A number of interesting characteristics of dyads - some benefits and some limitations - make them unique from triads and other larger group sizes, among them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotional Support&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commitment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reasoned Agreement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power Inequality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Group Accountability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;emotional_support&#34; name=&#34;emotional_support&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Emotional Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been some academic studies [&lt;a href=&#34;#Taylor&#34;&gt;Taylor&lt;/a&gt;] that suggest that it&amp;#39;s easier to be open and share within dyads. The research has shown that people feel safer about revealing personal and intimate information in a dyad than they do when a third person is added to the group. As a result, disclosure rates increase when people are put into dyads as compared to triads. Furthermore, adding a third person to a group causes its members to be more socially conscious, making it harder for members to listen to the conversation and at the same time be aware of their own thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together it&amp;#39;s this trust level (allowing for disclosure) and this focus level (allowing for better listening) that make dyads much stronger for emotional support than triads or larger teams. If the intent of a group is to have an intimate and fully open space, or if the work of the group is emotional in nature, this might make dyads a better choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though dyads are clearly more effective for providing emotional support, triads can still offer that as well under the right conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;commitment&#34; name=&#34;commitment&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Commitment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This intimacy and confidentiality of a dyad helps its members to build strong team dynamics relatively quickly. The two individuals not only will have formed a trust bond more easily than three or more individuals could, but they generally will have a better ratio of time to performance outcomes compared to groups of larger sizes, in part because less time is spent maintaining the team relationship itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a triad or larger group, the group would need to put effort towards team work over task work and thus less time is put towards performing the task. In other words, more resources would be spent on relating to a teammate than on finishing a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;reasoned_agreement&#34; name=&#34;reasoned_agreement&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Reasoned Agreement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most unique element of dyads is that they are the only group size in which one voice is paired against another voice equally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you were in dyad in which you did not agree on an issue? Most likely, you and the other individual spent some considerable time trying to convince the other of your reasons, and the outcome was one of two things: you either both stuck with your opinion and walked away, or one of you changed your mind after hearing the other&amp;#39;s ideas and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because members can&amp;#39;t &amp;#39;vote&amp;#39;, a dyad is either in agreement or disagreement, which forces a longer deliberation for tasks when consensus is required. There are times when you want a small group to deliberate deeply, and dyads are ideal for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;power_inequality&#34; name=&#34;power_inequality&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Power Inequality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though dyads have several advantages, they can also bring with them a few additional problems - one of which is a power inequality of knowledge that would be detrimental within some teams. For some tasks, this could offset the benefits of having a more intimate small group. For my BGIedu groups, I was concerned that it might prevent some students from benefiting academically from the study exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic has been addressed in a study &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160289604000972&#34;&gt;[&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#Day&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Day&#34;&gt;Day&lt;/a&gt;] that compared homogeneous teams that were entirely high-ability or low-ability to heterogeneous dyads of mixed abilities. The study found that while high-ability people tested better individually after learning the material in a dyad with another high-ability team mate, low-ability people did not gain much benefit from studying in a dyad with a high-ability team member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was somewhat surprising. A student with more knowledge of a subject should be able to mentor a student with less knowledge, therefore creating a true dyad study partner. However, this study showed that this was not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study also argued against another common conception. One might assume that two high-ability team members could learn more together, when they could bounce ideas off of each other, than they could alone. However, this was again not the case: high-ability individuals performed better after learning alone than after learning with another high-ability team member! Only homogeneous low-ability teammates performed better after being in a dyad than alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study pushed me toward triads for study teams at BGIedu, as dyads would not be large enough to guarantee high performance outcomes; the teams would always consist of one higher performing student and one lower performing student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;group_accountability&#34; name=&#34;group_accountability&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Group Accountability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another disadvantage of dyads shows up in the area of accountability. The simplest version of this issue can be shown in this question: if one teammate says she did the majority of the work, while the other teammate says the work was shared 50/50, who was correct? A tougher question: if they both say that the work was shared 50/50, how is a third party able to determine if this actually was true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elyn, my teaching assistant, interned in a high school in Seattle while working towards her Master&amp;#39;s in Teaching. Her experiences highlight this problem. In today&amp;#39;s educational model, collaborative learning is highly valued, and Elyn worked to incorporate in-class group work into many of her lessons. When assessing the students&amp;#39; group projects, however, she found that it was difficult to determine if the students shared the work equitably or if some of the students rode on the hard work of their partners. In some cases, Elyn doubted that the work was split equally. In particular, she found that if she let the students choose their own partners, the students were more likely to say that &amp;#39;both&amp;#39; did the work, rather than tell the teacher their friend slacked off on the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent study [&lt;a href=&#34;#Alkaslassy&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Alkaslassy&lt;/a&gt;]&amp;#0160;supports Elyn&amp;#39;s experience. In it, students working on a paired group assignment were asked to allocate the percent of work done between the pair. 86% of the students assigned equal credit between the two individuals in the group. At a surface level, one could presume that each party performed half the work and was honest in their assignment of credit. However, Elyn and I believe that in some dyadic relationships, friendship can become an overriding factor and that in those situations, students are more likely to allocate equal credit because of this friendship, not because of true equity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the psychological field, this relates to a well-known cognitive bias called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egocentric_bias&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; title=&#34;Wikipedia: Egocentric Bias&#34;&gt;egocentric bias&lt;/a&gt;, where an individual will claim more responsibility for group action then an independent observer would credit them. Although this is most often discussed for larger groups, in dyads a member might rate their own efforts as being half of the effort when in fact is it is less. Thus in academic group projects, it can sometimes be more effective to have the students rate their peer rather than themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though group accountability can be a disadvantage for dyads, it improves when you have triads, thanks in part to a triad&amp;#39;s inability to devolve. This, as it turns out, would be another comparative advantage that helped me choose triads over dyads for BGIedu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;triads&#34; name=&#34;triads&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Triads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/yaketyyakyak/5991422366/in/photostream/&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Fernando&amp;#39;s Kitchen, Cambridge 30-07-11 —&amp;#0160;Photo by Dave Catchpole CC-BY&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6123/5991422366_6301a83c43_n.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;There are a number of interesting characteristics of triads that make them different from dyads and also from small &amp;#39;working team&amp;#39; groups. I&amp;#39;ll talk about three of them in this article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inability to Devolve&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elemental Diversity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;inability_to_devolve&#34; name=&#34;inability_to_devolve&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Inability to Devolve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have experienced what happens when a party gets too busy or too noisy - the size of the conversation groups get smaller. If you are having an informal dinner for seven, sometimes the conversation will include the entire table. However while people are eating the conversation will typically devolve into smaller groups: four people at one end of the table will being having one conversation, while the remaining three will be talking at the end other. Sometimes one person will be left out of any conversation, but studies show that with small groups this is less likely to happen. We have a natural tendency not to want to exclude or reject individuals unjustly, so such a singleton will usually find a place in one conversation or another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working teams also have this natural tendency to devolve when confronted with external challenges (of which noise is one of the simpler ones) or internal challenges (such as differences of opinion), only reuniting when those challenges are resolved. A team of six can devolve gracefully a number of different ways: a three and a three; a four and a two; or three groups of two. Teams of five can devolve into teams of two and three. A team of four can devolve into two teams of two. In all of these cases the devolution does not exclude any individual&amp;#39;s voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a triad can not devolve without excluding someone. Triads thus have a lot of subtle pressure to try to keep the group together, so that no individual is explicitly rejected - except for a good reason. This leads to more accountability for the individuals in the group, compared to teams of two where the dyadic nature of the group can override liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;voting&#34; name=&#34;voting&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Unconscious Voting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dyad&amp;#39;s inability to vote was an advantage of that group size, and thus issues that require deeper deliberation are often better with dyads. However, you sometimes don&amp;#39;t want as much deliberation. You want fast action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that we unconsciously gauge each others&amp;#39; opinions in a small group very quickly, and even more so with a triad. This means that a triad seems to be able to come to at least some decision very fast. There are many cases where this can be very useful - if that is the intent of your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an personal example, I saw a presentation in the early 1990s from the Apple Human Interface Group (HIG) about their survey of how users colored &amp;quot;folders&amp;quot; on the Macintosh. The result was that there was little commonality - everyone colored folders differently for different reasons. Afterward, I met with the team and suggested that that if they instead asked teams of three to decide how to color code folders that they used together, then the results from all the different teams would have much more commonality. This suggestion ended up getting me a consulting job with Apple HIG, and shows how a triad can quickly create successful performance outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Triads are not the only group size that can vote easily - all odd size groups can - but I believe the voting of a triad to be fundamentally different because the voting can be so unconscious and informal that the members are not even aware of it. This can be useful, but it can also cause problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was just starting my business, I was doing a lot of work with a company formed by two partners who had a 50/50 stock split in their company. Theirs was a good partnership; they had very different but complementary skills and worked well and profitably together. As a fellow entrepreneur, I was a peer to both them, and we were developing a new product line together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when I worked with them on this product line, I saw that I&amp;#39;d changed their very successful dyad to a triad, and I thus became a tiebreaker in many of their business decisions - including business decisions on issues that had nothing to do with our joint product. This was caused by a shift in power: one partner might ask me a question about marketing rather than asking his partner (who knew marketing), and then it would become our opinion against the remaining partner&amp;#39;s. Conversely, I found the marketing partner asking me to side with him on development questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this quite troubling; a more manipulative person could have controlled or broken that relationship by always breaking the ties in their own favor. In our case, we never shipped the product line and went our separate ways. I couldn&amp;#39;t help but think it might have been because my unofficial &amp;quot;vote&amp;quot; was causing problems in their partnership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When getting a result is the purpose of a team, a triad is better than a dyad as it allows for this voting to take place. As I mentioned to BGIedu, a triad can have a two-to-one vote, allowing a better chance at task accomplishment. Task accomplishment is also achieved because triads stay on topic better than dyads due of this voting ratio: if one member of a dyad decides to go off topic, it is easy for the other to follow his or her lead. In a a triad, two out of the three members would need to &amp;#39;agree&amp;#39; to follow an unrelated discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;elemental_diversity&#34; name=&#34;elemental_diversity&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Elemental Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final advantage of triads when compared to dyads is that the knowledge base of the group is larger. I saw this issue clearly in my recent Social Web for Social Change class at BGIedu, where I changed the team size from two to three, and immediately saw a growth in elemental diversity that benefited the groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this class, I have the students participate in an exercise on personal branding. I originally had the students pair up in teams of two, effectively giving each student a &amp;#39;branding buddy&amp;#39; to help them form their personal brand and to give and receive feedback. In the last year, however, I decided to change this dyad to a triad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, these groups followed the same methods I used for dyads: one person would self-brand themselves to a second person in the group, who would then echo back what they thought they heard the first person say, using their own words. However, it is difficult for two people to really hear the similarities and differences between what they said and what they heard. The third person thus became a neutral sounding board who told both individuals that spoke what they said. Together, all three could figure out the similarities and differences between the statements. After consensus is reached, all three students switch roles. I call this the Echo Exercise, and it shows how triads can be beneficial at times when the natural characteristics of dyads don&amp;#39;t lead to optimum results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;finalnotes&#34; name=&#34;finalnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Final Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Triple-Spiral-Symbol-filled.svg&#34; style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Tripal Spiral —&amp;#0160;from Wikimedia Commons, Public Domain&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c2/Triple-Spiral-Symbol-filled.svg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; width=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;As it happens, this article was created by a triad. It wasn&amp;#39;t purposeful, nor was it meant to show off the findings of this article. Instead, the triad evolved naturally because it proved the best group size for writing this piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came up with the initial concept for the article and wrote out the problem and introduction. Elyn then did considerable research and wrote up a rough draft of her findings. To that point, we were a committed dyad, working together in an organic way. However, we also had an article that felt like it was in two parts. That&amp;#39;s when I had Shannon join us. He reorganized the article, unified its voice, and produced a final draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it wasn&amp;#39;t purposeful, you can see the advantages of triads just from this example. Most notably, our triad made great use of elemental diversity. Though I held the core ideas and concepts for the article, Elyn provided the research expertise and Shannon provided the editorial expertise that were required to complete it. Voting also came into the equation (in the unconscious way that it tends to in triads) when Shannon effectively &amp;quot;broke the tie&amp;quot; of two different writing styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, this triad has fallen apart. It&amp;#39;s something that was created for a specific project and with all of our other tasks, we didn&amp;#39;t have room for it going forward. Teams breaking apart is natural. Sometimes it happens under normal conditions (as was the case with this triad), and sometimes it happens as a result of unhealthy conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not give BGIedu any advice at the time about the termination of a team, although it will eventually come up: some teams will end badly, and members of these groups may leave with an impression that a triad is a bad group size, even though the size did not lead the group to ending in an unhealthy way. Perhaps the groups should be counseled, or perhaps the members should jump right back on the triad horse ... but that&amp;#39;s a topic for another article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, I&amp;#39;d like to open the conversation up to you. Have you had experiences in either dyads or triads that you would like to share? Were you one of the BGIedu students in a Study Buddy triad? Did the experiences match the studies shown here or did you have an experience that differed? We invite your comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reference:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Allen&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Allen, Christopher (2008) &lt;em&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part One: Group Thresholds&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#0160;Life With Alacrity (blog) (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;/2008/09/group-threshold.html&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Alkaslassy&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Alkaslassy, E. (2011)&lt;em&gt; How often do students working in two-person teams report that work was shared equitably?&lt;/em&gt; Assessment &amp;amp; Evaluation in Higher Education, 36. 367-375. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02602930903428700#preview&#34;&gt;(http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02602930903428700#preview&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Baer&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Baer, M. (2010) &lt;em&gt;The Strength-of-Weak-Ties Perspective on Creativity: A comprehensive Examination and Extension.&lt;/em&gt; Journal of Applied Psychology, 95 592-601. &lt;a href=&#34;http://apps.olin.wustl.edu/workingpapers/pdf/2010-02-008.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://apps.olin.wustl.edu/workingpapers/pdf/2010-02-008.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Basden&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Basden, B.H., Basden, D.R., Henry, S. (2000) &lt;em&gt;Costs and Benefits of Collaborative Remembering&lt;/em&gt;. Applied Cognitive Psychology, 1. 497-507. &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://124.42.15.59/ck/2011-03/165/030/165/530/Research%20ArticleCosts%20and%20benefits%20of%20collaborative%20remembering.pdf&#34;&gt;(ftp://124.42.15.59/ck/2011-03/165/030/165/530/Research%20ArticleCosts%20and%20benefits%20of%20collaborative%20remembering.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Bertucci&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Bertucci, A., Conte, S., Johnson, D.W., Johnson, R.T. (2010) &lt;em&gt;The Impact of Size of Cooperative Group on Achievement, Social Support and Self-Esteem&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of General Psychology, 137(2), 256-272. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20718226&#34;&gt;(http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20718226_&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Blaskovich&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Blaskovich, J.L. (2008) &lt;em&gt;Exploring the Effect of Distance: An Experimental Investigation of Virtual Collaboration, Social Loafing and Group Decisions&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Information Systems, 22 27-46. &lt;a href=&#34;http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;amp;id=JINFE3000022000001000027000001&amp;amp;idtype=cvips&amp;amp;gifs=yes&amp;amp;ref=no&#34;&gt;(http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;amp;id=JINFE3000022000001000027000001&amp;amp;idtype=cvips&amp;amp;gifs=yes&amp;amp;ref=no)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Day&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day, E.A., Arthur, W., Bell, S.T., Edwards, B.D., Bennett, W., Mendoza, J.L., &amp;amp; Tubre, T.C. (2005). &lt;em&gt;Ability -based pairing strategies in the team-based training of a complex skill; Does the intelligence of your training partner matter?&lt;/em&gt; Intelligence, 33, 39-65. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160289604000972&#34;&gt;(http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160289604000972)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;De_Cremer&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;De Cremer, D., Leonardelli, G. J. (2003). &lt;em&gt;Cooperation in Social Dilemmas and the Need to Belong: The Moderating Effect of Group Size&lt;/em&gt;. Group Dynamics: Theory, Research and Practice, 2, 168-174 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rotman.utoronto.ca/geoffrey.leonardelli/2003GD.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://www.rotman.utoronto.ca/geoffrey.leonardelli/2003GD.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Laughlin&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Laughlin, P.R., Hatch, E.C., Silver, J.S., Boh, L. (2006) &lt;em&gt;Groups perform better than the best individuals on letters-to-numbers problems: effects of group size&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 4. 644-651. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agileadvice.com/archives/Research%20on%20Group%20Effectiveness%20vs%20Individuals.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://www.agileadvice.com/archives/Research%20on%20Group%20Effectiveness%20vs%20Individuals.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Markam&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Markam, S.E., Dansereau, F. Jr., Alutto, J.A. (1982) &lt;em&gt;Group size and Absenteeism Rates: A Longitudinal Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Academy of Management Journal, 25 921-927. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/pss/256108&#34;&gt;(http://www.jstor.org/pss/256108)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Seibold&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Seibold, D., Kang, P., Gailliard, B., Jahn, J.. &lt;em&gt;Communication that Damages Teamwork: The Dark Side of Teams&lt;/em&gt;. Conference Papers - International Communication Association; 2008 Annual Meeting. 1-32. &lt;a href=&#34;http://citation.allacademic.com//meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/2/3/0/5/1/pages230513/p230513-2.php&#34;&gt;(http://citation.allacademic.com//meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/2/3/0/5/1/pages230513/p230513-2.php)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Smith&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Smith, S. and Haythorn, W.W. (1972) &lt;em&gt;Effects of Compatibility, Crowding, Group Size, and leadership seniority on stress, anxiety hostility and annoyance in isolated groups&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 22, 67-79 &lt;a href=&#34;http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;amp;id=1972-24882-001&#34;&gt;(http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;amp;id=1972-24882-001)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Taylor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Taylor, R. B. De Soto, C.B., Lieb, R., &lt;em&gt;Sharing Secrets: Disclosure and Discretion in Dyads and Triads&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 37, 1196-1203. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbtaylor.net/pub_jpsp_1979.pdf&#34;&gt;(http://www.rbtaylor.net/pub_jpsp_1979.pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I just discovered your site, and I&#39;m really enjoying your posts.
I am an Organizational Leadership student through Fort Hays State University, and this is a fascinating topic.
I can definitely see the point of the disadvantage of voting. Dyads are forced to use consensus decision-making, unless the power differential is so wide that unilateral decisions are made by the dyad&#39;s autocrat.
Consensus, of course, can take a little longer, but being the default for the Dyad, it makes disagreements automatically covert into brainstorming sessions to find solutions that satisfy both parties. Often, these solutions will be creative and superior to either original idea.
Triads, by virtue of the odd number, CAN employ democracy to make decisions, but the question is-- SHOULD they? A Triad can still opt to employ consensus. If it chooses democracy, it can speed decisions, but there is no requirement for democracy to govern the Triad&#39;s decisions. If they opt for consensus, they can once more engage in creative problem-solving that satisfies all parties.
A consensus-based Triad has all the other advantages of a Triad, without the down-side.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Kevin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2014-11-05T12:19:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2014-11-05T12:19:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2013/04/dyads-triads-the-smallest-teams.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing your Social Graph with Google&#43; [Google Plus]</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 16:29:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563798/&#34; title=&#34;Trust Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Trust Circle&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3230/3055563798_5355b9b99c_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With Google+ almost two weeks into its test phase, conversation about this new social network service seems to be going in circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because Circles is the Google+ feature that users are generating the most buzz about. It’s Google’s answer to the problem of organizing your social graph online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_graph&#34;&gt;social graph&lt;/a&gt; it’s a map of everyone you know and how they are related to you. Social graphs are tricky; as you try to define them you’ll inevitably run into some complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete Pachal, news director of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387808,00.asp&#34;&gt;@PCMag&lt;/a&gt; comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;“People want things easy, and Google Circles isn’t easy. It puts the burden on users to take the time to think about each and every contact and put them in a specific bucket. To use the feature effectively, users will certainly have to create new Circles, and that requires even more thought. After using Google+ for a few minutes last night, I was often unsure which Circles to put certain people in and, more to the point, which to leave them out of. And what if you create a new Circle that should include some of the people in other Circles you already have?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circles are lists that you’ve created by grouping people together and giving them a name. They’re important in Google+ because when you post you must explicitly say which “Circles” you wish to share with. Posting to a limited list of people is a big change from existing social networks such as Facebook, where posts are sent to all mutual friends by default, or Twitter, where posts are public. This change forces you to think more deeply about your social graph and who should see each item you post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BwvygI2xKGM&#34; width=&#34;560&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yourinitialsetofcircles&#34;&gt;Your Initial Set of Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google+ will present you with 4 suggested set of Circles: Friends, Family, Acquaintances, and Following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d image-full&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef014e89d8ca03970d-800wi&#34; title=&#34;Default-google+-circles&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Google+ also defines five special Circles: Two are only for reading: &amp;quot;Stream&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; and &amp;quot;Incoming&amp;quot; which is are posts that are shared to you by people not in your Circles. Then are three special Circles managed by Google only for posting: &amp;quot;Your Circles&amp;quot; which is everyone in any of your Circles; “Extended” which is everyone in your Circles plus the people in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; Circles; and “Public” which is &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few find this default set to be sufficient. As a result, most Google+ users are soon creating new Circles, moving people around, renaming Circles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sound reasons for people finding the default Circles limiting. Sociological research shows that everyone has a number of concentric personal circles (see my blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt; for more details). These circles are sometimes called “ego-centric” social graphs as the individual is located in the center. This sort of graph is the model I used when I began reorganizing my own Google+ Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out using Support (for my Support Circle), Close (for my Sympathy Circle), Trusted (for my Trust Circle), and Colleagues (for my Emotional Circle), but that didn’t work for very long. I’ve since been experimenting with a number of different ways to organize my Circles. I wanted an initial set that would offer useful early advice for using Google+ but would still be applicable for when expanded to hundreds of people. (I now have over 600 people in my Circles.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One insight I’ve had is to avoid the word ‘friends’, which has been corrupted to almost meaninglessness in recent years. So instead I use terminology like Peers for my trust circle and Kith for the combination of my support and sympathy circles. (Kith may be familiar to you from the phrase “kith and kin”. The root of kith means “to know”, thus it’s those people that you know very well and that know you very well.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that sub-Circles exist within Circles. Using a ‘general ledger’ system of naming Circles with numbers—which I’ll demonstrate in a moment—helps me keep these Circles and sub-Circles in order and allows me to easily add new Circles when I need to. Hopefully Google+ will in the future introduce features that allow us to order Circles as we please, but until then this numbering system works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Google+ has also shown me that some Circles are for reading and other Circles are for posting. I’ll talk a little more about this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has only been a week, but by combining these insights to organize my Circles I’ve improved my ease of use and become better able to manage my time while using Google+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my recommended initial list of Circles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 ME&lt;/strong&gt; - a simple Circle with just yourself in it, for saving posts, for drafts, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.0 KIN&lt;/strong&gt; - your family &amp;amp; extended family&lt;br /&gt; &lt;strong&gt; 2.0 KITH&lt;/strong&gt; - your best friends, your confidants (i.e. those with whom one shares a secret or private matter, trusting them not to repeat it to others)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.0 PEERS&lt;/strong&gt; - your trusted colleagues, those who you work closely with, your collaborators&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.0 LOCAL&lt;/strong&gt; - your neighbors, parents of your children&amp;#39;s friends, people you&amp;#39;d invite to a party&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.0&lt;/strong&gt; {various groups &amp;amp; interests}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;/strong&gt; - people you know, but that you don&amp;#39;t know well or that don’t know you well&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;/strong&gt; - people who follow you on Google+, who you may or may not know&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;/strong&gt; - people whose posts you read, but who don&amp;#39;t necessarily read your posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 9.0 SPECIAL&lt;/strong&gt; - useful for special lists &amp;amp; exceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expandingcircles&#34;&gt;Expanding Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people will find my default set of ~10 Circles to be very useful, and need only add a few more. However, the design of this set is to allow for much greater expansion should you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like those “personal circles” that I wrote about previously, most of the Circles above are ego-centric: they’re fundamentally centered on your own personal social graph. This isn’t the only potential type of Circle, however. Socio-centric Circles aren’t centered on you, though they still have some sort of membership boundaries, while info-centric Circles are based on topics instead of being based on relationships. These socio-centric and info-centric Circles will support many relationships better than ego-centric Circles do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone seems to write a lot about a particular topic, I put him or her into an appropriate info-centric Circle. My own info-centric Circles thus include people who post about topics like iOS Development, the Social Web, Sustainability/Green, and Entrepreneuring. If a number of people are all part of a group or all come from a certain geographical area then I put them together in a socio-centric circle. After creating the Circles, I put the ones that were geographic into 4.0 of my ledger, then placed the others in 5.0. (I tried separating out groups and interests, and found that didn’t work, so now I keep them together.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now have over 600 people in my Google Plus+ social graph. All together my Circles now look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 30px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0.0 Read Later&lt;br /&gt; 0.1 Drafts&lt;br /&gt; 0.2 Book Project&lt;br /&gt; 0.3 iPad Project&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 1.0 ALL KIN&lt;br /&gt; 1.1 Immediate Family&lt;br /&gt; 1.2 Extended Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 2.0 ALL KITH&lt;br /&gt; 2.1 Close Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.2 Old But Distant Friends&lt;br /&gt; 2.3 Distant Family&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 3.0 ALL PEERS&lt;br /&gt; 3.2 Collaborators&lt;br /&gt; 3.3 Current Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt; 3.4 Former Professional Colleagues&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 4.0 ALL LOCAL&lt;br /&gt; 4.1 Local Kith, Kin &amp;amp; Peers&lt;br /&gt; 4.2 Local Berkeley&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Seattle&lt;br /&gt; 4.3 Non-Local Portland&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 5.0 ALL GROUPS &amp;amp; INTERESTS&lt;br /&gt; 5.1 Entrepreneurs&lt;br /&gt; 5.2 Apple &amp;amp; iOS&lt;br /&gt; 5.3 - iOSDevCamp&lt;br /&gt; 5.4 Green &amp;amp; Sustainability&lt;br /&gt; 5.5 - BGIedu&lt;br /&gt; 5.6 Social Web&lt;br /&gt; 5.7 - Jerry’s Kids&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 6.0 ACQUAINTANCES&lt;br /&gt; 6.1 Familiar Strangers&lt;br /&gt; 6.2 Friendly Strangers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 7.0 FOLLOWS ME&lt;br /&gt; 7.1 Core Audience&lt;br /&gt; 7.2 Commented or Shared My Posts&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 8.0 WATCHING&lt;br /&gt; 8.2 Pundits&lt;br /&gt; 8.3 Celebrities&lt;br /&gt; 8.4 Noisy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 9.0 ALL&lt;br /&gt; 9.1 Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy&lt;br /&gt; 9.2 Read Daily&lt;br /&gt; 9.3 Read Weekly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future blog post I’ll share my ongoing experience with using this approach to Circles, but this example shows how easy it is to separate and add Circles as your interests change and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;managingyourcircles&#34;&gt;Managing Your Circles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, enjoy social networks in large part because we get to interact with people. Managing your Circles is thus about more than just understanding your social graph. It also allows you to manage your time effectively when you read and share with other people on Google+. Here is my approach for how to manage the time you spend reading, sharing, and managing your social graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforreading&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Reading&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it useful to think about Circles that are explicitly for reading as different from Circles intended for sharing. I have a few of these read-only Circles. Thus, my “Pundits” Circle contains people that share a lot and for whom I don’t always want to read everything. My “Read Daily” Circle is conversely for people for whom I want to read everything they post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also found Circles helpful for close collaborators. It’s easy in Google+ to have a conversation with someone directly by simply typing their name as +&amp;lt;name&amp;gt; into the share field of posts. However, I find these direct posts get lost over time. To resolve this problem, create a Circle dedicated to just the two of you: a dyad. I have a number of people that I’m collaborating with closely and I use these small Circles to both keep track of our mutual posts and to see what they are thinking about at the moment. Examples of this kind of two-person Circle include my “Book Project” and “iPad Project”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofreadingcircles&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Reading Circles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day I look first at my “ALL KIN”, “ALL KITH” and and “ALL PEER” Circles to see what is going on with my support, sympathy and trust cliques. Then I’ll read my “Read Daily” Circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading these daily basics (which I try to keep to a limited number), I’ll typically pick an interest, a geography, or a group, depending on what I’m doing that day. (My personal time-management style is to only follow one interest per day, e.g. if I am working on my iPad app then I’m not reading Social Web posts.) If I’m preparing a blog post and want to see what my audience is thinking I might review “Core Audience”, or “FOLLOWS ME”. If I’m traveling I might read one of my non-local Circles such as “Seattle”. If I’m doing ‘weak-signal research’ I might start with “ALL INTERESTS”, but if I’m particularly tolerant of noise I might read “Familiar Strangers”, “FOLLOWS ME”, “Everyone but Pundits &amp;amp; Strangers”, “Pundits”, or even “ALL”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;postingtocircles&#34;&gt;Posting to Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the important reasons for creating Circles in the first place is so that you can share with groups of people. I’ve developed some strategies for this as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;circlesforposting:&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circles for Posting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it useful to create a Circle that only contains yourself. I have two of these — “Read Later”, and “Drafts”. If I’m reading and I see something interesting but don’t have time for it immediately, I’ll share it with my “Read Later” Circle so that I can quickly go back to it. Similarly, if I need to do some more research before writing and sharing, I’ll share my immediate thoughts in “Drafts”. As new features are added to Google+ these Circles will hopefully become obsolete, but they are useful for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofprivateposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Private Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sharing, you want to ask yourself if this is ‘private’ post, a ‘quasi-public’ post or a ‘public’ post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My private posts tend to go “KIN”, “KITH”, a dyad project, or one of the sub-Circles of PEER depending on their context. Some posts that are of only geographic interest (say a party, or local event) will be shared privately to the appropriate local Circle. If you are using my ledger system of using numbers in Circle names, these are the lower numbers—5.0 and below are Circles where I’m more sensitive about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once shared, these more personal posts will be labeled as “Limited” instead of using the “Public” label that allows anyone to see them. If a recipient tries to share a “Limited” post, a box will pop up reminding the person: “This post was originally shared with a limited audience – remember to be thoughtful about who you share it with”. Unlike Facebook or Twitter, one purpose of Circles on Google+ is to determine who gets what information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it may be easy to create Circles to segregate those with whom you wish to share private information, the recipients of your posts have no such limitations and could share outward beyond your intent (though they will be warned if they try to, as noted above). To enable further privacy you can disable resharing of these personal posts made to your Circles. To do so, share your post to a non-public Circle, then you select the arrow in the upper-right-hand corner where you can edit, delete or disable the post, and click on the final option, “Disable Reshare”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another privacy issue: by clicking the grey “Limited” label, a message’s recipient can see all others you shared the post with. This could potentially result in privacy problems, as the reader could discover who is in one of your Circles. There are ways of eliminating this by going into your Privacy account settings, which I will cover in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofquasi-publicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Quasi-Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call posts “quasi-public” when they’re of narrow interest to a specific group or a topic that isn’t really relevant to other members of my audience. I find these quasi-public posts happen the most for my more esoteric interests—for instance, when I’m sharing a complex iPhone development article that is really only interesting to a narrow group of my contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Google Reader, I typically wouldn’t share these articles at all because there were so many of my contacts that wouldn’t be interested in them and it would only be noise to them. Ditto with Twitter. I found that sometimes people would stop following me after a conference I attended because I posted regularly and the conference was not of interest to them. This could be quite frustrating at times. Though these posts were not private by any means, I only wanted to share them with a specific group, such as an iPhone group. Now with Circles, I can share this information easily with my “Apple &amp;amp; iOS” Circle. I find that this feature is what makes Google+’s Circles so potentially powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I might offer much of this more esoteric information as “quasi-public” posts to a specific group or interest, I’ll probably offer the best of them to the “Public”. Sometimes that is what it means to be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maven&#34;&gt;Maven&lt;/a&gt;—you share across social network boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;managingsharingprivacyofpublicposts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Sharing Privacy of Public Posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing a post to your “Your Circles” is effectively public, as is sharing to “Extended Circles”. Ask yourself if there is really some reason why you don’t want to make a post totally “Public” so that it is searchable by those who are not members of Google+. If there is some reason, consider sharing to your “ALL” Circle or some other more limited circle instead, as you’ll have more control and can turn off resharing or commenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;managingyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;Managing Your Social Graph&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining your Circles can take away from the time you can spend on reading and sharing. I’ve come up with the following strategy to limit the time I spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, I have some basic rules for which Circles to place people in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone is following me, I add them to “FOLLOWS ME” and an appropriate other Circle. If I vaguely recognize a follower’s name or face, I put them in “Familiar Strangers”. If I don’t recognize them at all but they look interesting, I add them to “Friendly Strangers”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m notified that someone has +1’ed, commented, or mentioned me in a post, I add them to “Core Audience” and the appropriate sub-Circle. I will also make sure that the other Circles they are in are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I discover while I’m reading that someone is too noisy for the Circle I selected, I’ll move them to a more appropriate Circle—or place them in the “Noisy” Circle or even block them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;timemanagementofyoursocialgraph&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Management of Your Social Graph&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition I review a few of my Circles every day. I do so by going to “Manage Circles”, then selecting “People in your Circles” and sorting by last name. I choose that letter of the alphabet that corresponds to the day of the month and hover my mouse over each name. (For example, I look at names starting with “L” on July 12th, as “L” is the 12th letter.) Google+ highlights the Circles that each person is in. If they’re in the wrong Circle, I move them. I might even click on some people and review their profile so that I can see who they are—or (if I already know them) see what they are up to lately, update my address book, and maybe send them a brief email. At the end of the month (on the 27th through the 31st) I review my overall Circles lists. This way, over the course of each month I briefly review my entire social network, without spending too much time on it. (I try to spend 10 minutes or so a day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Periodically (right now weekly, but hopefully eventually monthly) I do some larger scale management of my Circles. Learning how to do this the first time is a pain, but once you know how it only takes a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to “Manage Circles” and select “People Who Have Added You”. I sort that list by “Not Yet in Circles”, “Select All” and add the people revealed to “FOLLOWS ME”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then do the same with all of my Circles to update my “ALL” Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I copy my “ALL” circle to “Everyone But Pundits, Celebrities &amp;amp; Noisy” and remove any Pundits, Celebrities or Noisy people from that Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When managing your Circles, remember the motto “Perfection is the Enemy of the Good”. You are the only one that sees who is in which Circle, and you can place people in multiple Circles. So your Circles don’t have to be perfect, just good enough. If you share a lot of private posts, concentrate on making sure that those more personal Circles are more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these approaches, you should find Circle management quick, and you won’t get mired down in Circle management for hours at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish I had this organization when I started on Google+ two weeks ago. By using some of these techniques from the beginning I would have made my life a lot easier. Over the next month I now have to go back and re-organize people and re-Circle them. I hope sharing these tips will make your use of Google+ simpler from the start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I expect that Google will be adding new features to make Google+ easier. For instance I’m hoping for #hashtags (the ability to tag posts into topic categories), favorites (the ability to tag posts into a persistent archive, hopefully with an option tag), ordering Circles, concentric Circles, and better integration with Google Reader. (I share my favorite blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/reader/shared/ChristopherA&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt; at &amp;#0160;and my best of best articles and posts in &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ChristopherA/favorites&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Twitter Favorites&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;or &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/christophera&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Delicious&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any new online feature, people are finding out new things and coming up with new ideas every day. So what are &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; methods for organizing your Circles and social graph?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want to follow me on Google+, I’m at &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/about&#34;&gt;+Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#39;d like to comment using Google+, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113059510043663667610/posts/2eYjBB2CpNm&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;public comment thread&lt;/a&gt; about this post.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you would like to subscribe to my Google+ posts in Google Reader, use my &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;feed://plusfeed.appspot.com/113059510043663667610&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PlusFeed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts from my blog related to this post:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/intimacy_gradie.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Intimacy Gradient and Other Lessons from Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/08/progressive_tru.html&#34;&gt;2004-08: Progressive Trust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some recent high signal-to-noise blog posts on Google+ and/or managing your Circles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107631581023945167601/about&#34;&gt;+Matt Stratton&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mattstratton.com/tech-tips/how-i-set-up-my-circles-in-google-plus&#34;&gt;How I Set Up My Circles in Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/113551191017950459231/about&#34;&gt;+Anson Alex&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ansonalex.com/tutorials/managing-circles-in-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Guide to Working with Circles in Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/101746196094367799224/about&#34;&gt;+Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/?p=2616&#34;&gt;The promise of Google+ for organizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104681313125038107957/about&#34;&gt;+Sterling Ledet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.weteachthecoolstuff.com/2011/07/09/a-thought-on-circles-privacy-vs-relevance/&#34;&gt;A Thought on Google+ Circles – Privacy vs. Relevance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/118432652629200965858/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Dave Pollard&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtosavetheworld.ca/2011/07/11/google-plus-on-communities-circles-friendship-and-love/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Google+: On Communities, Circles, Friendship and Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethkanter.org/np-google/&#34;&gt;Are You Going To Adopt Google+ for Professional Learning/Networking? Why or Why Not?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/104181568670836761473/about&#34;&gt;+Damon Morda&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brandedclever.com/five-steps-to-configuring-privacy-on-google-plus/&#34;&gt;Five Steps to Configuring Privacy on Google Plus (+)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some quality recent public Google+ posts regarding Google+ or managing your Circles (be sure to look over the comments):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/about/&#34;&gt;+Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/posts/ghn6Bu6tsmM&#34;&gt;My tips for newer users of Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/1SdhSBqwAmA&#34;&gt;Where circles can go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/D9bRJCmjJRV&#34;&gt;Sharing Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/about/&#34;&gt;+Dave Gray&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/117373186752666867801/posts/XHvCRURHidx&#34;&gt;Is Google plus public or private?It’s neither, and both!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/about&#34;&gt;+Beth Kanter&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/107965826228461029730/posts/DV8QxNzTxaF&#34;&gt;Insightful Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/about&#34;&gt;+Craig Kanalley&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/103399926392582289066/posts/52dmpNDbWtp&#34;&gt;Tips &amp;amp; Thoughts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/about/&#34;&gt;+Paul Goode&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/105611903933875658496/posts/W9CaNrwku3x&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;Sketch on Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on related to this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;personal circles&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the of personal limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;familiar strangers&lt;/a&gt; - those people you recognize by face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustration by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;, Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/102320045646237908121/about&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34;&gt;+Elyn Andersson&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;and&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;for their assistance with this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I really like the idea of using circles for social time management. One big problem I have with networks is that I feel committed (obligated?) to a certain, indistinct, level of communication - particularly with those people that social media has now kept me in &#39;contact&#39; with, and whom in the old days I would have lost touch with. The end result is always a big time defecit and multiple layers of guilt. The idea of being able to apply some kind of equitable rationing/priority to circles may be a bit geeky... but it&#39;s preferable to non-specific angst  ;0)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/grimbold&#34;&gt;Grimbold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T02:40:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I like your ideas; I&#39;ve also been trying to play about with the circles &amp; work out something that works for me.
How, however, do you manage to add people to them, when you have quite so many (looking at the second list with the 1.3 etc) - I can only see 1.5 rows of circles! (OK, I know you can add someone by right clicking &amp; going for the add to circle, but that&#39;s fiddly if you&#39;re block adding them!)
I&#39;ve also got in the (equivalent of the) me circle my &#39;other&#39; G+ account, that I&#39;ve been using to see the effect of things like extended circles. Which I do find useful.
Would be nice, if, at some point, rather than having &#39;stream&#39; it was possible to see in a single stream all the updates from a set of circles, rather than 1 or all. (Unless that&#39;s something I&#39;ve yet to find!)
(That, and I want boolean logic for them, so I can have everyone who is in both a &amp; b, but not a or b!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://profile.typepad.com/emmadw&#34;&gt;Emmadw&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&#34;&gt;2011-07-15T05:21:40-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2011/07/managing-your-social-graph-with-google-plus.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community by the Numbers, Part III: Power Laws</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/03/power-laws.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 01:46:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2009/03/power-laws.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;my first article&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;in this series I talked about community numbers: how the sizes of groups ultimately affect their success (or failure). However what I discussed only offers up the most rudimentary explanation of the dynamics, and that is because typically not all of the members of a group are equally involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to better define &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; constitutes the tightly-knit &amp;quot;participant community&amp;quot; upon which the group thresholds act, we have to study power laws which let us measure the intensity of individuals&amp;#39; involvement in a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An Overview of Power Laws&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3366611997/&#34; title=&#34;Pareto Principle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pareto Principle&#34; height=&#34;179&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3616/3366611997_95f255e4a3_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The best-known power law is probably the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/a&gt;, which is otherwise known as the &amp;quot;80/20 law.&amp;quot; It&amp;#39;s been overused throughout the years; Pareto&amp;#39;s actual law only said that 80% of the wealth would be held by 20% of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it offers a fine example of how power laws work. They generally describe a discrepancy between intensity and population: inevitably, some people do a lot more of the work in any social situation. Other examples include &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipf%27s_law&#34;&gt;Zipf&amp;#39;s Law&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3367563212/&#34; title=&#34;Long Tail Curve by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img height=&#34;174&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3603/3367563212_8aa7a62c6f_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;which suggests that the frequency of a word&amp;#39;s usage is inversely proportionate to its ranking among words (making the second ranked word appear half as much, the third a quarter as much, etc), and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Long_Tail&#34;&gt;long tail&lt;/a&gt;, which talks about selling a very large number of items in a very small individual quantity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For online communities, which have been the focus of most of my studies on the topic of community sizes, I&amp;#39;ve found that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Participation_inequality&#34;&gt;participation inequality&lt;/a&gt; power rule is very apt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3366764093/&#34; title=&#34;Participation Inequality by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Participation Inequality&#34; height=&#34;192&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3613/3366764093_29495ce5b4_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This term comes from Will Hill of AT&amp;amp;T Laboratories, who said, &amp;quot;A major reason why user-contributed content rarely turns into a true community is that all aspects of Internet use are characterized by severe participation inequality.&amp;quot; It&amp;#39;s often equated with the 1% law, though I like to be more precise and say that 90% of an online community tends to be lurkers, 9% tends to be intermittent participants, and 1% tends to be active participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These values heavily influence online community sizes that are larger than the tightly-knit communities group thresholds that I previously discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Power Laws &amp;amp; Group Thresholds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I wrote about tightly-knit communities in my first article, I didn&amp;#39;t consider the degree of participation. That&amp;#39;s certainly an entirely valid model for some types of groups. Corporations, for example, ideally should be entirely filled with active participants, while Skotos&amp;#39; online game &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/marrach/&#34;&gt;Castle Marrach&lt;/a&gt; also fits into the category due to the implicit requirements it creates for participation. There are some challenges to grow this type of community, since you&amp;#39;re only searching for a specific type of high-energy participant — but they can be overcome if you offer sufficient incentive (such as a salary or a lot of internal feedback).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, most communities, and in particular, online communities, will not fall into this category, and thus when we&amp;#39;re looking at group thresholds, we have to measure them against the number of &lt;em&gt;active participants&lt;/em&gt;, not against the number of total members. Thus, for groups which allow for non-participation, we&amp;#39;ll often measure 10% (or maybe 1%) of the group size against the group thresholds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rpg.net&#34;&gt;RPGnet&lt;/a&gt;, one of the community sites that Skotos runs, offers a good example of this. We regularly see monthly uniques of approximately 200,000 users. However we probably have about 20,000 active registered users, confirming the lurker:participant ratio. When we recognize that only 2,000 of those are particularly active participants and that they&amp;#39;re divided upon 6 successful forums, we start to see how community numbers that actually match the group thresholds can gel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can reverse this approach and look at active participants first. During some recent consulting for a local non-profit organization with 60 active online members, I was able to infer that their broader community was around 6000, which turned out to fairly accurately predict the total number of people who came to their live events over the course of a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, this logic can be applied to a community of any size. You first measure whether it&amp;#39;s an all-participant community or one that matches an existing power law, and then you use the corrected community number to truly measure which of the group thresholds may apply to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Power Laws &amp;amp; Leaders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power laws can also help you to measure the number of leaders in a community. Inevitably all of your participants will become leaders of some sort, while your high-level participants will become the top-tier leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noted this in my first discussions of group threshold. In a group of 7 members, you can reasonably expect to have one higher level participant, and thus the one leader that we saw naturally appear. Similarly in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html#Judas_Number&#34;&gt;Judas group of 13&lt;/a&gt;, there&amp;#39;s the opportunity for more than one leader to appear, creating the possibility for the first hierarchical conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3367609602/&#34; title=&#34;Participation Inequality 90 9 1 by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Participation Inequality 90 9 1&#34; height=&#34;153&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3600/3367609602_4445e5cfb9_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Understanding your count of leaders can help you see how to grow groups. For example when I first created &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iphonewebdev.com&#34;&gt;iPhoneWebDev&lt;/a&gt; I had to do an immense amount of effort to grow the community. This is because with Participation Inequality I had to grow the group by 10 members before I got the least amount of help increasing the content of the group and I had to grow it by 100 members before I had someone who was doing as much work as I was to create content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 100 members, with my first active participant, we continued to grow, but we were both were working hard and felt rather lonely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3366786135/&#34; title=&#34;Participation Inequality 700 70 7 by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Participation Inequality 700 70 7&#34; height=&#34;196&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3564/3366786135_53f8ebcf47_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I finally saw the group stabilize, then take off on its own, when it hit 600-700 members, and that shows how beautifully the power logs work hand-in-hand with the group thresholds. With 700 members, I could reasonably expect there to be 7 leaders. In other words, I had a committee of leaders: the perfect size for a starting&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html#Working_Group&#34;&gt;working group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience with other online groups, if the iPhoneWebDev grows to over 10,000 members, I can expect that there will be some transition issues. As the core active community members exceed 100 people I will start having some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html#Non-Exclusive_Dunbar_Number&#34;&gt;Non-Exclusive Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; problems, typically social contract failures. These can be solved by either adding some hierarchy (appointing some people to be official &amp;quot;staff&amp;quot;), or by starting to break the group into sub-communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Varying the Power Laws&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my first article, I noted that it&amp;#39;s possible to expend additional energy to make tightly-knit groups able to function effectively at non-optimal sizes. It is similarly possible for the values of the participation inequality sized groups to change by expending more energy. Conversely, a drain on energy&amp;#0160;may decrease this ratio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3367609374/&#34; title=&#34;Participation Inequality - High Energy by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Participation Inequality - High Energy&#34; height=&#34;169&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3626/3367609374_3975fe9bf7_m.jpg&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For example when I used to run AOL forums I would frequently reward first-time participants with free time (at that time worth $5 an hour) if they asked good questions or offered valuable input. CompuServe similarly offered constructive feedback by telling users how many responses they&amp;#39;d received to a new comment when they logged back in, encouraging them to leave lurker status. More energy in the community — driven either by the moderators, good social software design, or by a greater commitment by its members — can allow you to increase the active participant percentage, maybe times 2, or even 4, but even with a lot of effort not by an order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a group grows in size, I believe the participation inequality worsens. A huge Yahoo! group with a million members might have moved from a 90/9/1 ratio to 95/4.5/.5. I suspect this is because the energy required to change the participation inequality numbers is so large as to not be economical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some interesting interrelations between the numbers of people at the various levels of participation. Though discovering 100 new members has a good chance of adding 10 new participants, 1 of whom is very active, my experience has been that things trickle-down in the other direction as well: that adding 1 new high-level participant can lead to the creation of 9 medium-level participants and 90 lurkers (though don&amp;#39;t let that suggest that all of your effort should be expended on the high-level participants only).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Looking at Participation Inequality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a close look at four online communities, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quantcast.com/&#34;&gt;quantcast.com&lt;/a&gt; metrics service, where you can see some participation inequality in action:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3367609306/&#34; title=&#34;Participation Inequality - quantcast.com by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Participation Inequality - quantcast.com&#34; height=&#34;235&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3472/3367609306_023c85652f_o.jpg&#34; width=&#34;961&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From this you can see a typical online community site shows the normal 90% 9% 1% participation inequality. RPGnet shows a slightly better then average participation inequality due to its longevity and the quality of the community. ObesityHealth shows evidence of a great community with its 4% active participants, probably because you have to be very committed if you are going to have bariatric surgery. Last, an example of relatively&amp;#0160;unhealthy&amp;#0160;community that is unable to sustain its active participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do have to be careful when analyzing quantcast numbers if you see active participants of greater then 6% — in almost all cases if you look deeper it is because there is some restriction that keeps people from lurking, either a fee or some other type of gateway, causing a distortion in the statistics.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple factors influence the success (or failure) or community. As we saw in my&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;first article&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;on community numbers, the first factor is the&amp;#0160;differing&amp;#0160;group thresholds of community sizes. In my&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;second article&lt;/a&gt;, I show that&amp;#0160;personal limits on the number of people you can have intimacy and trust with is an important factor. In this article I show that larger groups are subject to the power law of participation inequality, causing a small fraction of a community to be subject to group thresholds. In all three articles I show how expending energy can allow you to change the numbers, but with limits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope this discussion of community numbers will give you some tools to look at the communities you are in, or are trying to build, and to better understand how to make them more successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;2008-09: Community by the Numbers, Part One: Group Thresholds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2008-11: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/participation+inequality&#34;&gt;participation inequality&lt;/a&gt; - more specifics on participation inequality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/power+laws&#34;&gt;participation inequality&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the topic of power laws, including participation inequality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have any links on this topic that you would like to share with me, tag them &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/tag/for:ChristopherA&#34;&gt;for:ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;#39;ll take a look.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustrations by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;. Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://randy.thefarmers.org/&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt; for their assistance with this series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Having been the leader in several groups, I can truly relate to Participation Inequality.  Wow, it&#39;s tiring being the driving force behind a tremendous idea until it takes off.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.barbaraling.com&#34;&gt;Barbara Ling, Virtual Coach&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-03-20T02:34:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-03-20T02:34:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It has been interesting to be part of a local blogging community and how it actually somewhat detracted from my overall bigger online community I was a part of before.  I seemed to have kept only the most dedicated readers (1%) from just simply joining a local group.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.logtar.com&#34;&gt;logtar&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-05-18T11:49:00-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-05-18T11:49:00-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris - this was a really great series of 3 posts - it is outlined as well as anything I&#39;ve seen on the subject.
In the course of your experience have you seen much of a difference between the style of content produced in communities and how that impacts the power law?  A few years ago I started a project to create an open source methodology for information management http://www.openmethodology.org, which worked in concert with corporate solutions also built in a collaborative fashion.  At least in this case, we have found the power law threshold to be even higher when creating a more structured, method-based approach to collaboration.  We did feel there was a need to put some controls in place for an &#34;open method&#34; and have experimented with different ways to build a collaborative commmunity.  Some good progress has been made, but its been tough going!
We also applied this same approach to sustainability http://www.open-sustainability.org.  Once again, very hard work to build the community but some slow steps are being made.
Do you have any thoughts around more structured collaboration and how it can negatively impact community growth in readership and contributions?  Any recommendations on ways to improve it?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.openmethodology.org&#34;&gt;Sean McClowry&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-07-15T15:33:05-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-07-15T15:33:05-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2009/03/power-laws.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2008 12:44:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; post, I talked about the limits on sizes of tightly-knit communities. These group limits are closely related to a number of interesting personal limits, and are often confused with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the group limits, personal limits actually measure something different: the number of connections that an individual can hold. They&#39;re yet another thing that you must consider when thinking about communities of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal Limits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3054773873/&#34; title=&#34;Support Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3183/3054773873_07514d66dc_m.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; alt=&#34;Support Circle&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Support Circle:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the number of individuals that you seek advice, support, or help from in times of severe emotional or financial stress. In most societies, the average size of an individual&#39;s Support Circle is 3-5. The people are the core of your intimate social network and most typically are also kin. In sociology papers this is often called the &amp;quot;support clique&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563324/&#34; title=&#34;Sympathy Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3068/3055563324_f62dbcdc7d_m.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; alt=&#34;Sympathy Circle&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sympathy Circle&lt;/strong&gt;: This is larger then the Support Circle — it is the number of people that you go to for sympathy and also those people whose death would be devastating to you. The Sympathy Circle typically is in the range of 10-15 people, but can vary widely from as few as 7 to as many as 20. The Sympathy Circle often may be made up of kin, but usually includes some peers as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sociology papers the Sympathy Circle is also known as a &amp;quot;sympathy group&amp;quot;, but I wanted to avoid the term &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;, as it is implies that all the members of a Sympathy Circle are connected. Instead, members of your Sympathy Circle will have additional people in their own Sympathy Circles that are not part of your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting issue with the Sympathy Circle is that as a personal limit, 10-15 is a typical size. however, if you bring them all together in one place, they will likely become a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html#Judas_Number&#34;&gt;Judas-Number-sized group&lt;/a&gt;, with all of the problems associated with that size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3055563798/&#34; title=&#34;Trust Circle by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3230/3055563798_5355b9b99c_m.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; alt=&#34;Trust Circle&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Trust Circle&lt;/strong&gt;: These are the people that you have some type of intimate connection to. One study measured it as the people that you would send a family Christmas card to, while another simply tested emotional closeness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In pre-Friendster days the Trust Circle would be those people that you considered your &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot;, however today the meaning of that term has begun to change. In my own usage, your Trust Circle are people that you have strong ties to and that in some measure you can trust. I have also called the Trust Circle your personal &#34;intimate social network&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of different individuals&#39; Trust Circles can vary widely (40-200), but &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/christophera/trustcircle&#34;&gt;some studies&lt;/a&gt; show that the mean is on the low side of 150. This has led a number of researchers to compare this number with the Exclusive Dunbar Number of 150. However, I believe that this is a mistake; they are related, but in today&#39;s society members of your Trust Circle are rarely in the same mutual group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Emotional Circle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; I personally define your Emotional Circle as the total number of people that you can have some type of non-mutual emotional connection with, most likely spread across numerous groups of all sorts. You &amp;quot;like&amp;quot; them in some way, but do not necessarily have to have strong ties to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia this threshold is called &amp;quot;social channel capacity&amp;quot;. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/channel+capacity+christophermccarty&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; using two different methods to estimate, both suggest that it falls right around 290. However, I like to describe this number as &amp;quot;just short of 300.&amp;quot; As I wrote in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Triage&lt;/a&gt;, many people confuse this number with the Dunbar Number (and in fact I have in some of my older pieces). However, like the Trust Circle, it&#39;s a distinct entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotional Circle size can vary quite a bit from individual to individual. Some people might have half the average capacity, and others considerably more — which is much more variation than you see among the sizes of smaller personal thresholds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of those variations are individual, but some are societal. As I wrote in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;, I believe that our modern era of television causes us to create para-social relationships with imaginary characters who we nonetheless become emotionally involved with, and thus might reduce our social channel capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is our Emotional Circle smaller today because of TV or is it higher because online communities can help to remind us of our emotional connections to other people? That&#39;s a topic that probably deserves more study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting point to make is that the people who are in your Emotional Circle, but are not in your Trust Circle, are your &amp;quot;weak ties&amp;quot; in social network terms. What is important about weak ties is that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/225469&#34;&gt;studies show&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stanford.edu/dept/soc/people/mgranovetter/documents/granstrengthweakties.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;) that opportunities and knowledge flow to you much more through weak ties than through the more insular strong ties of your trust circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Familiar Stranger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://flickr.com/photos/dlytle/2215047019/&#34; title=&#34;Familar Strangers, from Blue Bottle Coffee Line by davitydave on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2125/2215047019_80e572fe0d_m.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; alt=&#34;Familiar Strangers&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Outside of our Emotional Circle is a larger, more tenuous circle: those people whose faces you recognize, but who you know nothing more about. These are your &amp;quot;Familiar Strangers&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/familiar+stranger&#34;&gt;Studies show&lt;/a&gt; that the percentage of familiar strangers in your vicinity has a real impact on your willingness to take risks. If you are in a new place with no one that you recognize, you&#39;ll avoid eye contact and will generally be unwilling to approach strangers. In a place where there are a lot of people that you&#39;ve seen before (say in your favorite cafe, at a conference, or in the lunchroom of a large company), you&#39;ll be much more willing to take risks, such as asking questions, or sitting down next to someone to eat lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#39;t been able to find any studies to show how many people that we can recognize, but for some people it is much larger than the number of people in your Emotional Circle, probably well over a thousand. However, there is also a lot more variance: some people are face-blind or near face-blind, and have a difficult time even recognizing friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There could also be some interesting research looking more closely at social network software. I find it fascinating that the professionally-oriented social network LinkedIn resisted supporting photos in profiles for so long yet ultimately failed, as well as how other social network software companies have attempted to require &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; photos of people rather then allowing &#34;fakesters&#34; or avatars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crossing the Circles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve used the term &amp;quot;circles&amp;quot; throughout this article because it&#39;s a great metaphor for these levels of personal involvement. They can literally be thought of as concentric circles of people getting further and further away from an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/christophera/3054729757/&#34; title=&#34;Personal Circles Landscape by ChristopherA, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3252/3054729757_4fa37f7a6e_m.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; alt=&#34;Personal Circles Landscape&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;However, if you want to consider them with an even more graphic bent, think of these circles as the ridge lines of a topographical map. An individual sits at the center, and around him lie many other people, fading slowly away as the distance increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winding through these topographical lines, like forests or rivers, are geographies of physical and emotional connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kin are one of the most interesting geographies, because they lie all across the map. There&#39;s a clump of them in the innermost circles, but there are also many who lie in the realm of Familiar Strangers, including those cousins and great-aunts who you only see at family gatherings, and whom you know nothing about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also forces being exerted upon the circles, acting like gravity to draw people together. They are the forces of trust, influence, and more. Their pulls are greatest toward the center, across your Circles of Support and Sympathy, but as people move farther away, these forces drop off quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;Thus, though I&#39;ve described them as circles, with strict boundaries, we should also see these personal connections as fluid entities, a regular ecosytem of personal community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas the group thresholds that I discussed in my last article define the limits placed on community group size, the personal limits described herein instead define the limits placed on how many people an individual can know with various degrees of intimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there are societies where these two things might be the same. A true survival community might contain everyone a person knows, and thus he could draw out all his personal circles across that community canvas. However, in our modern era they&#39;re much more likely to be distinct, with an individual interacting with the members of his circles of acquaintances through numerous different group communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this bifurcation of personal and group community limits, we have to briefly stop and ask a few questions. How do they relate? What can personal limits tell us about efficient community creation? Does founding a group upon a personal circle make its growth easier or harder? Conversely, what type of communities lead naturally to the creation of intimate circles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;Herein I&#39;ve simply outlined personal thresholds as a contrast to group thresholds. The exploration of how these limits interact is worthy of additional studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my next article &amp;quot;Community by the Numbers, Part III: Power Laws&amp;quot;, I will talk about how both group thresholds and personal thresholds have a role in larger, less tightly-knit groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34;&gt;2008-09: Community by the Numbers, Part One: Group Thresholds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;personal circles&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/personal+circles&#34;&gt;familiar strangers&lt;/a&gt; - those people you recognize by face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have any links on this topic that you would like to share with me, tag them &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/tag/for:ChristopherA&#34;&gt;for:ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; and I&#39;ll take a look.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illustrations by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancymargulies.com&#34;&gt;Nancy Margulies&lt;/a&gt;, photo by &lt;a href=&#34;http://flickr.com/photos/dlytle/&#34;&gt;davitydave&lt;/a&gt;. Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://randy.thefarmers.org/&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt; for their assistance with this series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I like &#39;circles&#39;; a very useful contrast to groups where the members are interconnected and know each other. I usually think of this as the difference between &#39;networks&#39; and &#39;communities&#39; on a larger scale. Looking forward to the next article about power laws across larger communities; in particular, I&#39;m curious what you think the Dunbar number and other descriptions about group interaction and stability have to say about the dynamics of large groups with a shared identity (like enthusiasts in a large online community or &#39;offline&#39; groups like labor unions, professional organizations or political parties).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://lithosphere.lithium.com/t5/Enterprise-on-the-Surface/bg-p/scott&#34;&gt;Scott Dodds&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-11-26T16:15:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-11-26T16:15:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I cannot agree more, actually I wrote a similar post weeks ago
Edward
Frontier Blog - No one ahead, no one behind
http://www.hwswworld.com/wp
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.hwswworld.com/wp&#34;&gt;frontierblog&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-02-17T22:53:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-02-17T22:53:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The Information and findings about familiar strangers really inspired me a lot. I have the same experiences and I totally accept this point of view about feeling unsecured about taking risk at place where you have no familiar strangers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.guitarhype.com/&#34;&gt;Candace Bogert&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-03-03T03:39:32-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-03-03T03:39:32-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I&#39;m just getting started reading your blog (first two articles of the By The Numbers series), and I&#39;m very interested.  A few random reactions so far:
- You speak of &#34;circles&#34;, but you diagram spirals.  Would it be useful to recognize the differences and similarities?
- In &#34;Bowling Alone&#34;, Robert Putnam speaks of two kinds of social capital: bonding (that holds groups together) and bridging (that relates a group to &#34;others&#34;).  Would this distinction be useful in your model(s)?
- I&#39;ve got a tentative start at a project intended to explore all aspects of communities, in particular the aspects that affect a community&#39;s health, resilience, and relationships to its environment (including other communities, of course).  See my URL from this comment.  I suspect I&#39;ll be referencing your work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://dwigki.wikispaces.com&#34;&gt;Dwig&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-04-06T20:49:10-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-04-06T20:49:10-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
The different kind of &#39;circles&#39; we have in the social networking are included in the reality friends we have now.The thing is, people don&#39;t really go out much now, but instead they are just trying to connect with these &#39;circles&#39; we have in order to communicate. Some are really risking to go out beyond circles to explore. And this what social networking can do. Thanks, great read!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;bebes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-04-22T22:26:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-04-22T22:26:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community by the Numbers, Part One: Group Thresholds</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2008 13:53:36 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/09/group-threshold.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/2008/09/22/circle_of_hands.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/22/circle_of_hands.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Circle of Hands&#34; alt=&#34;Circle of Hands&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
We often think of communities as organic creatures, which come into existence and grow on their own. However, the truth is they are fragile blossoms. Although many communities surely germinate and bloom on their own, purposefully creating communities can take a tremendous amount of hard work, and one factor their success ultimately depends upon is their &lt;em&gt;numbers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a community is too small you&#39;ll often have insufficient critical mass to sustain it. Conversely, if it&#39;s too large you can end up with a community that&#39;s too noisy, too cliquey, or otherwise problematic. These optimal and sub-optimal community sizes appear in strata, like discrete layers of rock. For a community to advance from one strata to the next often takes immense energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can analyze these community sizes in three ways. In this first article I&#39;m going to talk about numerical group thresholds that have been observed in various sizes of tightly-knit communities, while in its sequel I&#39;m going to talk about personal thresholds and how they relate to group thresholds. In my final post, I&#39;m going to consider how power laws and inequalities of participation further complicate these simple values in the creation of larger communities. Together these three articles constitute what I call &amp;quot;Community by the Numbers,&amp;quot; a theory of community size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I&#39;m going to point to some studies which support these numbers, in general my goal here isn&#39;t to try and prove this theory of community size numbers, but rather to lay the theory out completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tightly-Knit Group Thresholds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groups can clearly exist at any size, from a partnership of two, on upward. However what I&#39;m going to write about here are the threshold values: the ideal numbers where a community seems to function best, and the less than ideal numbers at which a community begins to grow unstable, remaining so until a new threshold number is reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m also specifically talking about groups that are both tightly-knit and participatory communities. Clearly Ford Motor Company, with 250,000 employees, doesn&#39;t match any of these group thresholds. But any self-contained community within Ford probably will (and in fact, it will probably be either a &amp;quot;Working Group&amp;quot; or a &amp;quot;Non-Exclusive Dunbar Group&amp;quot;, both terms I&#39;ll explain below). Similarly, a non-corporate community that doesn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; everyone to participate won&#39;t work quite the same as a community that does require participation from each member (though that&#39;s again the topic of the third article in this series).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.singers.com/jazz/group7.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;132&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/22/group7.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Group7&#34; alt=&#34;Group 7&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;7, &amp;quot;The Working Group&amp;quot;.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;Working_Group&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This community size probably runs from about 4-9 members, but 7 is a pretty good average, and one that shows up in &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/workinggroup&#34;&gt;multiple studies&lt;/a&gt;. This number may well relate to the general &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rule_of_seven&#34;&gt;rule of seven&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.musanim.com/miller1956/&#34;&gt;original paper&lt;/a&gt;), which suggests that 7 is a number that the brain can easily and intuitively comprehend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has become increasingly clear that a tightly-knit group of 7 is the first group size which is truly an optimal community size. Groups below this size can function effectively, but risk not having
enough manpower to deliver a result that everyone is happy with, or having insufficient viewpoints to avoid group think. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven is not only an optimal size for a wide variety of corporate and government committees, it is also a healthy size for a small business and even a good size for a party of close friends. More importantly, 7 is a very comfortable group size as it &amp;quot;feels&amp;quot; relatively natural. At this size members find it easy to get to know the other members of the group, and they&#39;re able to function well together in a very intuitive and organic fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/2008/09/22/squadfireteam.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=560,height=403,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;143&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Squad and Fire Team&#34; title=&#34;Squad and Fire Team&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/22/squadfireteam.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
An interesting example of this group size is the modern infantry
&amp;quot;squad&amp;quot;, which consists of two fire teams of 4 people, and a squad
leader, for a total of 9 people. Each fire team is is large enough to
function on its own, but together the group of 9 can still have effective
small group dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is typically at this size that the first signs of leadership in a group informally emerge, but the leadership usually isn&#39;t overbearing at this level, nor does there tend to be any rebellion against it — perhaps because the group may be too small to elicit multiple leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Last_Supper_(Leonardo)&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;109&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/22/lastsupper.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Last Supper&#34; alt=&#34;Last Supper&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;Judas_Number&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
13—&amp;quot;The Judas Number&amp;quot;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; A group size of 13 doesn&#39;t represent a threshold ideal value, but rather a threshold nadir. It is one of the points where groups can change behavior and risk becoming dysfunctional. There&#39;s one of these nadirs beyond every group threshold, where the previously harmonious group dynamics become more difficult. I&#39;ve chosen to highlight this specific number because it&#39;s a point that small communities often hit, particularly as entrepreneurial organizations try to grow above their startup beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I should note that 13 isn&#39;t a precise number, but rather one offered because it&#39;s in the right range and because it&#39;s poetically easy to remember. The exact number occurs somewhere between 9 and 25, but I suspect it is worst in the range of 12-15.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a group of this community size no one ever feels like they get a fair share of time. Studies show that at this size participants underestimate the amount of time they contributed to the conversation, and thus will come out feeling like they were unfairly ignored despite having a fair share of the conversation. Groups of this size risk people being lumped into categories and ceasing to be trusted as individuals. In addition, problems start with the development of &amp;quot;too many chiefs,&amp;quot; yet there is not enough enough variety of non-chiefs for them to direct. Furthermore, multiple leaders may struggle for hierarchical status, increasing the conflict in an already troublesome group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your community is unfortunately stuck at this nadir, one of two things usually occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most commonly, the group shrinks. This could be because participants unhappy with the group dynamics abandon it; or it could occur in a more organized way with the unwieldy large group breaking into two or more smaller groups. For example, a terrible group of 13 could become two more functional groups of 6 and 7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, more energy could be expended. This could be in the form of more formal organization, rewards for participation, or more time to be casual and socialize in order to shake off the tensions of this size group. Though these efforts don&#39;t usually change the size of the group, they can improve its dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy could also be spent to help push the group up to the next threshold. Though this could occur naturally — for example if the group focuses on a topic of particular interest that causes new people to continually be added. In addition, in order to grow a group to a new threshold it often requires the efforts of more than one leader to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A group size of 13 isn&#39;t necessarily bad, just more difficult. Anthropological studies show that primitive hunting tribes often temporarily broke into &amp;quot;bands&amp;quot; of this size — my presumption is that the value of having that many people hunting together outweighed the social costs of the group. It is interesting that most juries are made up of groups this size. I believe that the social dynamics of this size of group with all new members creates some tension among the jurors, which may serve justice to make sure that all sides are considered by the jury without falling into groupthink. However, from my experience, the interpersonal conflict in a jury can also slow down the deliberation process and cause much frustration among the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/2008/09/23/nonexclusivenetworks.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/23/nonexclusivenetworks.png&#34; title=&#34;Non-Exclusive Networks&#34; alt=&#34;Non Exclusive Networks&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
50—&amp;quot;The Non-Exclusive Dunbar Number&amp;quot;.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a name=&#34;Non-Exclusive_Dunbar_Number&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;More properly this group size falls in the range of 25-75 participants, but it seems to feel the most natural in the range of 50-60. Studies of the sizes guilds in online games &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;support&lt;/a&gt; this hypothesis. For instance, based on graphs of the guild sizes in Ultima Online, groups have a median of 61 members. Similar numbers hold true in studies of a more recent game, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call this value the &amp;quot;Non-Exclusive Dunbar Number&amp;quot; because it matches the lower end of a threshold that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Robin Dunbar&lt;/a&gt; set for group sizes. However, at this size it applies to mostly non-exclusive groupings, which includes the above mentioned online guilds, many employee communities, and the majority of social gatherings that manage to rise above the size of a Working Group. Groups of this size &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be serious or take up a lot of time, but in general they are not exclusive — they don&#39;t tend to be the only group that individual participants are involved in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;90—&amp;quot;The Dunbar Valley&amp;quot;.&lt;/strong&gt; As Non-Exclusive Dunbar Number communities grow, they reach a point where increased time obligations and the noise of socialization required to keep the group cohesive requires a much more serious commitment from the participants. Like the Judas Number, the Dunbar Valley is a threshold nadir where more energy is required to keep a tightly-knit community together;&amp;nbsp; either the community agrees to a higher level of commitment and grows to the next level, or the community splits apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve found this to be true when growing a small business — where it is too small for any middle-management, but the sub-groups are too large for one person to manage effectively. I&#39;ve also seen this with more ephemeral groups, such as when a small conference that worked well at 60 participants tries to grow and finds at at 100 participants they can&#39;t sustain a high enough intimacy level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=400,height=290,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/2008/09/22/legion_2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;145&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/22/legion_2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Roman Legion&#34; alt=&#34;Roman Legion&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Another illustration of the Dunbar Valley is the history of the ancient Roman &amp;quot;century&amp;quot;, a grouping that was originally 100 soldiers. However, as the years went by, centuries tended to decrease in numbers to only include 70 or 80 soldiers. This might well be due to Non-Exclusive Dunbar constraints: even in a very devoted group of military men, there was still the need for relationships with other century groups, with support staff, and with camp followers, ultimately lowering the attention that could be spent on the century itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;150—&amp;quot;The Exclusive Dunbar Number&amp;quot;.&lt;/strong&gt; Robin Dunbar got much of the discussion of group thresholds started with his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isrl.uiuc.edu/~amag/langev/paper/dunbar93coevolutionOf.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;quot;Co-Evolution Of Neocortex Size, Group Size And Language In Humans.&amp;quot; However, as I&#39;ve written &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;, and as I&#39;ve described in this article, Dunbar&#39;s group threshold of 150 applies more to groups that are highly incentivized and relatively exclusive and whose goal is survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar makes this obvious by the statement that such a grouping &amp;quot;would require as much as 42% of the total time budget to be devoted to social grooming.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The result of the grooming requirement is that communities bounded by the Exclusive Dunbar Number are relatively few. You will find hunter/gatherer and other subsistence societies where this is a natural tribe size. You&#39;ll also find these groups sizes in &lt;a href=&#34;http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2004/03/what_is_the_opt.html&#34;&gt;terrorist and mafia&lt;/a&gt; organizations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=430,height=279,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/2008/09/22/sopranos_dinner.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;129&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/2008/09/22/sopranos_dinner.jpg&#34; title=&#34;The Sopranos at Dinner&#34; alt=&#34;The Sopranos at Dinner&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Clearly, as we step up toward higher group thresholds, more and more
time is required to simply keep the group going. You see this in
depictions of mafia life — in the TV series &lt;em&gt;The Sopranos&lt;/em&gt; a lot of time
is spent dining, hanging out, and drinking together. That is part of that 42% social
grooming time required for that intense of a survival group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible for a large company to force groups up to this size by expending lots of energy (which is to say money) to keep it healthy. Apple did this during the invention of the Macintosh, the first OS X operating system, and the iPhone, but the intensity required of such large teams is not sustainable for long periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without that extra energy, few modern tightly-knit communities can reach this threshold, or else can&#39;t hold it for very long. Instead they fracture into groups of individual interest (even if they continue to &amp;quot;meet&amp;quot; in the same real-world or online forum), which are more than more likely to be bounded by the Non-Exclusive Dunbar number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the difficulty in even arriving at the Exclusive Dunbar number, it may well be the highest limit of all for a tightly-knit community. Beyond this limit, communities are less cohesive, less trusted, and less participatory (and the topic of my third article in this series.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many different ways to measure groups, and one is by counting its members. As I&#39;ve discussed here, the number of members can have a huge impact on whether the communities are successful or not. Thus, as community organizers, social software engineers, game designers, or as sociologists interested in community dynamics, we must ultimately consider group thresholds and group nadirs; to understand how to create cohesive communities, rather than groups that fly apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;next article&lt;/a&gt; I&#39;m going to talk about thresholds that are personal, rather then group-oriented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2008/11/personal-circle.html&#34;&gt;2008-11: Community by the Numbers, Part II: Personal Circles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My bookmarks to various papers and websites on this topic are available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA&#34;&gt;delicious.com/ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; under some of the following tags:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/group+threshold&#34;&gt;group threshold&lt;/a&gt; - everything I have on the topic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/workinggroup&#34;&gt;workinggroup&lt;/a&gt; - on small groups such as committees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/ChristopherA/dunbar+number&#34;&gt;dunbar number&lt;/a&gt; - on larger groups such as tribes
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have any links on this topic that you would like to share with me, tag them &lt;a href=&#34;http://delicious.com/tag/for:ChristopherA&#34;&gt;for:ChristopherA&lt;/a&gt; and I&#39;ll take a look.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/about/staff/shannon_appelcline.php&#34;&gt;Shannon Appecline&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://randy.thefarmers.org/&#34;&gt;F. Randall Farmer&lt;/a&gt; for their assistance with this series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This view of group size dynamics has a lot of potential implications for all kinds of things including management science and more specifically/interesting to me startup dynamics. Namely, you&#39;re proposing an outline that can be mapped to company size and funding levels, amounts of management required/deployable etc. Have you thought of making a stronger connection in this area?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://michaeledwards.com/&#34;&gt;Mike Edwards&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-09-30T20:09:05-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-09-30T20:09:05-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hey Christopher,
Have you thought about turning this into a general outline for managing startup growth, funding levels, and exit scenarios?
--Mike
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://michaeledwards.com&#34;&gt;Michael Edwards&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-10-02T21:15:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-10-02T21:15:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Reading :
&#34;These optimal and sub-optimal community sizes appear in strata, like discrete layers of rock. For a community to advance from one strata to the next often takes immense energy.&#34;
Reminds me of Quantum states of Electrons spinning around the nucleus. So, maybe different quantic numbers of persons generate different energy levels, apt for different services?
Also as an analogy, if I recall well, when coming from an external path to an internal one allows the matter to shed light. So, maybe as we internalize we allow light to reach outward?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Louis-Martin Michaud&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2010-07-30T08:05:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2010-07-30T08:05:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2008/09/group-threshold.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Number Presentation at MeshForum 2006</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2006 11:52:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/davegray/147934089/&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/christopher_allen_sketch_at_meshforum_20.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Sketch by Dave Gray&#34; alt=&#34;Sketch by Dave Gray&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Last May I did an abbreviated version of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; talk at MeshForum 2006. A MP3 podcast of that talk is now available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itconversations.com/shows/detail1072.html&#34;&gt;IT Conversations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itconversations.com/shows/detail1072.html&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt; or can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itconversations.com/audio/download/itconversations-1072.mp3&#34;&gt;downloaded here (10mb)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;d like to follow along, here is a pdf copy of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.lifewithalacrity.com/christophera/MeshForum_2006_Dunbar_Number.pdf&#34;&gt;presentation sides (10mb)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biggest addition to what I&#39;ve written about before is some discussion about different kinds of social software and what what size groups they seem to be appropriate for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2006/08/dunbar_number_p.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Number &amp; Group Cohesion</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2005 16:16:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is some more excellent research this week by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nickyee.com/&#34;&gt;Nick Yee&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.parc.com/nicolas&#34;&gt;Nicolas Ducheneaut&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.parc.com/playon/&#34;&gt;PlayOn&lt;/a&gt; blog. Again, their research provides good insight into social group dynamics as they appear in online games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I last mentioned their research on guild sizes in my blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt; where I compare the distribution of guild sizes in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uo.com/&#34;&gt;Ultima Online&lt;/a&gt; vs PlayOn&amp;#39;s results from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofwarcraft.com/&#34;&gt;World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;. However, both distribution tables suffer from a variety of biases due to the nature of the different game designs, many of which are discussed in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html#comments&#34;&gt;commments in the post&lt;/a&gt;. For instance both guild graphs include &amp;quot;alts&amp;quot;, which are alternative characters of individual players. Thus one player might be represented multiple times in a guild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nic &amp;amp; Nick&amp;#39;s more recent research, they are looking deeper and are &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/mapping_social.html&#34;&gt;mapping social networks&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;&lt;em&gt;(now 404, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20090425222428/http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/mapping_social.html&#34;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; on World of Warcraft. Using tools available to them, over the course of the month of August they looked at 241,378 characters and 5569 guilds. From that data they were able to able to discover how often guild members were co-present (online at the same time) or co-located (online and in the same zone in the game)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c611970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;G-3&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c611970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c611970c-500wi&#34; title=&#34;G-3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in this map you can see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;...we have a guild where we see more distinct cliques. There&amp;#39;s a somewhat hard-core 4 character cluster on the left- hand side, a mid-level triad on the bottom left, a mid 20&amp;#39;s clique that&amp;#39;s held together by the druid in the middle, and finally a more casual low-level clique on the top right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this same data, they then looked at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/guilds_max_subg.html&#34;&gt;max subgraph size of guilds&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;&lt;em&gt;(now 404, use&amp;#0160;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/guilds_max_subg.html&#34;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;. A &amp;quot;subgraph&amp;quot; in a social network can be thought of as a &amp;quot;clique&amp;quot; of people that interact with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c82940ec970b-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image005&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c82940ec970b img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b7c82940ec970b-500wi&#34; title=&#34;Image005&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in the social network of this guild there are 5 subgraphs, 4 of which are just 2 people and 1 subgraph that is of 6. The 4 subgraphs that are only of 2 people are members of the guild who did not participate much in the guild. But the number of people in the subgraph of 6 is much more interesting, as it shows that these members are &amp;quot;cohesive&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the max subgraph size of a guild is plotted against the guild size, you get some interesting results -- the maximum guild cohesiveness occurs around the guild size of 50. Larger then that, guilds have a much more difficult time remaining cohesive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c66b970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image011&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c66b970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c66b970c-500wi&#34; title=&#34;Image011&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These results strong support my hypothesis in my original &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; post, where I...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;hypothesize that the optimal size for active group members for creative and technical groups -- as opposed to exclusively survival-oriented groups, such as villages -- hovers somewhere between 25-80, but is best around 45-50. Anything more than this and the group has to spend too much time &amp;quot;grooming&amp;quot; to keep group cohesion, rather then focusing on why the people want to spend the effort on that group in the first place -- say to deliver a software product, learn a technology, promote a meme, or have fun playing a game. Anything less than this and you risk losing critical mass because you don&amp;#39;t have requisite variety.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some possible other support for this hypothesis comes from another post by Nic &amp;amp; Nick where they analyze the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/guild_members_t.html&#34;&gt;time guilds spend together&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;(now 404, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20081119142033/http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/guild_members_t.html&#34;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c680970c-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image004&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c680970c img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01b8d1b3c680970c-500wi&#34; title=&#34;Image004&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the mean amount of time that guilds spend together in the band 31 - 60 is only 95 minutes and that the standard deviation is the lowest, as compared to groups that are larger then 120 where the mean time is 141 minutes at the standard deviation is higher. This says to me that keeping a large group cohesive requires significantly more time in social &amp;quot;grooming&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my original &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; post I had a secondary hypothesis where I talk about peak in satisfaction in smaller groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In my opinion it is at 5 that the feeling of &amp;quot;team&amp;quot; really starts. At 5 to 8 people, you can have a meeting where everyone can speak out about what the entire group is doing, and everyone feels highly empowered. However, at 9 to 12 people this begins to break down -- not enough &amp;quot;attention&amp;quot; is given to everyone and meetings risk becoming either too noisy, too boring, too long, or some combination thereof.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is strong support for this in another plot found in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/guilds_max_subg.html&#34;&gt;max subgraph size of guilds&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#0160;&lt;em&gt;(now 404, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20081231143011/http://blogs.parc.com/playon/archives/2005/10/guilds_max_subg.html&#34;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; post where they compare the subgraph ration to guild sizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;asset-img-link&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb08cde1c9970d-pi&#34; style=&#34;display: inline;&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image013&#34; class=&#34;asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb08cde1c9970d img-responsive&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/.a/6a00d8341d8bc053ef01bb08cde1c9970d-500wi&#34; title=&#34;Image013&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you can see a strong peak at 10 people, that rapidly falls with guild size. This shows that guild cohesion is relatively easy to maintain up to size 10, but becomes much more difficult to maintain as guilds grow larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been saying for some time that studying online games is a valuable place to understanding social software. I&amp;#39;m quite pleased that this research is proving this to be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;12
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ross.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Ross Mayfield&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-10-29T00:08:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-10-29T00:08:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris, intersting data.
I am not sure that with standard deviations so high on the &#34;Time spent together by guild size&#34; that you can draw super strong conclusions about differences been group cohesiveness by group.  One or two extra-connected group is going to throw off your numbers quite a bit.  If you have the data and can scatterplot them instead of showing averages I suspect you&#39;ll be able to make a case more clear.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://vielmetti.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Edward Vielmetti&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-02T21:18:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-02T21:18:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I would also like to see a scatterplot.  It would really help to make time spent together by guilds alot more clearer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;York Ash&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-05T21:12:01-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-05T21:12:01-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The military, and educational institutions, have discovered similar thresholds for collectivities. I think the number of friends any of us can sustain, in any manner (on, offline) is around 200. And that&#39;s pushing it. Magic numbers in small business are 12 and approx 30-35, I believe. Intersting that it might hold for online as well as offline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.gravity7.com/blog/media/&#34;&gt;adrian Chan&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-17T13:42:52-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-17T13:42:52-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Great series on Dunbar limit. One minor nitpick - I think your first PlayOn image link might be wrong. I thing the text you&#39;ve quoted refers to their bottom-left image which is g-3 rather than g-4 (the 4-character cluster is *really* obvious in g-3).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.itee.uq.edu.au/~ianm&#34;&gt;Ian MacColl&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-04-14T05:15:04-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-04-14T05:15:04-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks, the image is corrected to be g-3.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.LifeWithAlacrity.com&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-04-14T05:23:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-04-14T05:23:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2005 16:35:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In yesterday&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/templates/rundowns/rundown.php?prgId=2&#34;&gt;All Things Considered&lt;/a&gt;, NPR commentator &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakehalpern.com/news.html&#34;&gt;Jake Halpern&lt;/a&gt; questions why you feel like you have a relationship with the characters in your favorite TV shows. His answer: &amp;quot;That&#39;s because you do.&amp;quot; This idea is interesting not just to help us understand how we relate to imaginary characters, but also to correlate with our own understanding of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; relationship limits and how they might relate to this concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4772145&#34;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt;, Bostonian Jake Halpern considers two academic ideas, &amp;quot;belongingness theory&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;para-social relationships&amp;quot;, and how they affect the relationships we develop with television characters. He puts it all in the context of the 1990s TV show &lt;em&gt;Cheers&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/cheers.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Cheers&#34; alt=&#34;Cheers&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&amp;quot;My preoccupation with &lt;/em&gt;Cheers the Bar&lt;em&gt; puzzled me until I stumbled upon a rather obscure but quite fascinating academic notion called &lt;/em&gt;belongingness theory&lt;em&gt;.The argument goes something like this: in ancient times humans who stuck together increased the chances that they would survive and reproduce. So, when it came time to, say, hunt a large animal, or defend the cave against marauders, groups fared better then the guy on his own. In addition, adults in the group would have been more likely to find mates, reproduce, and raise their children. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The likely result of all this evolutionary selection is the creation of an internal mechanism that makes human beings crave social acceptance. The way I figured it, my irrational fondness for &lt;/em&gt;Cheers the Bar&lt;em&gt; was just my belongingness mechanism kicking. I just wanted to be part of the gang.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belongingness theory seems to have a good scientific basis. In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy.fsu.edu/faculty/baumeist.dp.html&#34;&gt;Baumeister&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Leary&#39;s 1995 paper on Belongingness Theory, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;amp;db=PubMed&amp;amp;a mp;list_uids=7777651&amp;amp;dopt=Abstract&#34;&gt;The Need to Belong&lt;/a&gt;, they stated that in order for belongingness to be considered a fundamental human motivation (as opposed to a want), it would have to be universal, affect a broad range of behaviors, lead to ill effects when thwarted, and elicit goal-oriented behavior designed to satisfy it. They found evidence for all of these. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&#39;m quite comfortable with the idea that evolution has encouraged us to have a number of &amp;quot;social emotions&amp;quot;, and that these may include a strong desire to belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halpern continues in his commentary with a discussion of &lt;em&gt;para-social relationships&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;And this brings to yet another academic theory, that of &lt;/em&gt;para-social relationships&lt;em&gt;. According to academics Horton and Wohl, who originated this concept, television gives viewers the &amp;quot;illusion of a face-to-face relationship with the performer&amp;quot;. Gradually over the course of many episodes, viewers come to feel that they &#39;&lt;/em&gt;know&lt;em&gt;&#39; a persona.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I totally buy it. After watching dozens of Cheers episodes, I felt as if I knew the personas in the show intimately. In fact there were times when I had seen more of the characters on Cheers then I seen of the people in my own family. So, yeah, I definitely had some para-social relationships going on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The truth is, we all yearn for companionship. The only problem is, that for many of us, myself included, the notion of a well-functioning family and a welcoming group of friends and co-workers, is occasionally more easily found on television or in the movies, than in life itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After all, in order to maintain &lt;/em&gt;&#39;real&#39;&lt;em&gt; relationships, you have to put in a tremendous amount of effort: making phone calls; returning emails; planning weekends together; etc. To maintain para-social relationships, however, all you have to do is flick on the TV.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I&#39;m being honest with myself, I have to admit that at times, Norm, Cliff, Carla, and Sam have formed, well, a kind of para-family to which I yearn to belong. I suppose that hideously hackneyed as it sounds, it&#39;s just like the show&#39;s theme song goes: &lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;Sometimes you want to go where everybody knows your name, and they&#39;re always glad you came.&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt; Only, they &lt;strong&gt;don&#39;t&lt;/strong&gt; know your name, and they really don&#39;t know you came.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jake&#39;s description of Horton &amp;amp; Wohl&#39;s theory on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aber.ac.uk/media/Modules/TF33120/horton_and_wohl_1956.html&#34;&gt;para-social relationships&lt;/a&gt; definitely parallels my thoughts in a previous post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt; where I ask &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; As Jake said, it&#39;s difficult because you have to make the effort: the phone calls, the emails, meeting in person, and all the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the concept of having real relationships with television characters might give us enlightenment into some other relationship issues. I personally find it difficult to reconcile the mismatch between my number of connections and my own limits due to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;; intuitively I feel that limiting my television watching can help. This is because these TV relationships are what I call &amp;quot;junk relationships&amp;quot;. Sometimes when I talk about the concept of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;, I said that we may have difficulty even reaching the Dunbar limit of 150 people because of the &amp;quot;junk relationships&amp;quot; we maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does every ongoing para-social relationship with an ongoing series character, such as Cliff on Cheers or Kate on Lost, lower the number of relationships we can have with real people? I believe that this may be so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, if so, the answer to maintaining more connections with real people may be simply to turn off the television and tune in the real world instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some related posts about group behavior:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;That does not bode well for those of us with &#34;relationships&#34; to multiple blogs we read regularly.....
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.BenYehudaPress.com&#34;&gt;Reb Yudel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-08-04T19:23:31-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-08-04T19:23:31-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;How did the link to this blog get into the blog on server side browser. That blog does not even allow comments so that one can ask questions like that. That blog has given links to some 100 blogs that have nothing to do with server side browsing.
I hope I&#39;d be in order if I enter a link to one such blog below.
http://www.newerawisp.blogspot.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/users/fakir005/335.html&#34;&gt;Satish Bhardwaj&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-09-15T13:05:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-09-15T13:05:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;What about characters in books?  Should I stop reading the Diskworld series?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blog.lib.umn.edu/denis036/thisweekinevolution/&#34;&gt;Ford&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-02-01T10:20:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-02-01T10:20:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:38:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my post about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt; I offered some evidence on the levels of satisfaction of various group sizes based on some empirical data from online games. There I was able to show that even though the Dunbar Number might predict a mean group size of 150 for humans, that in fact for non-survival oriented groups the mean was significantly less, probably between 60 to 90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/groupsatisfaction.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=436,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;272&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Groupsatisfaction&#34; title=&#34;Groupsatisfaction&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/groupsatisfaction.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I also offered a second hypothesis, that there is a dip in satisfaction level of groups at around the size of 15. Unfortunately, I could only offer anecdotal evidence that this threshold existed. My personal belief was that this dip was caused by not enough &amp;quot;attention&amp;quot; being given to everyone and that group gatherings of this size risk becoming too noisy, too boring, too long, or some combination thereof. Yet groups of this size are not large enough to allow for different perspectives (i.e. insufficient &lt;a href=&#34;http://pespmc1.vub.ac.be/REQVAR.html&#34;&gt;requisite variety&lt;/a&gt;) or for other group processes to come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading through the current (12 March) issue of &lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt;, and found an interesting table in the article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=mg18524901.600&#34;&gt;Charity Begins at Homo Sapiens&lt;/a&gt;. It stood out to me as it showed a dip approaching zero average cooperation for group sizes of 16 -- almost precisely same place that my hypothesis predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging further, I found the original source for this table was published in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; back in October 2003, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/papers/NatureOfHumanAltruism.pdf&#34;&gt;The Nature of Human Altruism&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/&#34;&gt;Ernst Fehr&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fischbacher/&#34;&gt;Urs Fischbacher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=495,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34; href=&#34;http://lifewithalacrity.blogs.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;309&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1.gif&#34; title=&#34;Nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1&#34; alt=&#34;Nature_of_human_altruism_fig_4_1&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: left;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What the chart shows is actually not empirical data from human experiments, but instead data from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_theory&#34;&gt;game theory&lt;/a&gt; simulation of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&#34;&gt;prisoner&#39;s dilemma&lt;/a&gt;. This is the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-sum&#34;&gt;zero-sum game&lt;/a&gt; where if you cooperate, the joint payoff of the players is higher. However, in zero-sum games there is also incentive for the players to cheat by defecting and thus taking less risk. Robert Axelrod showed in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0465021212/102-0974708-1794504&#34;&gt;The Evolution of Cooperation&lt;/a&gt; back in 1985 that in spite of the statistical best individual strategy being that of defection, cooperation inevitably evolves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fehr and Fischbacher, in their &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; article, took this idea a bit further by creating 100 independent simulations with group sizes ranging from 2 to 512, and then executing each simulation 1,000 to 2,000 times. Each generation of the &amp;quot;players&amp;quot; was allowed to evolve different strategies of cooperation vs defection, the classic successful strategy being &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tit_for_tat&#34;&gt;Tit for Tat&lt;/a&gt;. They would then evaluate the percentage of players who had cooperative strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If punishment of defections was ruled out, they discovered that over the 1,000+ generations of the simulation that the rate of cooperation quickly crashes, such that at the group size of 8 a little over 50% cooperation evolved, and for groups that are larger than 16 none cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next they added to the simulation &amp;quot;&lt;a name=&#34;altruistic_punishment&#34;&gt;Altruistic Punishment&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. This is the ability for players to punish those who did not cooperate -- however, such punishment is at some cost to the punisher. Earlier game theory &lt;a href=&#34;http://ideas.repec.org/cgi-bin/get_doc.pl?urn=RePEc:wpa:wuwpmi:0305006&amp;amp;url=http://econwpa.wustl.edu:8089/eps/mic/papers/0305/0305006.pdf&#34;&gt;research on altruistic punishment&lt;/a&gt; has shown that cooperation flourishes if there is some price for punishing defectors -- if you allow punishment at no cost then cheating strategies emerge. This earlier research determined that allowing individuals to punish at some cost that yields them no material gain will paradoxically result in an average gain for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding altruistic punishment to the simulation increased the amount of cooperation that evolved, such that groups with the size of 32 would have 50% cooperation. But even this had limits; at the group size of 128 no cooperation would evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if they added to the simulation the ability to punish those who did not participate in punishing (i.e. didn&#39;t pay the cost to punish defectors), then the percentage of cooperation that evolved was never less then 60%, and in fact got better as groups got larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very interesting result. To explain it in different terms, if you have a system that depends on sharing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons&#34;&gt;commons&lt;/a&gt; and there are no process or trust metrics, a group as small as 16 may find themselves not cooperating very effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of commons can be as simple as how much speaking time participants in a meeting share. The time that each participant uses during the meeting can be considered the shared &amp;quot;commons&amp;quot;. If there are no enforced rules, with a group size of 16 there will inevitably be someone who will abuse the time and speak more than their share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some simple rules (some type of process to partition time more fairly), or through some trust metrics (punish those who abuse the commons), larger groups can gain value from cooperating, but even these groups have limits. As long as there is some effort required to punish those who abuse the process, eventually the price for that effort becomes too high, and no one is willing to punish any longer. You see this in moderated discussion groups, where the guardians of the common good have to spend too much time moderating, given the number of people that wish to participate. Moderated newsgroups and early versions of SlashDot moderation had this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting observation from this simulation is that for larger groups, you needed to have a system to punish those who did not participate in punishing -- or to put it another way, get everyone involved with the process, not just a few. I think that this explains something that I&#39;ve always wondered about SlashDot&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usemod.com/cgi-bin/mb.pl?MetaModeration&#34;&gt;meta-moderation&lt;/a&gt; system -- with this feature you grade those who have moderated, and if someone abuses it they will no longer be able to moderate. What I suspect, given these results, is that if you don&#39;t participate in the meta-moderation system, you have less a chance of being able to moderate; thus SlashDot has a system that punishes those who are not involved in participating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have some questions based on this simulation -- I would like to see results with more granularity then powers of 2. I&#39;d also like to know the percentage of players participating in punishment -- I suspect that you&#39;ll find a very small number of &amp;quot;moderators&amp;quot; are required in the middle graph, even when cooperation evolves successfully. I&#39;m curious as to how many moderators are required to participate in punishing the non-punishers for cooperation to evolve in the third scenario. Also, in meta-moderation this simulation emphasizes punishing the non-punishers -- is that as successful as rewarding the punishers? I&#39;m also interested in investigating some of the further works where Fehr and Fischbacher are among the co-authors, such as this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iew.unizh.ch/home/fehr/science/Altruistic_Punishment.pdf&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; using MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging) that shows that our brain&#39;s pleasure systems are activated when we altruistically punish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure that the findings of this simulation are not the only reason why there might be a dip in group satisfaction at group sizes around 15, such as I observed. However, it does offer some interesting insights into group size thresholds, both for the threshold at 15 and for threshold of non-survival groups which I&#39;ve identified as being significantly less then the Dunbar mean of 150. It also shows that for large groups we need to offer not only moderation, but meta-moderation capabilities that involve all the participants in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary this research offers me another widget for my social software toolbox: in any group process look for the commons, allow participants to participate in identifing defectors; determine what the costs are for such identification (which may be as simple as requiring some attention or charging for such punishment); and encourage participation in the common good by punishing those who do not participate in seeking out defectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
For role based community blogging, check out http://go.webassistant.com/wa
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Garsett Larosse&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-22T21:09:33-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-22T21:09:33-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You may be onto something. The Dunbar number was referred to in the Tipping Point and in some places plays a role in tribal-forming. But for smaller activities the number 15 seems ideal, eg, for a classroom or workshop. If there&#39;s under 10 or 12, regardless of the room size people want to bail out because there doesn&#39;t seem to be &#34;enough&#34; people. Much over 15 and the group dynamic must change to lecture style as if there were 50 or 100 people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.pagehalffull.com/humanyms/&#34;&gt;Pearl&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-23T12:16:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-23T12:16:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Association Football (&#34;soccer&#34;) and cricket teams are 11 strong and are organised by a single player, the captain.  Rugby Union sides are 15 strong, and the organising job is split: the forwards are led by a &#34;pack leader&#34; who is subject to the team captain.  Any significance?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;dearieme&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-30T03:16:15-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-30T03:16:15-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
A superb blog Chris, but just a few errata on the post.
First the simulation in Fehr,et al is a multi-person prisoner&#39;s dilemma--a public goods game--which is identical to the game in the &#34;research on altruistic punishment&#34; link which I think is a great introduction to the literature.
Second, the prisoner&#39;s dilemma is not a zero-sum game although often times mis-attributed as such. In zero-sum games, the total payoff in each possible outcome must be the same; thus, your gain must be my loss. The tragedy of the prisoner&#39;s dilemma is simply that cooperate is not a good strategy for either player.
Third, I think the sentence with the &#34;research on altruistic punishment&#34; link should be &#34;... cooperation flourishes EVEN if there is a cost to punishing defectors.&#34; The later part of the sentence is incorrect. However, the result is still paradoxical as under the notion of rationality one would not expect anyone to incur the cost of punishing another without any personal profit.
Finally, although this research seems to be one capable of addressing organizational size, it is actually quite incapable of that feat. The number 16 on the graph is really a coincidence of circumstances see the graph in http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/anthro/faculty/boyd/SecondOrderFreeRidePublished.pdf for the impact of parameter values on the model. Actually, coincidence is not quite correct; it was a deliberate selection by the researchers. This literature is designed to unshackle economics from the rational agent paradigm not to address optimal organizational size.
I will try to see if there are more pertinent experimental research addressing the Dunbar number question and post them, but I&#39;m somewhat doubtful as the experimental design is still too limited to study such a complex phenomenon. I had thought to try to run such an experiment myself a year ago, but abandoned the idea. I think an econometric analysis of the online games data is probably the most promising course.
--an apologetic economist
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;chinteliu&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-11-07T03:45:56-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-11-07T03:45:56-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;is the supposed cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable social relationships: the kind of relationships that go with knowing who each person is and how each person relates socially to every other person. Proponents assert that group sizes larger than this generally require more restricted rules, laws, and enforced policies and regulations to maintain a stable cohesion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.edivergent.com&#34;&gt;Busby seo challenge&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-07-26T23:03:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-07-26T23:03:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2005 15:05:50 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/ryzeblogtribefriends.gif&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(this.href, &#39;_blank&#39;, &#39;width=640,height=579,scrollbars=no,resizable=no,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0&#39;); return false&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;181&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;Ryzeblogtribefriends&#34; title=&#34;Ryzeblogtribefriends&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/images/ryzeblogtribefriends.gif&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who now has over 171 professional &amp;quot;connections&amp;quot; in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/profile?viewProfile=&amp;amp;key=62844&#34;&gt;LinkedIn Profile&lt;/a&gt;, 198 &amp;quot;friends&amp;quot; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orkut.com/Profile.aspx?uid=2789681602836776519&#34;&gt;Orkut&lt;/a&gt;, many more non-intersecting friends and acquaintances on&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cluster.tribe.net/tribe/servlet/template/pub,pcard,PeopleCard.vm?personid=ce34093a-3c72-4954-b52f-3d6bc51884af&#34;&gt;Tribe.Net&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livejournal.com/users/christophera_/&#34;&gt;LiveJournal&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://socialsoftware.weblogsinc.com/sns-meta-list/&#34;&gt;other social networking services&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a plethora of correspondents that I only interact with via email, I am trying reconcile a mismatch between my connections and my own &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;Dunbar Number&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I maintain meaningful relationships with over 300 people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venture Capitalist &lt;a href=&#34;http://sapventures.typepad.com/main/2004/02/quality_or_quan.html&#34;&gt;Jeff Nolan&lt;/a&gt; relates similar concerns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;
&amp;quot;It strikes me that the social networking theory holds that the more volume you have, the bigger your network will become by introducing degrees of separation roughly along the lines of Metcalfe&#39;s Law. I disagree, human networks do not grow in value by multiplying, but rather by reduction. For me, it&#39;s the quality of relationships that enhances my professional and personal life, not the sheer numbers.&amp;quot;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately social networking services -- be it LinkedIn, Tribe.Net, Orkut, or LiveJournal -- are making the problem worse, not solving it. Any engineer or information theorist can tell you that a system that only has amplifiers will be out of balance, and that you need attenuators in the system as well. Our current breed of social networking services have focused on amplifying our contacts not only because it serves us, but because it serves them. The more contacts that you make, the more people they potentially have in their service. However, in the long run this is unsustainable -- a social networking service also has to be useful -- merely amplifying your contacts isn&#39;t enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the problem becomes not just one unique to me, where my friends network is overextended, but rather one that&#39;s endemic to the current generation of social networking services. In order to solve it we need to look at the traditional cultural answers to the problem, compare them to technical solutions, both current and to-be-invented, and then see how a new generation of social networking services can be designed that molds the two ideas together into a more cohesive whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offer here the beginning of that discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Cultural Strategies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of overextended social networks are not new with the Internet generation. Many professions require maintaining a large base of relationships and have done so for hundreds of years, among them: politicians, salespeople, public company CEOs, and even professions that you might not think of requiring these skills such as family doctors. The Dunbar Number of 150 may be a kind of species-wide average limit, it is not an individual limit -- thus my guess is that people with an innate talent for maintaining more relationships are attracted to these professions. But even with innate talent those who follow these professions can be overwhelmed, and each have found different cultural strategies for managing larger numbers of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Spending More Time:&lt;/strong&gt; Some people just spend a lot more time keeping up with their connections. Politicians and salespeople are classic examples of professions that require significant schmoozing time in order to keep trusted connections together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does someone like a member of the US House of Representatives manage their relationships? In no way can they even come close to having a relationship with all the 645,952 people they represent. They would, however, at least have to keep up at some level with the other 435 House members, their own staff, key members of the staff of other House members, as well as key politicians and contacts back home. From what I&#39;ve read, successful politicians spend most of their days just meeting with people, and have staff dedicated to &amp;quot;tickling&amp;quot; -- keeping track of constituents, schedules, issues, etc. and reminding the politician before each meeting of the essentials they need to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of this strategy is twofold -- the time spent managing relationships can&#39;t be spent elsewhere, and the quantity of relationships lowers the quality of those relationships. For instance, my experience with most politicians and many salesperson is that I will be forgotten as soon as I leave the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Changing the Standard:&lt;/strong&gt; There are different cultural standards in each profession as to what is an acceptable relationship. Thus some people chooose a profession that manages relationships in different ways. Doctors are a good example of socializers who fit into this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your family doctor has a similar problem to that of politicians -- too many people to keep track of. Yet a good family practitioner can see you and look beyond just today&#39;s symptoms. Thus because of an ongoing relationship with you he can be a better doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way the doctor does this is through cultural and professional limits. Because of the authority, status and title granted to doctors, patients tend to defer to them. There is not an expectation that the relationship is equal. This allows the doctor to have a &#39;shallower&#39; relationship with the patient that is still acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, even this level of serial, shallow socialization can be excessive for many people. A Radiologist acquaintance of mine told me the reason why she ended up in her specialty was that she just couldn&#39;t handle the ongoing patient relationships required by other specialities -- instead, she now looks at one set of images at a time, performs a diagnosis, and doesn&#39;t have to retain any relationship to move on to the next patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also problems with changing your socialization standards. Unless it is culturally understood, or your standard is reciprocated by others, it can make you appear shallow and not trustworthy. I&#39;ve seen this when someone moves from one profession to another, say a salesperson to a manager -- styles of relationships that were acceptable among salesperson and between salespeople and customers are not quite as acceptable as those between managers and their staff. Another example is when someone moves from the East Coast to the West Coast, where the usefulness of casual alumni connections is significantly less valued, but those casual connections are unable to understand the change in standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Strategy - Prioritization:&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps a more common cultural strategy for managing excessive relationships is prioritization. I could prioritize my relationships and focus only on the 100+ or so that might be the most useful to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two problems with prioritizing. First, analyses of social networks show that it is often the weak and most unrelated links that can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/context/1333462/0&#34;&gt;the most important&lt;/a&gt;. Thus any attempt to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triage&#34;&gt;triage&lt;/a&gt; may cut off some of these weak ties because I thought that the links might not be &amp;quot;useful&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, how do you tell someone &amp;quot;I&#39;m sorry, but I&#39;m overly Dunbarred, so I have removed you from my list.&amp;quot; Rejection is painful (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csudh.edu/dearhabermas/mripain01.htm&#34;&gt;MRI brain studies&lt;/a&gt; have actually shown), so I risk offending people forever by excluding them today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Technological Solutions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great hopes of social networking services is to improve the ways that we interact with other people, particularly those that we know at a distance -- the &amp;quot;weak links&amp;quot;. Right now, these services are part of the problem because they offer out-of-balance social systems. However, they can also be part of the solution; science-fiction writers and social software designers alike are starting to look at these issues and offer new solutions that would not have been possible before the advent of widespread software communication systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technological Solution - Augmentation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/geodesica.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Geodesica&#34; alt=&#34;Geodesica&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;I recently read in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0441012698/qid=1107286515/sr=8-1/ref=skotos_20/102-0974708-1794504?v=glance&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;n=507846&#34;&gt;Geodesica: Ascent&lt;/a&gt;, a new science fiction novel by Sean Williams and Shane Dix, a futurist example of augmentation as a method of maintaining extended social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0441012698/qid=1107286515/sr=8-1/ref=skotos_20/102-0974708-1794504?v=glance&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;n=507846&#34;&gt;Geodesica: Ascent&lt;/a&gt; the protagonist, &amp;quot;Melilah&amp;quot; is a politician in the distant future. She has her own problems with the Dunbar Number, and solves it with her own personalized social networking service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two things she had learned from her political career were that society depended on interpersonal relationship networks, and that everything could turn on a simple misidentification. In her fifties she had set about ensuring that her memory remained in good working order in order to avoid the latter. Anthropologists had known since the twentieth century that people were born with a ceiling on their social groups. Once Melilah exceeded the Dunbar and Hill number of 150, and rapidly acquiring still more associates, it became progressively harder to keep track of everyone she had to know. As she passed her hundredth birthday, it became only worse. Some of her contemporaries option for cortical grafts and other memory prosthetics. She, motivated by a gut-level -- some would say irrational -- desire to keep her body as free of technology as possible, opted for other means.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She had found that using a name once every two months was enough to keep her memory fresh. Any longer than that between reminders, and the associations faded, rendering recall unreliable. So she programmed a complete list of her occasional acquaintances and enemies into a database and programmed it to cycle through them ever sixty days, shuffling the order each time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A hundred years on, she was still in the habit of skimming fifty or so names a day, just to keep on the ball. By flicking through the images, voice files, place names, and more obtuse clues, she felt confident of recognizing any of the several thousand people more or less likely to interact with her at any point in the near future. The list had grown and shrunk down over the years, and many people had dropped off it entirely because of death or distance. Sometimes she added names to the list only to be surprised that they had been on it once before, decades ago, and she had forgotten them completely. That only reinforced the need for the list and the effort to keep it fresh in her mind.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure that the Dunbar Number problem is solely one of &amp;quot;recognition&amp;quot;, as illustrated by Williams and Dix. However, I think this is a great example of seeing how a traditional cultural solution to network overextension (namely, &amp;quot;Spending More Time&amp;quot;) can be better applied by Social Software. In this example Melilah&#39;s software automates the &amp;quot;ticklers&amp;quot; that politicians use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/photos/uncategorized/spokekeepintouchsettings.gif&#34; title=&#34;Spokekeepintouchsettings&#34; alt=&#34;Spokekeepintouchsettings&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; float: right;&#34; /&gt;Already at least one social networking service has adopted a somewhat similar idea.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://center.spoke.com/person/personalProfileTab.spoke?id=[serverID=center,ID=4877427]&#34;&gt;Spoke&lt;/a&gt; has a &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; setting. The Spoke client software will watch your Outlook mailbox and addressbook to see how often you contact various people, and if you don&#39;t email them or modify your address book entry for them periodically, will remind you that you should contact them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve never used Spoke&#39;s &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; feature -- largely for privacy reasons (I was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/04/annoyed_by_zero.html&#34;&gt;stung by a Zero Degrees&lt;/a&gt; Outlook extension), but also because Spoke seemed to be oriented toward salespeople and thus emphasized growing the network. My problem is not growing my network, but managing the network I already have more effectively. But I may have to take another look at Spoke. So, it doesn&#39;t quite offer the same solution that Melilah used in the far-future, but it&#39;s still a start upon that path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusions and Questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not certain that Spoke&#39;s &amp;quot;Keep In Touch&amp;quot; feature, or Melilah&#39;s social recognition reminder service are the full solution to the &amp;quot;Dunbar Triage&amp;quot; problem. However, they do at least offer a few examples of people looking at the problems, and how social software can help solve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;ve outlined here there are at least three traditional methods&amp;nbsp; that we&#39;ve used to manage Dunbar Triage prior to advent of social networking services: spending more time, changing standards, and prioritization. The technological solutions that I&#39;ve offered up as an example concentrates upon the first of those cultural solutions, but it is by no means a conclusive statement on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could next-generation social networking services improve upon the ideas of changing standards or prioritization? Could simple categorization help improve expectations for attention levels that various associates receive from you? Are there ways that social networking services, acting as an intermediary, could better manage disappointment-inducing events, such as a decision to spend less attention on an associate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More so, could social software offer solutions that aren&#39;t even being considered right now? For example, many Cyberpunk novels have suggested the ideas of avatars that can collect information for you on the &#39;net while your attention is elsewhere. Could these avatars likewise maintain more distant social networks for you, without your full attention? Would that function even be desirable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some solutions are not technological -- what new skills and changes to practices, etiquette and ethics are required for our ever expanding network of relationships? Or as &lt;a href=&#34;http://alevin.com/weblog/&#34;&gt;Adina&lt;/a&gt; asks: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Who will offer us a 21st century, internet-augmented take on Dale Carnegie and Emily Post?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any problem in the developing technical world, the first step is to define the problem and to consider possible solutions. Here&#39;s the start: social networks can become too large, and many social networking services are causing the problem rather than solving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s your solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000219.html&#34; alt=&#34;gapingvoid blog, by hugh&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/zzzmkghilkj38.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Too Many Friends, by hugh, from gapingvoid blog&#34; alt=&#34;Too Many Friends, by hugh, from gapingvoid blog&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;(comic illustration from the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000219.html&#34;&gt;gapingvoid&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gapingvoid.com/Moveable_Type/archives/000823.html&#34;&gt;hugh&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34;&gt;2004-03: The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes&lt;/a&gt; (also some really good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html#comments&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-10: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think the politicians and sales people use another strategy - they pretend that they keep up with the connections, but in fact they don&#39;t.
That&#39;s why they have the people to keep them informed about people they are going to meet. They don&#39;t remember the people but they use techniques to impress them that they do. And that is why we don&#39;t like them.
YASNS let us all switch into the politician networking mode.
For some time I have beed thinking that Huminity which bases the networking on IM buddy lists is a step in the direction of making SNS more balanced, since it bases the networking on the most scarce Internet resource - user attention.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://zby.aster.net.pl&#34;&gt;Zbigniew Lukasiak&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T03:21:13-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T03:21:13-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Nice post. A few random thoughts:
This seems analogous to what happens when people move from rural communities with relatively sparse social options to the city.
Another prioritization scheme is to emphasize face to face relationships, or to distinguish between real-time and non-realtime relationships. These are not always appropriate filters, but because getting f2f or talking realtime requires a special effort, I&#39;ve found these approaches can help me gauge whether a relationship is maintainable.
The older system of etiquette, which separated personal from professional relationships, is another approach, though when I hear the words &#34;I don&#39;t do business with friends,&#34; it means someone neither a friend nor a business associate.
Perhaps there are some other frames for looking at this, e.g. time management or attention management, or as another instance of the Tyranny of Choice.  Approaching the problem as one of more choice in who we pick to be our friends and associates, or as one of more demand on us from others also colors our choice of solutions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.archival.tv&#34;&gt;Jeff Ubois&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T12:03:24-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T12:03:24-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;One way of putting the brakes on endlessly expanding contact lists is to have the SNS site charge per contact. If you really need more than 100 contacts then you&#39;d pay for them, but if not then when you&#39;ve got another 1 person you want to add to your list you&#39;d consider dropping one off your current list. It might work better with per-contact charges, so you&#39;re not forced into making a decision when you hit the package borders (101, 201, etc)
Not only does it counter the pack-rat mentality, but it also provides a business model.
Another idea I had was if the SNS would provide me with a continuous feed of updates and changes in the profiles of my contacts - I occasionally notice that some contact of mine has changed jobs, but more likely I wouldn&#39;t notice. The list of contacts just sit there, passive. This feedback would provide two forces: (1) the memory refreshing effect, and (2) the opportunity to drop those contacts that are moving into areas I don&#39;t care for.
A third idea: I&#39;d like it if the SNS I use (LinkedIn) allowed me to attach some notes or tags to each contact in my list ... I have a few there where I have to think really hard just how I happen to know them. Right now it seems that every SNS I look at lets me make connections, but every connection is bland and generic. The system is relying on me remembering why I know that person, when instead it could remember it for me.
When it comes time to triage, I&#39;d really like it if the SNS would provide a simple network map for me. Show me my immediate contacts, any connections they have amongst themselves, and my second circle contacts (anonymised if necessary). This way at least I can see that Person X is a gatekeeper to a whole different community from all my other contacts, and so should reconsider dropping them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://IAwiki.net/&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-04T18:44:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-04T18:44:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid has the right idea... but his number of 100 is still too high.
His last paragraph is golden.  When I first joined RYZE  in 2002 [ no longer an active member] I mapped out my 1 and 2 step network there.  In the diagram linked below I am the green node, my immediate neighbors are in blue and my two step contacts are in grey.
The network map reveals why Eric&#39;s 100 number is too high...
http://www.orgnet.com/RYZE2a.gif
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orgnet.com&#34;&gt;Valdis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T10:02:26-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T10:02:26-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;This, and the earlier article on Dunbar numbers are interesting reading.  I&#39;m not sure whether the Dunbar number applies in all cases.
In some discussion on SNs recently, I theorised that if we analysed Social Networks that there would be people who maintained relationships in Groups, i.e meshes where everyone knows everyone.  Bridging between groups occurs because of multiple membership, i.e. person X knows all the parents in their kids soccer club, AND all the people at the office.  Dunbars number, and the theories around it, seem to apply here, i.e. to the social-grooming required in GROUPS.
There would also be people who maintain relationships, between a lot of people who mostly do NOT know each other. We used to call these people Networkers, and typically they are the people you call when you want to know who to talk to about some topic where you have no personal connections.  I&#39;m not sure whether the Dunbar number applies to those people&#39;s connections, probably the power-law applies better, i.e. they can maintain progressively more distant connections with progressively more people.
Anecdotal, if you randomly pick people in for example Orkut then you&#39;ll see the same names turn up as intermediates in many cases. This is not necessarily because those people have large numbers of Orkut friends, but because their Orkut friends are dispersed over a range of sub-groups.
I don&#39;t think that any of the SN tools do a good job of managing these kinds of relationships yet, in particular the lack of interworking between them causes problems as different Groups tend to belong to different SN systems, so the bridges are often not evident. Also the relative strength of a connection doesn&#39;t seem to drive the ranking of possible connections, i.e. I&#39;m just as likely to be presented with a potential introduction through a person with a weak connection to the target, than through someone with a strong connection.
- Mitra
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.mitra.biz/blog&#34;&gt;Mitra&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-05T15:40:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-05T15:40:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;On tactic that comes to mind is the automated equivalent of an 18th/19th century butler, who mediated social interaction at a time when the intrusive, in-person visit was one of only two ways to make social contact.
The butler has broad and nuanced knowledged of the circumstances in which the Lady is to be acknowledged to be IN.
Today&#39;s online presence indicators are flat; they tell everyone the same message; that one is working, or eating ice cream in front of the television.
A butler would understand whether one is working or not, and would put through different connections at different hours.
A butler would understand the understand the nuances of one&#39;s social circle, and admit some people automatically, allowing others to wait, and requiring still others to leave a message.
We also need the 18th/19th century interface to the Butler, the calling card, which conveys by its printed message and accompanying whether the caller is a longlost relative whom the butler may not remember; a recommendation from a reputable source; a specific message about the urgency of the visit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/weblog&#34;&gt;Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-06T08:42:20-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-06T08:42:20-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I think that the key to defeating the Dunbar number is to a) establish a real relationship to begin with and b) massage that relationship at least once per year.
I find that if I&#39;ve built a meaningful relationship with someone, based on some shared experiences, simply getting in touch with someone once a year on their birthday is enough to keep the relationship alive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://chrisyeh.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Chris Yeh&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T06:25:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T06:25:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You&#39;ve got to distinguish between &#34;friends&#34; and everything else - the relationships that range across acquaintance, association, colleague and just plain &#34;potentially useful.&#34; Why treat them all with the same UI? Why not invite your true friends to share a more intimate online relationship and keep the rest in the &#34;relationship parking lot&#34; of an Orkut? Yeah, I know that friends are often useful, too, but they deserve better than to share the same utilitarian role as that guy you met at SXSW last year.
I&#39;ll invite my real friends into my Grouper hangout, but I&#39;m not a Congressional Rep, so I don&#39;t need to be responsible to hundreds of familiar names. I&#39;ve got plenty of other things to do with my time, which I believe is the case with most of us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.socialchemy.com&#34;&gt;Cliff Figallo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T15:53:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T15:53:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi, Crhis. Three years&#39; ago Adrian Scott asked this question too, and it led to his founding Ryze...
from: http://www.edge.org/q2002/q_scott.html
Edge.org&#39;s Question Page of 2002 - by Adrian Scott.
******
&#34;How do we scale up the number of quality human relationships one person can sustain by many orders of magnitude? In an increasingly connected world, how does one person interact with a hundred thousand, a million or even a billion people?&#34;
Our one fixed resource is time — human attention. As we become increasingly networked in the technological sense, we also become more networked in the social sense.
As our social networks scale up, we move more and more of our interactions to the technological sphere. We can have many more telephone interactions than we can have hand-written letter interactions. When we move from telephone to e mail, the number of interactions between people goes up even more dramatically.
Then we pair our e-mail interactions with a personal Web site, and we start moving our personalities into the technology net, as a way of automating and scaling up the number of relationships even further.
We end up with personal CRM systems to handle our increased interaction load, and then add interfaces from our technology net to our human forms. These interfaces will develop from current-day Palm Pilots and Blackberry&#39;s to heads-up display style interfaces in glasses and eventually retinal and neuronal interfaces.
&#34;Hi Jerry, Ahh.., we met back in 1989, May 14th at 7pm, and since then we&#39;ve exchanged 187 e-mails and 39 phone calls. I hope your cousin&#39;s daughter Gina had a wonderful graduation yesterday.&#34;
The whole range of interactions becomes organized. Introductions from one person to another, and rating systems become automated.
Currently many people run into barriers as their personal networks approach the range of thousands of people. Soon they will move to the tens of thousands, to the millions and beyond.
With these trends, the friction costs of personal introductions go down, and consequently the value of quality measurement and gatekeeping go up dramatically. As the depth of knowledge in a relationship increases, the threshold point at which you &#39;really know someone&#39; increases also. It&#39;s an arms race of intimacy.
Adrian Scott is founder of Ryze, a business networking community. He is a founding investor in Napster, got his Ph.D. in nonlinear optimization at age 20, and has sung with Placido Domingo and performed with the NYC Ballet.
*****
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://dijest.com/dontblog/&#34;&gt;Phil Wolff&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T20:12:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T20:12:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
An Avatar? Maybe that&#39;s what I&#39;m doing. I look at life as a whole. Coincidences (for lack of a non-cliched word) are road signs helping us determine a direction of movement (not necessarily in the physical realm).
I&#39;m working on a software module which links coincidental interaction within Nature and published human consciousness. Currently I&#39;m modeling Climate Change.
For my software to ultimately work within a social network, a persons daily life of data would be connected via an identifier - and freely available. Too, an aspect of human momentum would need to change dramatically - we would trust that life is a whole and not something to be mastered, assimilated, conquered. We would need to move to a much less mechanical decentralized world. And our user base would need to be decreased.
Which coincidentally, Climate Change is forcing upon us. And it&#39;s ramping up.
Google, with all the tools I need (email, blog, webpages, and soon a social network site) seemed like a potential opportunity. They never responded to my email :)
My profile is lost within LinkedIn...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;michael white&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-20T10:05:53-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-20T10:05:53-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Learning by Subtraction
The human brain has on half the number of synapses at age six as it had at age two. It learns by subtraction. So do computer based neural nets.
This principle could well be applied to organizations to increase the size of the Dunbar number that could work effectively without drowning in bureaucracy.
Consider three ways to bring order in a human organization. The chain of command, community spirit and marketplace choice.
The chain of command tends to keep demanding ever more connections. You must get permission from all these people before taking action. The free intraprise systems we set up (See The Intelligent Organization by Gifford &amp; Elizabeth Pinchot and link at the end of this post) allow people to connect and disconnect at the end of each contract at will. Teams contract with line officers and each other to get the work done, much like a virtual organization except that key competencies and trade secrets remain in the organization.
Relationships that create value are maintained; those that consume value are terminated by either party. This provides a powerful advantage over the innane connections that are often maintained in highly time consuming ways in a bureaucracy.
The force of community also has a self-organizing quality that allows people to volunteer for what has juice and walk away from relationships that consume purpose and meaning. Community is a necessary balance to free enterprise or free intraprise. Both should be used in place of the chain of command in many of the situations where the chain of command is used today.
http://www.pinchot.com/MainPages/BooksArticles/InnovationIntraprenuring/FreeIntraprise.html
http://www.pinchot.com/MainPages/BooksArticles/OtherArticles/GiftEconomy.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.bgiedu.org&#34;&gt;Gifford Pinchot&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-23T22:43:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-23T22:43:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Adina: Getting in touch once a year may keep a relationship alive, but only just. This begs the question, what do you want from your relationships? What do you value them for? What is the point in keeping a relationship on drip-feed attention when putting so little in precludes the possibility of growth, of enrichment, of greater intimacy, of learning something, of sharing the experience of life in some way.
Perhaps what we&#39;ll see, with or without the help of clever internet applications, is a polarisation: a small circle of close friends, a very wide circle of friendly acquaintances (whether social, professional, shared interest, discussion group, blog reader, etc, by origin), and an almost infinite range of potential one-off contacts. Along the lines Chris Reh is suggesting, I think.
I&#39;m not sure I need to know which of my friendly acquaintances are in touch with one another. Better just to get on and live, and concentrate on putting something into those relationships, the better to get something out of them.
Or have I missed the point?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://thiswayplease.com/extra.html&#34;&gt;Fred&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-30T21:48:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-30T21:48:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Fred, is there someone in your household who sends birthday cards and holiday cards? These are traditional tools for staying minimally in touch. They don&#39;t maintain intimacy, but they do keep an open door, so that it&#39;s easier to keep the benefits of weak ties, and regain contact when the time is right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.alevin.com/weblog&#34;&gt;Adina Levin&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-09T13:26:17-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-09T13:26:17-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I just had a minor realization: when we speak of &#34;dropping&#34; someone from our personal network, are we really doing that? The fact is, they are very probably connected to other people we do know, and so what we are really doing is *delegating* the intimate relationship to someone we also know. Being able to see a map of my local network would help a lot in deciding whether to cut someone loose or not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://IAwiki.net/&#34;&gt;Eric Scheid&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-07-30T01:53:38-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-07-30T01:53:38-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dunbar Number as a Limit to Group Sizes</title>
      <link>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 14:17:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately I&#39;ve been noticing the spread of a meme regarding &amp;quot;Dunbar&#39;s Number&amp;quot; of 150 that I believe is misunderstanding of his ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Science of Dunbar&#39;s Number&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar is an anthropologist at the University College of London, who wrote a paper on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbsonline.org/documents/a/00/00/05/65/bbs00000565-00/bbs.dunbar.html&#34;&gt;Co-Evolution Of Neocortex Size, Group Size And Language In Humans&lt;/a&gt; where he hypothesizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;... there is a cognitive limit to the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable relationships, that this limit is a direct function of relative neocortex size, and that this in turn limits group size ... the limit imposed by neocortical processing capacity is simply on the number of individuals with whom a stable inter-personal relationship can be maintained.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar supports this hypothesis through studies by a number of field anthropologists. These studies measure the group size of a variety of different primates; Dunbar then correlate those group sizes to the brain sizes of the primates to produce a mathematical formula for how the two correspond. Using his formula, which is based on 36 primates, he predicts that 147.8 is the &amp;quot;mean group size&amp;quot; for humans, which matches census data on various village and tribe sizes in many cultures. The following chart shows the distribution produced by Dunbar&#39;s analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.bcg.com/images/this_is_bcg/strategy_institute/brain_size_02.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.8em;&#34;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcg.com/strategy_institute_gallery/gorilla3.asp&#34;&gt;Boston Consulting Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This number of 150 has become &amp;quot;Dunbar&#39;s Number&amp;quot; and has been popularized by various very popular business books such as Malcolm Gladwell&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0316346624/ref=skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;The Tipping Point: How Little Things Can Make a Big Difference&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0111705/categories/collaboration/2003/12/21.html#a358&#34;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt;), Duncan J. Watts&#39; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0393041425/ref=pd_skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;Six Degrees: The Science of a Connected Age&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/joss/content/reviews/Podolny/&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0691005419/ref=skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;Small Worlds: The Dynamics of Networks between Order and Randomness&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ams.org/notices/200008/rev-chow.pdf&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;), and Mark Buchanan&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0393041530/ref=skotostech-20/102-9060851-3407332&#34;&gt;Nexus: Small Worlds and the Groundbreaking Science of Networks&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americanscientist.org/template/BookReviewTypeDetail/assetid/16209;jsessionid=baadd3W3trYipI&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;), the ideas from which are the foundation of the various Social Network Services that I&#39;ve discussed elsewhere in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Revisiting Dunbar&#39;s Number&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, Dunbar&#39;s number has been taken as a mean size for online networks and groups, as shown in &lt;a href=&#34;http://radio.weblogs.com/0114726/2003/02/12.html#a284&#34;&gt;Ross Mayfield&#39;s Weblog&lt;/a&gt;, where he states:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;table border=&#34;1&#34;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Distribution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Political Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;~1000s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Blogs as mass media&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Power-law (scale-free)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Social Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;~150&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Blogging Classic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Bell-curve (random)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Creative Network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;~12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Blogs as dinner conversation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: 0.6em;&#34;&gt;Dense (equal)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Dunbar&#39;s work itself suggests that a community size of 150 will not be a mean for a community unless it is highly incentivized to remain together. We can see hints of this in Dunbar&#39;s description of the number and what it means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The group size predicted for modern humans by equation (1) would require as much as 42% of the total time budget to be devoted to social grooming.&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
My suggestion, then, is that language evolved as a &amp;quot;cheap&amp;quot; form of social grooming, so enabling the ancestral humans to maintain the cohesion of the unusually large groups demanded by the particular conditions they faced at the time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunbar&#39;s theory is that this 42% number would be true for humans if humans had not invented language, a &amp;quot;cheap&amp;quot; form of social grooming. However, it does show that for a group to sustain itself at the size of 150, significantly more effort must be spent on the core socialization which is necessary to keep the group functioning. Some organizations will have sufficient incentive to maintain this high level of required socialization. In fact the traditional villages and historical military troop sizes that Dunbar analyzed are probably the best examples of such an incentive, since they were built upon the raw need for survival. However, this is a tremendous amount of effort for a group if it&#39;s trying not just to maintain cohesion, but also to get something done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Dunbar specifically restricts himself to physically close groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;... we might expect the upper limit on group size to depend on the degree of social dispersal. In dispersed societies, individuals will meet less often and will thus be less familiar with each, so group sizes should be smaller in consequence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My anecdotal evidence generally seems to support the idea that group sizes will usually plateau at a number lower than 150 participants. This comes from 20 years of doing facilitation both on and offline, running several software companies, and running various forums at America Online. In particular, many online communities provide good evidence for Dunbar&#39;s Number actually being an upper limit (either due to reduced efficiency or due to increased dispersion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;onlinecommunities&#34;&gt;Dunbar &amp;amp; Online Communities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ultima Online&lt;/em&gt; provides one of the best examples of what sizes an online community will support because it&#39;s well documented and the overall game size is large enough to generate many smaller communities. If you look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.legendmud.org/raph/&#34;&gt;Raph Koster&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; statistics for the size of groups in &lt;em&gt;Ultima Online&lt;/em&gt;, you will see a definite point of diminishing returns at around 150; however, you will also see that most groups are around 60 large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/UOGuildPowerLaw.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;UO Guild Power Law&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/UOGuildHistogram.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;UO Guild Histogram&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jessica Mulligan, executive producer at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.turbinegames.com/&#34;&gt;Turbine Games&lt;/a&gt;, confirmed these numbers to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The numbers match up with my (currently) mostly anecdotal evidence for &lt;a href=&#34;http://ac.turbingames.com&#34;&gt;Asheron&#39;s Call&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; We have allegiances in the hundreds and even thousands of members, but most of those members are inactive, non-participatory in the group on a regular basis or are mule accounts for farming XP.&amp;nbsp; It is rare to have more than 40 or so active participants in an Allegiance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve seen similar limits myself in some of the small online games that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.com&#34;&gt;Skotos&lt;/a&gt; produces. For instance, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/marrach&#34;&gt;Castle Marrach&lt;/a&gt;, which is a social-dominant game (i.e. like a MUSH), the game grew quickly until we reached approximately 150-200 active users. However, whenever it grew beyond that number, it always seemed that politics and dissatisfaction would bubble up such that people would drop out, leaving us back close to 150 or 160. (That we would ever exceed 150 is a bit of a surprise, but I think it&#39;s due to any number of factors, including a variable 24-hour user base, wherein on a given day we might only see a little more then half of our community members, below Dunbar&#39;s Number, and only get up to close to 200 or so over a full week.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have had some games at Skotos that do manage to overcome Dunbarrian social limits, prime among them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skotos.net/games/eternal-city&#34;&gt;The Eternal City&lt;/a&gt; which regularly exceeds the Marrach community by more then double. However, TEC is a much more achievement-oriented game, meaning that people spend much of their time interacting with the environment -- fighting monsters and training skills as it happens -- rather than directly interacting with other players all the time. Thus social limits become less important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other online communities that I&#39;ve had experience with have been more traditional, and thus more closely met my expectations for Dunbar&#39;s Number acting as a limit rather than a mean. When I managed the Mac Developer&#39;s Forum community on AOL, a forum would start to break down when it reached about 80 active contributors, requiring a forum split before continued growth could occur. Wikis provide another good example; the WikiPedia, one of the largest active Wikis online, appears to have hovered at approximately 150-175 &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Administrators&#34;&gt;active administrators&lt;/a&gt; for over a year, in spite of a huge growth in usage during the same period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These numbers just keep coming up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all leads me to hypothesize that the optimal size for active group members for creative and technical groups -- as opposed to exclusively survival-oriented groups, such as villages -- hovers somewhere between 25-80, but is best around 45-50. Anything more than this and the group has to spend too much time &amp;quot;grooming&amp;quot; to keep group cohesion, rather then focusing on why the people want to spend the effort on that group in the first place -- say to deliver a software product, learn a technology, promote a meme, or have fun playing a game. Anything less than this and you risk losing critical mass because you don&#39;t have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doceo.co.uk/background/requisite_variety.htm&#34;&gt;requisite variety&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thus Dana Boyd gets it right when she uses the word MAXIMUM in her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zephoria.org/thoughts/archives/2004/02/11/my_etech_talk_revenge_of_the_user.html&#34;&gt;eTech Talk&lt;/a&gt;, not average or mean:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Dunbar] found that the MAXIMUM number of people that a person could keep up with socially at any given time, gossip maintenance, was 150. This doesn&#39;t mean that people don&#39;t have 150 people in their social network, but that they only keep tabs on 150 people max at any given point.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Expanding Dunbar&#39;s Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To open up the discussion a bit, I&#39;d also hypothesize that Dunbar&#39;s Number is just one datapoint in an overall equation describing what group sizes work and what don&#39;t. Working our way up from the smallest group sizes, I think we can find many break points, both above and below Dunbar&#39;s Number of 150.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience the smallest viable group size seems to be somewhere in the range of 5 to 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking smaller, we see that a group of 2 can be tremendously creative (ask any parent), but often has insufficient resources and thus requires deep commitment by both parties. Notably, often the difficulty of a 2-person business partnership is compared to that of a marriage. A group of 3 is often unstable, with one person feeling left out, or else one person controlling the others by being the &amp;quot;split&amp;quot; vote. A group of 4 often devolves into two pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion it is at 5 that the feeling of &amp;quot;team&amp;quot; really starts. At 5 to 8 people, you can have a meeting where everyone can speak out about what the entire group is doing, and everyone feels highly empowered. However, at 9 to 12 people this begins to break down -- not enough &amp;quot;attention&amp;quot; is given to everyone and meetings risk becoming either too noisy, too boring, too long, or some combination thereof. Although I&#39;ve been unable to find the source, I&#39;ve heard of some references to a study from the 1950s that says that the optimum size for a committee is 7. Likewise, it&#39;s fairly easy for us to see and agree that a dinner party starts to break down somewhere above 7 or 8 people, as do also tabletop games of both the strategic (I prefer 5) and role-playing varieties (I prefer 7). These size limits can be overcome, but require increased amounts of &amp;quot;grooming&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chasm that starts somewhere between 9 to 12 people can be especially daunting for a small business. As you grow past 12 or so employees, you must start specializing and having departments and direct reports; however, you are not quite large enough for this to be efficient, and thus much employee time that you put toward management tasks is wasted. Only as you approach and pass 25 people does having simple departments and managers begin to work again, as it starts to really make sense for department heads to spend significant time just communicating and coordinating (and as individual departments become large enough to once again allow for the dynamic exchange of ideas that had previously occurred in the original 5-9 member seed group).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve already noted the next chasm when you go beyond 80 people, which I think is the point that Dunbar&#39;s Number actually marks for a non-survival oriented group. Even at this lower point, the noise level created by required socialization becomes an issue, and filtering becomes essential. As you approach 150 this begins to be unmanageable. Once a company grows past 200 you are really starting to need middle-management, but often you can&#39;t afford it yet. Only when you get up past that, maybe at 350-500 people, does middle-management start really working, primarily because you&#39;ve once again segmented your original departments, possibly again reducing them to Dunbar-sized groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following chart shows anecdotal satisfaction ratings for these lower group sizes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/GroupSatisfaction.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Group Satisfaction&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is probably predicted by Dunbar&#39;s model, if you add in the non-survival and dispursed community modifiers that I discuss here. Essentially, as we increase group sizes beyond 80, to 150, 200, or even 350-500, we typically do so by breaking larger groups down into smaller ones, and continually reducing community sizes down to the point where they can be understood and managed by people -- and so efficiency reasserts itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since this post was originally posted, I have added a number of other posts about the Dunbar Number and group size issues:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/02/dunbar_triage_t.html&#34;&gt;2005-02: Dunbar Triage: Too Many Connections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/03/dunbar_altruist.html&#34;&gt;2005-03: Dunbar, Altruistic Punishment, and Meta-Moderation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/07/cheers_belongin.html&#34;&gt;2005-07: Cheers: Belongingness and Para-Social Relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/08/dunbar_world_of.html&#34;&gt;2005-08: Dunbar &amp;amp; World of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/2005/10/dunbar_group_co.html&#34;&gt;2005-19: Dunbar Number &amp;amp; Group Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Excellent analysis!!!
We must remember that people in a group are connected by direct AND indirect ties.  We can keep tabs on many via indirect ties.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.orgnet.com&#34;&gt;Valdis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T14:55:59-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T14:55:59-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris, this is a very impressive and useful piece of thinking - quite a contribution.
The formulation &#39;7 plus or minus 2&#39;, which I have often heard (and used) over the years as an ideal team size is well-supported by your thinking. It&#39;s worth noting that team-size in thriving real-world team games (basketball, baseball, US football) hover in this area.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.tommandel.com&#34;&gt;Tom&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T15:19:21-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T15:19:21-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris,
Pretty amazing stuff. I&#39;d like to add another break-point. It is anecdotal (but amazingly consistent based on my experience.)
I was part of a company that grew very quickly both organically and through acquisition. In every single office, things worked as you stated from 5-8(or 9), broke down until about 25 and then stabilized. However, the next breaking point was consistently between 50 &amp; 60.
It became my theory after witnessing this again and again that at around 40 people, the *PHYSICAL SPACE&#34; requirements become so large, that you can&#39;t easily shout across them. This may sound silly, but what that physical separation creates is a dynamic where decisions are made on &#34;one side&#34; without the &#34;other side&#34; being involved.
Up to this point most everyone feels included in the whole because news travels so fast, and is often within earshot. Once we passed 40, the only news that travels fast is bad news and &#34;secrets.&#34; ;-)
After much trial and error in trying to scale up offices with &#34;teams areas&#34; of multi-disciplinary folks, we ended up creating physical pods which accomodated 25-35 people. This allowed enough people to manage and have economies of scale, but small enough for quick communications.
The 80 breaking point is certainly when the next breakdown began in those offices that grew that big, but it wasn&#39;t until we got closer to 100 that the crap really hit the fan.
Hope this adds to the discussion and again... wow on the piece.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.inventionasylu.com&#34;&gt;Kyle Shannon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T16:12:45-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T16:12:45-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Nice job. FYI, we have intentionally segmented the forums on SWG and other games in order to reduce the admin load--this also entailed getting rid of the “general” forum, because it served as an attractor for too many people. Smaller communities of interest prove to be far more manageable from a policing point of view because of peer pressure and tighter social strictures.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.legendmud.org/raph/&#34;&gt;Raph&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T16:20:22-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T16:20:22-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Interesting stuff.  But, what is a &#34;group&#34;?  If it means &#39;the number of individuals with whom any one person can maintain stable relationships&#39;, the what is &#34;stable&#34; and what is a &#34;relationship&#34;?  What is the context of relatedness?  Is the point of orientation a conversation? a product?  a service?  an battle? a political action committee?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Rob Kost&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T17:47:30-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T17:47:30-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Well put, its important people understand the scaling limits at 12 and 150.  I never ventured a guess at optimal group size, as its heavily context dependent. Instead I would suggest that our challenge as creators of social software is to enhance social capital so productive teams can be dynamic while extending their limits with cohesion.
On 12 &amp; 150 with Wikipedia: http://ross.typepad.com/blog/2004/01/phantom_authori.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://ross.typepad.com&#34;&gt;Ross Mayfield&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T19:59:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T19:59:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Great article &amp; comment thread, Christopher -- thanks for posting that. Was there something in particular that prompted you to write this? Love to hear the backstory if there is one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://socialarchitect.typepad.com&#34;&gt;AJ Kim&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T20:46:19-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T20:46:19-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Great stuff, Christopher!
I like to include the following in explanations of the 147.8 number, because the range is pretty large (100 to 231):
&#34;Because the equation is log-transformed and we are extrapolating well beyond the range of neocortex ratios on which it is based, the 95% confidence limits around this prediction (from formulae given by Rayner 1985) are moderately wide (100.2-231.1).&#34;
From Dunbar&#39;s 1993 Behavioral and Brain Sciences article.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://peterkaminski.com/&#34;&gt;Peter Kaminski&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-10T23:19:39-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-10T23:19:39-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Interesting. I just finished an analysis of the e-learning industry here in New Brunswick, Canada. of the 40+ companies surveyed, almost all of them were less than 8 or more than 50 employees. Nobody in the middle, as it seems that&#39;s an uncomfortable place to be.
Also, I remember reading about W.L Gore Assoc, who insisted that all of their plants have less 150 people. More than that and they would create another plant, even if it was next door. Something about group cohesiveness.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.jarche.com&#34;&gt;Harold Jarche&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-11T08:15:17-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-11T08:15:17-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
The references to Ultima Online parallel my experiences with the game. Most guilds that I socialized with or had battles with showed the most solidarity with only 5 to 8 players present in the same area. With too many players, things would get &#39;silly&#39; as players would become bored. Also, too many players in a guild would cause fragmentation since players could never be on at the same times or preferred to play in a different part of the world. When I played, the largest guild around was HKU (Hong Kong Union) with 230+ members. It was a common occurrence to spot two HKU members fighting in anger. I have no idea how the guildmaster of HKU managed to get any actual game play in. :)
Excellent article Chris!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Wes Connell&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-11T09:48:00-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-11T09:48:00-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Just wanted to add my agreement. The larger the general communities get, the weaker the signal in any discussion. I think barriers to globally-broadcast participation can alleviate that to some extent. For instance, we charge some in-game currency (gold) to post on the in-game
general forums. We&#39;re even considering charging gold to file a complaint against another player, as the validity (signal) of people&#39;s complaints
(communication) against others has also declined as the population as gotten larger.
--matt
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ironrealms.com&#34;&gt;Matt Mihaly&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-13T11:40:08-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-13T11:40:08-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Chris, Must be tough keeping up with all the compliments :-). Let me add mine but also point back to Raph&#39;s comment earlier. The most amorphous piece here is the defintion of a group. I would also suggest that as opposed to non-human primates, humans have the ability to segment their neocortical capacities discretely between various groups and for various function - they can change roles completely. Thus we have multiple networks layered on top of each other - some w/ 2 members, some with 1000 and we swap our focus among them depending on our task, goal, etc.
I think that Dunbar&#39;s number is a strong predictor of a single group&#39;s optimal size but not so much of an individual&#39;s capacity to maintain multiple social contexts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://blogoehlert.typepad.com/eclippings/&#34;&gt;mark oehlert&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T06:29:47-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T06:29:47-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Although I haven&#39;t read Dunbar&#39;s work directly, the material I have read suggests that individuals are keeping track of &#34;who did what to whom&#34;, suggesting that group complexity grows as n^2. When n=40, we&#39;re well within our limits, and we can handle many groups of such size (and we all have multiple social groups). My theory is that when n=150 or greater, we&#39;re pushing the boundary, and our ability to handle multiple social groups is diminished.
Marvin Harris, noted anthropologist, says in his book &#34;Our Kind&#34; (isbn:0060919906) that you can find no cases of larger groups forming except when there is both direct military power and no place to else to go. Let me reemphasize this: In no case in history can we find groups that voluntarily formed that were significantly larger than Dunbar&#39;s number. Larger groups formed only when agricultural communities created food, that food was controlled by a chief who had armed guards/police, and it was impossible to splinter off into a new tribe because there was no other life-sustainining land to go to.
-- Will
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.liquididea.com&#34;&gt;Will Hertling&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T18:42:02-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T18:42:02-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Anthopological research shows that primate groups thirve at about the size of 30 members. Human tribes in traditional tribal communities around the world demonstrate that same ideal number.
Here&#39;s a thought: If you we could manage group relationship the way of some sports leagues, we would maintain A, B, C... Groups.  We would work with each of these groups differently and communicate in different ways.  Individuals could move up and down as their relevance to our current activity changes.
You know come to think of it... I think I already do group people like that! The A&#39;s are the ones I meet with in person at least once in a while. The B&#39;s are the ones I call at least somewhat frequently and the C&#39;s are the ones I email with.
I guess there&#39;s a group that could be an A+ which are people who have directly lead me to business or are current customers. That would be a very short list, but the most protected and fruitfull.
In that paradigm, these tools are helping me turn C&#39;s into B&#39;s and A&#39;s, and helping me grow my C farm. The more C&#39;s I have which can be turned into B&#39;s and A&#39;s, the better my networking results!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Shally&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T18:43:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T18:43:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Dunbar would agree with your main point: &#34;... the suggestion [in his paper] is simply that there is an upper limit on the size of groups that can be maintained by direct personal contact. This limit reflects demands made on the ancestral human populations at some point in their past history. Once neocortex size has evolved, other factors may of course dictate the need for smaller groups. Precisely this effect seems to occur in gibbons and orang utans: in both cases, neocortex size predicts groups substantially larger than those observed for these species, but ecological factors apparently dictate smaller groups.&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Rick Thomas&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-15T19:08:58-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-15T19:08:58-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I&#39;ve never seen this stuff before but it jibes really well with a hypothesis I had made, based on personal observation of group dynamics in my local pagan community, particularly the coven(s) with which I have worshipped the last seven years.  The points at which the dynamics change seem to hover around powers of two:  one person, two people, three or four people, five to eight, etc.   While thirteen is a traditional &#34;target&#34; the groups I&#39;ve circled with have ranged in membership from three to thirty.
In my observation, when a group fell below five active members for more than a few weeks it either sought out new students, merged with another small group, or dissolved completely.  Groups ranging from five to ten members tended to be most stable, with all members actively participating under the &#34;leadership core&#34; of two to four persons.  Groups of nine to fifteen people tended to split into &#34;active&#34; and &#34;less-active&#34; members with the active component having five to nine participants.  This commonly led to less active members either dropping out entirely (reducing overall group size) or complaning mightily about being left out.   The one group which grew above fifteen participants, reaching thirty at its maximum, was extremely unstable as the leadership core struggled to coordinate three sub-groups, each of whom complained mightily about lacking the leaders&#39; attention and feeling left out...
It seems that the 16-32 person group is the one that really needs a leader, though leadership develops at the 9-15 level. Would be interested in seeing if someone has applied this direction of thought (Dunbar&#39;s number, etc) to decision-making processes in groups.  A group that can&#39;t make a decision can&#39;t (as a whole) do much of anything else, either.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Thena&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-16T20:29:35-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-16T20:29:35-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Sébastien Paquet had a comment in his blog http://radio.weblogs.com/0110772/ I thought was interesting: &#34;Note that if this graph is accurate, jury duty (size=12) must be pretty nerve-wracking!)&#34;
I hadn&#39;t even thought of jury duty as an example, and I just recently was foreman of one.
With only one example my experience is purely anecdotal, but I think the value of 12 in a jury is that that the group isn&#39;t cohesive, and has a tendency to break into two groups, i.e. guilty and innocent. Then it is up to those two groups to persuade each other one way or another.
Also, a smaller jury pool might allow for someone&#39;s personality to win over some else&#39;s judgement. Not that this don&#39;t happen anyhow, just that with 12 people you are more likely to find someone with a like opinion and you&#39;ll be able to stand with them against the strong personality.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-03-19T09:42:31-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-03-19T09:42:31-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;The applicability of Christopher&#39;s work to analyzing terrorist networks.
http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2004/03/what_is_the_opt.html
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas&#34;&gt;John Robb&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-06-27T11:40:25-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-06-27T11:40:25-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Dunbar&#39;s original work was concerned with social groupings that were effectively the whole of an individual&#39;s &#34;stable relationships&#34;.  Ignoring for a moment his insight as to the utility of language in lowering the cost of social grooming, would this not suggest that an individual&#39;s stable relationship total should be aggregated over all groups - so that if you&#39;re in a role-playing guild of, say 70, have a close-knit extended family of, oh, 40, you&#39;re not going be be able to sustain a business (or blog) network of more than about 40.  Now, adding language back in should allow these numbers to grow, but I guess the point is that the limit is individual-based, rather than group-based.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Bob Bechtel&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-01T06:38:18-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-01T06:38:18-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Someone asked me via email &#34;Is there a format for assessment which you have found useful which you share with others?&#34;
I&#39;ve been thinking about assessment, but I&#39;m not sure about how to approach it.
One argument is to look at it from an individual perspective. Their approach says that each individual has a max 150 meaningful relationships, so if they have 50 professional relationships, 50 personal relationships, they only have room for relationships with a group of 50 additional people. Thus for you to join another group of 10 you need to triage your existing relationships and drop 10 relationships.
The problem with this approach is that although there is probably some truth to it, it doesn&#39;t lend itself to understanding how assess how group works. Does in a new group of 10 each person all only have &#34;room&#34; for 10 more people in each of their networks -- that is doubtful. So there must be separate group dynamics involved with group sizes other then just the Dunbar number.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-07-01T10:06:27-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-07-01T10:06:27-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I have a question about that last graph -- the Group Satisfaction one. What is its source? Is it just a visual representation of the anecdotal experience that precedes it? Because if so, it should really be labeled as such. Otherwise it carries the same validity weight as the other graphs, which represented empirical data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.johntynes.com/&#34;&gt;John Tynes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-13T09:56:55-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-13T09:56:55-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;You are correct, it of the anecdotal experience. I&#39;ll change the text right above it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Christopher Allen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2004-10-13T10:34:42-07:00&#34;&gt;2004-10-13T10:34:42-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Dunbar says that human group size, &#34;...would require as much as 42% of the total time budget to be devoted to social grooming.,&#34; and you suggest, &#34;Some organizations will have sufficient incentive to maintain this high level of required socialization,&#34; as long as they&#39;re &#34;...built upon the raw need for survival.&#34;
It is interesting in that regard that two groups of professionals who habitually deal with the &#34;raw need for survival,&#34; soldiers and sailors, are often characterized by their love of conversation, &#34;war stories,&#34; &#34;yarning,&#34; and the like, a social-grooming pastime that may approach the percentage of waking hours that Dunbar mentions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;johne&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-07T12:15:50-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-07T12:15:50-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Hi Christopher!
My groupmates and me are writing a paper about groupsize and leadership. We read your article and we found it very useful for background theory about group size. Can you please tell us if this article has been published somewhere and in which magazine?
Thank you!
Best regards,
Anke Koszczol
University of Tilburg
Social studies
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.uvt.nl&#34;&gt;University of Tilburg&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-02-28T04:05:35-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-02-28T04:05:35-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Belbin did studies on working groups in the 80s and discovered that there were 8 roles in play and each had its part to play in the group objectives.  The best groups were 4 to 8 sized, and the optimal was 4, where each person fulfilled 2 roles.  (Of course this was latter statistically unlikely.)
Unfortunately, there is very little info on Belbin on the net, as the work is sold as a sort of corporate training aid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://iang.org/papers/&#34;&gt;Iang&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-03-17T15:27:05-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-03-17T15:27:05-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Several comments:
- Running live-action role-playing adventures, I have found that the ideal size of an adventuring group is around eight to ten players &amp;mdash; this allows for one or two players to hang back and recuperate while the others interact, as it can otherwise be fairly draining to be in character for hours or days at a time, and the interactions get a bit sparse with fewer than six participants.
- There is a religious community in Canada that lives together and practices low tech farming.  Their farms are not necessarily adjacent to one another, and each farm has up to about 100 members.  Whenever a farm begins to approach this limit, it starts the process of splitting in two.  This involves working together to acquire a new piece of land, build the new buildings, and prepare everything needed in the new location.  The group splits into two, and each chooses a leader.  On the night before the move, everyone packs &amp;mdash; in both groups.  The inhabitants of the new place are not determined until the day of departure.  On the morning of the move, the two leaders flip a coin to decide which will go and which will stay.  This has the function of investing everyone in the new buildings.  In order to replicate this growth strategy, of course, one would have to make sure everyone felt their survival depended on the community, and that they would be willing and able to relocate that investment from time to time.  Not so hard online.  Rather more difficult in the real world.
- Someone is going to start claiming that Dunbar&#39;s analysis doesn&#39;t hold, due to evidence from the recently discovered &#34;hobbits&#34; of Flores Island &amp;mdash; comparative complexity of mental capacity in a much smaller brain-case.  I offer a pre-emptive counter-argument, in the form of an amendment to Dunbar&#39;s anaylsis.  The graph of brain size vs group size might equally well represent brain complexity vs group size.  Someone should re-analyze the data on the basis of complexity of the neocortex (or even of the whole brain), rather than its size, in order to back this up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.wandreilagh.org&#34;&gt;Gavin Weld White&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-04-07T16:08:12-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-04-07T16:08:12-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Don&#39;t you think that with the advent of computer technologies, the dunbar number has lost its relavance? I mean with all these modern gadgets like computers and Cable Television, people have lost the will and the art to communicate with others. About 10 Years back, there was enough time after work for members of a family to get together after a hard day&#39;s work to discuss about their current day and have relavent communication. But now there is no time for any communication at all in this fast paced world. And if at all  there is time, it is spent in front of the Idiot box (TV) or the more intelligent idiot box (computer) surfing the web.
So much for communication!!
--
http://linuxhelp.blogspot.com
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://linuxhelp.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Ravi&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2005-05-15T03:27:44-07:00&#34;&gt;2005-05-15T03:27:44-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I guess Judas got cranky being in a group of 13... :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://euroblogalan.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Alan R&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-05-04T11:18:51-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-05-04T11:18:51-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Bless you for this. I have been searching for so long. Now, I need to find fourteen years to study everything you have written so that my questions start to find answers. Thanks sincerely for freely sharing you knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://AmyStephen.us&#34;&gt;Amy Stephen&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2006-10-13T07:34:49-07:00&#34;&gt;2006-10-13T07:34:49-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
I believe the significance of the range of 5 - 9 may come from &#34;The Magical Number Seven, Plus or Minus Two: Some Limits on Our Capacity for Processing Information&#34; (1956) by George A. Miller, cognitive psychologist. Another thought: with language comes the ability to think to oneself, thereby increasing the number of people in one&#39;s tribe by at least one or two (more for Sybil) ...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Michael Crowe&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-04-03T09:32:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-04-03T09:32:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;I was absolutely mesmerized by this blog post, I have to read the others as well!
Anyway, so it&#39;s no coincidence the movie is called &#34;12 Angry Men&#34; ( http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0050083/ )? :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://flickr.com/people/cjsveningsson&#34;&gt;Carl-Johan Sveningsson&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-04-04T10:03:46-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-04-04T10:03:46-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
Ok, this is ridiculous.  Some assertions here must be answered.  People can maintain more than 150 relationships.  The idea that people can only keep up with 150 people is clearly outside the assertions of Dunbar&#39;s work.  Dunbar only says that the maximum sustainable size of a single group is somewhere between 100 and 230 with a 95% confidence.  (With the mathematical tendency toward 148.something)  This is for a single group with all members fully invested in the group.  The real limit in the human mind is the ability to keep track of the relationships between all 150ish people.  If the maximum size of a single undivided social network with no outside relationships is 150, his research therefore suggests that the average number of relationships a person can keep track of is 11,175 inter-relationships (1 interrelationship between every possible group of 2 people).  It is wrong-headed to say that the limit on a single network of 150 means that someone couldn&#39;t have a network of 50 people in their family network, 70 people in their work network, and another 70 people in their friends network.  If these networks are fully separate, then there are only 6,055 total inter-relationships, which lends credence to later research by H. Russell Bernard and Peter Killworth showing the average modern American maintains a social network of mean 290 members (median 231 members).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Echelon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2008-09-30T12:54:07-07:00&#34;&gt;2008-09-30T12:54:07-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;Thanks for this writeup on Dunbar&#39;s number, and your scholarship into it.  I followed a Twitter message from Luis Suarez to this blog posting.
When Malcolm Gladwell was lecturing on &#34;The Tipping Point&#34; at the Rotman School at the University of Toronto, I asked him specifically about the number 150 (in particular, on the Goretex example cited in the book).  He didn&#39;t explain that the number 150 was associated with Dunbar, but instead referred to Thomas J. Allen at MIT.  I had found a copy of the 1997 book &#34;Managing the Flow of Technology&#34; in an old booksale, which wasn&#39;t very satisfying.  I now note that Allen has a 2006 book on &#34;The Organization and Architecture of Innovation&#34; which would be contemporaneous with &#34;The Tipping Point&#34;.
Now that you&#39;ve provided with the direct source of the citation, you&#39;ve opened up the academic bottleneck for me.  I appreciate your writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://coevolving.com&#34;&gt;David Ing&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-02-12T08:39:57-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-02-12T08:39:57-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;It is interesting in that regard that two groups of professionals who habitually deal with the &#34;raw need for survival,&#34; soldiers and sailors, are often characterized by their love of conversation, &#34;war stories,&#34; &#34;yarning,&#34; and the like, a social-grooming pastime that may approach the percentage of waking hours that Dunbar mentions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;http://www.paragraf.su/&#34;&gt;Типография&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2009-12-26T15:36:20-07:00&#34;&gt;2009-12-26T15:36:20-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;u-comment h-cite&#34;&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p-content p-name&#34;&gt;URL:
What a nice collection of reflections on the Dunbar Number.
I would like to add a different formula that I created when studying human groups for my PhD.
A = R + (Sq.Rt)M
where A = attendance at meetings
M = number of formal roles (eg. chair, secretary, coach, etc)
M = total number in group membership
and of course SqRt is Square Root (won&#39;t use the symbol in case the ascii doesn&#39;t work for anyone)
I have found it a pretty good predictor of meeting size all my (post-PhD) life.
It is usually more pessimistic that the anticipations of group members that organize the meetings.  Sometimes I explain that the best way to increase the attendance is to introduce more (real) roles..... sometimes not, as you are not always thanked for suggestions.
I have always felt a fondness for the formula as it is one of the very few non-statistical uses of number in Social Psychology, and it seems a good predictor.
For this reason I throw it into the discussion.
The original publication was in my PhD
1977    Human Social Groups: A cybernetic account of  stability and instability PhD Thesis. Brunel University.
and later in book form (now sadly out of print... but I still have some copies if anyone wants one)
1984    Groups  John Wiley. Chichester and New York
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;u-author h-card&#34; href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Mike Robinson&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;time class=&#34;dt-published&#34; datetime=&#34;2010-02-24T12:55:43-07:00&#34;&gt;2010-02-24T12:55:43-07:00&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/previous/2004/03/the_dunbar_numb.html&#34; rel=&#34;syndication&#34; class=&#34;u-syndication&#34; &gt;orginal layout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>